at some point near the end of last year
I realized that I had a problem I was
trying to do way too many things with my
days I was working on multiple software
development projects I was doing CEO
things in my company I was working on
videos for both this Channel and my
second Channel doing product design
tasks basically I was trying to do the
work of like three different people and
I didn't have a lot of clarity which had
two negative knock on effects that you
might be familiar with number one I
started a whole lot of things that
didn't end up getting finished and
number two I was working way too much I
was often in the office until 8:00 p.m.
my my wife was wondering where I was I
was skipping workouts I knew something
needed to change so over the holiday
break I took a morning and sat down and
did a planning exercise to get clarity
on what I actually wanted from the
coming year and what I was going to do
to get it and that exercise which really
started out as just kind of a free
writing exercise turned into something
so useful that I had to make a video and
share it with you because I think a lot
of other people deal with this problem
of doing too many things so in this
video as the title says we're going to
talk about how to get everything you
want this year or at least how to to get
clarity on the things you actually want
and on what you need to do to get those
things this will be a process of
answering six key questions that we're
going to go through in this video which
at the end should leave you with three
distinct to-do lists or lists of action
items and a bit later you're going to
understand why in this case three is
actually better than one but more
holistically this process is also about
solving a problem that I like to call
low pressure when it comes to your
productivity consider for a second this
CO2 canister there is so much gas packed
into this small form factor that it's
under extremely high pressure and with
that high pressure we can do useful
things like pumping up a bike tire
really quickly even the air that you and
I are breathing right now is under a
fair bit of pressure both due to gravity
and all the other air stacked on top of
it and because of that pressure we can
breathe it we can live in it but if you
were to get into a rocket and go all the
way to the upper level of the atmosphere
and then step outside you wouldn't be
able to breathe the air at all or at
least it would be very very tough
because there's such low air pressure up
there that all the gas molecules in the
atmosphere are so thin spread apart so
pressure is often what makes things
useful and I think about this in terms
of our productivity and our
prioritization all the time if we think
about all of our goals all the concerns
in our lives as a sphere the bigger that
sphere is the more we're trying to do at
any given moment then the more our
limited resources our time our attention
and our energy get spread thinly and the
less effective they are so the goal of
an exercise like this is to take those
limited resources and put them into a
smaller form factor to put them under
higher pressure and point them at a
smaller but mightier list of priorities
and goals so the first part of this
process the first question to ask
yourself is deceptively simple what do
you want so this is where I started the
exercise for myself I went to a coffee
shop I opened up a blank page in notion
no fancy templates or worksheets needed
and I simply started writing out the
things that I wanted and to guide my
thinking I had to find six different
categories to kind of ensure that I was
trying to prioritize across my entire
life as well as my business so you can
use these categories if you want maybe I
missed some but the ones that I defined
are number one personal growth number
two business career and finance I kind
of lumped all those into one category
number three leadership and Community
number four Health number five
relationships and number six a category
for fun and daily experience and
throughout these six different
categories I just started listing out
things that I want I'll put some of them
on screen right now I'm not going to go
through every single thing I listed so
we won't be here for an hour but a few
of them are do 20 pull-ups get back to
my 1,000 pound powerlifting total spend
more time with my mom and my brother uh
develop my team's leadership
capabilities and help their career
growth as well and then for the new
startup we're building fly lighter I set
a kind of holistic goal to have people
that I respect come and tell me that
they're using the app and enjoying it
without prompting I thought that was a
good proxy metric for both product
Excellence as well as distribution and
getting the word out about this tool
that we're building now as I was writing
this list I had another sort of sub
question in the back of my mind which is
if I achieve this goal what does my
average daily experience look like and
do I actually like that experience and
I've learned to ask myself this question
when I'm setting goals or trying to
prioritize because in the past I've
often prioritize things that actually
don't really matter to my daily
experience don't really help the world
but are more just things that I would
sort of like to happen and I think you
know I would look cool if they happened
or I'm sort of idealistically thinking
about them so for example since I live
in Denver one of the things I've always
added to my goal list every year prior
to this year was to go skiing more often
I live in Denver after all I'm an
athletic person I like skiing I should
be doing it every week right but when I
look back and observe my average daily
experience over the last years even when
I had free time during the ski season I
didn't go skiing instead I lifted
weights I went for long walks I played
video games with my friends I played
guitar I made music I did a whole lot of
stuff that wasn't skiing so I kind of
came to realize that I liked the idea of
myself as a frequent skier but it's not
something that I really prioritized when
I looked at my actions when I looked at
my history history it wasn't something
that happened so when thinking about how
to get everything I want I had to think
about again how am I going to prioritize
how am I going to allocate my limited
resources and if I tried to allocate it
to something I didn't really care about
I was just going to be muddying the
waters and again inflating that sphere
and creating that problem of low
pressure again so I think this is a
useful question for you to ask yourself
as well do you like your average daily
experience if you achieve the goal that
you're setting out to achieve so once
you've answered that question once you
have your s paired down list of wants or
goals the next question to ask for each
of them is how do I get it and that is
exactly what I did I just entered down
from each of those little list items
indented in and started listing out the
things I knew I would need to do for
each of them and I think for the rest of
this video I'm going to pick at least
one of the goals from my list and use it
as an example for how to go through this
thinking process for each question so
for this one we'll pick the goal of
getting to 20 pull-ups in one set for
that I know I can do at least two things
number one when I'm doing my sets of
daily pull-ups throughout the day when I
I just get up from my desk and do some
random pull-ups I can jump down from the
bar after I max out rest about 10 or 20
seconds and then try to get at least a
couple more reps this is basically going
to be challenging my body a little bit
more and training it for that higher
number of Reps versus uh the plateau
that I'm sort of stuck at right now
another thing I know I can do is add
weight to the pull-ups when I'm in my
actual workout sessions now I'm not sure
if those alone are going to get me to 20
pull-ups there might be other things I
need to do there might be questions I
need to ask but I do know those two
actions are at least going to get me
moving in the right direction question
number three in this process is to ask
yourself are there any common actions
across different goals you have and I
came to realize that this was a really
important question when I noticed that
there was a frankly quite scary action
underneath several of my different goals
so underneath spend more time with my
family uh help my mom financially and
also have a bigger yard for my dog to
run around yes I'm now one of those
Millennials getting a house specifically
for my dog
I realized that moving to a different
city specifically Minneapolis would be
an action that would put us in the right
direction and I started talking with my
wife and her goals were in alignment
with that as well and even though that
is a super scary goal and it has a lot
of trade-offs and a lot of unknowns we
do like it here in Denver there is a lot
of good stuff here seeing that
underneath multiple different goals and
understanding that in the first part of
the process I had identified those as
the things I wanted the most started to
make me realize that's probably an
action that is worth taking or at least
worth really seriously considering
because it's not just in service of one
goal it's in service of many so if you
have actions that are similar if you
have actions that are going to push the
needle in multiple areas of your life
that you truly care about those are
actions that you should probably
prioritize and I would recommend Bolding
those actions in your list if you're
writing this out and following along
with me and that brings us to the final
three questions in our list which are
going to create those three lists of
action items that I talked about in the
beginning of this video the first
question to ask is which of these items
on my action list is actually a project
so if you've ever read getting things
done or you've heard about David Allen's
work he often talks about how an action
is something that has an obvious next
step right so if I have a check and my
action is go cash this check at the bank
I obviously know what to do I need to go
to the bank I need to talk to the teller
get it cashed that's clear but if I have
something big and scary or ambiguous
like maybe move to Minneapolis that's
not an action that's a project that is
something I need to break down into a
series of actions and then Define a very
next action so for each of the items on
your list ask yourself is this an action
or is it a project and if it's a project
you'll want to do two different things
first start breaking it down into
smaller actions that you know you need
to do and try to identify the first one
that you should do right away secondly
create what I like to call an ignorance
list so for almost every project that I
start there's a whole bunch of stuff I
don't know how to do and that doesn't
actually worry me in fact that often
indicates the project is worthwhile and
is going to result in some growth right
now I'm reading Seth godden's new book
the song of significance and one of the
stories he tells in that book is about a
guy who built a carpet Manufacturing
Company back in the 1970s and they
became one of the market leaders and
realized that manufacturing carpet is
actually incredibly environmentally
destructive so one day the CEO got with
his leadership team and said I don't
know how to do this but we are going to
become a carbon neutral carpet company
this is the challenge I'm giving you go
figure out how to do it and that is an
example of a project that is worthwhile
they actually achieved it and they had
to start out by asking questions so if
you've got a project and there are
things you don't know how to do in that
project create an ignorance list create
a list of questions and people that you
could go ask or resources you could
consult and that's going to give you
some more actions questions you can go
out and ask and research for your action
list and once you finished answering
this question you're going to have the
first of our three lists which is your
next actions list this is a list of
either one time actions that will
immediately help you achieve a goal
probably a small one or a list of next
actions for the projects that make up
what you need to do for your larger
goals and with that we can move on to
our fifth question which is what are the
systems you need to build and habits you
need to adopt to ensure that you are
putting daily or at least regular effort
into these goals that you have
identified as priorities and when it
comes to building these systems I have
two little sort of subcategories to
think about here first what are the
environmental changes you can make that
are going to make it easier to adopt
better habits and second what are the
systems of accountability you can put
into place that are sort of going to
hold your feet to the fire so again
taking some examples from my own goal
list with the pull-up goal a very very
easy environmental change that I
actually already made but is a good
example nonetheless is putting the squat
rack right next to my desk in this very
Studio that way when I want to take a
break I can get it from my computer I
can go do a bunch of pull-ups or I can
do some other exercises and I'm getting
exercise throughout the day and I'm
getting closer to my goal of doing doing
20 pull-ups uh likewise with another one
of my goals play more guitar I've got a
guitar right back there I have another
one right next to my desk I have one in
the living room of my house and because
they're just sitting out all the time I
pick them up and I play them multiple
times a day and as a result I'm playing
more guitar and I'm getting a lot better
very very quickly but sometimes those
environmental changes aren't enough on
their own and that is where systems of
accountability come in now there's a lot
of ways that you can sort of hold your
feet to the fire there are habit
tracking apps there are more hardcore
apps like be- minder that will actually
charge you money if you don't do what
you said you were going to do but I
think and I talked about in a video
about the five levels of self-
discipline that the best way to sort of
hold yourself accountable is to have
other people that are relying on you to
either work as a team or to get a coach
or an accountability partner basically
if there's another person that I know is
expecting me to do something I am much
more likely to do it one example would
be my lifting coach he sends me
programming and expects me to get my
workouts done and send video footage of
my final sets so I make sure I get those
done but a more important example which
pertains to one of my goals this year is
my team that is helping me with content
so a huge goal I have this year like I
mentioned earlier in the video is for
people that I respect to start using the
app that my team and I are building fly
liigh and to tell me without prompting
that they love it and there are a couple
of different sub goals we are going to
have to achieve to make that happen
number one we're going to have to make
an excellent product but we're also
going to have to up our distribution
game so to do that we need to publish
more videos on this Channel and we need
to make sure they're good as well and to
do that I have built an entire dedicated
content team in my company before
everyone was kind of wearing a lot of
hats and they were sort of switching
rolles all the time at this point there
are people in my company who are
entirely dedicated to content which
means that they are relying on me to do
what I said I'm going to do on time so
that way they have the time they need to
say edit the videos or write the videos
or research or do whatever it is that
they need to do that means there's a
system of accountability that isn't just
an app or a habit tracker or a calendar
but it's a real person depending on me
to get their work done and that will
ensure that I will get my work done so
think about that idea when you're trying
to build systems of accountability for
your own goals who are the people who
are dependent upon you can you align
your goals with uh other people's goals
can you join a team or can you at least
get an accountability partner or a coach
or somebody who's going to hold your
feet to the fire and once you've
answered that question and also answer
the questions of environmental design
you're going to have our second list
your systems building actions the
actions you need to take to either
change your environment or add systems
of accountability to keep yourself in
line and finally we have perhaps the
least fun question here what are the
things that you might need to cut out of
your life or at least put on pause so
you can shrink that area of concern down
to only the items you listed in the
first question so you can create that
area of higher pressure now there are
some lwh hanging fruit here for sure bad
habits for one if you're say staying up
way too late watching Netflix at night
and it's affecting your sleep or you're
trying to get up earlier and read books
every morning like I am you might want
to cut out one of those Netflix episodes
you're watching every night and that's
going to be a pretty easy decision to
make but a harder decision to make is
going to be cutting out things that you
see as beneficial maybe that are even
fun but that weren't on the initial list
and I have a perfect example for that
it's one that I don't really want to
admit to myself but it's programming the
last video I made was all about how I
learned how to code last year and I made
some really cool stuff last year but
when I sat down and I listed out all the
things that I truly cared about all the
things that I wanted for myself for my
family for my company this year me
programming is not going to move the
needle in a positive direction for any
of them now me actually acting as CEO me
helping to develop the talents and the
abilities of the people who are working
for me me making content all those
actions will have a beneficial impact
but me sitting around programming it's
not going to do it and I hate admitting
that to myself because I like
programming but it wasn't on the list
and I didn't even write program more as
like a a fun goal I wanted to sing I
wanted to play guitar I wanted to play
magic with my friends I didn't want to
program so what I've started to realize
is that programming is something that
I'm going to have to put on pause if I
want to shrink that area of concern
create higher pressure and actually
achieve the things that I want to get
done and I'm admitting that to myself in
this video for you because there's
probably something in your life that you
know is beneficial to a degree but is
sort of taking your time and attention
and energy away from the things you know
are actually higher priority and that
you want more now the good news here is
that for items like this that are not
actually bad habits you don't have to
commit to cutting them out of your life
forever you just have to put them on
pause if you truly care about the stuff
that's on your list the stuff that you
wrote down in the first question in this
exercise you would put those things on
pause and then later on you can always
re-evaluate you can ask yourself do I
now want to add this into my life have I
achieved some of these goals and created
space for myself to add this back in do
I now care about this a bit more you can
always re-evaluate but for the time
being you need need to figure out what
you're going to commit to for at least
the next few months I think and at the
end of this question you're going to
have your third and final list which is
your list of cutting actions actions you
need to take to cut out the bad habits
and to put the nonprioritized activities
and habits on pause so you can truly
focus on the things that you said you
care about so that my friends is how to
get everything you want this year how to
get clarity on what it is you actually
want how to break that down from
projects into next actions and how to
figure out what you might need to cut
out of your life to make time for the
things that truly do matter now the
entire point of this exercise and this
video was to help you get clarity and
direction at a bird's eye level to
understand what you really want and need
to do this year or maybe even within the
next few months and if you also have
your more in the trenches productivity
figured out you wake up every single day
knowing exactly what you need to do then
you're good to start executing but if
you're the kind of person who often
wakes up and is not sure what you're
supposed to do in the next hour or
you're not sure how to plan your day
then you probably should invest a bit of
time into also building building what I
like to call a productivity system this
is basically an external collection of
tools or external system that gives you
Clarity on what you're supposed to be
doing next and also gives you a trusted
place to put anything that comes into
your life that you shouldn't be storing
up in your head ideas tasks events all
that kind of stuff and if you want to
learn how to build a great productivity
system I have an entire course that you
can take over on skillshare who have
kindly sponsored this video this is a
1-hour mey course that will show you
exactly how to set up your productivity
system with calendar a to-do list a
note-taking system and a system of file
organization and make all these pieces
of your productivity system work in
Harmony and skillshare actually launched
a really cool new feature this year
called learning paths and that class is
actually in a new productivity learning
path along with four other classes one
of which I'm super excited about because
it's all about automation so if you want
to know how to get from point A to point
B if you want again more guidance on
getting a specific outcome their
learning paths feature and in particular
that productivity learning path with my
course in it is a great place to start
and if you're one of the first 500
people to join skillshare using my link
in the description down below you're
even going to get a one-month free trial
of skillshare which will basically let
you take at least my class if you can
get through an hour of material within
one month for free and I know that you
can plus after you go through that
learning path skillshare has thousands
of other classes they are the largest
online learning community for creatives
they've got classes not just in
productivity but also in film making in
graphic design in animation video
editing even building and setting up in
running a freelance business so they
have something for pretty much everyone
who wants to boost their creative skills
maybe even make money through their
creative talents so once again you can
use that link in the description down
below be one of the first 500 to do so
and you're going to get that one Monon
free trial and also help to support my
content thanks as always to skillshare
not just for sponsoring this video but
for seriously being a long-term partner
on this channel I think I've been
working with them since 2017 and being
able to work with a trusted partner for
now seven years is truly awesome so I
want to thank them for that I want to
thank you for watching this video all
the way to the end and also if you
choose to support my sponsors thank you
for that as well and I want to end this
video with a bit of a note on
productivity systems and in particular
something that we will be adding to your
productivity system if you want to use
it in the future and that's an app we're
building called fly lier which is all
about both idea capture and also
knowledge capture we want to build a
suite of tools that helps you to capture
any of your ideas frictionlessly but
also helps you to capture knowledge and
resources you come across on the web and
I am obsessed with idea captures that's
the entire reason that I started
building this over a year ago because I
think the easier it is for you to
capture your ideas and the knowledge you
come across the more dots you're
collecting as Steve Jobs would have put
it and the more dots you collect the
more dots you're able to connect the
more creative insights you can have the
more problems you can solve and when you
have tools that allow you to collect
those dots more easily you're going to
do it more often and you're going to
have more of those creative insights
that's the entire point of what we're
trying to build with fly lighter and now
that I've Got Talented developers on my
team designers people who are working on
this tool the sponsors that we work with
on this channel and the content that we
make isn't meant just to fund the
channel itself but it's also helping to
fund the tools we're building without us
having to go out and take VC money uh
without us having to take on the
different incentives that investors
might have we can focus entirely on
building a great tool for you listening
to customer feedback and also when we
launch later this year having a more
powerful free tier than we otherwise
would be able to have we kind of have
this whole entire business now with a
Content arm the notion arm over Thomas
Frank explains and now with our SAS for
fly lighter we have that tool that we're
building as well so just wanted to give
you a little bit of insight into some of
the business decisions that me and my
team are making this year give you a
little teaser of fly lter and hopefully
build some excitement for that as well
once again thank you so much for
watching this video I hope you found it
helpful got a couple more videos right
there and right there that can help to
boost your productivity even more and I
will see you in the next one