hey what's up guys and welcome to my
second video this week I know that's
pretty rare and to make it rarer still
this is actually my first full
collaboration video so this week I
partnered up with my friend Jess who
runs another Channel about studying and
learning called fittingly study with
Jess and I thought it'd be really cool
to do a video on how to manage stress
since we're just about into finals right
now and hopefully you'll be able to use
some of the tips in this video to manage
any stress that you're feeling hi
everyone so when I was studying my
postgraduate diploma of psychology I
learned a great deal about stress but
also some really effective techniques
that you can Implement throughout the
year to help you feel more calm and stay
on top of your stress levels so I'm
going to be Shar with you my top five
tips for reducing stress and staying
calm throughout the busy school year but
before I get into that I actually wanted
to cover what is stress and what happens
in our body when we start to feel
stressed so stick around so what is
stress stress is your body's reaction to
any change in the environment that
requires an adjustment or a response the
body then reacts to these changes with
either physical mental or emotional
responses so in daily life we often use
the term stress to mean something
negative but that's not actually the
case stress can either be positive or
negative known as you stress or distress
so ESS is the term used for describing
positive stress and this is the kind of
stress that motivates us increases our
Focus gets us excited and increases our
performance some examples of you stress
could be receiving a promotion starting
a new job or having a child in contrast
to you stress distress is the term used
for describing negative stress and this
is the kind of stress that impairs our
Focus leaves us feeling anxious or
nervous often is perceived as outside of
our coping abilities and impairs our
performance and some examples of
distress could be losing a job sickness
or the death of a loved one so what
happens to our body when we start to
feel stressed in the event of stress our
body's defense systems are activated in
a rapid and automatic response known as
the fight or flight mode your body then
releases stress hormones called cortisol
and adrenaline which cause your heart to
beat faster your breathing to Quicken
your blood pressure to rise and your
senses begin to sharpen also so that
your body is preparing you to either
fight or flee the situation so how much
stress is too much stress some stress is
good in fact it actually helps to
improve our performance and increase our
Focus so that we can execute a task more
effectively but at what point does
having too much stress impair our
performance the inverted U model or y's
Dudson law shows the relationship
between stress or bowel and performance
this model demonstrated by a bell-shaped
curve says that up to a point stress
actually improves our performance but
when it becomes too high it makes our
performance drop rapidly so let's put
this graph into perspective shall we for
example you sit down at your desk to
take an exam as you turn that page over
you can feel your heart start to beat a
little bit faster you can feel your
breath start to Quicken you feel wide
awake and focused and maybe even a
little bit eager to keep turning those
pages and tackle that exam this scenario
would be demonstrated by the middle of
the curve showing that you've
experienced an optimal level of stress
and your performance is actually
improving but what if we actually turned
up the level of cortisol and adrenaline
pumping through your body this time you
sit down at your desk to take an exam
and as you turn that page your breathing
quickens you feel a pit at the bottom of
your stomach and the thought of actually
trying to Fathom what these questions
are becomes overwhelming this scenario
would be demonstrated by the bottom of
the curve showing that you've actually
experienced too much stress and your
performance is impaired so how can we
manage stress to stop it from getting
the better of us well here are my top
five tips tip number one is to do some
deep breathing so when doing deep
breathing you're actually switching on
your parasympathetic nervous system to
create a calming effect try to increase
your exhalations to be longer than your
inhalations breathing into to the count
of four and then breathing out to the
count of six can have a really calming
effect on the Mind tip number two is to
use positive selft talk write down on a
set of flashcards some positive
statements starting with I this way you
can pull them out at any time that you
need and read over them to get you into
a more positive mindset some examples of
what you might like to write down
especially if you're just about to have
a test would be I know that I have
studied to the best of my abilities or I
have survived exams before and my
favorite is I'm going to ace this exam
tip number three is to seek support So
talking to a family member a friend or
even a staff member can be really
effective because it reminds us that
we're not alone and often they'll come
up with some really effective strategies
as well the next tip is to ex exercise
and get Outdoors regularly so when you
exercise you're able to reduce your
cortisol levels and also produce
endorphins to make you feel better the
other great thing about exercising
regularly is that it promotes a good
night's sleep tip number five is to
engage in self-care make sure you set
aside at least 30 minutes every day to
do something nice for yourself don't get
consumed in all of your work and end up
neglecting your own personal needs it's
important to prioritize yourself and
have some important me time every day so
that you don't end up feeling burnt out
or run down close to the end of the year
or even sooner some examples of what you
might like to do for yourself could be
to read a book go to the park play with
a pet or even see your friends so
there're my top five tips for managing
stress and I hope you found them helpful
all right I'm going to hand you back
over to Thomas all right guys so really
hope you enjoyed Jess's part of the
video and before I close this video out
I've just got a couple of different
things I want to mention number one if
you're looking for some more note-
taking hacks I actually made a video
about that topic on her channel so you
can click right there to watch it and
also I just really encourage you to go
over to Jess's Channel and check out
some her videos and subscribe if you
like them because she's one of the few
people that is also dedicating all of
her time to making videos about studying
and learning here on YouTube that is all
I've got for this video so thanks so
much for watching and as always I will
see you next
week hey there guys thanks so much for
watching this video If you enjoyed it it
would be awesome if you gave it a like
to support this Channel and you can also
subscribe using the big red button right
there to get new tips on being a more
effective student every single week you
can also pick up a free copy of my book
on earning better grades by clicking the
picture of the book and if you missed
the other video I did this week is over
how to build a study SCH schedule for
your finals so definitely check it out
lastly I'm Tom frankly on both Instagram
and Twitter if you want to connect or
you can just leave a comment down
[Music]
below