hey what's going on guys so recently
over on my site college info geek
published a post on soft skills which
are important to learn for getting jobs
and for doing basically anything in your
life and today we're going to dive deep
into one of those soft skills because
today we were talking about how to
become a more confident person now I
think a lot of people look at confidence
as one of those qualities that you're
either born with or not born with when
you look at one of those people who can
just come into a room and absolutely own
it there's this feeling like that person
was born with that quality they are just
innately confident and I might not be
that way but contrary to that popular
belief confidence is indeed a skill that
you can build it's a quality that you
can't cultivate through deliberate
action and through changes to your
mindset and that's what I want to talk
about in this video because you might
not believe this but a few years ago
when I was early on in my college career
especially when I was a teenager I was
quite an insecure person and I didn't
have a whole lot of self-confidence now
part of the reason for this was that
when I was a teenager and when I was an
early college student I had really bad
acne like a terrible facial complexion
and I almost felt like I had to wait
until I grew out of that or grew out of
puberty or whatever people told me would
happen before I could be a confident
person I felt like I was worth less in
public situations than I would be when I
looked better and as I've learned over
the intervening years that was
absolutely not true
but it's something that really helped me
back when I was younger as you can
probably tell right now things have
definitely improved and that is due
partly to age but it's also due partly
to improvements in my diet and my
exercise regimen so keep that in mind if
it's something that you're dealing with
as well but even before those
improvements started to happen with my
face I was able to increase my internal
self-confidence and decrease that
insecurity I had through some changes to
my mindset and through some challenges
that I gave myself now four out of the
five strategies I'm going to share with
you in this video involve things that
you can do relatively quickly to start
building your confidence or at least
they were things that had relatively
quick results for me two of them will be
mindset hacks ways that you can subtly
start shifting the way you think about
both yourself and the world around you
and two of them will be tactical actions
that you can take immediately
or very very soon from now that will
help to build your self-confidence but
before we get into those we have to talk
about the most important factor in
building confidence and that is that you
must simply do that which you want to
become confident in doing confidence is
built through experience but the key
term that we should be using to talk
about this here and this really does
make a difference is relevant experience
you have to gain experience in relevant
areas to whatever you want to build
confidence in doing and this is
something that Charlie from the channel
charisma on command makes sure to stress
in one of his videos on confidence and
I'm going to be linking to that video at
the end of this one because I think it's
a good follow-up but I really want to
dig into this term relevant experience
because I think there are two main areas
that are related to it first up we have
the obvious one which is direct
experience for example if you're going
to go give a speech the tenth time you
do that is going to be much much easier
than the first time especially if the
intervening nine times went well as the
former US Secretary of State William
Jennings Bryan once said the way to
develop self-confidence is to do the
thing you fear and to get a record of
successful experiences behind you and
this is a dude who gave 500 speeches in
1896 alone and he's the guy who
basically invented the entire concept of
the stump speech campaign so he is a guy
that puts his money where his mouth is
when it comes to getting experience
secondly though and perhaps even more
helpfully you can gain experience in
related areas because every single
discipline in the world shares certain
qualities with other disciplines for
example even though I have only gone
skiing about six or seven days in my
entire life I am able to ski double
black runs I can ski moguls I can go up
to the top of the summit and ski all the
way down I have a disproportionate
amount of skiing skill for the amount of
days I've actually spent on a mountain
and that is because at the beginning of
this year I started figure skating as my
winter sport and as I discovered serious
figure skating and time on the ice
translates surprisingly well to skill on
the slopes even though you've got big
boards strapped to your feet instead of
what are basically knives to give you a
more professional example my ability to
speak in public both on a stage in front
of a physical audience and for however
many thousands of people watched this
video through this video camera stems
from my experience in podcast
sting now podcasting is pretty different
from making YouTube videos or from
speaking in public because I'm just
sitting in my room there's no camera or
eyes on me but I'm still building my
ability to speak clearly and confidently
and I podcast it for over a year and a
half before I ever started making
YouTube videos and my experience as a
podcaster both interviewing people on
skype but also just monologuing like a
supervillain in my bedroom built a lot
of those speaking abilities and my
confidence to speak in public so the
lesson here is that you can find
ancillary activities that can help to
build your confidence and your skills in
that main activity you're trying to get
good at but one word of warning here
don't let this tip encourage you to
delay your first forays into that
difficult main activity you want to get
good at because the stress of stepping
up to something you're afraid to do is
going to help you progress faster than
all of your practice time in the
ancillary activities and I'm going to
give you an example here that might
bring back some feelings of nostalgia
for some of you because when I was 8
years old I got my first Game Boy Color
and the first game I got for that
gameboy color was pokemon blue and as
somebody who chooses the objectively
best pokémon Charmander I had some
trouble with the initial first gym
because Brock is a rock trainer and fire
doesn't do too well against rock right
so my eight-year-old strategy was to
just grind for hours and hours and hours
and Verdean forests and in the easy
areas so that when I actually went and
challenged Brock I was so high level
that I could just steamroll him and I
thought I was so smart in doing this but
I realized later on that if you have an
easy time with the Gym Leader
you get no additional reward and if you
just scrape by the by the skin of your
teeth so later on I would just get as
good as I needed to be to beat him and
then progress forward and as I did that
I realized I could beat the game even
faster because when you step up you get
the rewards faster than if you just stay
in the kiddie pool area for much much
longer so build your skills and
confidence on those ancillary activities
but before you think you're ready when
you're still scared to do it jump into
that main activity and it doesn't have
to be crazy right as a public speaker I
wasn't giving hour-long keynote speeches
right at the start instead I took speech
classes in high school and then in
college and then from there I move
joining Toastmasters which is an
organization full of people who just
want to get better at public speaking
it's really inviting and it's all about
feedback and growth from there I moved
on to an organization called ignite
which puts on events where you give five
minute speeches on a very constrained
topic your slides auto-advance
and you have to practice and I thought
to myself that's something I can do and
I did that twice which helped to build
my skills even further and now I'm
charging thousands of dollars to give
hour-long keynotes but it was a long and
gradual path all right so now we are
going to move on to the mindset hacks
that I talked about in the intro to this
video we're gonna go a little bit faster
here so the first mindset hack that just
dawned on me during my speech class is
that people in my audience or people who
I interact with in the the world at
large they care a lot less about how I
perform about the little individual
characteristics of what I do then I
think they do and Eleanor Roosevelt put
this best she said you wouldn't worry so
much about what others think of you if
you realized how seldom they do and like
I said this hit me in the face like a
ton of bricks when I was in my speech
class because everyone was going up and
giving their speech in front of the
class and while they did that I would
look at the audience and realize that a
lot of people were on their phones or on
Facebook on their laptops or they looked
generally bored and it just kind of
dawned on me that if I go up there and
give a basically mundane performance
nobody's gonna remember it because
they're thinking about themselves so in
my mind that meant they're one of two
possible outcomes either I'll give it
completely mundane imperfect not that
great performance and people will be
kind of bored
they'll be polite and then they'll move
on with their lives and they won't
remember at all or I'll dazzle them
there's a much much less likely chance
that I'm gonna do something so stupid so
silly or so embarrassing that they're
going to make fun of me or actually
remember it and once I realize this I
was so much less scared to get up and
talk in front of groups or to do
anything else and this leads directly
into my second mindset hack which is to
realize that people love confidence and
here's the thing that kind of dawned on
me a few years ago most people's average
everyday experience is kind of mundane
right there's fun things you do and
there are certain amazing days but work
school the average human experience is
kind of
you know not all that crazy and people
they're fine with that but what they
want is novelty what they want is
something exciting something out of the
ordinary something that makes them smile
or laugh or makes them happy and
confident people are much more able to
deliver that than unconfident people so
here's what I do when I'm invited to
speak in front of an audience or when I
have to basically perform quote-unquote
in any way I picture a stereotypical
image of an unconfident person in my
mind and just like what is the complete
average person going to do in this
situation maybe they're going to have
more reserved gestures they're going to
look back at somebody else who's kind of
leading whatever's going on for cues and
overall they're just not going to have a
whole lot of confidence in whatever
they're doing and how's the audience
going to react to that
well one they're not going to heckle
they're not going to laugh they're just
going to be like mad and they'll go on
with their lives and they won't remember
it now here's the key part once I have
that picture in my head and I realized
that the worst possible scenario for
that stereotypical person isn't death
isn't heckling isn't rotten tomatos it's
just moving on with their lives I
resolve to be better because I know
people love confidence they want to be
happy they want to smile they want
something novel so I step into it even
if I don't actually feel that I have the
skills to pull it off I just try to do
it for example my girlfriend dragged me
to a Renaissance Fair in Minnesota last
weekend and I had a lot of fun so I
won't say dragged but she brought me to
it
and we went to see one of the shows they
had at the fair and I didn't know at the
time but this show had a lot of audience
participation and I was the lucky or
unlucky Harvey seeit person who was
chosen to go up and do the most stuff on
stage and this culminated with me having
to put a bra on my head and give my best
evil laugh and then pick a dude up and
spin him around and I was scared to be
honest and if I had been like 17 years
old and this had happened I would have
just refused to go up but I went up and
I looked out at the hundred or so people
in the crowd and I realized these people
paid money to come here and have fun and
if I'm sheepish if I put my hands in my
pockets and look back too much they're
not gonna have as much fun as if I just
completely make a fool out of myself and
step into the persona of an actor now
I'm not an actor but I can at least try
to do it because I know it'll make them
happy alright so you've got the mindset
you've got the commitment to doing now
get into a couple of tactical decisions
actions you can take right now they're
gonna help you become more confident and
the first one is to record your
accomplishments now you have a couple of
different ways you can do this one way
and I've tried both of these one works
better than the other for me but one way
is to keep a daily accomplishment
journal so maybe you wake up and you
have it to-do list every single day well
at the end of that day simply write down
what you did in Evernote or journal that
you keep with you all the time you never
throw away and then when you're facing
something you're not confident about
look back through your accomplishment
journal and it will remind you you have
overcome so many challenges in the past
many of which you didn't think you could
do until you achieve them and that will
help you to realize that I am a human
being who overcomes challenges I get
stressed I get scared but I win more
often than I lose and that is what I'm
going to do with this next challenge now
this is the exact same mindset that I
use with my impossible list and this is
not a daily accomplishment journal but
this is a public list on my website
where I list out all of my big goals in
life and then I cross them off when I
accomplish them and what I do when I
cross them off is I iterate upon those
goals and I add the next more difficult
goal beneath it and the key thing here
is I'm leaving the goals that I've
achieved up there to remind me that I
have overcome them even though I was
once unable to do them and now I'm
challenging myself to step up and keep
doing that in the future and this helps
me to keep my confidence high and that
finally brings us to my last tip for you
which is another tactic and this is very
different and it actually takes the
focus off of you so this is something a
personal friend of mine once told me
about confidence and she said simply
speak more slowly and speak less smile
more and put the focus on the other
person try to be a great listener and
try to build up the other person in any
other interaction you have this is a
really good tip for building it
meaningful relationships for building
friendships and for making other people
happy but it's also going to build your
confidence because when you do this
you'll start coming out of your
interactions and conversations with
other people happy and they'll seem
successful and you'll realize this was a
great conversation and I didn't have to
spend any of my effort trying to build
myself up or make myself look good
and what this does is it starts to build
this internal self-confidence you can
feel really good about yourself without
having to boast about your
accomplishments or one-up things people
say you just know that you're a
confident person and you don't have to
try to wear it on your sleeve so guys I
really hope you found this video useful
and it was longer than usual but I
really hope you got some value out of it
and like I mentioned earlier on in the
video Charlie over at charisma on
command has a really great channel full
of content like this but the one video I
want you to go watch it's basically your
homework after this video is his
breakdown of Conor McGregor the UFC
fighters confidence and he talks about
relevant experience he talks about
mindset things so I think it's a great
compliment to this video and I'm going
to have it linked down in the
description below if you like this video
you can definitely leave a comment and
if you want me to do more stuff like
this in the future ask questions down in
the comments so I know where to put my
focus and beyond that you can subscribe
to this channel to get more content on
being a more effective student and a
human being every single week by
clicking right there you can also get a
free copy of my book on earning better
grades by clicking right there you want
to watch another video of mine you might
find interesting check it out right
there and you'll find more useful links
down description below if you enjoyed
this video give it a like to support
this channel and thank you so much for
watching see you next week