thanks to Shopify for sponsoring this
video and supporting my channel okay so
I am running the risk of making myself
look pretty old here but 10 years ago
this month I opened up a laptop on the
desk underneath my dorm room loft bed
and I bought the domain college info
geek com which started out as a side
project blog but eventually became my
full-time job and launched this very
YouTube channel so that means that this
month marks a full decade that I've
spent as a content creator and as an
entrepreneur so today I want to share
some of the lessons that I've learned
during my long tenure journey as both a
content creator and as an entrepreneur
and each of these five lessons is
something that I wish I would have known
at the beginning of my journey so if
you're a creator yourself or if you have
aspirations to become one in the near
future I hope these lessons will be
useful for you as well lesson number one
your best friends are deadlines and
accountability running my own company
means that I am my own boss and this is
awesome for many different reasons I can
get up whenever I want there's no
corporate policy telling me I can't
install what I want to install my
computer but it also comes with certain
downsides when I started working for
myself I lost all the structure that I
took for granted in school and in the
jobs that I'd held the deadlines and the
oversight and the bosses that came built
into both the school system and into
work created pressure that forced me to
get my work done on time but as an
entrepreneur everything is on me and to
be quite honest my self-discipline is
not always up to the task of reining in
my brains more impulsive system-1
tendencies so what do I mean by system 1
well this is a term from Daniel
Kahneman's book Thinking Fast and Slow
which introduces two different systems
within the brain system 1 and system 2
system one is the largely subconscious
system it does all that fast reactive
thinking when you have an involuntary
reaction to a bee buzzing near your ear
which is one of the things I hate most
in this world
or when you instinctively reach for your
phone to check a notification when it
comes in that is system one at work and
by contrast system two is the slow
system the one that handles thinking
that is voluntary and effortful so when
you work
tough math problem or you play through a
difficult piece on the guitar or you
have try to resist checking the
notification on your phone you're
utilizing system to and it's worth
noting that system two is very much the
self-discipline system in fact when
we're talking about self management we
can think of system one as the horse and
system two as the rider the ladder has
some limited ability to control the
former but system one is still a 1200
pound horse and the deadlines the
authority figures that come with schools
and companies are examples of external
controls that lend system to a helping
hand in guiding and controlling system
one and without them it will inevitably
fail more often and I've learned this
the hard way more than once one of the
most prominent times is back in 2012 and
my blog finally started gaining some
traction and I actually started earning
enough passive income from a few my
articles to pay my very meager bills I
lived in Iowa at the time so living
basically cost nothing but it was pretty
awesome
but then in 2013 I made the fatal
mistake of getting into a little game
called Magic the Gathering and then I
ended up spending much of that year
doing very little other than building
decks and very little to grow my
business now this wasn't intentional I
would wake up each day intending to
write an article or code a new feature
for my site but then I would invariably
get distracted researching card combos
or building new decks without any real
deadlines without a boss without any
pressing need to bring in additional
money right now because I had passive
income I found myself controlled by the
whims of system one and this pattern
continued for quite some time in fact if
you look at my website's analytics from
that time period you're gonna see a long
period of well stagnation but you'll
also see something else to the right
side of the graph because in mid-2014
things finally started to move upwards
leading to a big increase in average
daily visitors starting in 2015 and
that's because mid 2014 was when I
finally decided to start acting like a
professional and when I use that term
professional I mean it in the sense that
James clear meant it when he said
amateurs wait until they feel inspired
to do creative work professionals do it
on a strict schedule and that is exactly
what I started doing
I committed to creating one blog post
one podcast episode and one YouTube
video every single week and they used
apps like hebediah and b-minor to keep
myself on track to guarantee that I
would get that work done and these tools
essentially replace the role of a boss
acting as those all-important external
controls the lesson here is clear if
you're gonna work for yourself act like
a professional and that might mean
making the executive decision to add
some kind of external commitment device
that helps you stay on task lesson
number two
reach out and build relationships
working for yourself which is often done
by yourself can get pretty lonely often
you're running your own business and
you're in real life friends they do not
understand what it is you're doing or
why you feel compelled to stay up until
4:00 am tweaking button colors on your
website I know this was absolutely case
for me I had a great group of fence and
I started my business but all of them
were still in college at the time and
they really didn't understand what I was
doing or why I was so passionate about
it
and this is just one of the reasons why
the relationships I've built with other
entrepreneurs and other content creators
have been so valuable to me when I
started out I didn't have anyone to talk
to about SEO or web designer habit
trackers are small tiny details and
typography or any of the other nerdy
stuff that I was into mostly my friends
just like to make fun of me for spending
all my free time blogging instead of
playing video games with them but once I
started reaching out to my
contemporaries that all changed I was
still isolated geographically but I
started to gain a network of friends on
the internet who shared my passions who
understood what I was doing because they
were doing it themselves
and not only did we share a lot of
common ground we were also often able to
help each other we could give each other
feedback from other each other's stuff
and my only regrets related to this are
that I didn't start sooner I kind of
wish I would have started right when I
started my blog and secondly that I
continually even to this day sometimes
given to my fear that reaching out to
somebody who I admire would bother them
and I want to talk about that second
regret here for a second as it's
something that again I even deal with
now as somebody with nearly 2 million
subscribers on YouTube I will often
start following somebody whose work I
really admire and I want to reach out I
want to be friends
them I want to potentially work with
them but I'll hesitate because I feel
like I'm not impressive enough yet I
feel like I need to get to a certain
follower account or I need to write more
articles or make more videos about a
certain topic so I can be legit in their
field I can be worth their time and I
will be honest there is a certain
element of truth to this fear because
when you want to connect with somebody
especially somebody who has a large
following who has a lot of respect in
their field you have to be aware of the
fact that many other people are also
trying to connect with that person as
well for just one example can you
imagine how many people are trying to
get gary vaynerchuk's attention each and
every day so naturally if there's
something that makes you stand out
then that person you're trying to reach
out to may be more likely to take an
interest when you do so and this is
simply how the human mind works we are
wired to pick out interesting or
threatening things in a noisy complex
environment and this means that there is
in fact some amount of merit to the idea
that you should be ready before reaching
out to someone you admire but that's
only true if you're making a pitch see
when you pitch something you are
creating a transactional interaction you
want something from them and you're
offering them something in return and
this isn't a bad thing much of the world
runs on transactional interactions but
you can't pretend that a pitch isn't a
pitch and when you're making a pitch you
want to make sure that whatever it is
you're offering is going to interest the
other party in these instances it may be
worth waiting to reach out until you're
ready whatever that means and you're
gonna have to define what that means for
yourself but not every interaction is
transactional you don't have to be ready
to email a creator that you admire to
tell them that an article they wrote or
a video they made really resonated with
you you don't have to be ready to share
someone's work to your own followers or
to respond to them on Twitter with your
own thoughts in fact many of the first
interactions I had with a lot of my
online friends started on Twitter it's a
really great platform for casually
interacting in a way that's not
intimidating and these kinds of
interactions are what I call the fan
first approach
when you admire somebody a great way to
start building a relationship with that
person is to simply be a fan to share
their work give feedback interact in
casual ways and later if you see an
organic way to further that relationship
you can then take it
lesson number three know the taxes that
you have to pay as an entrepreneur all
right let me tell you a story I had a
rude awakening during the 2013 holiday
season I was visiting my girlfriend now
fiance but then girlfriend's house for
Christmas and I was talking with her
uncle who was a financial advisor and
somehow we got on the topic of taxes I'm
not sure how should be Christmas I don't
know why we're talking about taxes but I
do remember myself saying something
along these lines being an entrepreneur
is great it is awesome that I only have
to pay self-employment tax because it's
actually lower than regular income tax
and if you know anything anything about
taxes
you probably winced a little bit just
now because well that is not how
self-employment tax works
self-employment tax is something you
have to pay on top of regular income tax
and when her uncle helpfully informed me
about that fact my stomach dropped
probably my heart as well a lot of my
internal organs probably just like
dropped a foot so I spent some time
running the numbers on my mistake and
realized that I owed the government
about thirty thousand dollars in
additional taxes all due by April 15th I
thought I was all paid up but no another
thirty thousand dollars do so for the
next few months things were pretty tight
and I had to scramble to get everything
paid on time because I didn't want to be
in the hole going forward but it could
have been avoided entirely if I had been
better informed about the taxes I needed
to pay so please learn from my mistake
if you're going to work for yourself
make sure you know what you owe to the
government I'm not gonna go too deeply
into this here because this is a list
video and it's not a video about taxes
but if you want to get a decent estimate
of your tax breakdown again if you're
us-based in the description I have
linked to the budget model or
spreadsheet that I've built and used for
my own finances and I built a ton of
formulas into it that taken your rough
monthly income and then spit out
estimates for each of these three main
and in the template version I've also
put lots of little notes in many of the
cells that can explain things so if
you're curious you can feel free to make
a copy play around with it look at those
notes hopefully you found it useful
now keep in mind that it is not a
panacea because there may be other taxes
that you're gonna have to pay depending
on the kind of business that you run for
instance my fiancee sells art prints and
other physical goods at anime and sci-fi
conventions all around the country and
since she is selling things directly she
has to collect and pay sales tax on
those goods in addition to all the other
taxes lesson number four get yourself a
lawyer and an accountant look even if
you are a solopreneur travel on the
dusty roads the internet with nothing
but a Sun faded Stetson and a adobe
suite subscription this joke seemed
funnier when I wrote it if you're
content to DIY everything I totally get
it but it is still worth putting
together a team of sorts that consists
of a lawyer and an accountant now it is
possible to get by without either of
these especially when you're just
starting out sites like Legal Zoom can
help you do things like setting up an
LLC and tools like TurboTax can help you
to figure out your taxes even if you're
self-employed they work pretty well it
is also possible to build a table with
nothing but a screwdriver instead of a
power drill but that doesn't mean you
should actually do it there is a lot of
value in using certain tools or getting
certain kinds of help to accelerate
things so even if you wait years to
delegate other work like I did I highly
recommend building a good relationship
with a lawyer and an accountant early on
don't be like me because I didn't do
this for my first few years as an
entrepreneur and there was a pretty
stupid reason why see I was afraid that
hiring these people was going to be
prohibitively expensive so I just never
really reached out to either I tried to
do everything myself I never even asked
about pricing and it must be said there
was some amount of good that came from
that I did learn how to do my own taxes
albeit on turbo tax and I did develop a
pretty wide array of knowledge for
running my own business that does come
in handy on a regular basis but I can
tell you from experience that there's
only so much that googling around can do
and if that's the route you take
sometimes your
and yourself in trouble because you
missed something important case in point
my thirty thousand dollar tax mistake
that I talked about earlier that could
have been avoided if I'd had an
accountant as the old saying goes
nothing is more expensive than a cheap
lawyer and the same thing goes for
accountants and make no mistake would
you convince yourself you can handle
everything with nothing but Google foo
you are hiring a very cheap accountant
and a very cheap lawyer so start
building your team it is a very
worthwhile investment if you're gonna
run your own business and if you don't
know where to start a great way to get
accountant and lawyer recommendations is
to simply ask your local entrepreneur
community back in Des Moines where I
used to live there was one co-working
place where many of the city's
entrepreneurs worked so I asked around
there and I got a great lawyer
recommendation who really really helped
me out and my accountant actually came
recommended by my fiance's uncle who was
the one who pointed out my thirty
thousand dollar tax mistake so I guess I
owe him twice but as you can see
building relationships in your community
is a great way to get recommendations
for professionals who can help you and
that goes beyond accountants it goes
beyond lawyers it's gonna help you when
you need a hire other help as well
lesson number five become an unprompted
learner another quick story for you
something odd that I noticed near the
end of my high school career was that a
lot of my friends would spend a lot of
their time complaining about how much
work they had to do to apply for
colleges they would complain about
having to search the college website for
degree requirements they would complain
about writing essays and applications it
would complain about applying for
scholarships and this always struck me
as odd because in doing all of this work
they were literally signing themselves
up to do a lot more work like a college
application takes a few hours but in
doing it you are literally signing
yourself up to be a full time student at
the time that baffled me later on I came
to understand that there is a difference
see despite the feeling of freedom that
College brings at least in comparison to
high school part of the allure of
college is the idea that you're gonna be
guided through a structured curriculum
that will eventually render you ready
for a high paying job college is or at
least it purports to be a
I did path it provides you with a solid
set of directions and I found that most
people are willing to work really hard
as long as you hand them a solid set of
directions but much rarer is the type of
person who is willing to do the mental
work of figuring out what they have to
do in the first place which explains why
my friends complain so much about the
college application process it involved
a lot more independent decision-making
it was a lot fuzzier but that is exactly
the kind of person that you have to be
if you're gonna work for yourself you
have to be willing to spend a bunch of
hours googling questions like do I need
an LLC what taxes do I have to pay as an
entrepreneur do I need a business
license and probably hundreds or
thousands of others in short you have to
become an unprompted learner the kind of
person who not only relishes solving
tough problems but who is willing to go
out and figure out what problems they
have to solve in the first place
being your own boss means being the one
who builds literally every single
guiding structure that employees and
normal jobs rely on and take for granted
and this con relates back to my tip
about getting a lawyer and an accountant
don't be like me don't just assume
they're too expensive and then never ask
anyone what they charge ask around get
quotes you can always say no to a pitch
if it's too expensive but on the other
hand if you don't ask then you're never
going to get an answer or to simplify
that and to put it in the words of
Stevie Wonder if you don't ask you don't
get
now if you're ready to start building a
business of your own and if you have
something to sell then one of the first
things you're gonna need other than
again making 100% sure you know what
taxes you have to pay please make sure
you do that but another thing you need
is an online store and that is exactly
what Shopify provides Shopify makes it
incredibly easy to set up a great
looking online store without any any
coding skills and if you'd like to see
an example well you've probably seen me
wearing this shirt or drinking coffee
from this mug in past videos and
actually use Shopify to run the online
merch store where I sell both of them
they also make it super easy to manage
and market your business with a
dashboard that shows your customers your
inventory and your sales data email
marketing and SEO tools and a great
payments platform
in fact one of the reasons that I really
love using Shopify in particular for my
store is that people who have bought
from other Shopify stores in the past
can choose to automatically fill in
their details when they're checking out
which reduces friction for them and
helps to boost sales for me plus the
team at Shopify also has 24/7 support
which is one of the reasons why over a
million business owners trust them with
their stores and if you'd like to give
it a try for yourself you can actually
start a 14-day free trial by going over
to Shopify dot-com slash Thomas Frank
and signing up which also helps to
support my channel so check it out if
you're interested and as always thank
you so much for watching and hopefully
you found this video helpful if you did
maybe consider gently fist bumping that
like button with your middle knuckle on
your right hand we got to be specific
here and I'm actually curious I really
wanted to make this video because again
you only have a 10 year anniversary of
starting your business once but I enjoy
talking about content creation I enjoy
talking about entrepreneurship
I love getting nerdy about this kind of
stuff so if this is something that you
like I would love to hear from you down
in the comments below and if you have
any specific questions that you want
answered let me know and I'll see if I
can make content on those questions if
you haven't subscribed yet you can
subscribe right there to get new videos
when they come out and I also wrote an
article version of this video which is
actually a lot longer and more detailed
so if you want to check that out I have
it up on my website and I'll link to it
right over there beyond that there's a
couple of other videos floating around
on the screen here well they probably
not floating but I can float and make it
look like they're kind of floating and
relative yeah I don't know but smash
your face into your phone screen to
check those out if you're curious
otherwise go do whatever you want to do
as long as it's safe because as always
I'm not your dad