Hey, what's up everybody? It's Thomas
Frank and it's almost finals
week. So, this being a channel where I
teach you how to study better, I figured
I should probably make a video on
finals. I want to make it short, I want
to make it to the point, and I want to
help you both study more efficiently for
finals and also reduce some of the
stress that comes along with finals
week. So, to that end, I've got five
tips that can help you do both of those
things. And the first one is to know the
difference between your planning mode
and your doing mode, or as I like to
call it, the robot mode. Now, the word
robot is actually an adaptation of the
Czech word robotnik, which translates
directly to worker or slave. And the
thing about workers and slaves is they
do things. They don't plan things. As a
student, you got to do both of them, but
you should do them at different times,
and you should plan before you do. So,
when it comes to finals, you want to
figure out how many days you have until
your first exam and your last exam, how
much time you actually have to study,
and what all you need to study during
that time. Then you can make a detailed
plan for what you're going to study in
order based on priorities, based on
contexts and mental uh intensity that
you can put toward your studying and
anything else that's pertinent. You also
want to break individual studying
projects into actionable steps. So
something like study calculus isn't
really actionable. It doesn't really
tell you what to do next. So break that
down into something more actionable.
Something like get out all of your
material, review the chapter on layup
opal's rule or something like that. uh
go through a practice problem set. Just
make sure your list of tasks includes
things that you can sit down and
definitively achieve. Now, once you
actually have that plan set in stone for
studying, it's time to go from planning
mode and switch over to robot mode. And
actually, on the College Infogeeek blog,
I wrote an article this week all about
planning mode and robot mode and gave
specific examples and things you can do
to make this a more efficient process.
So, at the end of this video, I'll put
up a link to that blog post where you
can go read it. But first, we have a few
more tips to go over. So tip number two
is to know the format of your exams and
then tailor your studying efforts to
match those assessments. For example, if
one of your finals is going to be a
multiple choice test, then you want to
make sure you have a solid understanding
of the facts in the class. And a good
way to do that would be to maybe build a
deck of cards in ANI and do space
repetition studying or create your own
study guide that asks specific questions
and then you have to answer them later.
If a final is going to be based around
essays, then you want to know the main
ideas of what you're studying and then
force yourself to write those down in
your own words. Get practice beforehand
so when you actually go into the test,
it's easier to do. My third tip is to
base your studying efforts around active
recall. This means actually digging into
your brain and forcing yourself to bring
forth information that you've learned
before. The opposite of this is passive
review, simply reading a book or looking
over your notes and exposing yourself to
information. And it doesn't work as well
as active recall. In 1885, a German
psychologist named Herman Ebinghouse
came up with a theory he called the
forgetting curve. And it was his attempt
to explain how memories degrade
exponentially over time. Ebanous's
theory is that the strength of your
memories is subject to a lot of
different factors. And the frequency of
active recall is one of them. So, if you
just listen to me tell you about this
guy, you're probably not going to
remember him very much later on. But if
you actually try to answer this question
for yourself, what year did Eving House
do this research? and you pause the
video and actually do it, you're
probably going to remember it later on.
My fourth tip is to review old material
while you're studying. And there's a
site called kofers.com where you can
actually look up old tests and exam
questions for your classes, and you may
actually be able to find something very
similar to what's going to be on your
final exams. If you can't find it on
Kofers, you can also look at fraternity
test banks, uh, professional
organizations, and other student
organizations on campus. And my fifth
and final tip has to do with your
stress, and it's this. Anticipate your
failures in advance. So, what I mean by
this is that you probably are going to
procrastinate. You're probably going to
lose willpower at some point during your
studying. And the most successful
students recognize this and plan ahead
for it. The way you can take advantage
of this and plan ahead is to set breaks
in the future that you're going to take.
So, maybe after 50 minutes of studying,
you're going to let yourself go on
Facebook or you're going to let yourself
play a video game for a while.
[Music]
But the key here is that you plan for
this in advance. You plan for dealing
with the pain point before it actually
happened. And when you do this, you're
more likely to be able to move past that
painoint and get back to studying. So
that's it for this video, but I do have
a couple other resources you can check
out if you're still looking for some
more tips. The first one is my mutant
guide to studying for finals, which I
wrote over on the College of Oge blog a
couple of years ago, and you can find
that by clicking right there. Also, the
article I mentioned earlier about
planning mode versus robot mode. You can
find by clicking right there. Hopefully,
you found these tips to be helpful.
There are definitely going to be a lot
more coming in the future as I'm trying
to make this channel the ultimate
resource for studying in college. So,
definitely hit the subscribe button
below if you want to get those tips
every single week. Otherwise, good luck
on your finals. Use these tips to study
more efficiently and please manage your
stress, take breaks, and make sure that
you are staying sane.
[Music]
Hey everybody, thank you so much for
watching my video on acing your finals.
If you found it helpful, you can support
this channel by giving the video a like
on YouTube or sharing it with a friend.
And also, if you want to get new videos
on studying better coming out every
single week on Thursdays, just hit that
subscribe button, which you can find
right there. If you happen to miss last
week's video, it's over active reading
strategies, and you can find it by
clicking the moving picture below there.
And if you want to find any resources
that I talked about in this video and
extra links, they are all listed at the
companion blog post, which you can find
by clicking the orange button right
there. Also, I have a little bit of an
announcement to make. I'm actually
writing a book called 10 Steps to
Earning Awesome Grades While Studying
Less, and it's going to be absolutely
free. So, if you want to get that book,
it's coming out right as the new
semester starts in January. Click the
picture of the book right there. You can
sign up for the email list for the
College Infogeeek blog, and you will get
that book for free when it comes out in
a few weeks. I'm very excited to release
it to you. So definitely check it out.
Also, if you want to suggest any video
topics or anything else of the sort,
follow me on Twitter, Tom Frankly, or
leave a comment on this video and I will
get back to you. Thanks.