In last week's video, we talked about
the concept of biological prime time,
which basically explains how there's a
time of the day when your energy levels
and your ability to focus and manage
your attention are at their absolute
peak. And if you can figure out what
your biological prime time is, and it is
different for everyone. We all kind of
vary in that regard, then you can start
to manage your schedule a little bit
differently and you can try to schedule
your most intellectually demanding and
challenging work to coincide with your
biological prime time. So hopefully
you're bringing your agame when you get
it done. But that begs the question, how
do you figure out when your biological
prime time is if it changes for
everyone? This was a really common
question that I got in the comments from
last week's video. And one method that
you can employ to figure it out is to do
an experiment where for maybe a week or
two weeks, you track your energy levels
for every waking hour. And when I went
out looking for a system to build this,
I figured there'd be an app or something
that someone had already set up, but
there really wasn't. So, I had to build
it myself. And in this video, I'm going
to teach you how you can build your own
easy to use energy tracker system.
There's a little bit of setup involved,
but I think I've done a lot of the heavy
lifting for you. And once it's set up,
you're basically going to get something
where you can open your smartphone, open
a link to a Google form. Basically, just
hit one button to tell it your energy,
and that is going to feed data into a
graph that will in real time start to
average your energy levels. And after a
week or two weeks, you're going to be
able to see your average energy level at
each hour of the day. and you can use
that to start making decisions. So, if
you're on board and you want to try
this, let's dive in and build it. All
right, so the first thing you're going
to want to do is go over to my
spreadsheet template, which you'll find
linked down in the description or in the
companion blog post for this video, and
you're going to go to file and make a
copy. So, you have your own copy of the
spreadsheet, which you can edit. So, now
this copy of the spreadsheet will be in
your Google Drive. You'll see it's
called copy of hourly energy tracker.
You can rename that to whatever you
want. But the most important thing you
want to do right now is to create a new
version of results sample, which is
where you're going to have your actual
energy data recorded. So we'll just
click here and go to duplicate. And now
you'll have copy of results sample. I'm
just going to go ahead and rename this
to results. And this will be mine. Now
right now it's filled with uh sample
data which is taken from responses
sample. And this is just a bunch of
completely random data. It's not
actually accurate. But eventually,
you're going to get rid of this, and
it's going to start filling in with your
own data over time as you track your
energy. So now, let's go over to
google.com/formms. We're going to click
this go to Google forms button. And then
we're going to create a blank new form.
Let's call this form energy tracker. And
the one question on it will be, what's
your current energy level? And this is
built so you can enter data as fast as
possible. Now, for the options, you can
really name them whatever you want, but
you want to make sure the first
character is a number. And I'm going to
go ahead and use a 1 to4 scale because I
think 1 to 10 is a bit too much for
tracking your energy levels. Once you've
got your options entered in, let's go
ahead and make this question required.
And then let's head over to the
responses tab where we're going to link
this up to our spreadsheet copy. So
click this green button here. And then
we'll select an existing spreadsheet and
we're going to use copy of hourly energy
tracker right here. And now you're going
to see a new tab added to that
spreadsheet which is going to be called
form responses 2 at this point. Now,
here's where it gets a little bit
technical, but if you follow along, it
should be pretty easy. If you go over to
your results tab, you're going to notice
that in cell A2, we're using array
formula and value and hour to grab the
responses and uh track them here. Now,
the reason we have to do this is because
Google Forms actually adds new rows to
the spreadsheet when responses are sent
in. It doesn't just fill in the existing
rows. So, we can't put some formulas in
here and have them track the data that
way. we have to actually have a
different sheet over here using array
formula to watch the responses sheet and
copy the data over and then we can do
operations on it like get the averages
and graph it. So let's go over here to
this new form responses to tab. We're
going to rename it to
responses and the last part of this is
we're going to go over to results. We're
going to edit our little array formula
and all we're going to do is change the
sheet that it's referencing to responses
which will make everything disappear.
And the last thing we'll do is do the
exact same thing over in the B
column. And now you're going to have a
bunch of zeros and a bunch of divide by
zero errors here because you don't have
any data currently in your responses
tab. But as you enter your data through
the next week or so as you're doing the
experiment, the data is going to be
ported over here and you're eventually
going to get a nice looking graph that
looks like this except for it will be
accurate to your energy levels. From
there, you're going to want to open your
form on your phone so you can save the
link to it on your home screen. So,
let's click send. And then we're going
to click this little link icon and
shorten the URL. And then copy the URL
you get, not this one, but the one that
you get and send it to yourself via
email or via Facebook or any way that
you can use to get it on your phone.
Once you've got your form pulled up on
your phone, you're going to want to
click this middle icon here and then hit
add to home screen. So, you can
basically create an app out of this
form. And if you're on an Android phone,
I'll have a link in the description for
a way to do this because I don't own an
Android phone myself, but it's pretty
simple. And from there, the only thing
left to do is to set up some sort of
system to remind you to enter your
energy data every single hour. Now, I
actually looked into this, and there are
not a whole lot of apps on the iPhone
that can tell you to do something every
single hour without a lot of setup. So,
I ended up going with a very simple app
called every hour, which will simply
make your phone beep or vibrate every
single hour. And you can actually set a
bounded time period, so it only happens
between, say, 6:00 and 10:00 p.m. And if
you're on Android, you can use the Blip
Blip app. Now, there's a lot of other
apps out there, but this is the one I
found. And since I don't have an Android
phone, uh, it gets my tentative
recommendation. So, to give you a quick
demonstration of how this works, I'm
going to go ahead and enter some data
into the form here. And let's just go
with a four and submit it. And if we
check out our spreadsheet here, we can
see we've got a time stamp and a
response. And if we check out our
results tab, we're going to see that
data has been ported over. It's starting
to be averaged and we have a single
point of data, which as you enter more
will turn into a graph. And that's all
there is to it. So once you've got the
system built and then you've entered
data in for maybe a week or two weeks,
at that point you're going to have a
really good idea of when your individual
biological prime time is and from there
you can start making changes to your
schedule so that your most
intellectually challenging and difficult
work is done right at those highest
energy time periods. And hopefully as a
result your work output will be better
and you'll be happier while you do that
work. Once again, you can find that link
to my spreadsheet template down in the
description. And there's a couple of
other things you're going to find down
there as well. Number one, you'll find
the link to the companion article for
this video which has step-by-step
instructions for the whole process. So
check that out if you need some
clarification on anything. And number
two, there's going to be a link to a
thread in the College of Oge community
over on Reddit where I would love to
hear either improvements to the system
or maybe different approaches you might
have. And I would also love to hear your
results from doing this experiment if
you choose to. With that being said, I'm
going to go ahead and close this video
out. Hopefully you found it helpful. And
if you did, you can give it a like to
support this channel. Also, if you want
to get new tips on being a more
effective student every single week, you
can click that big red subscribe button
down there. And if you want to get a
free copy of the book I wrote on earning
better grades, you can click the picture
of the book right there and I will send
a copy to your email. In last week's
video, I went over five lessons that I
learned from the book, The Productivity
Project. So, if you want to get those
lessons, click the video right there to
watch it. And once again, that full
article with step-by-step instructions
is right there if you want to read it.
If you'd like to connect with me, then
pick up a wired telephone receiver and
sneeze my name in Morse code. Otherwise,
you can use the social media links down
below.