a couple of days ago we went over some
tips on how to meet new people and make
new friends but as everyone knows
friendship is a complex and multifaceted
concept there isn't just one level
friendship
you have your casual acquaintances but
you also have your best friends
your two Leos and Miguel's your Lesley's
and ands your rust-eze and Danny's your
Batman's and/or solo well maybe not
Batman but you get the point
also just saying here have you ever seen
Batman and me in the same room at the
same time anyway I'm sure that you feel
just as strongly as I do that having
nothing but shallow surface level
friendships is no way to go through life
so as a follow-up to that video today I
want to talk about how to actually
strengthen the relationship for the
friends that you already have how do you
make those connections deeper and more
meaningful and since we haven't seen
them in a couple of videos let's queue
those llamas now in just a few minutes
we're going to talk about some
actionable tactics for strengthening
your relationships things that you can
actually do but before we get into those
things we have to talk about what is the
foundation for strong friendships and
that is time as Aristotle once said
wishing to be friends is quick work but
friendship is a slow ripening fruit now
this statement might seem obvious but
there is more than just common wisdom
behind it there was actually a study
done at the University of Kansas
recently that shed some light on just
how long it takes to move through the
different stages of friendship from the
responses they collected the researchers
found out that takes on average between
40 and 60 hours of interaction to go
from mere acquaintances to casual
friends to have somebody call you one of
their actual friends it takes between 80
and 100 hours and again this is an
average figure and over 200 hours before
you're considered close friends this is
the biggest reason why busy college
students and adults especially find it
so difficult to build meaningful
relationships with people who they
haven't already known for a long time
we're all just so busy right y'all got
packed schedules we're running all over
the place and this is why we find it so
hard to spend any decent amount of time
with any one person and when we were
kids it was a very different story I
remember when I was a kid growing up in
the neighborhood I would go out every
single day in the summer and I would
knock on the doors of all my friends in
the neighborhood and see if they were
available to play and if they were I
would probably
end up spending between six to eight
hours every single day with those
friends and even when I was in high
school that didn't have sports practice
or if I wasn't working I would be going
over to a friend's house almost every
single day after school and over the
course of a week if I'm doing that I'm
spending 4 to 5 hours there well you do
the math so before we get into the rest
of the tips in this video keep this in
mind you have to put in the time
ask yourself how closely does your daily
experience right now match up to that
story I just told about me in high
school if it's a very different story if
you find that your schedules super
packed with all kinds of stuff and the
only time you're gonna see that one
person you want to be friends with is
like next weekend for a two hour
barbecue and then not again until
October well you're not gonna become
very good friends with that person so
you have to start making time to see
these people and you have to do it on a
regular basis now how exactly do you do
that well yes be the organizer be the
leader this is my first and I think most
important actionable tip from this video
you have to be the person that puts
things together now you might think that
this is unfair you might think that
you're building one-way friendships why
aren't they reaching out to me why
aren't they organizing events well
here's the thing everybody is thinking
that right everyone's like why haven't
my friends reached out to me in a long
time why haven't they invited me to go
do something cool why haven't they
invited me to bungee jump out of a
helicopter Will Smith's doing that on
Instagram but my friends aren't well the
thing is people when they get older they
get into their comfort zone and get into
their routines they have all this kind
of stuff going on in their life they've
got their job they've got the
relationships all these demands on their
time and a lot of people in response to
that crazy schedule don't reach out
don't organize don't be the person who
takes action so you have to be that
person there's a saying that goes around
in the YouTube and blogging and content
creation spheres that goes like this
only 5% of people are creators
the other 95% are simply consumers and I
think that this applies to friendships
and relationships as well only 5% of
people or the organizers only 5% of
people are the action takers the people
that will put something together the
other 95% well they're willing to do
things they'll show up but they want to
be told when and where to be so if you
want to find more of your hours filled
with meaningful interactions with people
that you'd like to be better friends
then be the person who sends out the
invitations be the person who organizes
things let people show up and be okay
with being the leader additionally be
very deliberate about the activities you
choose yes the hours you put in is very
important is probably the main factor as
that study showed but what you choose to
do with those hours the quality of those
hours also matters a lot
friendship doesn't happen simply by
osmosis and there's a big difference
between say having somebody come over
just to watch a movie where you're both
staring at a screen not talking to each
other at all and maybe inviting them to
go climb a mountain together or you're
out of nature and you're talking the
entire time alright something else I
think is really important to talk about
here is the difference between group
interactions and one-on-one interactions
group interactions seem to be the norm
and this makes sense a lot of times when
invites are going out they're going out
to lists of people they're going out to
workplaces they're going out to clubs so
everyone can show up and these can be a
lot of fun a lot of insight jokes come
out of them there's a lot of shared
experiences and there's less pressure on
you individually to contribute to the
conversation all the time since a lot of
people are there but the problem with
group interactions is that there's
really no room for deep meaningful
conversations with any one person since
everyone has to be included you kind of
have to make sure the activities you
choose and the topics of conversation
are palatable to all involved and as you
add more people into the mix things
inevitably become more general and
surface level like if I want to talk
about say deep lyrical meanings behind
the mars volta song drunk trip of
lanterns I can probably do it with you
and by you I mean you Ashley but if I
want to talk with every single person
watching this video right now in one big
group well we probably can't even pick a
Marvel movie to talk about without a lot
of people getting bored and actually
aside from that hypothetical example I
do have a real story about this last
year I went to a sushi dinner with
probably six or seven of my friends
including my best friend Martin now in
that group of friends was another guy
who I didn't know super well at the time
but who was pretty into linguistics and
as any of you who listen to my podcast
no Martin is also very into linguistics
and at one point during the dinner they
got into this very deep linguistics
conversation but it became apparent
after about thirty seconds that everyone
else at the table had absolutely no idea
what they were talking
about and after a while that
conversation became kind of awkward
because everyone else kind of got quiet
and really couldn't contribute and I
remember talking with Martin afterwards
and hearing him say that he wished he
could have had a longer conversation
about linguistics with that guy but he
said that he felt like he needed to kind
of cut the conversation off because it
wasn't relevant to the whole group so in
addition to your group interactions and
your Ultimate Frisbee games and your 6v6
overwatch matches make sure that you're
also making time for one-on-one
interactions with specific people this
is where people are gonna open up about
the things they truly care about and
we're gonna have conversations about the
passions that you both share and unlike
with your group interactions where in my
experience the conversation usually
consists of memes and shared inside
jokes and surface level talk when you
hang out with somebody alone they tend
to get more vulnerable they tend to open
up more so these are the hours that are
lead to closer friendships developing
now it's important to note that
friendship isn't just about having fun
together isn't just about hanging out
friendship is about being there for the
other person so if you want to build
closer friendships make sure that you
are there for that person make sure
you're there to help out this applies in
both an emotional capacity when
somebody's hurting be there to support
them but also in other capacities and
yes I'm talking about helping people
move if one of your friends has some big
chore to do next weekend and you're free
that weekend then why not show up and
help them out with that chore they're
gonna be greatly appreciative and you're
actually gonna enjoy the time even
though it's work because you're with
somebody that you like and even though
this is a video about building deeper
friendships I do want to add one more
tip to last week's video about making
more friends if you're in college and if
you're moving into a dorm and our
apartment and you're kind of done with
all of your own stuff why not offer to
help somebody else who's moving in who's
gonna be your neighbor if you've got
time on your hands do that and you're
probably gonna make yourself a new
friend
[Music]
lastly even if you don't get to see your
friends in person all that often don't
let a whole lot of time go by without at
least letting them know that you're
thinking about them and this doesn't
actually have to involve a lot of effort
my friend Martin does this all the time
by as he puts it texting his friends
nonsense
and sometimes this literally is nonsense
I have seen him text one of our friends
the word dogs just the word dogs and
nothing else but it's still a little
blip on the radar right it's still you
popping up on your friend's phone
letting them know hey I'm thinking about
you I care about you enough to text you
the word dogs I guess I'm not just going
about my life and forgetting about you
and this process is integral to
maintaining your friendships if you
don't get to see people all the time if
you don't get to have those face-to-face
interactions every single week at least
keep the fire going so when you do get
to see people there isn't a whole lot of
ketchup to do you can just sort of pick
right up where you left off to give you
a personal example my friend Andrew
lives about a thousand miles away from
me now that I've moved to Denver but
even still he probably texts me at least
once a week just to tell me about things
going on in his business or things going
on back home or just to share a new app
that he's discovered with me though with
regards to that last one since he and I
are both mat geeks that constant deluge
map recommendations can really put a
hurting on my wallet or at least it
would if not for setup setup is a
service that gets you unlimited access
to over a hundred and twenty excellently
designed Mac apps for just one low
monthly price these are apps that you
normally have to buy individually either
online or in the Mac App Store and a lot
of times they have ads or in-app
purchases with them but when you
download the app from setup you get the
completely upgraded version no in-app
purchases and no ads in their catalog
you're gonna find apps for productivity
for writing for photography and lots
lots more a couple the apps on a
highlight here for you include focus
which is an app that we've talked about
on this channel before which blocks
distracting websites and applications
when you're trying to get work done and
rocket typist which is a really cool app
that I love which allows you to set
different snippets for text that you
type really often so instead of having
to type it over and over again you can
just press the keyboard command to have
it fill in wherever you want again you
can get unloaded access to these apps
and all the apps in their catalogue for
just $10 a month with their subscription
to get started you can get a 7-day
completely free trial of their service
unloaded
access to everything for seven days
absolutely free by going and signing up
at link in the description and down
below I want to give a big thanks to
setup for sponsoring this video on being
a supporter of this channel and as
always guys thank you so much for
watching if you enjoyed this video and
you found it informative and useful
maybe give it a like and subscribe right
there if you don't want to miss new
videos when they come out every single
week you can also get a free copy of my
book on how to earn better grades right
over here follow me on instagram at tom
frankly or check out one more video on
this channel right over here thanks so
much for watching and if you missed the
first video in the series on how to make
new friends that'll be in the
description down below is to check that
out as well
otherwise I will see you in the next one