this is one of those things I tell you
never to say during a job interview when
they ask you what your greatest weakness
is because it's like a humble brag but I
struggle with perfectionism like where
other people are willing to just say
things are good enough or they quite
rightly realize that little tiny details
in their work are never going to be
noticed by anybody else I'm the guy
that's like tweaking the position of the
light behind that toy ship so that makes
the perfect silhouette but over the past
few years I've learned to deal with my
perfectionism and at this point it
doesn't really hinder me that much
anymore so what I want to do with this
video is share some of what I've learned
for dealing with perfectionism because
as the writer and Lamont very poignant
Lee says in her book bird by bird
perfectionism is the voice of the
oppressor the enemy of the people now
before we move on I do want to say that
perfectionism isn't all bad in fact many
psychologists will separate
perfectionism into two different
categories adaptive and maladaptive
adaptive perfectionists are motivated by
their high standards they pursue their
goals without compromising their
self-esteem they're not hyper critical
of their work or themselves and they
invest massive amounts of time and
energy into projects that require a lot
of attention and focus and effort
maladaptive perfectionists on the other
hand feel constant pressure to meet an
unrealistic standard they procrastinate
because things are so hard to get into
they feel a lot of anxiety and sometimes
even depression because they're holding
themselves to an ideal they can't
possibly reach now I don't believe these
are too binary states there's certainly
a spectrum between perfectionism of the
adaptive and maladaptive sorts and for
you perfectionism probably has some
benefits but it probably also brings
along some problems and personally the
main problems I see with perfectionism
are number one it makes tasks seem
monumental because you want to do
perfectly on them so you procrastinate
number two constant tweaking and editing
will cause you to never actually publish
and put things out there and move on
because you're always second-guessing
your previous decisions number three
your skill development is hampered
because you aren't allowing yourself to
make mistakes which are absolutely
critical to the learning process and
lastly you have a lot of anxiety and
stress because you're holding yourself
to an unrealistic ideal and you're
constantly worried about your work being
judged so how do you overcome
perfectionism well number one you need
to realize that you're not perfect and
neither is any
and I realize the second half of that
statement can be really hard to
acknowledge sometimes because the
Internet is always presenting us with
things that are finished and polished
like we have so many connections to so
many people and they're all presenting a
tailored version of themselves to you
they're so proud to show off the fruits
of their labors but they never show off
the hours that went into it they never
show off the mistakes and the failures
that they had along the way and these
are vital parts of the learning process
you can't have success without these
mistakes so embrace imperfection embrace
mistakes realize it's going to happen
like think back to when you were a kid
you were learning to ride a bike you
probably fell off a ton of times you
probably still have scars and your
shoulders that remind you of those times
and you weren't worried at all about
riding the bike perfectly the first time
you just want to ride the bike you
probably wanted to get the training
wheels off and you try it and try it and
try it until you did it if it took so
many tries to learn to do something as
simple as riding a bike why do you think
you have to be able to write a paper or
give a speech perfectly on the first try
number two just get started and let your
work become a mess work in private and
don't worry about the state of the
project on the first pass through and is
meant more on writing Stephen King
advises to write with the door closed
and rewrite with the door open don't
worry about the state of your project
during its first stage just get it
created in its rough initial form and
then invite feedback and constructive
criticism once you're ready to start
shaping the prototype into something
that's truly worthy of being finished
number three work with a deadline now
this is the practice that's helped me
overcome my perfectionism the most when
I first started my youtube channel I had
a lot of other influences and creators
that I liked to watch and because of
that I had this excellent taste right
but I realized that I was a beginner and
if I wanted to meet that ideal standard
with my videos I would never be able to
do that and I would never put anything
out there so instead I told myself I'm
gonna put out a video every single week
and I remember after I released my first
video I was having a conversation with
my friend Matt and I told him a year
from now I want to have at least 50
videos out and putting those videos out
every single week as imperfect as they
may be has helped me progress a lot now
I realize that some people will say that
creating deadlines and forcing yourself
to put things out there at an arbitrary
time isn't necessary and indeed you need
time to meander through a project and
try things and work at your own pace if
that works for you if you believe that
that's fine but
remember there are differences between
adaptive and maladaptive perfectionism
if your perfectionism is causing you
anxiety and stress that I think it's a
really good idea to create that deadline
and force yourself to finish you need a
structure that forces you not to focus
on the minutiae of one project for too
long
number four focus on getting just a
little bit better each time if you
improve one percent each time you make
something then over time that progress
compounds and before you know it you've
mastered whatever it is you're learning
creating things putting them out there
and having the imperfections and
mistakes pointed out these are all parts
of the learning process that have to
happen skill and knowledge come through
countless iterations not through
executing perfectly on the first
iteration the skill that you gain
through making the first nine things
will allow you to hone the 10th one to a
degree you didn't even know was possible
when you were making the first one and
lastly let your influences inspire you
but don't measure yourself up against
them a beginner shouldn't measure their
work against that of a masters if you
were to start a YouTube channel tomorrow
and you put out your first video you
shouldn't compare it against somebody
else's 500th video that's not a fair
comparison the only thing you should
measure your work against is your
previous work and when you're looking at
things other people have made you can
let them inspire you you can let them
influence you and motivate you to
improve but don't hold your work up
against theirs and judge yourself based
on that standard so this is what I'm
going to end this video and to be honest
I feel that it's imperfect there's a lot
more I'd like to say on this topic
there's more research I came across and
my brain keeps throwing up things people
are going to bring up at the comments
counter arguments other points and I
want to cover them all but like I said
earlier there's a deadline and I just
have to finish this and put it out there
is it perfect no but I do think it's
useful and that is enough plus as a
friend of mine as a professional speaker
once told me the audience never knows
what you didn't say hopefully what I did
say was helpful to you in some way
thanks for watching hey there guys
thanks so much for watching this video
if you want to get new videos every
single week on being a more effective
student you can hit that big red
subscribe button right there and I also
wrote
how to get better grades which is
absolutely free if you want that click a
picture of the book and I'll send you if
you want to read the companion blog post
for this video you can put the orange
logo right there and last week's video
was about what to do when you're
studying at a time crunch one of my best
videos ever so definitely check it out
lastly I'm Tom frankly both on Twitter
and Instagram if you want to connect to
ask questions or you miss leave a
comment down below