Hey, what is going on guys? So today I
want to talk about a topic I get asked
about all the time and that is
self-discipline. And specifically what
I'm going to do in this video is share
an exercise that I've done in the past
and that I believe is one of the best
ways to build a universally applicable
mental toughness and self-discipline
that you can apply to basically any
situation. So here is the exercise and
it comes in the form of a challenge that
I'm going to issue you. If you're
willing, for the next 30 days, take an
ice cold shower every single day. Now, I
know some of you flinched just at the
thought of doing that, but like I said,
I've done this. In fact, I did it for 60
days, and now on a regular basis, I end
my showers cold, even though I do do
them warm at this point. So, the
question is, why is an ice cold shower
challenge the best way to build
self-discipline? Well, to answer that,
first I want to talk a little bit about
what self-discipline is. At its core,
self-discipline is the willingness to
accept discomfort. And that could be in
the form of physical pain or discomfort.
Or it could be in the form of the
discomfort that comes from denying
yourself instant gratification in
service of making progress on longerterm
goals. In either case, your ability to
deal with that discomfort is a skill
that must be built through repeated
exposure. It's as Aristotle once said,
or rather the historian Will Durant
paraphrased, we are what we repeatedly
do. Excellence then is not an act but a
habit. And if you take self-discipline,
which is one of the core components of
excellence, and slot it in there in
place of that word excellence, the quote
still holds up. And the great thing
about this process of building up
self-discipline is that no matter how
you do it, it's an adaptable skill. Much
like our focus or our willpower or the
muscles in our bodies, it's able to
tackle a variety of different
situations, even if it was trained in a
different way. So, we've laid the
foundation to self-discipline, but the
question still remains. Why the heck is
an ice cold shower challenge any better
than any other method for building that
mental toughness? And the answer is
twofold. First, and most importantly,
taking a cold shower is an exercise that
is particularly resistant to excuses.
So, take something else like writing a
term paper, for example. Say you've got
a term paper coming up and it's due in a
week. This is an opportunity for your
brain to come up with lots of insidious,
clever little rationalizations for not
doing it now. You might tell yourself,
"Hey, I've got plenty of time remaining.
No need to rush things now." In fact, I
do work better under a deadline anyway,
so I'll be more creative if I wait till
Friday to start, and I'm just going to
play some Mario Kart now because my
schedule seems to be cleared. In any
case, you're going to come up with a
rationalization that seems to make sense
instead of telling yourself the truth,
which is that you're lazy and you just
don't want to do the work. By contrast,
taking a cold shower affords you no
opportunity for these clever little
rationalizations because you are already
going to take a shower every day anyway.
So, you're left with nothing but a
simple binary decision. Either you turn
that handle to cold and embrace
discomfort headon, or you avoid that
discomfort and turn the handle to hot.
And regardless of what choice you make,
you know the reason you made it is
because of your ability and your
willingness to accept or not accept that
level of discomfort. The second reason
this is such a good exercise goes back
to what I was saying earlier. You were
going to take a shower anyway, so you're
not taking any extra time out of your
day to do this. Instead, you're just
facing that same decision you make every
single morning, and you're choosing
discomfort rather than comfort. And
every time you do it, you're building
that universal mental toughness that you
can use in every other situation. And it
really is universal. Otherwise, people
in boot camp wouldn't be forced to scrub
floors and toilets because it wouldn't
apply to combat situations. But it does.
And in the same way, a cold shower
challenge is going to apply to your
homework or that side project you've
been doing after you get home from work
or that gym session you've been trying
to convince yourself to go to. Because
all of these things draw from that same
reserve of willpower and grit and mental
toughness that you build every single
time you face discomfort willingly. So
that's it. I've said my piece and I
realize that not everyone is going to
like this challenge. And hey, I get it.
This is ice cold water coming down on
your face every single day for 30 days.
That's not a whole lot of fun. But like
I said, I've done this challenge myself.
In fact, for double the amount of time,
and I really did see results. Now, the
creative people among you might realize
that there are other things you could do
that you already do every day where you
could just choose the uncomfortable
option rather than the comfortable
option. So, if you have additional ideas
for self-discipline exercises, I would
love to hear from you down in the
comments below. Anyway, I hope you guys
enjoyed this video, and if you did, you
can give it a like to support this
channel. Also, if you haven't subscribed
yet and you want to get new videos on
productivity, on self-discipline, on
being a more effective learner, you can
subscribe right there. And on the
learning front, if you're in school and
you want to get a book on how to earn
better grades, whether you're in high
school or college or whatever, you can
get a free copy of the book I wrote by
clicking right there. You can listen to
our latest podcast episode right there.
And if you click right over there,
you'll find a video that I don't know
about right now, but hey, you'll
probably like it.