when it comes to taking multiple choice
tests there's this common piece of
advice that often gets thrown around
when and doubt always choose C right or
maybe for you it was B because this
advice comes from everywhere maybe you
heard it from your dad or your teacher
or you read it on the internet I'm
pretty sure that I heard it from some
kid in my eth grade history class named
Jimmy but as Abraham Lincoln once didn't
say always independently verify advice
given to you by eighth graders named
Jimmy true words have never not been
said so today we are going to go over
some more well-founded and useful advice
that you can use to make sure you Ace
that next multiple choice test you got
coming up in the future and I've got
five main strategies to go through as
well as one secret weapon of sorts so
let's just get started first off when
those test papers flutter downto your
desk don't just start immediately going
through the questions one by one in a
linear fashion instead take a few
minutes to go through and skim the test
and just get a general overview of the
questions now as you're doing this you
can answer any of the questions that
stand out is really really easy or that
you're really really confident in but
another thing you're doing by doing this
whole little skim once over for the test
before you actually start in Earnest is
you're priming your brain for some of
the questions and details that are on
the test as a whole and this can be
really really useful for a couple of
different reasons one you're priming
your brain to start thinking about some
of the harder questions and we're going
to get to that in a minute but number
two sometimes multiple choice tests will
have questions that hold details and
hints or sometimes outright full answers
to other questions on the test for
example say you're taking a history test
one day and you come across a question
like this which American president's
death caused Napoleon to order 10 days
of mourning in France now as you're
going over the answers you can eliminate
one of them right off the bat but the
other ones Thomas Jefferson John Adams
George Washington you don't know which
of the three is the correct answer so
maybe you skip it you go on into the
test and then later you come across a
question like true or false even though
Thomas Jefferson and John Adams were
bitter political Rivals during the
Heyday of their careers they eventually
regained their friendship and kept it
until both of their deaths in 1826 now
that question just established that
Thomas Jefferson and John Adams both
died in 1826 and say that you knew from
some other source that Napoleon himself
had died in 1821 if you knew that then
that question answers the previous
question because both Thomas Jefferson
and John Adams are not possible answers
therefore it's Washington these kind of
details and questions aren't always
going to crop up in your tests and in
any case you probably shouldn't waste a
whole ton of your test time digging
around for him because you know
preparation is a much better strategy
you should hopefully come into the test
prepared to answer most of the questions
in the first place but it can be helpful
in certain occasions so just prime your
brain with a little bit of a preliminary
past before you start in Earnest the
second technique on my list is what
Barbara Oakley's book aine for numbers
calls the hard start jump to easy
technique this is a technique where
basically you jump into a difficult
problem and you spend a couple of
minutes thinking really deeply about it
but if you can't get the answer to that
problem you move on now this is
something your teachers have probably
told you in the past just to save time
on your tests but there's another
benefit that they might not have have
told you about if you spend some time
thinking about a hard problem you're
engaging your brain's focused mode and I
know this focused and diffused dichotomy
is something I talk about a lot in these
videos but it's really really important
so while you're using Focus mode you are
concentrating on the problem and you're
using your conscious resources to try to
solve it but once you jump into a
different problem your subconscious
resources the more distributed parts of
your brain work on that difficult
problem in the background and then when
you go back to the problem a little bit
later you probably have a better chance
of answering it oh and my apologies to
Dr Oakley but we have got to get a
better name than hard start jump to easy
technique so I'm going to go ahead and
recoin it the tiny the tiger technique
because it's like that one boss battle
in Crash warped where you spend some
time fighting the boss and then you
switch over to avoiding these tigers and
go back and forth from there tip number
three is to make sure that you read each
question on your exam twice doing this
is really really important because
multiple choice questions can be tricky
and because they have a limited number
of answers and those answers are just
written out for you it can be really
tempting to simp skim over the question
very quickly and then go to the answer
that looks most familiar but professors
can be pretty sneaky when they're
writing these kinds of questions so you
need to watch out for a few things that
can trip you up for example some of the
questions on your exams might ask you
which of the following is not X Y or Z
and it can be really easy to fail to see
that word not if you're going through
really fast and just skimming the
questions other questions might actually
have more than one correct answer and
your job there will be to find the
answer that is most correct and of
course in that vein there are also all
sorts of questions that have all the
above or none of the above as potential
answers and I am not too proud to admit
that in several classes during my
college career I took tests very quickly
and failed to see these types of answers
on a few questions which I of course got
wrong tip number four is a tactic that I
found personally useful all throughout
high school and college and it's to
double check your answers as you get to
the end of each page of your test
instead of just waiting to do it all at
the end and the reason this is so useful
is that once you get to the end of a
page on your test you probably only have
five or 10 questions to go over and
because you have so few you're probably
not going to rush or get intimidated by
the number of questions you have to
check and that's going to decrease the
likelihood that you'll skip over a dumb
mistake or something that just should
glaringly stick out and that's going to
increase your scores now this is not a
replacement for giving your test a good
once over once you finished it and I
definitely think you should be budgeting
time with the outside of the test to do
that but by adding this technique into
your test taking Arsenal you can
increase your scores even more all right
let's move on to tip number five here so
if you come across a question that you
just can't get the answer to or maybe
you feel like the answer is on the tip
of your tongue which you just can't
quite get it try to Envision yourself in
the room in which you learn that piece
of information maybe it was your
classroom maybe it was your normal study
spot but either way science has shown
that if you can Envision the area where
you learn something it activates
something called context dependent
memory basically humans are more able to
remember things when they're in the
context or location in which they learn
them but research done in 1984 showed
that if people simply Envision the place
in which they learn something they can
sort of Channel some of that ability
even though they're not physically in
that room now if even that doesn't work
or maybe you've run across a question
where you just absolutely have no clue
what the answer is you've never seen it
before or you just can't eliminate any
of the choices whatsoever well it's time
to break out that secret weapon so
remember our friend Jimmy who gave us
that old advice you know when I doubt
pick C well yeah Jimmy was wrong but
that's okay because instead of following
some dumb rule or just randomly guessing
you can actually use statistic to
exploit the way in which human beings
typically write multiple choice tests
and that's because as the author William
Poundstone points out in his book rock
breaks scissors humans are pretty bad at
creating actual random distributions of
answers during his research Poundstone
collected over a 100 multiple choice
tests from all sorts of different
sources schools colleges driver's exams
online quizzes you name it he got it and
that total over 2400 questions and what
he learned from doing statistical
analysis on all those questions was
pretty surprising first off he did
discover biases for individual letter
answers but those biases changed based
on how many answers were available on
the question for three answer questions
you know a b c there was no bias and for
four answer questions the bias turned
out to be B not C though it was a very
statistically small Advantage 28% versus
the expected 25% and then when we go
over to five answer questions you know a
through e it was actually e that was the
most common answer and C was the least
commonly right answer those findings are
just the tip of the iceberg though and
personally I find them far less
interesting than all the other things he
discovered including the fact that with
true false questions there is a definite
bias towards true answers being correct
in his research 56% of the time true was
the correct answer and only 44% of the
time was false the correct answer even
more interesting and potentially useful
to you is the fact that a question has a
higher than average likelihood of not
having the same answer as the question
that came before it so if you have one
question on a test where you knew the
answer was C you're definitely sure of
that and then you move on to the next
question and you're stuck or maybe
you've narrowed it down to C or D then
it's likely that D is the answer not C
and perhaps most astoundingly for
questions ah had either in all the above
or none of the above answer present that
answer was correct 52% of the time which
means that if you're stuck on a question
and you can't narrow it down that
answers your best bet now even though I
had fun calling these findings a secret
weapon of sorts I really want to
emphasize that you should only use them
when you're completely at a loss and you
have to take a shot in the dark you
should use every other technique in the
book to narrow things down to give
yourself some space to use that tiny the
tiger technique because at the end of
the day all you're doing is exploiting
the way that people write tests you're
not actually learning anything and
you're not actually using your mental
faculties to work with the actual
information and content of the exam
anyway beyond all the tips in this video
the most important aspect to your
success on any multiple choice test or
any kind of test at all is preparation
and if you want to learn how to prepare
for your tests more effectively I
actually just put together a resource on
my website called The Ultimate Guide to
AC your final exams and it collects
everything that I've ever made related
to exams so if you haven't seen all
those videos or you're looking for a
specific tip you might want to check it
out you can find it on the card on the
screen right now or in the description
down below beyond that if you enjoyed
this video you can give it a like to
support this channel it's much
appreciated and if you have additional
tips on acing your multiple choice tests
that I didn't talk about right here I
would love to hear from you down in the
comments below if you want to subscribe
to this Channel and get new videos on
being a more effective student every
single week you can click right there
and you can also click right there if
you want to get a free copy of my book
on earning better grades now the
recommended video this week is actually
something related to this because it's
about a technique called confidence
tracking that can help you even further
increase your scores on multiple choice
tests so check it out