one of the biggest sources of stress in
my life is that I have too many
interests and I often find it difficult
to find just one pursuit to put all of
my focus and energy on and I got a lot
of questions from students and viewers
who have the exact same problem so if
you feel like you have this problem as
well you're not alone in fact this is a
really common problem and it's often
been referred to as the Paradox of
choice one person who has done a lot of
research on this problem is the Columbia
School of Business Professor Sheena iar
and she summed this problem up really
well when she said there are times when
the presence of more choices can make us
choose things that are not good for us
for me the clearest example is that the
more retirement fund options a person
has the less likely they are to save for
their old age so here is the big
important question how do you narrow
down this ridiculous amount of choices
you have to a few things that you can
really focus your time attention and
energy on well there's a story about the
billionaire investor Warren Buffett that
might actually help The Story Goes that
Buffett was talking with the pilot of
his private jet and the pilot asked him
about how he could narrow down his
career goals and really focus so Warren
asked him to do an exercise he said
first write down your top 25 career
goals then once you have that list
Circle the five most important goals on
the list and come back to me so the guy
went and did it he wrote down those 25
goals he circled five and he came back
and essentially at this point he had two
lists list a which were those five most
important goals and list B which were
the 20 other goals that weren't as
important so at this point the pilot
says okay I think I got it now the five
that you had me Circle are the most
important things I should be focusing on
whereas the 20 I didn't Circle are less
important so I can practice those
intermittently when I have some spare
time but I shouldn't focus on them as
much and Buffett's response was no the
list of 20 items you didn't circle is
now your avoid at all Costless these are
goals and interests you have that have
enough pull on your interests that they
will distract you from the five most
important goals if you want to be a
superstar at something you can't afford
to be diversifying your attention across
all these interests you have to focus
now it is likely that this story is
actually fake I've read in several
places online that Buffett himself has
said that he didn't have this
conversation with his Pilot however even
if a famous person didn't give these
instructions and have this guy do this
exercise I think the exercise is
actually still useful to do but I want
to do you one better you can definitely
go through that exercise but I want to
share something that I discovered last
week that I have adopted in my own life
there's a guy I've been following for a
number of years online named Derek cers
and he's an author a public speaker and
the founder of a company called CD bab
he's had a lot of success in his life so
I've been really inspired by his
writings and especially this booknotes
section on his website that he has where
he summarizes books and last week I saw
that he put something on his website
called a now page it's basically a page
where he writes what I'm doing now he
lists out a few of his main priorities
like being a full-time dad being a
programmer answering emails and writing
blog posts and then he says these are my
priorities right now and because of that
I'm not going to accept New
Opportunities I don't want to speak
publicly and I'm going to focus my time
on these things I've listed so this page
serves a couple of different functions
number one it's a public Declaration of
his main priorities which can help him
justify saying no to other opportunities
and explain that to other people who
bring those opportunities to him but
it's also a private reminder for when
he's feeling unfocused of what he should
be focusing his mind on now I think this
now page is a fantastic idea so just
like the impossi concept that my friend
Joel came up with I have appropriated
for my own uses and now you can go to
college infogeek
docomo to see what I'm doing with my
life on that page you'll see a similar
layout to Derrick's page I've got what
I'm doing now with a few different
priorities listed out but there is a key
difference since I'm a bit earlier on in
my career than drik is I've decided to
be a little less staunch about saying no
to New Opportunities on that page than
he has been on mine I say that I'm still
open to New Opportunities I really value
spontaneity and novelty but 90% of my
time is still going to go towards those
main priorities so if you're a student
or you're early on your career and you
want to use this page for your own
purposes my suggestion is to be a little
bit more open to other opportunities and
take a stand in that camp but still be
focusing the majority of your attention
on the priorities you've already set out
on the page so that is all I got for you
in this video if you'd like to see my
page I've got a link down in the
description and also on the card right
now and if you want to make your own
page well I've got a tutorial on how to
build your own website on my site that
I'll link to in the description you can
also use something simpler like
wordpress.com or even Tumblr if you want
a free and simple option or if you don't
want to make it public you could even
just put it in a Word document or an
Evernote document just to be a private
reminder to keep your own mind focused
on your priorities that's all I've got
for today so if you enjoyed this video
give it a like so other people can find
this Channel and if you have additional
tips that have helped you to focus your
priorities share them down in the
comments and other than that I will see
you as always next week
hey guys thanks so much for watching
this video If you want to get new tips
on how to be a more effective student
every single week you can click that big
red subscribe button right there I also
wrote a free book on how to earn better
grades so if you want to get a copy you
click a picture of the book and if you
want to find a summary and links to both
my now page dereck's original now page
and some additional now pages that other
people have been making you can click
the orange logo right there to go to the
blog post last week we did a fun bonus
video about my top 10 favorite fiction
books so check it out if you haven't
seen it and if you want to connect with
me I'm on Twitter at Town Frankle also
on Instagram at frankly and you can
leave a comment below as well