this video is brought to you by skill
share an online learning platform with
over 16,000 courses that you can use to
improve your life and learn new skills
and the first 500 people that sign up
with link in the description down below
will get a 2 month free trial alright so
tell me if the scenario seems familiar
to you you get an interest and you want
to learn a new skill or you have a goal
in mind that you want to achieve and you
realize it's going to take daily
practice and at first that's easy
because you're on what we call the
honeymoon phase it's novel it's exciting
and you can't really think of anything
else but that thing but of course to
learn any skill worth learning to
achieve any big goal you need daily
consistent practice over a long period
of time and that honeymoon period
doesn't always cover it so how do you
make sure you stay consistent over the
long term and keep putting in that daily
practice even once that honeymoon period
is over and the novelty has sort of worn
off well that's what I want to cover in
this video and we're going to talk about
a technique called
a 20-second rule which you can use to
make sure that that's exactly what
you're doing I learned about this
technique in a book called the happiness
advantage by an author named Shawn
anchor and it's based on another
technique in psychology that was created
by a psychologist named and gonna need
your help on pronunciation for this one
I don't speak Hungarian but it looks
like me hi to sends me hi e yeah that
one
anyway the technique is called
activation energy and essentially this
refers to the effort or willpower or
time that it takes to go from wherever
you are right now into the actual act of
practicing and as you can see from my
very scientific graph right here as the
activation energy required for any
activity goes up the willpower required
to get into it does as well and that's
why it's so hard to go out and do things
like ride your bike or practice guitar
and why it's so easy to play candy crush
on your phone so essentially the twenty
second rule is all about lowering this
activation energy for positive behaviors
that you want to do on a consistent
basis and in case you're wondering here
twenty seconds isn't some scientifically
precise number here it's more a marker
to illustrate the main point which is
that you need to start modifying your
environment to put whatever it is you
want to do consistently on the path of
least resistance
to illustrate this think about your
living room or your dorm room wherever
did you spend most of your time indoors
how is that set up if it's set up with a
lot of video games with your TV and your
mote then that's the path of least
resistance when you come into the room
you're likely to pick that up and start
playing video games what did you change
that a little bit what if you put the
controller and the remote in the drawer
somewhere that's out of sight and
instead you put a book on the copy table
or you put an instrument right there
where you could grab it well then when
you come in you'd be more likely to grab
that book and do some reading or grab
the instrument and do some practicing
now we're going to go more in depth on
this in a second but I do want to note
one thing which relates to that whole
idea of putting the remote and the
controller in the drawer which is that
there is a flip side to the 20-second
rule if there's a behavior you don't
want to do so much like playing video
games or procrastinating going on social
media sites then you can increase that
activation energy one of my personal
favorite examples of this particular
principle comes from the creator of the
webcomic xkcd Randall Munroe because he
found that he was having trouble going
on social media sites and distracting
himself when he should have been working
so what he did is he set up a system
where he would have to turn his computer
off and turn it back on before he could
switch any task so instead of just going
from his work to Facebook he would have
to reboot his computer go to Facebook
then reboot it again to get back to his
work so he wasn't really blocking
himself from going to these distracting
websites but he was setting up the
process that took so much effort that he
just didn't want to do it and if you
want to put this principle into action
yourself as well you could start
rebooting your computer but there's also
a Chrome extension called crack book
which essentially creates a delay before
you can go on any distracting website
that you set so for example if you
wanted to go on Facebook you could but
you'd have to wait 30 seconds for the
page to load
[Music]
Chrome extensions and xkcd aside what I
want to focus on now is the positive
side of that 20-second rule how do you
reduce the friction required to getting
into whatever it is you want to make
consistent daily progress on now I'm
going to get into a few specific
examples of goals that I'm making
progress on myself in a second in order
to illustrate this for you first I want
to talk about the idea here in general
so whatever you want to make progress on
whatever goal you have picture in your
mind and sit down and create a plan for
how you can start modifying your
environment ask yourself what kind of
tools do I need two practices have it if
you're playing guitar obviously you need
a guitar if you're doing electric guitar
you need like an amp and a cord you need
a pic so ask yourself like how can I
make these things more accessible to me
also ask yourself what kind of
maintenance tasks do I have to do on a
regular basis that don't really count as
practice but that still have to be done
nonetheless I do a lot of cycling and as
anybody who's ever ridden a bike knows
you have to keep your tires pumped up
but because I live in a really tall
apartment building taking my bike pump
down from the apartment to the by garage
pumping it up and then going back to my
apartment and back down drive my bike is
a huge pain in the butt so instead I put
my bike pump in my car trunk that way I
can grab my bike ride it over my car
pump the tires up and I'm on my way you
could also apply this concept to your
learning materials as well for example a
lot of you guys have asked me how I
create the animations that you see in my
videos and do that I use a program
called Adobe After Effects now After
Effects is one beast of a program it's
ridiculously complex and it took me a
long time to learn and to learn it
I watched video tutorials online and I
took online courses at places like
Skillshare but I also implemented the
20-second rule here as well one way I
did this was by creating what I like to
call a default project this is basically
a project that spent a lot of time
setting up that already contains some
templates and a lot of the images and
sound effects I use that way when I come
into After Effects to make my video for
the week it is basically ready for me to
create whatever it is I want to create
and if I want to learn some new
technique I don't have to spend a whole
lot of time setting things up I can just
jump right into the animation process
the other way I do this is that when I'm
taking a new course like on Skillshare
to learn a new technique I will bookmark
that course and put it right up in my
Chrome bookmarks bar that way when I
want to
I can just click it and instantly get
into the content instead of having to go
through a bunch of menus and type a
bunch of things by the way if this is
something that you want to do Skillshare
is an excellent place to do it they have
a ton of courses on animating with After
Effects ranging from a beginners course
with over five hours of content that
covers all the basics to these more
intermediate hyper-focused courses that
teach you how to make one really cool
thing and I found personally when I go
through a few of those I start to pick
up some little tricks that I can use in
my own animations to take things up to
the next level and that range of content
isn't just limited to after effects or
even animation Skillshare actually has
over 16,000 courses in a ton of
different topics including graphic
design photography web development
cooking music production even
presentation skills anyone can sign up
and take a class they can dig into the
example projects and files that are
included with many of the classes on the
site and they can even teach a class of
their own a premium membership gives you
access to unlimited learning and starts
at around 10 bucks a month so it's
basically a Netflix subscription that
you feel good about and the first 500
people who go down in the description
below and click the link to sign up are
going to get a two month free trial all
right so to round this video I want to
give you a few specific examples of
skills that I'm working on and how I've
implemented the 20-second rule in teach
them and the first one is with guitar
playing I started playing guitar when I
was around 12 years old but at some
point during my college career my guitar
and all of my gear got stolen and for a
long time I never went and replaced it
because I kind of wanted to play guitar
but I knew that it was like at least a
couple of days shipping away or I'd have
to drive to the guitar store and I
always let that friction defeat me but
now that I've moved to Denver I've been
trying to make a lot of changes in my
life and one of the things I resolve to
do is to become a musician to actually
learn how to play guitar and do
something with it so I went to the store
I bought an acoustic guitar which I can
just pick up and play with no amps no
cords no nothing and I also bought a
guitar stand so I could put the guitar
right in the living room and since I
started doing that I have practiced
every single day because it's just right
there I can just pick it up and play but
I have it limited it to just that I've
also put a couple of apps to write on
the home screen in my phone I have my
guitar tuner app which is called guitar
tuna and it is an amazing app by the way
and I also have the ultimate Guitar Tabs
app right there so if I get the
operation to learn it song I can look it
up within seconds and start practicing
I'm also applying this concept to my
exercise habit you guys follow me on
instagram you'll know that right now I'm
doing a 30 day challenge to exercise
intensely at least once a day for 30
days straight and that public
accountability definitely gives me
motivation but I also knew I needed to
reduce the friction and the activation
energy required to go workout so every
night before I go to bed I pass my gym
bag I fill up my water bottle I lay out
my gym clothes and I make sure my
headphones are charged that way when I'm
ready to go to the gym in the morning I
can just walk out the door and there's
no fuss so at this point you know how to
use 20-second rule you know how to break
it down into a process and you've seen
how I do it myself so now I'm curious
what goal are you working on and how are
you going to implement this rule into
your own life I'd love to hear from you
in the comments down below because as
Stephen Covey once said common sense
isn't always common practice so if you
found this video helpful let me know
down below how you are going to make
this common practice in your own life
and thank you so much for watching if
you haven't subscribed it you can
subscribe right there for new videos
every single week you can also get a
copy of my book right there you can
check out early this podcast episode
which is all about how to get started
investing right there and if you want to
watch another video on this channel
right there is your best bet once again
I want to say thank you to Skillshare
for sponsoring this video and if you're
interested in trying them out make sure
you click that link down below and sign
up for the free trial before those 500
spots are filled and I will see you next
week