welcome back to the procrastination
series that I have been intending to do
for the past three years and yes if
you're wondering this series is a self
intervention for me
so in yesterday's video we went deep
into the science of procrastination
there were lots of research studies lots
of results lots of insights and if you
haven't seen that I'm gonna have it down
in the description below but this video
is gonna be a lot more actionable
because in this part 2 of our
procrastination series we're gonna be
talking about how to stop
procrastinating in the moment when you
notice yourself putting things off and
to do that we are going to go through a
process of 6 steps starting with a step
that you might not have thought to do
otherwise but that science actually
shows to be effective which is to
forgive yourself for any prior
procrastination if you remember from
yesterday's video we talked about a
researcher named Timothy pitcher who's
done quite a lot of research into the
subject of procrastination and one of
the studies that he did examine the role
of guilt and procrastination and the
forgiveness of that guilt when he
surveyed 119 college students he found
that students who took the time to
deliberately forgive themselves for
procrastination in preparation for a
midterm exam were actually less likely
to procrastinate on future exams so
before you get into any of the other
steps in this process if you are a
chronic procrastinator if you've been
kicking yourself for wasting tons of
time first forgive yourself and it's
also useful to realize that going
forward there is never going to be a
perfect moment to study there's never
gonna be a perfect time to do it and
this is one of the stories we tell
ourselves right we think that in the
future things are going to be better the
stars are going to be aligned we're
going to be in a much better position to
actually get to work and what you have
to do is tell yourself that this moment
right now it's imperfect it's not
exactly what you want it to be but it is
passable it's enough for you to get to
work and at least make some progress
from there it is time to move on to step
2 in the process which is to redefine
success to fit your present
circumstances if you are already late on
a project or a homework assignment and
you've put things off to the point where
now it's unrealistic to finish things
with the original due date then even if
you try to work really really hard
you're likely to fail and as we talked
about in the first video in this series
part of the temporal motivation theory
or the procrastination equation is
expectancy when we don't have an
expectation that we can achieve the goal
we set out to do we are much
likely to procrastinate on it or to put
it off so clearly if you're sitting
there looking at the hand that you have
now dealt yourself and you realize that
failure is likely option you're probably
not going to be very motivated to work
so instead sit down and define a new
version of what success looks like for
example if the original deadline is now
unrealistic you may need to set a new
deadline maybe you even need to email
your teacher or email your group members
and ask them for an extension or for an
example that isn't based on time if you
realize that you're not gonna get a 4.0
the semester and that's what you wanted
to do sit down and redefine your goal to
be maybe a 3.8 that way you can actually
succeed from where you are right now of
course you do want to make sure that
this goal is still fulfilling and
challenging to you because if you make
it too easy it's not gonna be motivating
for different reasons and you're not
gonna feel good about yourself even if
you do manage to achieve it all right
steps 1 & 2 are now out of the way those
were kind of mental steps about kind of
getting your brain in the right place to
get your work done now we are moving to
step 3 which is the first really
actionable tangible step in the process
and it's to remove potential short-term
distractions from your environment for
me the first item of business here is to
clear my workspace close my tabs close
programs that are unrelated to my work
clear my desk off basically try to get
my space as optimized for the one task I
have decided to do and if you can't get
your workspace into the right
configuration for doing this then you
may want to change it if your dorm is a
bad place to work for example then maybe
go to the library or go to a coffee shop
but you do want to make sure that you
don't fall into the trap of finding a
work space that is perfect because no
work space is and if you get into that
trap trying to find the place that is
the most optimized place for working
then you're never actually going to
start your work you're just gonna keep
searching secondly it's probably a good
idea to have a list somewhere on your
computer or on a scrap of paper where
you can write down errands that come up
or small tasks that you think of doing
so you can do them later I'm not sure
about you but one of my biggest
procrastination triggers is convincing
myself that I just need to go check my
email or check a few other things or do
some small tasks before I sit down and
do the thing that I really should be
doing and I have had days go by even
weeks sometimes where I have filled my
time with those small tasks that really
aren't all that important and I never
actually get the real work done the real
effective work that moves the needle in
my business
or my work so make sure that you have
that list that you diligently write
things down when they come in to your
attention then later on when you have
some time you can probably batch all of
those tasks at once next try to dedicate
at least a little bit of time to taking
care of your biological needs if you're
hungry make sure you eat a snack maybe
have a bottle of water or some tea or
coffee next to you on your desk go to
the bathroom and if you're feeling tired
or fatigued at least take five minutes
to go for a quick walk before you start
working once you have checked off all
those little biological boxes though
you're gonna want to make sure to one
get comfortable so if you're energetic
maybe try to find a standing desk or a
counter you can work at otherwise just
make sure that you are seated with good
posture and you're wearing clothes that
make you comfortable within the
temperature of the room that you're in
and lastly and you knew this was coming
ask yourself do I need the Internet do I
need access to a lot of the tools that
are kind of like defaults in my life do
I need my phone remember when you are
really close to the Internet when you're
really close to the things that could be
potential distractions
your impulsiveness is higher you are
more likely to give in to those
distractions so maybe put those away or
maybe disconnect from the internet on
your laptop all together step 4 in the
process is to break your task down into
smaller more actionable subtasks so
here's the thing when you aren't working
on a project you're never actually
working on that project as a whole
you're only ever working on one specific
task and then in retrospect all those
add up to look like a big project but
when you're looking forward and you're
telling yourself I have to do that
entire project it looks a lot more
difficult and as we talked about in the
first video the series expectancy the
belief that you can actually do the
thing you've set up to do is a huge
factor in whether or not you're going to
procrastinate a good example of this is
the tough motor that I decided to run a
couple of months ago this was 10 miles
with more than 20 obstacles and going
into it I was pretty confident that I
could do it but it still seemed like a
huge challenge
so once the starting gun was fired and
we actually got to start running I
didn't think of it as a ten-mile
challenge I wasn't thinking about all
the obstacles to come instead my goal at
any given moment was just to make it to
the next obstacle and of course I did
eventually cross the finish line
shivering and on the verge of
hypothermia actually but I did finish it
and it was a result of finishing one
tasks at a time and as those stacked up
one after the other they formed a huge
project but in the moment I was never
thinking about the project as a whole
and this is exactly how you should think
of your project think about it in terms
of the individual task that needs to be
done next the next step and speaking of
next steps the next step in this process
is to reframe your task as input based
rather than output based what I mean by
this is instead of focusing on the thing
you need to do even if it does feel
small and actionable instead try asking
yourself to simply work for 20 minutes
or work for 25 minutes in the case of
the pro Maduro technique and this is
something that I've talked about many
times in previous videos I have made an
entire video about it but in case you
haven't heard me talk about it before
here is the ten-second version
essentially the Pomodoro Technique has
you pick one task to work on you sit
down you set an actual physical timer
for 25 minutes and you only work on that
task during that time and what makes
this technique so effective and why I
use it almost every single day is that
it reframes your task whatever the task
is no matter how difficult it is it
refrains it and makes it just work for
25 minutes which is something that you
know you can do finally for our sixth
step in the process if you are starting
a brand new task then make that first
Pomodoro session or that first input
based session simply be the act of
setting things up to do that task by
this I mean instead of actually diving
in and working on the parts of the task
that you know are difficult see what you
can set up around it and I actually did
that for this video series during the
editing process instead of starting the
edit right away which I know is
difficult and frustrating sometimes I
first set a timer and I set up the file
structure for it I set up all the
folders all the quick access links all
the little things that I do for every
single video that just make the editing
process more convenient and as often
happens when I do these Pomodoro
sessions I kind of got into the zone and
once all that little setup work was done
I actually spent about a full hour
editing before I took my first break and
even if for some reason you don't find
yourself in the flow state after doing
this well you have at least put in about
20 or 25 minutes of work getting
everything set up so when you come back
for the next work session it's all kind
of ready for you now in the next and
final video in the series we're going to
talk about some more high level concepts
that can help you become less
Nader overall and kind of shed that
label of chronic procrastinator if you
identify with it but at least for now
with the process we've just outlined you
now have the tools to stop
procrastinating in the moment of
whatever it is you have been putting off
now as I may have mentioned before there
was a ton of research that went into
this miniseries one of the most
important and useful sources that I
consulted was Barbara Oakley's book a
mind for numbers which in addition to
having several great chapters on
procrastination is also just one of the
best books that I have ever come across
for anyone wanting to learn more
effectively across the board and that is
why if you've not already read this book
I highly recommend that you pick it up
or potentially listen to it on audible
which is the world's best place to get
your hands on audiobooks I have been an
audible subscriber for years one of the
most useful subscriptions that I have
and if you're not already a subscriber
as well now would be one of the best
times ever to get started because for a
limited time you can get three months of
audible for just 695 per month by going
over to audible.com slash Thomas and
signing up or by texting Thomas to 500
500 on your phone audibles library of
audiobooks is absolutely massive with an
unmatched selection of titles ranging
from personal development to science
fiction biographies they've got all the
bestsellers lots of obscure stuff and
once you have that membership you're
going to access to three different
titles every single month one from that
huge library and to audible originals
that you cannot get anywhere else
additionally their membership is very
flexible for example the credits that
you get every single month actually roll
over if you don't use them so if you
happen to download a really long audio
book one month and you don't use your
credit the next month it's just gonna
roll over and you're gonna have to the
following month which is pretty sweet
and if you happen to use one of those
credits to download an audiobook thee
just don't like you can very easily
exchange it for another audiobook in
their library with no questions asked
plus if you ever do decide to cancel
your membership every audiobook you've
downloaded is yours to keep forever
you'll always have access to that
library no matter what best of all like
I mentioned a little bit earlier for a
limited time you can get three months of
audible for just 695 a month that is
over half off their normal price so
you're definitely going to want to go
over to audible.com slash Thomas and
sign up or text Thomas to five hundred
five hundred on your phone as always big
thanks to audible for sponsoring this
video and being a huge supporter of my
channel and if you guys enjoyed this
video in this entire miniseries
definitely give it a like and make sure
you subscribe so you get new videos when
they come out
every single week you can also click
right there to get a free copy of my
book and how to earn better grades which
might be pretty useful with finals
coming up you can follow me on instagram
at tom frankly or you can click right
here to get one more video on this
channel thanks so much for watching and
I will see you in the next one