one of the most important lessons I
learned in the process of going through
college and moving to the professional
world and eventually transitioning to
working for myself is that in most cases
feedback is a luxury now when we're in
school and college we don't realize this
because school and college are
institutions that are built to give us
feedback we get graded at almost
everything we do and there are
professors and teachers who are paid to
show us our mistakes and to help us move
forward but once we move into our
careers we're often given jobs that
don't come with a whole lot of regular
day-to-day feedback there's usually not
somebody telling us how we did each
individual piece of work and there's
also usually not a whole lot of
appreciation that comes from the hard
work we put in now this got me thinking
about my own job because as somebody who
makes YouTube videos for a living I get
a lot of feedback on my work almost
every single video I make gets a lot of
comments for people telling me they
appreciate the things I make and I
absolutely love getting that feedback it
validates my work it motivates me to
create more but it also got me thinking
I don't work disproportionately harder
than everyone else and my job isn't
disproportionately more useful yet a lot
of people who work really really hard
don't get that kind of feedback so why
is this I think the answer is that it
really comes down to expectations for
some jobs there isn't really a set
expectation or status quo out there so
by the very virtue of doing that work by
putting a video out there I'm exceeding
somebody's expectations I have the
opportunity to Delight somebody simply
by virtue of creating a video now if
Delight is one of the emotions that can
cause people to naturally want to give
feedback the other one is disgust or
disappointment when something isn't
working as it should but there's an
expectation already set people are apt
to give negative feedback the problem
with this comes the fact that a lot of
people have jobs but there's only really
two possible States either everything is
broken and people are giving that
negative feedback or it's at the status
quo where everything is as it should be
in which case people don't really think
about it they ignore it for example if
you live in an apartment think about the
job of running that apartment complex if
your heater is working if your water is
running everything is hunky dory you're
not thinking about your apartment
manager job but once your heater goes
out or somebody breaks a bottle in the
parking lot no one cleans it up now
you're mad and the only feedback your
apartment manager is going to get is
your complaint another good example is
the roads you drive on when the roads
are in good condition you don't think
about them because you don't have to and
now you can put your mind on wherever
you're going the only time you do think
about the roads is when they're broken
and then you just want the city to come
fix them or when there's a construction
crew out fixing them then you just want
that construction crew out of the way
and this is the problem I see so much
honest hard work goes into meeting
expectations that you already have and
when those expectations are Met You
don't notice that work now from your
perspective this is fine because it
allows you to think about everything
else that's going on in your life but
from the perspective of the person who
put that work in they're not getting any
validation for that work they did so
because of that I want to give you a
little challenge in this video but
before I do it I want to dedicate this
video to the people who work so hard at
simply meeting the expectations that are
already set for all you whose work goes
into simply meeting the status quo thank
you you probably don't get told this
enough but you really make people's
lives easier you make their day go
smoother you keep problems to a minimum
and you make everybody happy even if
they don't notice the work that went
into making them happy and if this video
resonates with you and you're thinking
of leaving a comment to give me some
feedback I definitely still appreciate
that feedback but here's my challenge
think about somebody else in your life
who also could use some feedback for the
hard work they're doing it takes
deliberate effort to notice that hard
work and to give positive feedback
because work that goes into meeting
expectations kind of Fades into the
background but I think if we can do this
as a population we're going to make
everyone's lives better so that's all I
have for this video hopefully you
enjoyed it and I will see you next
week hey guys thanks so much for
watching this video If you want to get
new videos on being a more effective
student every single week you can click
that big red subscribe button right
there I also wrote a book on how to earn
better grades and if you would like a
free copy of it click the book and I'll
send you one if you'd like to go to the
summary blog post for this video and
also maybe check out some articles on my
website you can click the orange logo
right there in last week's video I
answered the frequently Asked question
of what's in my backpack so if you're
curious about that click the thumbnail
and check it out lastly if you have
questions or just want to connect I'm on
Twitter at tomf frankley or you can
leave a comment down below thanks