it's 3:00 p.m. and your motivation to do
literally anything has evaporated you
feel tired you can't focus and the idea
of starting any of the tasks on your
to-do list is just mentally exhausting
in other words you've hit the afternoon
slump and you're not alone millions of
people around the world hit this wave of
tiredness during the early afternoons
every single day which is actually a
problem for me because people who are
tired tend not to watch YouTube videos
for quite as long so let me help you out
real quick in frame
this is helping are you awake okay
hopefully that helped at least somewhat
let's get back to video so like I just
said this is something that happens to
millions of people if you get tired in
the afternoon if you feel like you
should be going to bed but for some
reason the sun's still out well that is
absolutely common experience so what I
want to do today is share a three step
process that you can go through whenever
you find yourself in an afternoon slump
or battling that afternoon brain fog
going through these things can help you
gain back at least some of your energy
to tackle the rest of your to-do list
before you end the day but before we get
into that we do want to answer the
question of why does this happen in the
first place because there are definitely
some controllable factors that
contribute to the afternoon slump but
part of it is actually natural part of
it is due to something called our
circadian rhythm which is essentially
this internal clock that helps to keep
our body's internal processes
synchronized with the day and night
cycle which helps us go to sleep at the
right times and in doing some research
for this video I found out that there
are actually two parts of the day where
we actually have a dip and energy so
according to the sleep foundation's
website for most adults the biggest dip
in energy happens during the middle of
the night between 2:00 and 4:00 a.m.
which is the time where most people are
just fast asleep snooze and weigh like a
rock actually rocks don't snooze but
there is a another dip and energy just
after lunchtime around 1:00 to 3:00 p.m.
when they start to crave that post-lunch
nap but another website that I looked at
Science Daily said this in a strict
sense circadian rhythms are endo jenia
Slee generated and although the
definition for an
Jenny ously and I'm not even sure if I'm
pronouncing that correctly but I didn't
know what it meant when I was doing this
research so I'll put it there although
they can be modulated by external cues
such as sunlight and temperature and
keep that in mind for later on in the
video because what this is saying is
that circadian rhythms are for the most
part internally set you can't do a whole
lot to control them but some things do
affect them and with that let's go over
to step one in the process which is to
refuel your body is essentially an
engine and what you put into it the
quality of what you put into it and the
time at which you feel it these all
factor into how energetic you're going
to feel at all different times of the
day so in the afternoons when I start
feeling tired this is the first thing
that I think to do I want to get
something to eat get some to drink and
usually the first thing that I reach for
is either a glass of water or like a can
of sparkling water I think this is the
the Michael Michael Buble kind that's
how you pronounce it right Buble and
actually like sparkling water a little
more than regular water because when I
was in college I was super addicted to
energy drinks and I kind of identified
the reason for that it wasn't
necessarily the caffeine it wasn't
necessarily the taste it was actually
the fact that the energy drink and the
colorful can and everything in the
carbonation were sort of novel it kind
of injected a little bit of excitement
into an otherwise boring afternoon study
session and it was actually the power of
habit that helped me to differentiate
these different reasons for my cravings
for terrible unhealthy energy drinks
because there was a part of the book
where he was talking about this
afternoon habit that he had to get a
cookie every single day and he started
asking himself like what is the reward
I'd get for getting this cookie is it
the taste is the energy boost and he
actually came to the conclusion that no
it's just this ritual that allows me to
get it from my desk and then it gives me
an opportunity to socialize with some of
my co-workers so he just changed his
habit up to go to the water cooler or
something like that so we could still
talk to the co-workers so reading that
actually helped me to identify the
factors that caused my craving for those
terrible unhealthy energy drinks the
taste the caffeine levels Andals the
novelty factor and then I realized that
sparkling water especially flavored
sparkling water like this fills two of
those three categories and if I want
caffeine I can obviously go for tea or
I do want to talk about that as well
because tea and coffee can be useful in
the afternoons but you need to
understand how your body reacts to
caffeine later in the day
there are studies out there to show that
caffeine even six hours before bedtime
can significantly impact the quality of
your sleep in a negative way but
everyone's mileage may vary so some
people may be able to have a cup of
coffee at 4:00 in the afternoon while
other people if they have caffeine at
any time in the day that has a p.m. in
it they're not gonna be able to go to
sleep
so again do some testing if you want to
use caffeine in the afternoons and you
can also pair it with a light snack and
if you're gonna go for a snack the main
thing here is don't just reach for
simple sugars don't go for like candy or
soda especially but also if you're just
going for fruit you're just taking in
simple sugars this causes a spike in
your blood sugar with a subsequent crash
so you want to pair that with some
complex carbohydrates maybe some
whole-wheat bread or maybe some proteins
like a hard-boiled egg in fact my best
friend Martin who helped me write the
script for this video listed that you
should put a hard-boiled egg inside of a
banana which I sat there and thought
about for a second and I still can't
envision how you do it but if any of you
out there know what he means like put it
in the comments below because I'm kind
of stumped here anyway step 2 in the
process is to reset this means step away
from your desk and take a break from
your work now for me the ultimate wavery
setting is to go outside if you'll
remember earlier in the video I talked
about how the circadian rhythm is for
the most part endo genis Lee I think
that's how you pronounce it but endo
genis lee generated or controlled but
that there are some factors that you can
use to influence it one of them being
sunlight exposure so this is kind of my
main thing whenever I feel tired in the
afternoons I am reaching for our glass
of water or maybe make it some coffee
depending on the time but the next thing
is I'm going outside for a walk where
I'm gonna take a break to go for a
workout so I'm going to go outside and
do some skateboarding or rollerblading
but whatever it is I want to get outside
and get some sunlight exposure because
exposure to light especially sunlight
can be a cue to wake your body up
sunlight is actually one of those
external factors that really plays a
part in how your circadian rhythm is
governed and if for some reason you just
can't go outside you just don't want to
exercise you're trying to be as
sloth-like as possible just get into
that Zen state of mind at least let
yourself step back from your work and
take a little bit of a break to give
yourself some intentional fun time you
know play a video game but one word of
warning here if one quick game of
overwatch or one quick game of magic or
whatever game that you tend to get
sucked in too often turns into just a
quick several hours then that's probably
not a good way to take a break you want
to get into something that is not going
to suck you in not going to distract you
for a real long period of time it just
kind of provides some mental
rejuvenation one other option could be
to take a nap now I did a whole video on
naps about a year ago and for me naps
aren't the most effective thing I find
that even if I do the 20 minute power
nap or you're not supposed to fall
asleep not supposed to get groggy
I find myself slipping into a deeper
sleep wanting to sleep for 2 or 3 hours
so it's kind of a big time waster for me
but again your mileage may vary and a
lot of people get use out of naps in the
early or late afternoon in fact that's
why a lot of countries have a siesta
culture that brings us to step 3 which
is to refocus it is time to get yourself
back to work and focus is the key word
here I find that when I hit the
afternoon slump I often have several
tasks still left on my plate and my
brain will sort of just glide over them
and kind of listless ly try to get in
each one but I kind of know there's a
bunch of them and that makes it really
hard to get into any one thing and this
is where a bit of philosophy comes in
for for me because a lot of people when
they talk about the afternoon slump
they are talking about the nutrition
aspect of at the sleep aspect of it the
circadian rhythm aspect of it but I
think that the level of interest you
have in your work and how focused you
are on it actually plays a big role in
how energized you feel if you're feeling
kind of listless if you don't really
know what you're supposed to be doing or
you don't care about it you're gonna
feel tired because the brain and the
body they have a two-way connection
right your body's circadian rhythm your
nutrition all these factors play a role
in
motivate you feel mentally but it goes
the other way as well your level of
interest in your work how focused you
are this plays a role in how energized
in a wake you feel physically so if you
can find a way either intrinsically or
extrinsic way to get more interested in
a single task that you want to do then
you're gonna feel a little bit more
energized while doing it so here is how
I propose that you externally motivate
yourself first pick one task that you
have to do you can't let your brain just
listlessly glide over everything it's
got to focus in on one thing secondly
clear your environment and get it ready
for work so clear off your desk close
any open programs that don't need to be
open close any open browser tabs and
then maybe get some good study music for
getting into the work zone finally set a
timer for 25 minutes and do a poem adoro
session on the task I find that the
Pomodoro Technique please set a timer
for 25 minutes and you focus on one task
during the 25 minutes with absolutely no
distractions or anything else coming
into your field of view or focus this is
actually much more useful for me in the
afternoons than it is in the mornings
and this kind of makes sense in the
mornings I'm more mentally aware I'm
more awake I'm more easily able to focus
on my work intrinsically in the
afternoons I'm feeling tired I might
need that a little bit of external
motivation and the Pomodoro Technique
really provides that so from personal
experience I know that the three steps
in this process refuel reset and then
refocus these are very effective for
getting past that afternoon slump but if
it's not enough for you there are some
longer-term fixes that you can use as
well and the main one that I want to
mention here is changing up your
schedule if you have the freedom to do
so like I talked about in my previous
video which is all about my new morning
routine I mentioned that I move my
workouts from the mornings to the early
afternoons or late afternoons and this
had a lot of benefits
number one it freed up more time in the
mornings which were better hours for me
to work anyway but it also means that
when the afternoon slump hits I can just
go to the gym and I often find myself
being more energised when I leave the
gym
because I'm getting some exercise and
that helps me get through that tired
spell so if you can do some experiments
and play around with your schedule
hopefully that in combination with three
steps I shared here will help you to be
more productive during your actual work
hours and beat that afternoon slump
which will help you earn back some more
guilt-free evenings evenings that you
could use spending with friends or
playing halle night for the third time
or working on some personal projects
that you don't have time to do during
the actual work hours in the mornings
and afternoons and one personal project
that you should probably consider taking
on if you haven't done so already is
building a professional online presence
if you want to stand out from the
competition and get competitive jobs so
you want to build connections in your
industry and establish yourself as an
expert building a website for yourself
or you can show off your portfolio and
tell people how to contact you is a
great first step and the first step to
doing that is securing your professional
domain name like mine which is Thomas J
Frank calm and if you'll notice I had to
put a J in my url because I was not able
to get Thomas Frank calm since someone
else got it far before I was ever even
on the Internet and that's the thing
about domain names someone else could
get yours before you get the chance to
get it and if they don't let it
relinquish then you're kind of out of
luck
so get your professional domain name
before someone else grabs it and to get
it you should go over to hover.com
hover is the best place on the internet
to get your hands on domain names not
least of which because they have the
most streamlined hassle-free check out
process that I have ever seen there are
no upsells no annoying pop-ups you just
pick the domain you want and you buy it
and they have over 400 extensions as
well so you can get your coms
your dock means your hose which I think
are really good for a professional
presence but they also have lots of
other fun ones like demo ninja and lol
plus once you have your domain they have
some very useful tools for connecting it
to other useful web services like an
email tool so you can get a professional
look to email like mine which is Thomas
at college info geek calm a little more
professional than a gmail and they also
have a connect feature which can help
you connect your domain to website
builders like Squarespace and Shopify
and the best part is you go over to
hover comm slash Thomas Frank can buy a
domain through that link you're gonna
get 10% off of your first purchase and
helped us
worked my channel big thanks to hover as
always for sponsoring this video and
thank you as well for watching hopefully
you found this video helpful if you have
any other tips for beating the afternoon
slump or you know how to fit a
hard-boiled egg into a banana please
share what you know in the comments
below because well I really don't know
how to do that and also your tips
definitely help up other people who are
scrolling down they're looking for
additional information if you want to
subscribe to this channel you can do so
right there to get new videos when they
come out you can also click right there
to get a free copy of my book on how to
earn better grades or check out a couple
more videos right here and here thanks
for watching and I'll see you in the
next video