hey what's going on guys so I got a few
questions lately about how to stop being
late to things and I thought this would
be a good topic to cover because some of
us do have problems getting ourselves to
things on time even if we're not jerks
who don't respect the time of others we
simply have other problems little brain
bugs that cause us to be habitually late
so in today's video I've got five
specific tips that can hopefully help
you become the most punctual person in
your friend group and the first couple
are going to tackle what I think is the
main problem that makes people so late
which is that we as humans are very bad
at making accurate time estimates and we
are susceptible to something called the
planning fallacy which describes how
basically we are over optimistic in our
estimations and the first thing you can
start doing to fight against this
planning fallacy is to start envisioning
the entire sequence of steps it's going
to take to get you from whatever you're
doing right now to your next scheduled
event and the reason you should do this
is because it puts you on the right side
of What's called the segmentation effect
and this effect basically describes how
people make shorter time estimations for
an entire task then their time
estimations for the sum total of all the
subtasks were they to break that task
down and the reason this happens is
because we tend to fixate on the most
important part or the part that's going
to take the longest a perfect example is
Transit time if I need to get somewhere
my brain tends to naturally fixate on
how long it's going to take to get there
so I might think oh I need to get to a
coffee shop in the next town over it's
going to take 25 minutes to drive there
and if I were to actually write down all
the steps involved in getting up from my
desk and getting myself into the
building which I actually did I can find
out that this is actually a 16-step
process and there's about 8 minutes of
extra steps involved so instead of
budgeting 25 minutes to get there I
should budget 34 and in reality this is
actually not enough time because like I
said the planning fallacy has a pretty
tight grip on our brains and we are over
optimistic in our time estimations and
this is a natural brain bug in fact
researchers at the University of waterl
in Canada found this out by asking
people to make two different types of
time estimations for completing a task
they asked people for for best guess
scenarios basically like the everyday
run-of-the-mill average case and they
also ask people for hopeful ideal best
case scenario guesses and the results
were virtually identical for both cases
which indicates that we only see the
ideal scenario when we try to plan how
long it's going to take to do something
we don't think about the grandma that's
going to be driving 5 miles an hour in
front of us we don't think about the
ninjas that are going to attack us on
our way to school and these things
happen right we don't plan for the
things that will go wrong but there's a
natural distribution of outcomes for any
event both good and bad and our brains
just tend to fixate on that perfect
ideal tiny little end of the bell curve
where everything goes right and very
rarely is that actually going to be what
happens now with a lot of practice and
experience I found that it is possible
to get over this tendency to be
overoptimistic but an interim solution
is to use what's called a fudge ratio
and this is a concept that was created
by the writer and blogger Steve pavina
and it's basically the difference
between your time estimate for something
and the actual time it takes so for
example if you thought it would take 30
30 minutes to go to the store and it
actually takes you 45 then your fudge
ratio is 1.5 and what he recommends you
do is to keep this number in mind and
apply it as like a second step in your
brain like a revision step to all your
future time estimates for similar tasks
now with the third tip I've got for you
guys we're going to attack the problem
from a different angle tips one and two
were about estimating more accurately
and trying to Envision all the steps and
tip number three is to Simply remove
steps by doing stuff in advance if you
pack your bag the night before when you
go to bed or you lay out all your
clothes in advance or maybe you like
bulk cook your meals so you can just
wake up and microwave them then you've
got less to do in the morning or
whenever you need to start doing stuff
and the less steps that you have to go
through in any process the easier it's
going to be to estimate how long it'll
take but more importantly the fewer
instances there are for things to go
wrong right a simpler process has fewer
points of failure than a complicated one
all right so now that we've moved
through tips for making your time
estimates more accurate and for making
your processes simpler my penultimate
tip or fourth tip for you guys is to
schedule an end time to the task that
you're currently doing and the reasons
that we want to do this are number one
sometimes we just get caught up in our
work and we don't realize we need to get
going to our next thing and number two
sometimes we do know we need to get
going to the next thing but our brains
are kind of like being rewarded for
whatever we're doing right now maybe
we're on Facebook or maybe we're like
really into the work we're doing or
we're playing a video game and the you
know the old part of your brain the
limpic system that's kind of getting all
the dopamine hits is basically like a
little kid petitioning its mom saying
like just one more minute just one more
minute right and your preferential
cortex you know the more controlly part
of your brain has to be the mom and say
no it's bedtime turn off the freaking
video games turn off the Yu-Gi-Oh it's
time to go to bed and bed is probably
class but you know what I found is that
an external system is much better at
being a mom for the old part of your
brain than your PFC is so use an alarm
maybe use a promodoro session that ends
5 minutes before your next task needs to
begin or maybe just have an alarm on
your phone that says it's time to start
winding down that way your brain is
going to be able to kind of boot itself
out of whatever you're doing right now
and start doing the next thing when it
actually needs to do it and finally my
last tip is for any of you guys that
find yourselves forgetting events either
forgetting them entirely and completely
missing them or forgetting them until
like 5 minutes before they're going to
start which results in a panic attack
right neither is a good situation and
luckily both can be completely rectified
just by using a calendar efficiently
like the productivity Guru David Allen
once said your brain is for having ideas
not storing them this is true even if
you have some weird genius brain that
could remember 99 % of all the events
that you have to go to and I can tell
you mine is not like that I can probably
remember maybe 75% and usually those are
only the fun ones but my calendar is
always going to remember 100% of
everything that I put into it unless
evil hackers somehow get into it and
I've got pretty strong passwords so get
into the habit of putting events into
your calendar the moment they come up on
your schedule get them out of your brain
and into a quick capture system I like
to call it so it's basically in a steel
trap that you trust and I'd also
recommend setting up reminder noic
ifications for your events now part of
my morning routine is to wake up and
immediately check my calendar so I know
exactly what's going to happen that day
but for certain events I want to make
darn sure that I'm going to get to them
on time so I'll use Google Calendar's
reminder feature to set maybe like an
hour before notification to come to my
phone all right so those are the tips
I've got for you in this video and if
you're able to implement them all into
your life you are likely to become the
most punctual person in your group of
friends which will give you the honor
and privilege of being annoyed at all
the friends who are perpetually late now
that you aren't
but hey you could just send them this
video right so hopefully you found this
helpful if you got additional tips I
would love to hear about them down in
the comments and you can also check out
the blog post for this video which has
got some extra details and links to some
cool scientific studies about why our
brains are broken and overoptimistic if
you enjoyed this video you can give it a
thumbs up to support this Channel and if
you want to get new tips every single
week on being a more effective student
you can click that big red subscribe
button down there you can also get a
free copy of the book I wrote on earning
better grades by clicking the picture of
said book right over there and if you
missed last week's video I was about how
to wake up early so if that's something
you want to do and you missed it check
it out right there once again if you
want to check out that companion article
which has extra details and resource
links you can click the button right
there and if you'd like to connect with
me well you're probably going to need a
rooftop and a spotlight because all I'm
saying is have you ever seen Batman and
me in the same room at the same time
anyway thank you so much for watching
and I will see you in the next
video