one of the most important lessons that
I've learned about productivity is that
the way you start your day really
matters waking up on time and going
through a sequence of healthy habits can
give you the momentum that you need to
roll right into your work while waking
up late or waking up without a plan can
easily lead to procrastination and
wasted time so today I want to share the
morning routine that I've been using
recently it's pretty simple but it does
involve one pretty big change from the
way that I used to do things though
we're gonna get to that later because
well first things first I just have to
get out of bed and these days I'm waking
up at about 6:30 in the morning and I do
this using a pretty simple trick so if
you saw my video that I put out a few
years ago about how I used to force
myself to get up early I actually used
to use a social media schedule or to
schedule a tweet that would go out and
tell people that I was being lazy so to
prevent this from going out I would have
to get up before the tweets scheduled
time turn my computer on and either move
it to the next day or delete it and for
a really long time this was an
incredibly effective way to get up at
the time I wanted to get up and go
through my morning routine but when I
tried to use it again earlier this year
I found that it no longer works for me
because it led to me actually waking up
in the middle of the night worrying that
I had slept through my alarm that
something else had gone wrong and the
tweet had gone out so this method was
literally giving me anxiety and
negatively affecting the quality of my
sleep
so what I'm doing now is a lot simpler
but it's just as effective I just have a
second alarm on an iPad downstairs so I
have to actually go downstairs from my
room and turn it off and that alarm is
set for about five minutes after my main
one which virtually guarantees that I'm
never going to hit snooze and I'm always
going to go downstairs and get both
alarms turned off and then get into my
routine next I feed my cat I water my
plants and I do some pull-ups I'm trying
to gradually increase the number that I
do in the morning but right now I'm
doing just about ten and this is a good
way to actually make sure I feel fully
awake but it's also just another good
way to make sure that I stay in shape
for rock climbing and quick tip if
you're gonna use one of these doorframe
pull-up bars when you get one take an
old towel and wrap it around the contact
points with either a rubber band or some
tape that way it doesn't damage your
doorframe because these things can
definitely do that if you don't pad out
those contact points so once I've done
those pull-ups I will go outside for
about a 10 to 15 minute walk and this is
really casual I'm not power
kind of not out there jogging I'm just
going to get a walk because this was a
habit that I used to do every single
morning after I graduated from college
and I was living back in Iowa and I
really just wanted to add it back in and
while I'm walking I'll usually listen to
a podcast or an audiobook right now
listening to wonder ease
excellent business bores podcast
specifically the biker war series about
Harley Davidson along with children of
ruined by Adrienne Tchaikovsky and both
of these I highly recommend though with
Tchaikovsky you're probably gonna want
to start with children of time which is
the first book in that series once I'm
back from the walk it is time for
breakfast but before I get to cooking I
first activate a little routine that I
created on my echo speaker-elect morning
today at 2:00 p.m. there's podcast
interview with the rock and at 3 p.m.
there's callback to drag this lets me
know what's on my calendar for the day
it tells me the weather and then it
starts a little morning routine
playlists that are created on Spotify
which I'll share down in the description
below in case you're interested for
breakfast I will sometimes make a
smoothie which I made a video all about
a couple of months ago and you can check
that out in case you're interested
but recently I've just been sticking to
very simple rap eggs cheese bacon and
salsa and also slice up an apple and of
course make coffee and funny little side
note about that coffee a few months ago
actually decided to do a blind taste
test pitting the craft roasted expensive
beans of a local grocery store with
regular old Caribou Coffee dark roast
beans and when I did that I was
surprised to find that I actually liked
the Cariboo beans better which was
interesting because they were literally
half the price so doing that test
actually showed me that it's a good idea
to do these kinds of tests on a regular
basis to make sure that you're making
logical choices instead of just
following mere signifiers of quality
like price after breakfast it is time to
do some learning which usually takes the
form of reading though I don't always
just read books sometimes I do but other
times I'll dig into a really long
article for example one that I read
recently was Ray dolls new article on
paradigm shifts which I found pretty
difficult to read personally but it
actually led to me making some changes
in the way that I'm investing my money
so I'll have that link to the
description down below as well for
anyone who's interested I do think it is
a pretty good read anyway once that's
done it is time to shower and in my
bathroom I actually keep a small
Bluetooth speaker and I use my showering
time as time for
practice about a year ago I started
actual vocal lessons and I found that
singing in the shower is actually a
great way to get some real daily
practice in and in addition to that I've
also created several different playlists
on Spotify that each target a specific
type of practice in singing like high
range training low range training etc so
it's really easy to build up a queue and
get about 20 minutes of real deliberate
practice in and this is a great
complement to the more lengthy sessions
I do when I have time and the actual
lessons as well and that's it when I'm
done with all this I'll usually start
work at home or if I'm doing writing or
research I'll usually head out to a
coffee shop to do it
there now one thing that you might have
noticed is missing from this morning
routine is working out or going to the
gym and that's actually the big change
that I alluded to earlier after
stubbornly telling myself that I needed
to work out in the mornings for a really
long time I've learned through
experimentation that it's actually
better for me to work out in the
afternoons this is a pretty big
improvement to my routine for a few key
reasons number one I just get to work
earlier because I'm not going to the gym
for an hour or 90 minutes beforehand
number 2 and this is actually more
important this neatly solves the problem
of the afternoon slump now I don't know
if you get this but personally when it
gets around 3 or 4 p.m. in the afternoon
I usually get like this wave of brain
fog and it becomes hard to focus and in
the mornings I don't have this problem
I'm alert I'm easily able to do my work
but again when it gets to late afternoon
that ability really starts to diminish
so by going to the gym in the afternoon
I'm able to use more of my morning on
work and then going to the gym is
actually a great way to get rid of that
brain fog because I'm getting some
exercise finally number three I'm much
more consistent about putting in that
learning time in the mornings when I was
working out in the mornings I would
often feel pressure to get right to work
after I got back from the gym and I've
learned from personal experience that
I'm much less likely to read during the
evenings and I mentioned this because
even though it's easy to skip since it
doesn't seem urgent I think having this
habit of reading or learning every
single day is incredibly important for
me doing this keeps me from stagnating
since I'm no longer in school no longer
being forced to learn new things by
teachers and professors but it also
often leads me to making connections and
getting ideas that it wouldn't have
otherwise had and a lot of times this
improves the quality of my work it helps
me grow my business that's why I think
you should be making time
this habit as well and one resource that
I'd recommend you check out during this
time is brilliant brilliant is learning
website it takes an incredibly active
problem centric approach to teaching
math science and computer science and
because they take this active approach
to designing all of their courses and
their challenges when you're going
through the material you're actually
stretching your brains problem-solving
capabilities you're becoming a more
capable creative problem solver
Williams library includes over 50
in-depth courses and they also have a
feature called daily challenges where
every single day you can log in and get
a new problem in a different area which
can expand your horizons and your
interests and again build that daily
learning habit and build your
problem-solving skills so if you wanna
get started for free go over to
brilliant org slash Thomas Frank and
you're gonna get free access to those
daily challenges and if you'd like to
upgrade your account and get access to
their entire course library be one of
the first 200 people to use that link
and sign up and you'll get 20% off your
annual premium subscription big thanks
as always - brilliant for sponsoring
this video and being a big supporter of
my channel and thank you for watching as
well if you haven't subscribed yet you
can do so right there to get new videos
when they come out here you can also
click right there to get a free copy of
my book on how to earn better grades or
check out a couple of other videos on
this channel right here and right here
thanks again for watching and I will see
you in the next video