if you spent any time at all on YouTube
looking for study advice then you've
probably come across this video called
study L study smart now this is a
recorded lecture from Professor Dr Marty
lbell who is a former psychology
professor at Pierce College and wanted
to give his thoughts on How to Be an
Effective student and the video came out
when I was a sophomore in college and I
wanted to watch it but the problem was
it was an entire hour long and I could
just never make the time now I've seen a
lot of students say the exact same thing
about the video so what I want to do
with this video is try to give you about
80 to 90% of the value packed within the
lecture in about oneth of the time so to
do that I first watched the lecture
myself and took detailed notes on it and
if you want those notes I've actually
included them at the end of this video
but first let's get into the tips so tip
number one is to break your studying
into chunked sessions and the reason for
this is that the average student can
only really pay attention for about 25
to 30 minutes and this goes across the
board from lectures to reading to
studying after about 25 to 30 minutes
your efficiency starts to really taper
off and that's why the advice to Simply
study more is not effective at all
instead you want to break your study
sessions into about 20 to 30 minute
chunks and after those are done Take 5
minute breaks where you do something fun
or at least away from your studies and
also once your study sessions are done
for the entire day you want to give
yourself a real tangible reward for
doing it as Dr Lobdell says in lecture
reinforcement of positive things builds
good study habits and as an added
benefit you're training yourself to
study so as you keep doing this you're
going to be able to study for longer and
longer on each session tip number two is
to create a dedicated study area and the
reason for this is that our environment
the context that we're in largely
determines our Behavior so think about
when you're in class when the professor
presents a question to the entire class
you instinctively raise your hand but if
he asks you specifically you're going to
give a verbal response and this is
automatic your conditioned to do it well
your studying area is the exact same if
you do it in a place where you're
conditioned to do other things like
sleep or play video games or hang out
with friends it's going to be really
hard to get into your studying what you
want to do is find an area that is
specifically used for studying so the
context of the situation makes it easy
for you to get into your studies Dr
lobdell's third tip is to study actively
and it's best summed up with this quote
straight from the lecture the more
active you are in your learning the more
effective you'll be now the best way to
do this rather than going through rot
memorization or reading and rereading
chapters from your book is to first ask
yourself before studying what is it that
I'm learning and what you're learning is
going to fall into one of two categories
either facts or concepts a concept is
something like what what does this
particular bone in the human body do you
have to understand it and a fact is just
something you need to remember what the
name of this bone is now concepts are
more important than facts because once
you learn concept once you truly
understand its inner workings it's with
you forever you're going to remember it
facts on the other hand can sort of
drift away over time and the good thing
about that is that we have Google we can
look up facts very easily now
unfortunately in a testing situation in
class you have to remember both facts
and Concepts and you don't have access
to Google usually but still concepts are
going to be more important to learn
first now the best way to learn these
Concepts and to be sure you know them is
to put them in your own words test
yourself and learn actively and there's
one thing he gives as an example which I
think is one of the most important parts
from the entire lecture and it's his
example about highlighting now most
students know not to highlight entire
sections of the book because if you do
that you're basically highlighting
nothing at all but if you highlight
really important terms and then you go
back after your first read and highlight
session and study them and just simply
recognize the thing you highlighted
before and say ooh I know it then you're
getting into this dangerous territory
where you don't know whether you're
actually recalling something or simply
recognizing it now the human brain is
very good at recognizing things we can
recognize people's faces even if we
haven't seen them in a long long time
but the difference between recognition
and recollection is that recognition
requires an initial trigger a cue and if
you're in a test there is no Trigger or
cue you have to actually pull it forth
from your memory so to test and make
sure that you're actually recalling
something instead of just recognizing it
you need to quiz yourself you need to do
active studying and active learning the
fourth tip is to take more effective
notes and he's really brief on this one
basically he says after class as soon as
possible and truly as soon as possible
flesh out your notes a bit add some more
to them so you can actually solidify the
concepts in your mind and if you're
fuzzy on something ask another classmate
who also took good notes or go to office
hours or wait till the next lecture and
ask the professor before he starts if he
can clarify something that you don't
really have a good grasp on the fifth
tip is to summarize or teach what you
learn and he says the best way to
actually learn something is to teach it
and the reason for this is twofold
number one it's a great form of active
studying because you're forcing your
brain to recall all the information so
you can basically summarize it for
somebody and number two you're really
making sure that you fully understand
the subject if you're explaining it to
somebody who has absolutely no idea
about the topic and they're coming at it
from a beginner's perspective then
you're really going to have an easy time
of pinpointing gaps in your own
understanding tip number six is to use
your textbooks correctly and in this
part of the lecture he goes over the
sq3r method which stands for survey
question read recite and review and as I
talked about in my active reading video
I think overarching systems like this
are actually kind of cumbersome and
timeconsuming but I do think it's
important that you take individual
portions of these systems and see if
they're worth it for your studying
methods so as an example the survey
portion of sq3r surveying the chapter
before you read it and especially going
to the end and looking at the review
questions in the vocabulary can really
prime your brain for picking out the
most important information when you
actually do the reading and Dr lobdell's
seventh and final tip is to use
pneumonics when studying facts now facts
as opposed to concepts are a lot harder
to tie actual meaning to and as a result
a lot of students often turn to simple
rope memorization to remember them but a
better way to go about it is to use
pneumonics and a pneumonic is really any
system that facilitates recall but he
goes over three specific types of
pneumonics in the video and those three
are acronyms things like Roy G Biv for
remembering the color spectrum coined
sayings things like in 1492 Columbus s
the ocean blue and the third one which
both I and Dr Lobdell think is the best
one image associations another way to
think about image associations are just
interacting images including the thing
you're trying to study that create a
ridiculous picture or story in your head
and the more emotionally evocative or
weird it is the more easily you're going
to be able to recall that piece of
information so that is my summary of Dr
lobdell's lecture if you want to see the
entire hourlong video I have it linked
down in the description otherwise you
can get my notes and other things in the
end card thanks for watching this video
and I will see you in the next
one hey guys thanks for sticking around
to the end of my video now if you want
to get even more study tips I made a
video about Advanced study tips last
week and you can see those by clicking
the thumbnail also if you want to get
new study tips every single week in ways
to be an awesome college student then
just click the big red subscribe button
right there as I said in this video you
can get my detailed notes on the entire
lecture by clicking the orange button to
go to the companion blog post for this
video and also if you want to become an
awesome studier I wrote a 100 plus page
book on how to get better grades and you
can get it for free by clicking the
picture of the book lastly if you want
to connect with me or have ideas for new
videos you can either connect with me on
Twitter at tomf Frankle or just leave a
comment on this
video