So a couple of years ago,
a friend told me about a novel idea that he had,
it was this big, grand vision, that would take him
a really long time to write and he knew it
and in his defense, he did start working in earnest on it
for the first few days after having that idea,
but as you could probably guess, after those first few days,
his motivation waned and he stopped working on the book.
Now when this happened,
we didn't wanna see him give up on the project,
but one of the suggestions we gave him
was to first cut his teeth on some smaller projects,
maybe work on some short stories or some blog posts,
just something to basically get him
into the habit of writing regularly,
but his response to these suggestions
was that he didn't wanna waste his time
on these smaller projects, if he was gonna write,
he only wanted to tackle his grand vision
and this happens to a lot of people,
when they set big goals,
they don't wanna detour from their grand vision
to work on something a bit smaller
and this mindset, as well-intentioned
and determined as it may seem
is one of the biggest reasons
why people fail to achieve their big goals.
Far from being a waste of time,
these detours from your grand vision
which I like to call intermediate goals
are actually essential for helping you build
the skillset you need to actually
execute on that bigger project,
essentially no matter what the goal is, that you've set,
you need to be able to see regular
and tangible progress being made,
otherwise your motivation is going to wane
and you're gonna stop working on it
and to illustrate this point,
I wanna share a couple of examples with you
and we're gonna start with Neal Stephenson,
who is one of my favorite authors in the world.
Stephenson is one of those authors,
that writes huge, dauntingly complex novels
typically in the hard science fiction genre
and one of his books, Snow Crash,
which is one of my personal favorites
actually coined the term, avatar,
at least in its context of the term
related to computers and virtual reality and video games
and if you take even just a few minutes
to peruse Stephenson's work, particularly his longer novels,
like Cryptonomicon or Quicksilver,
you start to realize that this is a guy
with a ridiculously wide array of knowledge
and he has this uncanny ability to blend complex topics
like Sumerian mythology with really weird plot lines
involving a katana-wielding swordsman,
who delivers pizza for the Mafia and somehow it all works.
Among science fiction readers like myself,
few would disagree that Stephenson
is one of the titans of the genre
and even commands respect outside of literary circles,
he shared the stage at Arizona State University
with people like Neil DeGrass Tyson, Bill Nye,
theoretical physicist, Brian Green
and he's even worked as an advisor
to Jeff Bezos's space company, Blue Origin,
so you might find it surprising
that Stephenson's first novel, a book called The Big U
initially wasn't very successful at all,
in fact Stephenson himself isn't very proud of it, stating,
"The Big U is what it is, a first novel written in a hurry
"by a young man a long time ago,"
and for a long time after its publication in 1984,
the book was almost impossible to find,
it was only Stephenson's later success
that convinced Harper Collins to republish it.
Now if you look at the reviews of this book
over on a site like GoodReads, you find that most people
don't think that this is a bad book,
it doesn't have a stellar score,
but it's not terrible either and this kind of makes sense,
you would expect to see in this earlier work
some of the elephants that, some of the elephants,
some of the elements that would later be refined
into his more successful works,
but the key point is that it's not something
Stephenson was proud of and yet he published it anyway
and then a second book, Zodiac,
which also didn't really make waves,
but with each published book, Stephenson honed his craft
and then finally he published Snow Crash,
which was wildly successful and since then,
he's continued to write bigger and more ambitious stories.
Okay, so maybe Stephenson's example isn't enough for you,
so let's look at one more case study for good measure
and this time, I wanna look
at the game developer, Matt Thorson,
Thorson was one of the developers of Tower Fall Ascension,
which is by far, hands down one of my all time
favorite games, the simple, but ultra precise controls,
the deceptively deep strategy and the ultra fast gameplay
make it ridiculously fun to play with friends
and it's even made its way
to big fighting game tournaments like Evo.
Tower Fall was a really successful game
and Thorson's upcoming game, Celeste
looks to be even more ambitious and polished
and I cannot wait to play it in January,
so Matt Thorson is obviously a really talented
game developer, but the reason that I love him so much
as an example here is because on his website,
he has left a record of almost every game he's made,
you can scroll through and see almost everything
he's developed since 2004
and you can even download most of the games
and play them for yourself,
which gives you a really visceral picture of his progression
and these early games aren't bad at all,
but there's a stark difference between these earlier efforts
like Jumper and a game like Celeste,
so Matt Thorson is another great example
of the power of intermedia goals
and the history on his website is a perfect illustration
of the skilled development, that's brought about
when you regularly finish things
on a somewhat restricted timescale.
Of course, if I'm gonna make an argument for the strategy
of detouring from the grand vision,
of regular delivery on goals with smaller scope,
then I do need to acknowledge the cases,
where it doesn't seem to apply,
so let's look at the case of Stardew Valley,
this game is a brilliantly crafted homage
to the classics of the farm RPG genre, like Harvest Moon
and by all accounts, it has been wildly successful,
at the moment it's got almost 70,000 reviews on Steam
with overwhelmingly positive sentiment
and last time I checked, it was near the top
of the bestsellers list on the Switch game store as well
and all this success is deserved, it's an excellent game,
it's got deep and rewarding mechanics, there's a ton to do,
the graphics are beautiful for the style
and the music's pretty darn good as well
and the crazy thing is the game's developer, Eric Barone
did all of it, the coding, the art,
the music, like literally everything,
in total he spent over four years working on this game
and honestly, it's a pretty astounding feat
and as far as I can tell at least, it's his first game,
before working on it,
he did graduate with a Computer Science degree,
but he was working as an usher at a movie theater,
it's his first real effort,
so at least as far as his public record is concerned,
Eric Barone is proof that you can indeed
achieve something great on your first try.
Given that, let me put it to you this way,
if you know that you're that lone genius type,
if you've been toiling away quietly on your masterpiece
in between classes and underappreciated shifts
as an Applebee's line cook, then feel free to ignore me,
the reasoned arguments of somebody on the internet
could never outshine your conviction anyway
and honestly, you're probably not even watching this,
but if you really do think that you're that lone genius,
who shouldn't detour away
from the grand vision for anything,
then you had better be able to honestly say
that you're putting in the work on a regular basis
and Eric Barone is a great example of this,
he often worked 10 hours a day or more,
while working on Stardew Valley,
if on the other hand,
the grand scope of your ambitious project
is more daunting than anything,
if you find yourself working in fits and starts,
often abandoning the project for months at a time,
if you find yourself coming home from class or work
and deciding that you deserve to take a break
and just play some Overwatch,
rather than working for four more hours,
then you're just like me and most other people,
you just don't have that nearly rabid level of focus
and determination required to work for years in obscurity,
without any feedback or recognition
or even the satisfaction of finishing a project
and honestly, that's fine,
there's a reason we don't lock six-year olds in a closet
and tell them to learn calculus,
most of us do better, when given a task,
that stretches our capabilities to a point,
but isn't so far beyond them, that it seems impossible
and getting regular feedback
or being able to see a progression
of finished projects is a very good thing,
so here is the one idea,
that I want you to chew on for this week
and keep in the back of your head
the next time you're setting a goal,
restrict your timescale, ask yourself what you could
get done in a week or even a day,
if you wanna make video games,
challenge yourself to make one game this week,
even if it's just a red block, that jumps
or if maybe you wanna learn how to cook,
find a meal, that uses just a few simple ingredients
and make it tonight and then next week,
make something a little bit more ambitious
and build from there.
It's often the case that your grand vision
is full of challenges and difficulties,
that you aren't even aware of yet,
this is called second-order incompetence,
you literally don't know what you don't know,
but by taking on a series of smaller projects,
each of which stretch your capabilities
to just a little bit beyond where they are right now,
you start building that base of knowledge,
that's going to allow you
to someday execute on that grand vision.
Of course, if the goal you're setting for yourself
is something that you don't quite know how to do yet,
like cooking or game development,
then it can also be very useful to seek out experts,
who have been there and who can teach you
the most efficient techniques
and one of the best places on the internet
to find those experts is Skillshare,
Skillshare is an online learning platform
with over 17,000 courses in subjects ranging
from Presentation Skills to Graphic Design
to Javascript Programming
and in addition to those more professional topics,
Skillshare also has over 400 courses in cooking,
which is what I wanna highlight this week,
because one of the things I'm working on right now
is becoming a better cook
and this has been really rewarding,
I found that learning how to cook
results in me eating healthier,
makes me spend less money on food,
because I'm not going out as often,
but also most surprisingly,
it's made the process of cooking more enjoyable.
In the past, I've always seen cooking as a chore,
something that I wanted to get done as quickly as possible,
so I could go and do other things or do more work,
but I found that learning new techniques
and challenging myself to make new recipes
actually makes the process really enjoyable,
even kind of meditative and when I get into it,
I don't care how long it takes, because I'm having fun,
so for those reasons, I think that cooking
is one of those skills that basically everyone
could benefit from learning
and on Skillshare, Kenny Monroe's course,
Think Like a Chef is a great introduction,
that teaches fundamentals like knife skills,
what to have in your pantry, basic ingredients
and also goes through a couple of different recipes,
so if you wanna go through that course
and start learning how to cook
or dig into any of the thousands of other courses
on the platform, give Skillshare a try
using the link in the Description down below
and if you're among the first 500 people
to sign up with that link, you also get
a two-month free trial of unlimited learning
and there is a lot that you could learn in two months,
after that, their Premium subscription starts
at less than 10 bucks a month
and you can cancel at any time.
I wanna give a huge thanks to Skillshare
for sponsoring this video and many more before it,
they've been a big supporter of this channel
and I'm hugely appreciative of that support
and as always, guys, thank you so much for watching.
If you like this video, give it a thumbs up
and if you're not subscribed to this channel yet,
you can subscribe right there to get notifications,
when I publish new videos,
you can also get a free copy of my book
on how to earn better grades right there
or check out our latest podcast episode right down there.
Lastly, you'll find one more video from this channel
floating right around there, so check that out
and I will see you in the next video.
Thanks for watching.