I don't know about you, but I am an
absolute sucker for those kinds of
articles that detail like the daily
habits and the morning routines of
famous authors and other well-known
people. And I was reading one recently,
and I noticed that there's this
disparity between the morning routines
and the time at which a lot of authors
get to work. For instance, the author
Herukqi Murakami, who wrote IQ84 and the
Wup Bird Chronicle, among other books,
like to wake up at 4:00 a.m. in the
morning and write for 5 or 6 hours
before doing anything else when he was
in novel writing mode. And this is
pretty similar to what Ernest Hemingway
did as well. And on the other hand,
you've got authors like Margaret Atwood
who still woke up pretty early in the
morning, but tended to procrastinate and
like to get into her writing later in
the day. So, what that says to me is
that you can be a successful author or
really have success in any field without
adhering to a specific daily schedule or
pattern of doing things. And it's in
that context that I want to answer a
question that I got on Twitter a couple
of weeks ago. Do you have any advice for
somebody who plans out everything the
night before, but then loses all
motivation the next morning? So, first
and foremost, I want to give props to
this person for planning out their day
the night before. I think that is an
excellent habit to get into. It's what I
do in my daily schedule, and I think it
creates a nice separation between your
planning mode and your doing mode. And
at least in my case, when I wake up, it
makes me feel a little bit beholden to
my past self, and that helps me actually
do what I plan to do. With that being
said, though, let's get into some
solutions for this problem. And the
first idea I have for you today goes
back to that disparity between the
different daily schedules of famous
authors. If your current daily schedule
isn't working for you, try changing it
up. You see, I think there are two
different kinds of people and hence
there are two solutions for how to
structure your day. On one hand, you
have people who do their best work first
thing in the morning. These are the
people like Hemingway and Murakami, the
people who can just basically roll out
of bed and get straight to work on the
hardest task of the day. And if you
think you're that kind of a person, or
maybe you don't know and you want to do
an experiment, try putting the most
difficult task on your daily plan first
and then tackle that right when you wake
up in the morning. And if at first
glance you don't really know what your
most challenging task is, take a look at
your daily plan and ask yourself, which
of these tasks do I have the most
resistance to starting? As the author
Steven Presfield put it in his excellent
book, The War of Art, like a magnetized
needle floating on a surface of oil,
resistance will unfailingly point to
true north. Meaning that calling or
action at most wants to stop us from
doing. We can use this. We can use it as
a compass. We can navigate by
resistance, letting it guide us to that
calling or action that we must follow
before all others. Now, while trying
this strategy out might help you be more
motivated in the morning, it also might
not. And that's why I think it's
important to experiment a bit to see
which category of people you fall into
because there is a second category of
people. And I think that I fall into the
second category. And these are the kind
of people who need to build up a bit of
productive momentum before they get into
the most challenging work of the day.
Now, maybe you're wondering what
productive momentum means. And to
explain this, I want to tell you a story
about a piece of advice a friend gave me
a few years ago. He told me that when
I'm procrastinating on starting a big
challenging task, I should go do the
dishes. And the reason for that is that
dishes are a chore. They are work, but
they're what he called lowlevel work.
Doing the dishes is not a cognitively
demanding task, which means there's not
a whole lot of mental resistance to
starting them. But once you get into the
flow of doing them, or really any other
kind of chore or low-level task, you
start to build up some productive
momentum. you get your brain into work
mode and that momentum can carry you
into that more challenging task that you
were procrastinating on earlier. So, if
you're not the kind of person who can
start doing your most challenging work
first thing in the morning, I think you
should try to integrate that process of
building productive momentum right into
your daily schedule. And you do that by
building a morning routine. Now, we'll
definitely talk more about morning
routines in the future, and I'll be
sharing mine with you in detail. But to
get you started, if you don't have a
morning routine right now, sit down with
a piece of paper and create a list of
three to five habits that you'll do when
you wake up first thing in the morning.
And these things can be easy, but the
key is that they start to build up some
of that productive momentum and get you
ready for the day. So, they can be
things like meditating, cooking
breakfast, going for a walk, or going to
the gym. Really, anything that kind of
gets you in a productive mindset. Now,
whether you're that kind of person who
can roll out of bed and start working
right away, or you're the kind of person
who needs a morning routine, I do have a
couple more ideas that you can try out
as well. First off, if you don't tend to
get all the things in your daily plan
done each and every day, try putting
fewer things on that plan in the first
place. There's a concept that's talked
about in books like Getting Results the
Agile Way and The Productivity Project
called the rule of three. And this
concept advises boiling your daily task
list down to the three most important
items that must be done and nothing
else. Now, I don't think there's
anything particularly special about the
number three, but I do like this concept
because it's focused on helping you
narrow that gap between what you plan to
do and what you execute on. Because if
you're constantly maintaining this gap,
you're waking up every day and you have
this subconscious expectation that
you're not going to get done what you
planned. And that can only kill your
motivation. On the flip side, if you
eliminate that gap and you consistently
do what you set out to do, you're going
to wake up with a lot more drive to do
it because there's that confidence
there. The last idea I want to talk
about here might be the most important,
and it's the difference between push
motivation and pull motivation. And
there's this quote from Tony Robbins
that I really like that goes, "There are
two different kinds of motivation. Push
requires willpower and willpower never
lasts. What will last is pull. Having
something so exciting, so attractive,
something you desire so much that you
have a hard time going to sleep at
night. You get up so early in the
morning and you take it to the next
level. I wanted to include this quote
because at least on an idea level, I
absolutely agree with it. And I think
that it does play a large part in why
people like Murakami and Hemingway got
up and worked so hard first thing in the
morning. They had this overbearing idea
just pulling at them and making them
want to do nothing else. But I also
think that that was their personality
and that there are other authors out
there, other people in different fields
who work in different ways. And I'm also
a bit of a realistic person because I
know you might be in school or you might
be in a job right now or you might be in
that part of your journey where you're
kind of just having to embrace the grind
and there's not a whole lot of passion
in what you do, but it's still a
necessary part of the process. And if
you do happen to be in that situation
where you just don't have something
pulling at every fiber of your being and
making you want to work 25 hours a day,
you don't have to wait for that thing to
show up to gain motivation to work in
the morning. I think you can gain some
of the benefits of that idea by simply
building something smaller that does
pull you in maybe a weaker but still
significant way into your morning
routine. So in addition to those habits
that help you build that productive
momentum, I think you should also have
something that you truly look forward to
doing when you wake up in the morning.
And it could be really small. For me,
one of my favorite things to do in the
morning is to just go outside for a
short walk and listen to a podcast or an
audiobook. And that might sound mundane
to some people, but it did make me look
forward to starting my day, and that
raises my overall motivation level to
get into my work. Now, when it comes to
waking up more motivated, these ideas
are certainly not the only things you
can do, but I do think you'll find them
beneficial if you try implementing them
into your daily schedule. And if you've
got additional ideas, I would love to
hear from you down in the comments
below. If you enjoyed this video,
learned something new, you can leave a
like to support this channel. And if
you're not subscribed yet, you can do so
right there. You can also get a free
copy of my book on earning better grades
by clicking right there. And you can
find another video on this channel by
clicking right there. Additionally, if
you want to get a podcast episode that's
all about my motivation strategies and
daily habits, you can click right there
and listen to your heart's content.
Thanks for watching.