welcome to the most exciting video that
you are ever going to watch yes it is
and what will we be covering you ask
sports cars explosions the top 10 most
dangerous bees
even better
file organization oh yes friends buckle
up because this is going to be one wild
ride especially since i have access to
all this explosion footage which i'm
going to apply liberally throughout this
video
now i should say that this is one half
of a wild ride because there are in fact
two halves to your file system the files
that exist in your computer and the ones
that exist here in the real world and if
you're anything like me most of your
files exist digitally and we're going to
cover exactly how to organize them in
the next video in this series but due to
my very intense study on game design
principles i have learned that it is
best to start off with the easier stuff
so today we're going to focus on your
physical file system now my personal
physical file system is pretty small and
that is because whenever i get a piece
of paper my first instinct is to either
recycle it immediately or digitize it
and then of course recycle it and later
on in this video we're gonna talk all
about digitization and how to do it
easily but sometimes you're gonna have
physical files that you just need to
keep for one reason or another perhaps
it's your birth certificate or your
passport or a clipping of a newspaper
article that mentioned you back in the
eighth grade gotta keep that for
posterity's sake whatever it is it is
time to organize it so when it comes to
storing physical files i use a simple
system that consists of three locations
the main file box the inbox and a
portable file folder the main file box
is the place where the majority of your
physical files should eventually end up
if you're not going to digitize them and
if you have a lot of papers you need to
store you could buy a multi-drawer
filing cabinet for this purpose however
i find that a single file box is more
than enough for me and this is what it
looks like and now you know why the
continuity error was there now this file
box and pretty much every single other
one like it is built to store hanging
folders each of which gets a label and
that's how you can easily see what's in
them now when you're creating your
structure here i think it's a good idea
to try to adhere to a tree structure
where you have a top level of
organization which is essentially your
route and then from which you can create
multiple deeper sub-levels or branches
and personally i use these hanging file
folders as the top level of my
organization system i don't really have
a whole lot of files so that's really
all i need though there are ways that
you could go deeper if you need to the
first is to simply put multiple regular
folders within your hanging folders and
i actually do have an example of this
because my landlord left
this entire file box with the house that
i'm renting because she is supremely
organized and honestly she should be
making this video instead of me but
within her box each hanging file folder
is actually just repository for multiple
regular folders and each of these
folders in here is a place to store all
the manuals and instructions for all
kinds of stuff in the house so things
like the air conditioner the dryer the
hose reel now if you don't want to use
the folders within folders method
because you don't want to buy tons of
folders or you don't want to take up so
much space there are other methods such
as using a piece of printer paper as a
divider between different sections
within your hanging folders and to make
sure that you can easily thumb through
and see where your dividers are you can
use these little sticky flags i often
use these for taking notes in books and
making sure that i can see which page i
took a note on but if you just take one
of these off of here and then sort of
you know stick it right on your piece of
paper then that sticks up and you can
put that into your file folders and be
easily able to thumb through them and if
you wanted to you could use construction
paper instead of normal printer paper so
it's a little bit you know different
feeling from the rest of the documents
but either way is pretty easy now aside
from the ones i just mentioned there are
other methods such as the one you can
see in this picture where they're
actually using the colors of the folder
labels as an even higher level of
organization but let's move on to the
next location in the system the icebox
wait that's not right the inbox so be
honest with me here when you get a piece
of mail that needs to go into your file
box how often do you immediately open up
that file box and put it in the correct
spot
i'd wager a guest that it's not 100 of
the time and that your kitchen table is
often used as a convenient place to toss
things that will get dealt with later
here's the thing the first part of that
is fine and you probably shouldn't be
opening up your file box and finding the
exact folder every single time you need
to file at the exact moment you get it
it's a lot more efficient to have a
specific time blocked out for processing
all of your unorganized files mail and
of course cryptic messages nailed to
your door written and cut out magazine
letters but your kitchen table does not
deserve to be a dumping ground for all
these things in the meantime because
that is a job for your inbox so an inbox
is a simple tray or a stack of trays if
you really want to get fancy that sits
on your desk and whenever you get
something that needs to be processed
later on you put it in the inbox and
then at least once a week you want to go
through everything that's in this inbox
and decide what needs to be done with it
if it represents a task like paying
water bill then you want to deal with it
otherwise you might want to digitize it
or recycle it or put it in your main
file box pretty simple and that brings
us to the final piece of your physical
file organization puzzle which is the
one that travels with you so when you're
out of the house and you're away from
your file box and your inbox you still
need some way to store any papers you
get from work or class and of course
from the guy outside your local coffee
shop holding his the end is nice sign
he's got some pretty interesting
pamphlets and you should probably take
one now depending on the type of work
you do in the classes you attend your
portable file folder can function either
as a portable inbox which you want to
clear on a regular basis or as a mini
file box that actually holds papers for
a significant amount of time now if you
are anything like me then you probably
don't have any physical papers that you
need to carry with you you might have
like a physical notebook or be carrying
a novel but you're not actually carrying
worksheets or other papers that you
actually need to use on a regular basis
and if that's the case then i recommend
just keeping a single folder in your bag
this gives you a safe place to
temporarily store any papers that you
get while you're out and about and it
doesn't take up a whole lot of space at
all and then when you get home each day
you can move any papers and end of the
world pamphlets that you've received on
all of your adventures to either your
inbox for later processing or into your
main file system if you have a decent
amount of time but what if you're a
student who needs to carry around
assignments and handouts or what if
you're a high-powered slick care
business person needs to carry around
well you know
your business papers if this is the case
then i think a single file folder
probably isn't going to cut the mustard
actually
hang on a second
anna
do you have any mustard
yes where's the mustard
science
okay
you're worrying me a little bit
that's enough
okay
oh my god
okay i stand corrected the edge of a
folder is more than capable of cutting
mustard but you still shouldn't use it
instead you want to look into getting a
portable accordion folder these give you
several folders and one slim compact
package which means they act as a
portable file box you can actually work
out of and you can easily separate and
organize all the different papers for
your classes or very important business
deals and unlike old school binders with
a hard spine these expand or contract
based on how much you're carrying now
before i move on i want to briefly
mention a couple of other locations that
you may want to add to your file system
the first is what i call a manuals box
and for me this is just a regular old
cardboard box where i put things like my
piano manual or my tv manual because i
don't like keeping these things in my
main file box since they're bulky but
there really aren't enough of them to
warrant a whole new folder system which
brings me to a point that i wanted to
mention here sometimes over optimizing
one tiny part of your life ends up
taking so much time that you kind of
de-optimize your life as a whole so
sometimes letting something be a little
bit messy or a little bit you know
unorganized is fine because it really
doesn't matter in the long run so that
being said the second one that i want to
mention here is a safety deposit box you
can rent these at banks and they can be
a safe place to keep things like the
original copy of your birth certificate
to your passport and the rest of your
john wick coins now i don't use one of
these since i can just store all my john
wick coins under the concrete floor of
my basement and because well they cost
money but i do want to mention them
because i know a lot of my viewers live
in dorms and apartments with roommates
who don't always take even simple
security matters like not leaving the
front door wide open seriously so you
can consider it
all right to round out this guide i want
to talk about something that's even
better than properly storing and
organizing your paper files namely
digitizing them that's right it's time
to start adopting the mostly paperless
lifestyle so digitization is the process
of scanning your physical files and
turning them into electronic images or
pdfs and then from there you can easily
slot them into your beautifully
constructed computer photo system where
they no longer take up any space in your
home or backpack but more importantly
are backed up and no longer vulnerable
to fires bullies or the random escaped
zoo gorilla personally i try to digitize
almost every paper i get because it
takes very little time to do so and this
is especially true now that almost
everyone has an ultra high resolution
camera built into their phone now in the
past the only way to digitize papers
were either to go buy a scanner or go
down to fedex kinkos or staples and scan
documents there but now you can just use
your phone which means that you can
digitize handouts and receipts and other
papers literally wherever you are and
additionally if you're using the right
app you can also automatically send your
scans into your file system with no
manual choosing folders so here is how i
digitize my files and the first thing
that i want to mention is that for the
most part i send my scans into my
evernote account instead of my
computer's main file system why you
might ask well all of my article
research my book notes my recipes
journal entries and almost every other
idea that i have goes in to evernote so
that's why i choose to send scans there
as well but there is one other reason
evernote makes your scans searchable
even if they're images now i tend to
upload my scans as pdfs because i often
stitch lots of things together into like
a multi-page document but you can also
add pictures into evernote and its
optical character recognition algorithm
will allow you to search any text in
them even if it's handwriting that being
said i don't actually use evernote's
built-in scanning tool to do this
instead i use an app called scanbot i
found that scanbot's ability to quickly
detect the edges of a piece of paper or
a business card or receipt or literally
whatever it is that i'm scanning is a
lot better than evernote's and you're
also able to scan multiple pages at once
and then once you're done it will stitch
it into a pdf which is exactly what i
just talked about doing and these
features make scanning much faster but
there is one other reason why i like
scanbot so much the automatic upload
feature so within the app settings you
can actually choose a destination to
which all new scans will be
automatically uploaded moreover you can
choose a specific upload folder or
notebook for most of these destinations
so in evernote i've set mine to a
notebook called inbox which is also the
place where i create most new text notes
and that brings me to the final point
that i want to cover on digitization and
this is kind of verging on the computer
file territory but i do think it's good
to cover here anyway if you choose to
upload your digitized files to your
computer's native folder system instead
of an app like evernote then it might be
a good idea for you to create an inbox
folder on your computer and some people
actually use a digital inbox folder just
like a physical inbox they save all new
files to it and then they relocate them
later on when they have more time now i
don't do this for a couple of different
reasons one most of my frequently
accessed folders are pinned to my quick
access sidebar so opening them doesn't
really take much time and more
importantly number two a lot of my work
involves video editing and video
projects are full of references to
footage images music and tons of other
files and changing the file locations
for all these assets can really break a
project so i don't mess with the inbox
folder however using an inbox folder for
your automatic scan uploads is a really
good idea because it allows you to scan
a document in seconds and then move on
with your life you really don't want to
be standing around the grocery store
digging through google drive folders
trying to find the exact right one for
that receipt you just scanned instead
just sit down once a week and process
the inbox folder just as you would do
with a physical inbox and this is
exactly what i do with my inbox notebook
in evernote as well and when you work
this way you efficiently batch all of
your sorting tasks removing as much
friction as possible from the multiple
times during the week where you might
choose to make a scan which means you
become more productive overall and this
is something that you want to be doing
in every area of your life looking for
ways you can make things that you do on
a repeated basis more efficient not only
will doing this save you time but it's
also a method of thinking in an adaptive
way and of course the more time you
spend thinking adaptively the better you
get at it and at solving the tough
problems that you're going to be facing
in your higher level classes and in your
career and if you're looking for more
ways to improve your depth of thinking
you should check out brilliant brilliant
is a learning platform built from the
ground up for anyone who wants to become
a more capable and creative problem
solver they have an in-depth library of
over 50 courses that teach you math
science and computer science in a way
that focuses on active learning and
hands-on challenges and one course that
you might want to start with especially
if you want to start thinking more
naturally about how to make things more
efficient is their computer science
essentials course this course doesn't
require any coding knowledge beforehand
and in it you'll learn how algorithms
are designed and then approved again and
again in order to be as efficient as
possible and since brilliant focuses on
well-curated sequences of problems aimed
at getting you to actual mastery it is a
great compliment to watching traditional
educational videos and if you want to
get started right now you can go over to
brilliant.org thomasfrank to start
learning for free also if you're one of
the first 200 people to sign up with
that link you're going to get 20 off
your annual premium subscription to boot
big thanks as always to brilliant for
sponsoring this video and being a big
supporter of my channel and thank you to
you as well for watching if you enjoyed
this video you might want to give it a
like and get subscribed right there if
you want to see more on this channel in
the future otherwise you might want to
click right there to get a free copy of
my book on how to earn better grades
lastly you can click either here or here
to get more videos on this channel right
now and you might want to check back
next week or click right there to
subscribe if you want to get that second
video in my file organization series
which is going to be all about computer
file organization so i will see you in
that next one