here's an interesting question does
drinking coffee actually dehydrate you
being the kind of person who likes to
read Health books and health articles
and the kind of person who definitely
enjoys a morning cup of coffee I have
heard this assertion many many times
it's usually phrased this way coffee is
a diuretic so it'll dehydrate you if you
drink it but is this actually true well
the short answer is well actually two
short answers one yes coffee or rather
the caffeine within that coffee is
technically a diuretic but answer number
two no it will not dehydrate you for the
most part coffee will actually hydrate
you just about as well as normal water
will especially if you take it with milk
or cream so given that why are people
continually running around talking about
coffee as a diuretic I imagine it's
because people don't really know the
definition of a diuretic is they
probably think it's something that
actively dehydrates you which it's not a
diuretic is by definition just something
that increases the production of urine
so if you're drinking something that is
a diuretic you have to consider that
that's only one feature of that beverage
another very important feature being the
fact that it's probably mostly composed
of water this means that in order for a
diuretic beverage to dehydrate you that
diuretic effect would have to be
significantly powerful enough to offset
the increase in water flowing into your
body and in the case of coffee that
diuretic effect isn't very strong at all
and what's more if you drink coffee with
any regularity whatsoever your body
develops a tolerance to that effect
really quickly a study that was done
back in 1928 found that participants who
abstained from caffeine for over 2
months did have a substantial fluid loss
after being given caffeine but within 4
to 5 days of regular caffeine use their
bodies developed that tolerance and
putting the case of coffee aside most
beverages that are diuretics that we
drink in our everyday lives are in fact
weak diuretics which means that drinking
them will hydrate you nearly as well as
normal water will in fact 2015 study
that was done in the UK tested the fluid
loss caused by 13 different drinks
including and you and I both know I have
an iPad here that I'm reading off of so
I'm just going to read off of it coffee
tea logger beer orange juice soda and
milk and the data they gained from these
tests was used to create a beverage
hydration index which showed that all
the tested drinks hydrate nearly as well
as plain water coffee was the worst but
it was still pretty darn close also
surprisingly milk was found to be even
more hydrating than water which is why
earlier I said that if you take your
coffee with milk or cream it's probably
right on par with water so here's the
bottom line all the drinks you consume
throughout your day contribute to your
overall hydration and this is also true
of the food you eat especially if you
eat lots of water heavy fruits and
vegetables which you definitely should
be doing now this definitely doesn't
negate the other negative effects that
certain drinks can have though you can
still become caffeine dependent if you
drink too much coffee or too many
caffeinated Beverages and that can
really interfere with the quality of
your sleep and also impair mental
functioning and if you're drinking lots
of sodas or those energy drinks or even
a lot of fruit juice the sugar in those
drinks can cause an excessive insulin
response which can lead to weight gain
and all sorts of other health problems
so if you want to optimize your health
use common sense and make most of your
fluid intake be either water or low
caffeine teas like royos not royos but
royos and or green teas did I just say
and or in a video also a morning latte
or a glass of orange juice won't hurt
much either as long as you keep these
things in moderation but from a
hydration point of view all of it counts
none of these drinks is going to
dehydrate you in fact the ironic part in
this is that the most potentially
dehydrating part of coffee or any
beverage with the diuretic effect is the
fact that people tell other people that
it's dehydrating as the author Ben desb
put it by advising people not to consume
drinks they enjoy just because they
contain caffeine individuals may not
automatically replace drinks leading to
reduction in total fluid intake now if
you want to learn more about hydration
and figure out how you can make sure
that you stay hydrated stick around
because that'll be the topic for next
week's video Until then keep enjoying
your morning
coffee speaking of coffee and moderation
the one time when my caffeine intake
does tend to spike is when I'm editing
my videos and one of the most common
questions I get about my editing process
is what tools do you use now honestly I
use a lot of different programs to make
my videos because my videos have a lot
of different moving parts to them but
the two work programs that get most the
heavy lifting done are adobe's Premiere
Pro and after effects for animations
both of these programs are really
powerful but that also means that they
can be pretty complex at the start
especially after effects I remember
opening that for the first time it was
like trying to learn a new language just
to use the interface but eventually
through a lot of practice I was able to
learn the ins and outs of both programs
and they enabled me to now make far
better videos than what I was putting
out a few years ago so if you're a
budding YouTuber you want to make your
own videos I highly recommend learning
the ins and outs of both these programs
and learning the them well the
proficiency will enable you to far
better express your creativity and if
you happen to want to accelerate that
learning process you'll find a ton of
Great Courses and tutorials over at
skillshare skillshare is an online
learning library with over 177,000
courses in topics ranging from
photography to graphic design to web
development and many many more and that
includes tons of courses on both Premier
and after effects animation now while
skillshare has a huge amount of courses
on both premere and after effects I do
want to give you a couple of specific
recommendations to get you started the
first one I'll recommend is Jordy
vanderp put's complete course on
Premiere Pro which takes you all the way
through the basics of the software and
teaches you editing Basics like color
correction like this shot right now is
color corrected now it's not now it is
and things like sound editing and lots
of other techniques and secondly Jake
Bartlett's course on animating with ease
and after effects is a great one now
there are a ton of different skills you
can learn in After Effects but I think
that easing which is simply changing the
speed of an animation along a curve
rather than using linear motion is one
of the most fundamental and adds a ton
of Polish to my videos so if you want to
give skillshare a try and check out
those classes or any of the other on the
platform you can get 3 months of
unlimited premium access for just 90
cents using the link in the description
down below but you definitely want to
hurry because that deal only lasts until
the end of January after that their
premium subscription starts at less than
10 bucks a month and of course you can
cancel at any time I want to give a huge
thanks to skillshare for sponsoring this
video and helping to support this
Channel and as always big thanks to you
for watching as well if you like this
video you can give it a like down below
or share it with a friend if you think
they'd find it useful and you can also
subscribe to my channel right there to
get notifications of new videos when I
release them you can also click right
there to get a free copy of my book on
how to earn better grades or click right
there to watch one more video on this
channel thanks so much for watching and
I will see you in the next video