hey what's going on guys so one of the
most common questions I get asked about
myself is what is my MBTI myers-briggs
personality type I get this question all
the time and today I thought I would
just answer it by actually going through
the most popular personality test on the
Internet these sixteen personalities
dot-com tests if you google personality
test I believe that is the first thing
that comes up personality test yes first
thing that comes up so we're gonna take
this test and I'm going to show you my
score once we get whatever my type is
we'll look through the some of the
traits that that type contains and then
compare to some of the other traits out
there because there are it looks like 16
different personality types each a
combination of the four different
letters here now this is mainly based on
the myers-briggs personality type
indicator acronym here but I believe
that the sixteen personalities test
looking through their theory page here
uses a little bit different philosophy
behind their questions and there's lots
of different types of tests that use the
MBTI acronyms so it's important to
realize that people who tell you hey I
mean I am I an FTP or ENTJ or an ENFJ if
they say that they might have taken a
different test than the one you take and
it might mean something different
altogether the other thing that I want
to mention before I go into this is that
personality tests in general this one
and others are merely mental models that
can be useful for figuring out what kind
of personality you might have and what
things you might be better at than
others but I don't think that you should
use these to define yourself entirely in
fact there's a really good quote from an
article here on Quora called what is it
current thinking about myers-briggs that
I really liked here and this fourth
paragraph I think it is in this sense it
can be a good framework for developing
an intuition about one's own uniqueness
and how one can not use oneself as a
model to explain all other human beings
that's why that's the one quote there
that I really love you can use these
tests to remind yourself that the way
that you view the world is not the way
that other people view the world and
things that work for you may not work
for other people but I don't want you to
use these kind of tests to try to define
yourself and especial
the choices you make or make decisions
about what you maybe shouldn't try to do
because you fit into a certain
personality archetype so with all that
being said we are just going to get into
the quiz here you find it difficult to
introduce yourself to other people no it
has become much much easier in recent
years and I think this actually
highlights something right away if I
were to take this test in fact I did
take this very test about five years ago
I think this was more on the middle or
agry side because I was a little bit
more shy and now it's not hard at all
you try to respond to your emails as
soon as possible and cannot stand a
messy inbox oh boy can we use wishful
thinking here as an answer you have to
answer honestly even if you don't like
the answer okay I have seen friends of
mine I've seen their inboxes and I
sometimes see like 10,000 unread emails
in there I am not nearly that bad
however I am not super good at
responding to emails very quickly let's
go with it let's go with a soft degree
because I do try to do it and I do not
like a messy inbox I'm just not good at
it and I'm not one of those inbox zero
practitioners so I really don't think I
could put myself over here on the strong
agree you feel superior to other people
I don't even know how to answer that
I definitely feel superior to other
people in certain areas when I am very
confident in my skill set but in terms
of just general I mean I don't know I
realized that it's very easy to compare
yourself to a reference that you may
have but you may not have a reference
somewhere else so I really don't know
see I feel like I feel like the type of
work I do lends itself to the
development of an ego that I try to keep
in check so I'm gonna go ahead and I'm
gonna put that it's neutral I'm not
really sure to be honest being organized
is more important to you than being
adaptable ah no no no no not at all I
love being organized absolutely don't
get me wrong but I think the skill of
adaptability is actually a lot more
important than being organized when a
debate matters less to you
then making sure no one gets upset now
this is an interesting question I think
five years ago I would have put that yes
winning a debate matters more because I
was more interested in objective truth
and finding the right answer at this
point I think it depends because like
with my relationship with my girlfriend
I often don't care if I want a debate as
many times as I may have used to because
don't want her to be upset these are
these are tough questions because the
context matters and and I would I would
rather be wrong than win on an argument
that doesn't work so this is this is
kind of tough maybe putting aside the
context of my relationship with my
girlfriend on debates that don't matter
in general I think that coming to the
truth of the matter does matter more
than making sure no one gets upset
otherwise that's avoidance of conflict
for no reason so we will go with a
middle agree here you don't mind being
at the center of attention agree I do
not mind that you consider yourself more
practical than creative I think that I'm
more creative than practical and I
suppose my reasoning for this would be
that I have a lot of friends who do
YouTube and do entrepreneurial things
and a lot of a lot of those friends are
more willing to do things that they know
are going to be profitable with less of
an investment in the creative aspects or
as you guys know I put on a video once a
week if that because I'm so into making
sure that my videos have something
creative and new and different in them
every single time so I think I'm more
creative than practical we'll go with
that one people can rarely upset you
that is true I don't really get upset
almost ever it is often difficult for
you to relate to other people's feelings
I'm actually gonna go to disagree on
this one it's gonna be a sawfish degree
when I took this test a few years ago
probably five years ago at this point I
know that I was over here on the agree
side I have had trouble in the past
empathizing with other people's feelings
because I'm a very solution minded
person when there's a problem at least
in my mind the first thing to do is to
solve it but I think this is another
good example of how your personality can
actually shift through conscious effort
because I have worked to become more
empathetic with my friends and with
people in general and I think that work
has actually contributed to becoming
more me becoming more naturally
empathetic so we're gonna go with a soft
disagree there in a discussion truth
should be more important than people's
sensitivities this is another one of
those questions where I would have been
like hard yes and I'm not sure because
context matters so much how much does
the truth matter that's the real
question to be answered here so I think
once again I'm still on the side of
agree but it's it's not as hard of an
agree any more I try to think about the
texe now being able to develop a plan
and stick to it is the most important
part of every project I have to go back
to that adaptability question Dwight
Eisenhower once said that planning is
everything but plans are nothing and I
absolutely agree with that we often have
to change plans quickly and pivot so I
think that being able to develop a plan
is very important but the most important
part of every project I think is
adaptability and communication so we'll
go disagree if someone does not respond
to your email quickly you start worrying
if you said something wrong yes I do and
I know this is irrational I know this is
stupid because I have had people that I
haven't responded to in weeks and it is
no fault of their own it's just my poor
organization or you know prioritizing
other thing other things and I tell
myself that every time I send an email
and I don't get a response quickly I
tell myself they're just busy they you
know they're probably doing something
else their emails not a priority but
there's always this little thing in the
back of my mind that's like you probably
said something wrong or you probably
worded something you you put a period on
some sense it made it sound too terse
yeah what will go with that you do not
let other people influence your actions
ion I feel like if you answer agree on
this one you're a little bit self
delusional I think we all have
influences even if their subconscious I
think you have to disagree a little bit
so the question is to what degree I
definitely let people influence my
actions that's absolutely true
I have discussions with people that I
trust and people that I look up to and
they often will change my opinion on
something that I was going to do I do
think that there is a certain degree of
principle that I hold myself to and
there's a certain degree of confidence
in my ability to judge where I am and
what the best course of action is so
we'll go with a soft disagree here your
emotions control you more than you
control them
that does it disagree absolutely I like
to think I'm in control of my emotions
quite a bit like I said I don't really
get angry very often I don't let my mood
swing that much you would rather
improvise than spend time coming up with
a detailed plan there's the key question
rather or the key word here rather what
I rather improvise or spend time coming
over the detailed plan I like doing both
to be honest I think that where a lot of
my great work comes
through improvisation like I said here I
think my personality type actually leads
me to try to plan things out in advance
more and then I just end up into
improvising within the constraints of
that planet that makes any sense
you often contemplate the reasons for
human existence yes yes I do
logic is usually more important than
heart when it comes to making important
decisions I'm gonna go with agree there
so I did say that I do try to take
people's emotions into account more
often now but I still do believe that
logic Trump's my own emotions when it
comes to making important decisions
keeping your options open is more
important than having a to-do list this
all comes back to that improvisation
thing right I'm gonna go with disagree
here though because I think that keeping
your options open actually leads us to
in action many times when we just we
have too many options we have no
constraints to really put us down a
specific path I think when we create
constraints we actually give ourselves
the freedom to operate and make more
impactful decisions within those
constraints so I like having a to-do
list and then being able to adapt it if
I have to if your friend is sad about
something you are more likely to offer
emotional support than suggest ways to
deal with the problem so this is one of
those things five years ago I would have
been hard disagree I have worked very
hard to make myself give emotional
support but my gut answer the thing my
brain immediately jumps to whenever a
friend has a problem is to suggest a way
to deal with it and then I have to like
pause stop myself and decide to
purposely give that emotional support
first and wait so to suggest a solution
until they ask
alright you rarely feel insecure agree I
am NOT an insecure person you think that
everyone's views should be respected
regardless of whether they are supported
by facts or not disagree your right to
express your view I respect that with
certain exceptions but the view itself
does not deserve respect if it is not
supported by facts all right you feel
more energetic after spending time with
a group of people I actually don't I
have an introvert battery that drains
when I am in a group of people so you
feel very anxious in stressful
situations definitely disagree here when
I'm in a stressful situation I actually
feel very energized stress is a very
good thing for me at least if it's not
chronic you often take initiative in
social situations yes I do and this is
something that has served me very well
again this when I had taken this test a
few years ago the answer was probably no
I wasn't the person to plan things I
wasn't the person to be the leader in
that and that area in my life but now
I've learned that you kind of have to be
if you want things to happen so I do try
to do that all right so we are about to
get the results and I actually do not
know what I'm going to get so let's just
click it and see all right ENTJ okay so
that is what I got last time and there's
a - a on there so we'll see what that
actually means I'm not exactly sure what
the a means here but let's go through it
alright so 83% extroverted that is a big
difference from what I would have gotten
five years ago I think last time I got
ENTJ but I was like 52% extroverted see
here I have 56% intuitive energy versus
absorbent my nature is more thinking
than feeling but again my thinking
nature was actually much higher in the
past so it is balanced out over time
tactics this trait reflects our approach
to work planning and decision-making I'm
more judging than prospecting so we'll
see what that means and then identity
this trait underpins all others showing
how confident we are on our abilities
and decisions I'm 87% assertive and 13%
turbulent so let's see what all this
stuff means alright the ENTJ personality
type and keep in mind guys there are 16
different kinds so it looks like I am
here the commander within the analysts
category we also have diplomats
sentinels and explorers so we have a
Steve Jobs quote that's pretty cool
commanders are natural-born leaders
people with this personality type
embodied gifts of charisma and
confidence and project Authority in a
way that draws crowds together behind a
common goal however commanders are also
characterized by an often ruthless level
of rationality using the drive
determination and sharp minds to achieve
whatever end they've set for themselves
perhaps it is best that they make up
only 3% of the population oh pretty rare
I guess lest they overwhelm the more
timid and sensitive personality types
that make up much of the rest of the
world
we have commanders of thank for many of
the businesses and institutions we take
for granted every day I'm interested in
the strengths and weaknesses let's look
at that real quick so commanders are
efficient they're energetic
self-confident strong-willed strategic
thinkers and charismatic and inspiring
let's hear commander weaknesses I'm
actually more interested in these
because I feel like these are
interesting but they often are Mike ego
stroking a little bit maybe so I
to see what my weaknesses are here
stubborn and dominant sometimes all this
confidence of willpower can go too far
and commanders are all too capable of
digging in their heels trying to win
every single debate and pushing their
vision and theirs alone this was
absolutely me for a long time in fact in
high school I had a I had a girl break
up with me actually for this very reason
it's because I basically refused to give
ground on arguments I would like let my
logical mind just go too far and just
kind of run amuck without thinking about
the other person's feelings and that
kind of broke that relationship up so
I've learned to not let that part of me
dominate my thinking intolerant it's my
way or the highway okay so people with
the commander personality type are
notoriously unsupportive of any idea
that distracts from the primary goals
and even more so of ideas based on
emotional considerations I think this is
something that I also struggle with in
the past but it's another thing that I'm
trying to work on
all right impatient some people need
more time to think that another is an
intolerable delay to quick-thinking
commanders they may misinterpret
contemplation as stupidity or
disinterest in their haste I definitely
have this problem I have noticed it in
many different instances where I have
made my decision very quickly and when
somebody else doesn't make the decision
it kind of annoys me so it's important
to realize these things I think arrogant
commander personalities respect quick
thoughts and firm convictions their own
qualities and look down on those who
don't match up okay so that's something
I have to work out with poor handling of
emotions all this bluster is alongside
the assumed supremacy of rationalism
makes commanders distant from their own
emotional expression and sometimes
downright scorn full of others and
lastly cold and ruthless their obsession
with efficiency and unwavering belief in
the merits of rationalism especially
professionally makes commanders
incredibly insensitive and pursuing
their goals dismissing personal
circumstances sensitivities and
preferences as irrational and irrelevant
you know I'm reading the Steve Jobs
biography right now I'm listening to it
inaudible and this is like him to a tee
absolutely this is a good indication of
why these tests are not always
completely accurate so I look at these
and I see some of these weaknesses in
myself but this cold and ruthless one I
actually don't think this describes me
at all because I work with a team of
nine people at this point and whenever
they have a personal circumstance that
makes it so their work is you know has
to take a backseat to their personal
life or they have to take some time off
like there's never even an initial
thought in my head
oh they're in the way of my overall goal
and vision so again these these are not
always completely accurate let's look at
career paths and obviously this video is
gonna get very long if we go through all
of them but I'm very curious about this
one it is in the world of careers a
commander's boldness and drive are truly
at their best no other personality type
is better suited than commanders to be
the respected leader of an organization
or team and no other personality type
enjoyed it quite so much this is
interesting to read now I'm reading a
book right now called good to great by
Jim Collins and in that book he did a
ton of research on companies that
essentially went from like good or
mediocre to having great results over a
certain period of time and what they
found is that one of the common traits
between all these good to great
companies is that they had a leader who
was a little bit more quiet a little
more reserved didn't have that bold
charismatic personality they ended up
making better long-term leaders because
they were more willing to accept the
harsh truth all the environmental
factors and threats facing the business
and they were less intimidating to their
employees and they would take criticism
they would take ideas more seriously
from their subordinates than somebody
who maybe has a commander personality
like this so this is something that I
have thought about and tried to keep
front of mind in my own business I do
like being a leader but I also realized
that it's possible that this commander
personality which I think does describe
me to a good degree could be a weakness
within my career within the success of
my business here so there's all kinds of
stuff on here but yeah so I'm an ENTJ
hopefully that answers the question for
you guys and I would be curious to see
which personality type that you guys end
up falling into it's a pretty quick quiz
it's pretty fun to go through so let me
know down in the comments which one of
these you fall into and I would be
curious to know as you're going through
these descriptions of your personality
type and going through these different
exploration Parenthood friendships
romantic relationships what do you think
this test gets right and what do you
think gets wrong I would be interested
for you to scrutinize the test itself
against your own beliefs of who you are
and see if it actually is accurate in
all those dimensions one thing that I do
want to mention before I go if you are
like me you are probably always looking
for new YouTube channels and new
things to sink your teeth into and learn
new stuff I know I'm like that I'm
discovering new channels all the time
and because of that I thought that I
should start sharing some of those
channels on this channel maybe like once
a month or something just to share what
I'm watching with you guys so I want to
share a channel called wisecrack I got
to hang out with these guys at VidCon
they are freaking awesome and they do
all kinds of videos in their Channel but
I think that the main overarching theme
is they combine science and philosophy
and all kinds of educational content
with books and movies and video games
and all kinds of stuff that we are
probably usually more interested in than
all the academic stuff so they make
education fun in a way that I really
really quick click with and I've
actually been watching wisecrack for a
really long time because they started
with a series called thug notes which
does literary analysis of tons of
different books and I absolutely love it
but they have tons of other videos as
well including a really cool recent
video on the philosophy of Death Note
which is one of my favorite anime as
well as a thug notes on ready player one
which is one of my favorite recent
fiction books so I'll have a couple of
their videos linked up in the endcard
here as well as in the description down
below definitely go check them out and
subscribe if you like their stuff you
have channels that I haven't found yet
that you think I should check out also
leave those in the comments down below
anyway guys thanks for watching I will
see you in next week's video