this video is sponsored by brilliant
the robots are coming you've read the
headlines of course
you've heard all the hyperbole the
robots are coming
and well you'd better batten down the
hatches and stock up on the canned beans
because
they're coming for our jobs and
for some jobs well that's absolutely
true the
transportation industry just to give you
one example will largely be powered by
self-driving tech in the near future
obviating the need for human drivers and
for something that might hit a bit
closer to home for those of you with
more
dust bound jobs there are now algorithms
that can even write
news reports in fact in 2016 the
washington post's heliograph bot
wrote over 850 sports articles
and that was four years ago how long
until robots can create convincing
online videos in fact how do you even
know
that i'm human
it's not all bad news though and don't
worry i'm
actually human i'm not a robot like you
i enjoy ingesting organic material both
for enjoyment and refreshment
and hydration
necessary but more importantly there is
a simple rule that you can follow to
ensure that your opportunities for
employment and success in your career
continue to be plentiful even as
automation tech improves and competition
for jobs heats up
it's called the five-hour rule and in
this video we're gonna explain exactly
what it is and how you can use it in
your own
life but first let's set the stage with
a little story
hey charles can i trouble you for one of
those flashback sounds real quick
sure thing it's 1978
and all over the world accounting clerks
are recording data
in spreadsheets except these
spreadsheets are written
on paper physical paper and even a small
recalculation can require hours
spent tediously erasing and refilling
cells which
is a huge reason why these clerks are
employed full time
one year later the world's first
electronic spreadsheet is released
it's called visicalc and it becomes
known as the world's first
killer app just as halo made the xbox a
must buy back in 2002
visit calc helped make the apple ii
computer a success
it also erased hundreds of thousands of
jobs
all those accounting clerks who had once
made their livings writing
erasing and rewriting data into paper
spreadsheets
saw their jobs taken over by visicalc
and its many successors
which could do the work much faster but
that's not the end of the story
while it may be true that there are four
hundred thousand fewer accounting clerk
jobs
in the u.s today than there were back in
1980 it's
also true that there are now over 600
000 additional regular accounting jobs
while the electronic spreadsheet may
have eliminated some kinds of jobs
it also created others as well
with the ability to quickly make changes
and run calculations
on a computer the demand for high level
accounting
financial analysis and a lot of other
really
quite nerdy services but also quite
useful services
went way way up accountants could now do
things that were either
impossible or at the very least very
time consuming
in the past as the podcaster tim harford
once put it
automation reshapes the workplace in
ways much subtler than
a robot took my job automation can also
lead to the creation of jobs that
involve more creativity and more
strategic thinking both of which humans
are
pretty good at but that also leads us to
a conclusion
if you want to succeed in an
automation-driven future
then you must keep learning you have to
maximize your ability to think
creatively and you have to become adept
at working with these new tools
and systems and it's not just automation
driving this need for increased learning
either
if automation is the rock then our
increasingly connected economy
which enables remote work and a vastly
larger talent pool
is the hard place if you rest on your
laurels
you'll find yourself caught between them
and that brings us to
the five-hour rule this role simply
states that you should dedicate one hour
per day to learning
five days per week the author michael d
simmons came up with this role after
observing that ben franklin dedicated
one hour per day on his daily schedule
to reading and generally expanding his
knowledge he also noticed a similar
pattern in figures like barack obama
oprah winfrey bill gates and warren
buffett his conclusion is that the
constant among all these people's
success is their commitment to
continually
learning improving their skills and
their general knowledge across the
entirety of their careers and by doing
so
they're always opening themselves up to
new opportunities they're never resting
on their laurels
so that's really the five hour rule in a
nutshell it's an incredibly simple idea
in fact you could print it on a t-shirt
and in fact
i actually do but there are probably two
big questions sticking in your mind
right now
one of them being how do i make time for
constant learning especially if you're
somebody who's really busy with work
already
and number two what should i be
learning so what i want to do with the
rest of this video is answer both of
those questions and let's first start
with how to make
time first you have to acknowledge the
trade-off in simmons article about the
five-hour rule he notes that franklin's
daily hour of work
actually caused him to accomplish less
in terms of short-term productivity
however over time the gains he made
through that constant learning
accelerated they added up and they
propelled him to greater heights than
that extra hour
ever could have franklin understood that
learning
constant learning is a long-term
investment
all right on to more practical advice
starting with this tip
which is upside down i guess but do it
first thing
in the morning if you find it hard to
make yourself disciplined enough to do
your independent learning after work
then get up a little bit earlier in the
morning and do it first
i have found that like the blood pooling
into my head making me less and less
eloquent and able to think over time as
i do this particular shot
as the day wears on my willpower tends
to go down
but if i have a deadline or a boss or
some kind of assignment hanging over my
head
the lack of willpower doesn't matter so
much so take advantage of the maximized
willpower
at the beginning of the day and do your
learning then
secondly work to eliminate low value
activities
from your life see even if you've made
that trade-off acknowledgement in your
head
on an individual day it's quite easy to
say i just don't have time for that hour
of learning i just have so much work to
do
this is also a justification we tend to
use for skipping workouts particularly
when it's leg day
but i would encourage you to examine
that claim for yourself
and if possible test it you can actually
do this using an app like rescuetime
which will track the time you spend
on the apps and websites that you go to
and when you see
just how much time you spend on things
like social media or
mindless youtube binges of which this
could be won
well you're gonna find out that you do
in fact have the ability to cut some of
those low value activities from your
life
and make time for that hour of learning
that brings us to question number two
what should you be learning with this
dedicated daily learning time
well since we're talking about
increasing your career opportunities
even as automation takes over more and
more low-level jobs i want to talk about
three specific
types of learning first learning that
directly impacts the skill set you're
currently using in
your career for example as a youtuber my
main technical skill set
is making videos setting up lights
turning on the camera
all that kind of stuff as a youtuber the
technical requirements for getting
videos made are pretty
low but that didn't stop me from taking
a full week earlier this year to read
this
workflow guide put out by a company
called frame.io
and this is a hundred thousand word
guide that goes through the process
used by professional filmmaking teams
like actual hollywood studios and
documentary crews
and helps them get their bigger works
completed and put onto platforms like
netflix or
even big screen movie theaters and not
only does this guide go through the
entire process
starting with filming going to editing
covering color grading
sound vfx it also gets into really
technical territory exploring
color spaces and bit depth and garbage
mats and all kinds of stuff that i'd
really never heard of before
or at least had never explored and again
as a youtuber my productions are a lot
smaller and i didn't really
need to learn this stuff in order to do
my job but
learning it improved my craft i was
actually able to learn some things that
helped me to
make the workflow that we use for my
channel a lot more efficient
for just one tiny example we found after
reading this guide
that the video codec we were filming
with was actually pretty bad for editing
and that was why we were having a lot of
sluggishness in premiere pro
well one of the reasons why the other
reason being premiere pro
but once we change to a more
edit-friendly codec things got
a lot better and if this example teaches
you anything it's that no matter what
field you're in
there's always some area where you can
broaden or deepen your knowledge so go
find it
secondly we have learning that decreases
domain dependence
essentially domain dependence is what
happens when a person has a ton of
expertise and skills in one particular
area
but they have an inability to transfer
those skills to new
fields even if the two fields have a lot
of underlying similarities and people
with domain dependence
are not very adaptable but luckily the
fix here is pretty simple you just need
to take your skills that you already
have and spend some time applying them
to challenges that are slightly
different than what you're used to
in other words you want to put yourself
in what's called a wicked learning
environment which is the opposite of a
kind learning environment
kind environments have well-defined
rules and often perfect feedback
mechanisms that show you exactly what
you did wrong when you made a mistake
the game of chess is a great example
here but if you spend all of your time
in environments like these then you're
never really developing your ability to
deal with
unforeseen challenges so find a way at
least sometimes to make your learning
environment a bit more wicked for
instance switching up the tools that you
use sometimes
i've found that the time i've spent
building spreadsheets and big formulas
in google sheets has actually made me
better able to think about the templates
and databases that i build
inside of notion these are two very
different tools but they share a lot of
the same
underlying structures and i found that
time spent in either one
makes me better at both of them finally
we have time spent learning skills that
i think
everyone should know these are skills
that will both improve your life but
also sometimes expand your career
opportunities i'm talking about skills
like
public speaking like being able to
evaluate statistics well
budgeting and investing your money
wisely learning how to think logically
and to bring this all around full circle
learning how to make and use
spreadsheets
seriously a good working knowledge of
excel and google sheets can be a
really helpful thing right now my fiance
and i are actually starting to look at
buying a house
and the housing price calculator that i
built for myself in google sheets which
honestly wasn't that hard to do
has been really helpful for showing us
how much we'd probably pay per month
given certain house prices
and certain down payment amounts
whatever you decide to learn the
important thing is that you commit
to lifelong learning i've seen a lot of
people graduate school land a
comfortable job
and then become complacent which is a
dangerous state
to be in so whatever you do just
keep learning now if you're already
committed to continual learning
then one resource you may want to check
out to further that is brilliant
we talked earlier about how creative and
analytical thinking are both
hugely beneficial as automation
technology advances and these are the
exact types of thinking that brilliant
is designed to help you
improve for example their computer
science fundamentals course doesn't just
throw a bunch of code at you
instead it helps you think about
algorithms abstractly so you understand
how they work at a fundamental level and
having a firm grasp in these concepts
is even more important than knowing how
to code in any one particular language
these concepts make you more
adaptable though i will note that
brilliant does have a great python
programming course
and that course alongside brilliant
other courses across math science and
computer science
all focus on active hands-on learning so
you'll find yourself progressing more
quickly
and staying interested for longer in the
library you're going to find a full math
suite ranging from basic number theory
all the way up to vector calculus and
finance math so you can use that to
progressively go through entire math
education
along with science courses including one
on electricity and magnetism
and computer science courses covering
machine learning search engines
and like i said before algorithms so if
you want to start improving your
problem-solving abilities and learn an
active hands-on way then get started by
going over to brilliant.org
thomasfrank which you'll find in the
description down below and if you're one
of the first 200 people to use that link
to sign up you're even gonna get 20
off their annual premium subscription
guys that's it thank you so much for
watching
if you enjoyed this video and found it
helpful maybe consider gently fist
bumping that like
button with your middle knuckle you do
have to be specific here and if you're
looking for something additional to
watch i'm now doing some q a videos over
on my instagram
multiple videos per week so if you want
to follow me down in the description
down below i'll have a link
and you can get those videos whenever i
post them beyond that subscribe right
there if you haven't done so already
otherwise click the other videos i've
got linked
on the screen right now if you want to
keep watching stuff here on youtube or
don't do any of that and go do whatever
you want because as always i'm not your
dad