[Music]
hey what's up it's Thomas from college
infogeek today I'm going to show you how
to make a cool accent lighting system
for your room with Christmas lights and
a simple lamp dimmer and here's an
example of how it
works so let's get started all right all
right the first step to putting this up
is to put a nail in your wall up near
the ceiling and if you're in a dorm room
and you don't want to put holes in your
walls you can use a 3M command strip but
honestly the nails work better for this
project now not to insult your
intelligence but I'm going to
demonstrate it here
anyway and you want it to stick out just
a little bit and then you just string
your Christmas lights up by sticking the
nail in between the Twisted cords now
once this goes all the way around the
room basically holds itself up with no
adhesives or anything needed all right
step two is to acquire a tableside lamp
dmer from your local hardware store such
as Lowe's or Home Depot looks like this
I've got mine mounted to my bedside but
it doesn't come with adhesive so you
might want to buy some mounting tape to
mount it to your wall if you want and
you just take the lamp dimmer plug plug
it into any old
outlet and then take the Christmas
lights plug them into the lamp dimmer
and you're ready to
go I did not think Christmas lights were
dimer compatible I honestly bought this
setup just to turn them off and on but I
was pleasantly surprised to find out
that they actually work on dimmers so
now my room can be said to any number of
different lighting types that's all
there is to it if you're watching this
on YouTube you can click the link in the
description to see the full blog post
with cost breakdowns and other
information for more dorm DIY and
college tips and tricks check out
College infogeek
see you