let's be real here you and I both know
that the one singular difference between
you and people like JK Rowling Elon Musk
Saitama isn't your smarts it isn't your
motivation and it isn't even your work
ethic meet one difference between you
and them is that you are constantly
tired right if not for that one teensy
little difference then you'd easily be
able to crank out a couple of chapters
in the next great American novel each
morning before heading out to fight
crime and lesser tasks like studying for
exams and not subsisting entirely after
Totino's pizza rolls would be trivially
easy but as it stands you can't do those
things because you are basically a
zombie
well maybe not like a literal zombie
like in that one episode of space dandy
but the similarities are mounting you
got bags under your eyes you feel
sluggish and there's that inexplicable
craving for raw meat but more
importantly you just don't have the
energy to do the things you want to do
on a daily basis so what I want to do
today is explore some methods for
breaking that cycle of constant
tiredness and getting back your daily
energy reserves now before we get
started I do want to mention that I am
NOT talking about conditions like
chronic fatigue syndrome and STI d which
affect millions of people here in the US
alone and are very difficult to cure and
pin down what I am talking about is that
much more common feeling of general
tiredness that affects many many more
people and is entirely preventable
through adopting healthier habits chief
among them being to get better sleep now
you've probably seen their
recommendations put out by the National
Sleep Foundation about how many hours
you should be sleeping each night based
on your age but even if you're using
those figures to set your alarm clock
you still might be waking up in the
morning feeling like you just got hit by
a truck and if that's the case it's
probably because you're not respecting
your body's sleep cycle C during the
night sleep happens in several different
stages that each correspond to different
levels of brain activity and together
these are known as the sleep cycle now
I'll link to some sources down below if
you want to go more in depth on this but
what you need to know right now is that
if you wake up in the wrong stage of the
sleep cycle you're gonna feel absolutely
awful and that's a risk you run when you
use an alarm clock for most of human
history we didn't have access to alarm
clocks or electric lights for that
matter our sleep patterns were much more
in tune with the cycle of day and night
and they're also governed by the body's
sleep cycle itself someone living before
the invention of the alarm clock would
almost always wake up at the completion
of a sleep cycle as they were disturbed
by something like a roosters crow or an
invasion among those
because of that they'd almost always
wake up feeling well-rested by contrast
if you let an alarm clock startle you
awake in the middle of a sleep cycle
then you're gonna be waking up in Zombie
mode as Pierce J Howard put it in his
book the owners manual for the brain a
person who sleeps only four cycles or
six hours will feel more rested than
someone who has slept for eight to ten
hours but who has not been allowed to
complete any one cycle because it being
wakened before it was completed now each
of these sleep cycles takes an average
of 90 minutes to complete and in the
past I recommended the site called
sleepy type me which uses that number to
help you figure out when you should wake
up based on your bedtime but one thing
I've learned recently is that this 90
minute figure really is just an average
and it can vary by up to 30 minutes in
either direction so instead of just
setting your alarm based on that 90
minute ballpark figure you should
instead work to figure out when you
naturally wake up this might take a
while for you learn but once you know
what it is you can then use your alarm
as a backup method and ideally you'd
wake up at the completion of your final
sleep cycle before it goes off in a
natural well-rested State the alarm is
just there to make sure you do get up on
time if something goes wrong of course
that also means you need to get to the
habit of actually going to bed on time
to wake up before that alarm goes off
and if you have trouble doing this like
I do I did make an entire video that
I'll link to in the description down
below but the main key habit you to
establish now is building a winddown
ritual basically you want to disengage
from anything you typically get sucked
into well before your bedtime for me
this means turning off my computer
around 9 p.m. each night otherwise I'll
convince myself I can answer a couple of
emails and then I'll inevitably get
sucked into a click hole quiz to see if
I have what it takes to train Freddy
Krueger to be a barista spoilers I
really really don't now even if you have
got a rock-solid sleep schedule you
might still be suffering from a couple
of problems that are really common to
students and that are related a lot of
sunlight exposure and a lack of exercise
we're gonna get into some science here
in a second but first I do want to note
that when I feel tired during the day
when I get those feelings of brain fog
going outside for a 20 minute walk
always works is the number one method
that can get me out of that state so I
definitely recommend trying it out and
honestly this makes intuitive sense
because our bodies were designed to move
humans used to trek miles and miles to
catch their prey and even when we turn
to agriculture for food production
that's still involved being outside for
most a day doing hard work and plus you
get to wear stylish overalls but now a
lot of us are sedentary we spend a lot
of time in chairs and all the time we
sink into screens and books keeps us
indoors and away from the Sun
that could be a huge contributor to why
you feel so tired it might not be as
obvious a connection as it is for plants
which need nothing but sunlight and
brawn doh
but make no mistake the Sun plays a huge
role in maintaining your energy levels
for one sunlight exposure helps your
body correctly time its production of
melatonin which is a hormone that helps
you go to sleep and plays a part in
maintaining your circadian rhythm which
helps you stay in sync with the cycle of
day and night but sunlight exposure is
also your body's main source of vitamin
D which not only plays a role in keeping
your bones healthy keeps your immune
system working and your lungs working
but also plays a big role in helping you
avoid fatigue a study that was done in
2014 found a high correlation between
vitamin D deficiency and fatigue as well
as a big improvement in those fatigue
symptoms once patients of the study got
their vitamin D levels back to normal
now you might think that you can just
eat better food to get your vitamin D
but that isn't the case while improving
your diet will definitely help your
energy levels in other ways as Mark
Sisson points out in his book the primal
blueprint dietary efforts to obtain
vitamin D are almost inconsequential
compared to sun exposure put some hard
numbers behind that a standard American
diet will get you about 300 I use or
international units of vitamin D per day
but experts recommend getting around
4,000 that's a pretty big gap but
fortunately just going outside for 20
minutes during the peak months of saw
exposure can easily make up the
difference now one thing to note here is
that sun exposure alone often isn't
enough during the winter months if you
don't live near the equator it's just
not powerful enough which is why a lot
of people suffer from seasonal affective
disorder so if that's the case for you
you might also want to look into a
vitamin D supplement during those months
but even with those it is a good idea to
try to get outside of the Sun at least a
little bit every single day even if it's
for just a quick look and that brings us
the topic of exercise now you might be
thinking I'm gonna tell you that the
only way to not feel tired all the time
is to do an intense workout every single
day but luckily that isn't the case in
fact just doing some low intensity
exercise like going for a 20-minute walk
outside like we just said might even be
more effective at getting rid of those
symptoms of fatigue and brain fog than a
more intense workout in 2008 researchers
at the University of Georgia did a study
and found that students who did just 20
minutes of exercise three times a week
had huge improvements in both their
daily energy levels and their levels of
fatigue and what's more their
improvements in these areas were
actually better than the group in the
study that did more intense exercise so
the bottom line is if you're tired of
time get some exercise every single day
doing a heavy bench work out or running
10 miles is fun for you then defin
do that but if not you'll still benefit
from a quick walk at a pace that won't
make you spill your coffee
and speaking of coffee let's talk about
caffeine now I am NOT gonna outright
condemn caffeine here because if you use
it every once in a while it can actually
be a useful tool for staving off fatigue
when you need to finish a particularly
big project but as this recovering
caffeine addict can tell you it is super
easy to start using caffeine on a
regular basis and that is where the
problems begin for starters if you drink
something caffeinated late enough in the
day it can really mess with your sleep
and by late enough I'm not talking about
like a 9:00 p.m. cup of joe I'm talking
about like six hours before bedtime
according to one study so if you have an
afternoon coffee you could be
compromising your sleep which just makes
you further dependent on it the next day
additionally much like any other drug
your body starts to build up a tolerance
to caffeine as you use it regularly to
put this really really simply your body
and your brain both have lots of
receptors for a compound called
adenosine and this compound tells your
body that it's tired and that it's ready
to sleep caffeine works by essentially
impersonating that adenosine then it
blocks up the receptors and it prevents
the adenosine from getting through which
makes you temporarily feel like you're
energetic and not tired the author
Stephen Braun like in this process to
putting a block of wood underneath one
of the brains primary brake pedals once
the caffeine is moved through your
system though all that built-up
adenosine comes rushing through creating
that all-too-familiar caffeine crash not
only that but regular caffeine use will
also cause your body to upregulate to
create more adenosine receptors and that
means that as time goes on you need more
and more caffeine to do the same job and
get the same feeling eventually become
like my friend in college who would chug
three to four pots of coffee every
single day now if you are already at
that point maybe you are that friend of
mine from college or you're on your way
to it like I have been at several points
in my life the process of weaning
yourself off of caffeine can be tough
adopting the sleep and exercise habits
we've already talked about in this video
can definitely help but you can also use
the following few tips to make the
process even easier first if you drink
coffee or energy drinks try switching to
tea almost t does have some caffeine
it's almost always a lot less than those
other drinks and for those of you that
think tea tastes like dirty rain water
out of a gutter I have three words for
you loose leaf tea not only is it more
flavorful and higher-quality in the bag
kind but there are hundreds of different
flavors out there if you're a coffee
drinker you might wanna start with
something like girl Grey or Irish
Breakfast which aren't exactly like
coffee but when mixed with milk make
pretty good
substitutes second use a habit tracking
up like a bita and do a 30-day challenge
to kick caffeine this will give you a
little bit of extra motivation because
you now have a tangible goal that you're
working towards and you're marking on
your progress every single day and
lastly drink more water and you can
create this habit by carrying your own
water bottle with you wherever you go
this will basically make water or
replacement for all those caffeinated
drinks you usually turn to and well it
won't give you a buzz it actually will
help with those feelings of fatigue and
brain fog even mild dehydration can make
you feel tired
that's because basically every part of
your body including your brain needs a
good supply of water to function
properly and while the old advice to get
eight glasses a day might not be
scientifically sound most people aren't
even getting close to that amount and
that often includes me I don't bring
that water bottle with me when I go out
I will drink barely any water during the
day at all all right we have covered a
lot in this video so let's do a quick
recap if you want to not be tired of
time you want to be energetic first get
enough sleep and respect your body's
sleep cycles by not waking up with an
alarm clock try to wake up naturally and
use your alarm clock just as a backup
second get outside get a little bit of
sunlight exposure every single day and
in the winter months also consider using
a vitamin D supplement third get some
exercise every day as well even if it's
something relatively low-level like
going for a quick walk or pulling around
jumbo jets with your teeth fourth use
caffeine sparingly use it as a tool
don't be like my friend in college and
drink three or four pots of coffee a day
and build independence and finally
number five make sure you drinking
enough water now you might be thinking
that none of these habits seems
particularly out of blue or insightful
but I would ask you how many of them are
you sticking to because really avoiding
a life of constant tiredness comes down
to adopting healthy habits they might
seem obvious but sometimes we need a
simple reminder we need to stop and make
a commitment or put a system in place to
make us take them seriously especially
when we have things like goals and
school and relationships
video games all vying for our attention
at the same time now I don't agree with
a lot of what the dude says these days
but Elliott Hulse made a very good point
when he said the most important part of
the game is your game piece so make your
health a priority and in return you'll
be rewarded with an uncommon level of
energy and focus that you can use to
tackle all those other things with a
much greater level of intensity you
might even find yourself with the energy
to take on projects that you wouldn't
have even considered before instead of
finishing your homework and then just
watching Netflix or playing video games
you might actually have the energy to
teach yourself how to build video game
so learn landscape photography and
instead of just ordering pizza or make
it something easy you might actually
want to cook something that takes real
skill once you're at that point you'll
probably want to accelerate your
learning process as much as you possibly
can and that is exactly what you can do
with skill share with over 17,000
courses in a ton of different subjects
scousers library can help you quickly
build confidence in almost any area you
can think of photography music
production game design and yes even
cooking I recently took their knife
skills class which taught me some
techniques that I would have never
thought of in my own and that are
helping me spend a lot less time on
vegetable prep when I'm in the kitchen
which means that I'm actually cooking
with vegetables a lot more often and
rather than just giving you the
information like in lecture skills
courses offer hands-on projects I'll put
what you've learned the test and that'll
challenge you to improve your skills
even more quickly plus if you happen to
want help or you want feedback on your
project you can get it for both the
teacher in that course and the other
people taking it alongside you so if
you're ready to put all that newfound
energy into learning a new skill
effectively give Skillshare a try the
first 500 people who sign up put the
link down below get a free two-month
trial and after that a premium
subscription is as low as ten bucks a
month if you want to keep learning and
if not it's super easy to cancel thanks
so much to Skillshare for sponsoring
this video and helping to support this
channel seriously I love working with
Skillshare they are great guys over
there and guys as always thank you so
much for watching if you enjoyed this
video and you found it to be useful then
leaving like definitely helps this
channel out and if there's something I
didn't mention here that you found
useful in your own life definitely leave
a comment down below so other people can
benefit from it and speaking of things
that were left out I know we didn't even
scratch the surface when it comes to
nutrition and we also didn't talk about
how to take naps effectively so I will
definitely do videos on those topics in
the future and you want to get notified
about them and anything else I release
you can subscribe to this channel right
there and you can also hit that Bell
down below if you want to actually get
notifications additionally if you want
to get a free copy of my book and how to
earn better grades you can click right
there to get that you can also click
right there to watch our latest podcast
episode lastly if you want to watch
another video on this channel click
right there YouTube has select one and
you will probably enjoy it anyway
thanks for watching and I'll see you
next week