hey what's up guys so today I am really
excited to finally announce the launch
of something that I have been wanting to
build for years I kept it up in my head
as an idea for a long time but finally
last week I got around to building it
and there is now an official Community
for college infogeek and I decided to
set up as a subreddit on reddit.com and
I'll kind of explain the choice of that
platform in a minute but first I kind of
want to tell you kind of My overall idea
for what I hope this community can be
and if you want to check it out the URL
is college infog geek.com commmunity you
can check it out right there and um
essentially what I want to make this is
like the premier place for us to have
discussions for questions to be answered
for discussion to be had around videos
because YouTube comments while they're
cool and it's always great to get
feedback on them on the videos I make
YouTube comments and blog comments uh
likewise are are just set up for
reactions for the video maker like you
watch a video and then you can react to
it you can respond to it and then people
can reply to your comments that's true
but these systems are not set up to
promote good discussion between multiple
people in the audience between like me
and multiple people at once and um
likewise my email is only set up for me
to be able to correspond with one person
at a time and if I answer a question on
my email then only one person gets to
see that answer so I've always wanted to
set up like some sort of discussion
forum where we can all help each other
out and where all those answers can be
visible and where good discussion can be
promoted I chose Reddit because I've
been on Reddit for four years and I've
gotten a lot of value out of the site
there's certainly like certain areas of
the site with trolls sarcastic people
but in my experience the smaller
interest based subreddits where people
are trying to learn new skills or just
get better at things in general those
are always overflowing with positivity
and people just trying to help each
other out and um that's what I'm kind of
hoping this community will be and I
actually wanted to test it out before I
went live and told everyone about it so
I set it up last Tuesday I think is when
I went live and I kind of just told like
a little small percentage of the people
who are subscribed to the newsletter so
we've been having discussions in there
for the past week and it's going great
and I would love for you to join in and
help this subreddit grow to become like
the premier place for discussions to
happen around my videos uh that's kind
of like the first purpose of this
community I'm going to be making a
discussion thread for every new video
going forward and you'll find it linked
in the description for those videos and
I'm kind of hoping that most of the good
discussion on new videos can go over
there where people can upvote the best
comments and where replies are much
easier for me to see um I will say it's
like it's pretty hard for me to see
replies to comments on YouTube I can see
the new ones but it's really hard for me
see like replies and on Reddit that's
really really easy for me to see so
discussion for videos is going to be
there I'm also going to try to be
answering most questions from you guys
over on the community rather than email
because like I said with email only one
person can benefit from that answer and
to be honest it's really hard for me to
answer questions in the first place like
I can answer a few but all of them just
kind of gets overwhelming with the rest
of the work I have to do but with the
community I'll be able to answer just as
many as I was via email but also there's
so many of you guys out there who
already have have lots of answers and
knowledge and experience that I don't
have so if you've got a question there's
likely going to be somebody else who can
provide an answer and you can go to see
the threads right now in the community
I'm pretty sure every thread there right
now has an answer from someone even if
it's not me so ask your questions there
also if you have uh tips of your own or
experiences that you want to post about
they can definitely benefit other
students and if you got topics that
you'd like to see me cover on the
channel in the future or maybe guests
that would be good on the college
infogeek podcast I'm going to be making
a official topic request thread that'll
be at the top of the community every
single month so if you put your requests
there it'll be like a nice place to
consolidate them and I can kind of see
which ones people are up booting and
which ones I should make next also this
is kind of a way to hand a little bit of
the control of this project to you guys
because I'm really open to your ideas
and I want to hear like how we can make
this uh College info geek as a project
overall better for students all over the
world so uh if you have ideas there's
going to be an official discussion
thread for this launch video I'll have
it linked down in the description below
and I would love to hear your ideas for
what we can do in the Community to make
it better maybe we can have like monthly
discussion threads on certain topics
where you guys can submit your ideas or
your best tips or maybe favorite apps
and tools things like that and uh
otherwise yeah just let me know what you
think and I would absolutely love to see
you in the community you can subscribe
using Reddit it's really easy to create
an account and uh there's also apps for
pretty much every smartphone that can
make it really easy to browse on the go
so I'll see you over in the community
and as always thank you so much for
watching