should you take your notes on a computer
or should you stick to a paper notebook
if you're watching this video you're
probably looking for ways to take more
efficient notes in class and also make
those notes easier to study later so
which method is the best for both of
those on the one hand taking notes on a
computer is in most cases a lot faster
than writing them down by hand you can
also go back and add things to already
written notes reformat things easily and
as an added benefit you can sync things
to different devices if you're using an
app like Evernote that way you can study
notes on your phone or any other device
you have with you but on the other hand
when you take your notes on paper you
have a lot more flexibility you can draw
arrows and notes make symbols a lot
easier and for math notes it's hands
down a better method also there are some
research findings that actually speak in
favor of paper notes and those are what
I want to cover in this video the study
which you can read more about if you go
to the companion blog post for this
video found that students who take their
notes on a computer tend to write an
average of 310 words per lecture on the
other hand students who wrote on paper
took notes at an average of 173 words
the study also found that students who
took their notes on paper were more
readily able to recall what they had
learned about a half an hour after the
lecture and the conclusion that the
researchers came to was that students
who take their notes on laptops were
more apt to just record Verbatim what
was said in the lecture while students
who took their notes on paper were
actually recording what they were
learning and creating new conclusions on
the fly now my last video on notetaking
systems I talked about a system called
the flow method of not taking this
system was created by Scott young and
it's based on a principle he created
called holistic learning and holistic
learning basically means taking points
of information that may be unrelated
making a giant web of them and making
new conclusions out of that information
the foundational idea behind holistic
learning is to learn it once learn the
lecture material while you're in class
by creating your own version of it in
your notes and this is the point I want
to get at in this video whether or not
you choose to take your notes on a
computer or paper you need to be
deliberate about learning as well as you
can in class through the way you take
your notes think of it this way when
your professor presents A New Concept
class your brain interprets the data in
two different ways it sees the syntax of
the phrase of the word that was said the
letters and the way the words are
arranged in the sentence but it also
sees the meaning behind it so if your
professor says that koalas eat
eucalyptus leaves your brain sees the
sentence and the letters that make it up
the syntax but it also sees two
different concepts eucalyptus leaves and
quala bears and connects them together
now when you're recording your notes on
a computer it can be really easy to just
slip into the mindset of recording every
single thing that was said and when you
do this you're only paying attention to
the syntax which means that later on you
have to go back and relearn the concepts
people who take notes on paper are more
apt to look at the concepts as they're
presented and learn them right away this
is because they're not using so much
brain power on recording every little
detail in the lecture so if you choose
to take your notes on a computer be
deliberate about learning the concepts
as they're presented don't be a
transcription machine or if you find
that the temptation to just mindlessly
record notes on your computer is too
great try switching to to paper after
you've taken some notes on paper you can
use an app on your phone to record them
and store them in Evernote not only will
this give you access to your notes
wherever you have your phone but it also
makes the text of your notes searchable
as long as your handwriting isn't crap
so that's it for this video the takeaway
here is just to be deliberate about
learning the concepts that are presented
in class as they're being presented
instead of just trying to record them
all if you don't do this you're just
creating a lot more study time for
yourself after
class hey thanks for watching my video
if you liked it share it with a friend
or give it a like you'll be making the
internet a better place by adding a
number to a picture of a thumb yeah if
you want to get more videos every single
week on being a better student becoming
more productive and hacking your studies
then hit the Subscribe button which I'll
point out right about now if you missed
last week's video it's over the best
note taking systems out there and click
the moving picture underneath that to
watch it if you want to get links to the
study I talked about in this video click
the orange logo to go to the companion
blog post for this episode
also if you want to get a free chapter
of my book when it comes out click that
button lastly if you've got ideas you
want to share for a new video or just
want to connect hit me up on Twitter or
leave a comment