this video is sponsored by curiosity
stream and nebula hello and welcome
to yet another what's in my bag video
it's been
two years since i did a what's in my
backpack video and for the first time in
this series i'm not showcasing a
backpack i've actually switched from
using a backpack for pretty much my
whole life
to a brand new bag so in this video we
are gonna go through
my bag what's in it what i carry with me
on a daily basis when i go about my work
uh my edc the things that are not in the
bag
but on my person and i'm also going to
explain why i switched over to this
weird looking bag
instead of sticking with my tried and
true backpack and i think we're actually
going to start with this
so this is an ortlieb uh
city commuter pannier bag for a bike
and it's got this killer feature here
which is the ability
to automatically hook on to a bike rack
so if you have a bike with a rear rack
this can just clip on it's got this cool
quick release system so it can just
easily be put on there but once it's on
there it is completely secure so the
reason that i'm using this which you may
have seen me talk about in other videos
is that i recently bought an
e-bike and i've been commuting to a
downtown office about
44 miles round-trip on the days when i'm
not in the studio filming
and i love doing that but biking with a
backpack in the summer
is a recipe for becoming a complete hot
sweaty mess no matter what kind of
backpack you get
so this thing's killer feature is the
ability to go onto the rear rack
and allow me to bike with having nothing
on my back which is pretty sweet it's
also completely
waterproof so even when i've been caught
in rainstorms i don't worry about all
the stuff inside
anyway let's talk about what i'm packing
on a daily basis
so the main thing about this bag is it's
pretty much just
one big cavernous
space on the inside there are a couple
of pen holders there's a couple of
hidden pockets
but in terms of bags with like secret
tech and all the stuff
this doesn't really bring that to the
table it's just sort of cavernous space
that hooks onto your bike
but it is pretty big so i'm able to fit
pretty much everything that i need on a
daily basis into it so that includes
a 16-inch macbook pro a couple of years
ago i had this brief flirtation with a
windows laptop uh
that was very brief this is just so much
better in terms of portability and build
quality
than any windows laptop i have tried so
even though i am still a pc
user when it comes to the desktop side
i'm full on
apple when it comes to anything portable
we also have
the 11-inch ipad pro and on a lot of
days if i'm just gonna go to a coffee
shop or something i will often not bring
the laptop
because this thing functions as a pretty
complete
laptop replacement as long as i don't
need to edit or do
some kind of like photo manipulation or
anything if i'm just researching
i did a whole video about this earlier
this year this thing is actually
perfectly adequate for research and in
some cases even better
than the macbook because of an app
called command which allows me to
highlight
passages in my browser and then send
them over to notion via a pretty cool
integration i've also found that the
apple keyboard case is actually
really nice my hands are kind of big so
at first it took me a little bit to get
used to the keyboard here since it is
smaller than a standard size keyboard
but now that i'm used to it i can type
pretty much as fast as i can on my
regular mechanical keyboard and because
of the pencil it's great for if i want
to draw or take handwritten notes
i don't do that too often but sometimes
i'll get an idea for a diagram that i
want to sketch out and the ipad is
absolutely device for that
next up we have a couple of books uh
this is a random walk down wall street
and then we have seth godin's the dip
highly recommend this book i actually
reread this book very recently because i
was
contemplating whether or not to quit
something in my life and i'm going to be
doing a summary
video of this book pretty soon so get
subscribed if you want to see my take on
it but also
you can read this book in like an hour
and it's very well worth your time
next up we've got trusty wireless
headphones and i'm actually in the
process
of testing new wireless headphones
because my trusty bose qc35s are
starting to die
and there are newer ones on the market
so these are the apple airpods
max and i'm currently testing these and
then i will be testing the sony xm4s
and the bose 700 and i'm gonna do a
whole video about those
and basically give you my opinion on
which one's best so again get subscribed
if you want to see that in the future
these are pretty annoying when it comes
to the case
this case is absolutely uh ridiculous it
baffles me
why did they design it this way but
gotta say the sound so far is pretty
stellar so
even though these are goofy and
expensive they are definitely a
contender
and i'll give you my full opinion when i
test the other ones and get
my whole verdict sorted out now one
thing that i mentioned in my last
backpack video is that i always have a
folder
this one has a saturn made out of pizza
with a metal ring i'm not sure
why but it's always good to have a
folder in your backpack even if you're a
completely digital person because you're
always gonna
come across random bits of paper that
you may need to save i've got like
floor dimensions for my house in here
from a long time ago but most recently
some receipts for
some things that i need to expense later
on so keep a folder in your bag
and your life will be better a clean
canteen water bottle always good to have
this is usually living on the
water bottle rack on my bike but it's in
my bag right now
and finally chargers one for the macbook
pro
oh i will show you this thing i don't
know if you can zoom in very well on a
tony
i don't know where to get this but you
can get this little
hippo thing that goes in the end of your
cord it just keeps the usbc connector
from getting
bent and fraying that core connection i
got it as a stocking stuffer a couple
years ago for christmas so i don't know
where you'd get it but
it's great and i was gonna mention it
and last but not least for the bag a pen
so that is the stuff that lives in my
bag every day let's now move into
uh the other bag that i keep with me
because basically every time
i go somewhere i also have this bag
which is just one of those like
cheap drawstring bags and it's just my
workout bag
so there's a couple of interesting
things in here uh first and foremost
because i work with a coach who is in
springfield missouri and i'm in denver
colorado
i have to film my sets when i work out
so i can send them to him for critique
so i've got this cool little
contraption that gives me a super
portable
tall tripod that fits right into this
bag it is
the switch pod which is actually created
by my friends pat flynn
and caleb wojcik and it is one of my
favorite pieces of video gear ever made
it's kind of like the gorillapod if it
was even better
paired with the selfie stick that comes
with
the insta 360 360 camera and
on the end of that is just a really
cheap phone mount that i got from amazon
so by basically taking the selfie stick
and screwing it into the bottom of the
switch pod with
twist rod here you get a tripod of sorts
and then this thing
and telescope so when i'm in the gym i
need to film a squat set or
a deadlift set or anything else i can
create this tripod and then break it
down
so it fits into this tiny little bag
also within this bag
we have got a lifting belt which is
great if you're doing heavy barbell
training
this one's from amazon it's pro fitness
it's pretty cheap but it gets the job
done
we also have some wrist wraps these are
great for
uh supporting your wrists when you're
doing heavy presses or heavy bench
presses so those always go with me
and i didn't know these existed until my
coach told me to buy them
you can get 1.25 pound
plates so if you're doing something like
shoulder press where your gains
typically don't come five pounds at a
time
these allow you to go up just two and a
half pounds which means you can
keep the rep range that you are doing
with your programming
while still going up consistently in
weight every week
so that just leaves the edc portion
which stands for everyday carry and
there
are a few things that i do carry on my
person which are interesting so we're
gonna add
them into this video as well the first
thing is the phone
so you know phones aren't all that
interesting but i will say that i did
opt for
the iphone 12 mini when i upgraded my
phone earlier this year and
hot take the mini is the best size of
the iphone
if you haven't tried it seriously give
it a try fits in your pocket so much
better
and uh it's just it's just the best size
of phone
but cooler than the phone is this little
magsafe wallet that you can get for
apple which
slaps onto the back of it and gives you
the ability to carry one or two credit
cards on the back of your phone but what
i've actually got in the back of my
wallet
is probably the coolest thing in this
video
it's this thing called the pocket tripod
so it looks like a credit card it is
about the thickness
of maybe one and a half credit cards but
if you transform it
like this you get an instant tripod
so if we put it down here and we slap
the phone in it
now you have a tripod well hello there
so you can easily film something and i
was actually filming a little bit of
footage for my headphone review video in
the coffee shop today
next up we have the airpods pro which
are one of
my favorite things that i own actually
and these things last forever in terms
of battery
and the noise cancellation is a game
changer when i'm in places where i don't
necessarily have my big headphones but
might
need some cancellation so love having
these they're pretty much always in my
pocket
uh additionally always in my pocket is
this pocket knife so i usually keep this
in my left pocket it's great for opening
boxes
and this is the ontario knives
rat 2 and i guess rat stands for
randall's adventure training i'm not
sure who randall was
but uh he makes a pretty good knife it's
like 20 i've bought this for
a christmas present for several
different people and i've had this one
myself
for probably three four years now it's a
great knife sharpen it sometimes
just useful tool speaking of useful
tools this one on my wrist
is probably one of the most useful ones
that i have so the apple watch
uh number one tells the time gives me
the weather but also
tracks my exercise and as you can see i
have not yet done enough exercise today
which is not good for me because i'm
currently in a fitness competition with
brian from real engineering
so i will be going to the gym right
after filming this so i don't fall
behind in that competition
but in addition to the exercise tracking
here
i have the ability to tap one button and
get to my voice memos so i'm
constantly recording voice memos i've
got tons of ideas for videos and like i
said in my iphone apps roundup video
from last week i do like using otter
more than the built-in voice members app
but if i'm driving or if i'm on
the bike and just don't have quick
access to my phone i'll hit this in a
pinch i'm able to record my thoughts and
save them
so i can turn them into a video or a
song idea or what have you
that brings us to the wallet so this is
a
dash wallet which i believe is like 20
bucks i got mine on amazon
it's a pretty cool minimalist wallet
that actually holds
quite a few cards but before i talk
about a few that are in here i do want
my editor
tony to talk about his wallet because it
is honestly cooler than mine
all right so with this wallet it's
called i think it's called the set grid
or secreted wallet i
i don't know how to pronounce that but
this wallet is a wallet i got in canada
when tom and i went
a couple years ago and the cool thing
about this wallet is that
it keeps everything inside a little slit
so when you actually need to get your
your cards there's a little button right
here in the bottom all you do is pull
down
and your wallets shoot up and the cool
thing about this is you can fit up to
five cards in this wallet but then if
you need additional little bit like a
little bit more space what you do is
just open it up
and you have a little bit more space if
you want to put some money uh right here
in this little flap
and then just extra card slots anyway in
my wallet which is way too full of cards
for that wallet i think there are a
couple of interesting cards that i will
point out so recently i switched over to
the sofi card
for my main credit card the reason i'm
using this one is it gives you two
percent cash back as long as you use it
to buy stocks and i was using the
capital one
quicksilver card which gives you 1.5
cashback so
as long as i'm investing my rewards i'm
getting point five percent cash back on
every single purchase when i use this
card
so it's now my main card another cool
card actually
probably a cooler card is the carrot
card so this is a credit card
specifically for creators
and uh it gets me a pretty decent
percent cash back
on tech and travel but the coolest thing
is
i got to engrave my little sunglasses
llama right onto the front of the card
and they actually let you engrave pretty
much any design you want so
this is probably my favorite credit card
it's also metal so
i try not to drop it because it's
basically like a throwing star
last but not least is this canadian
10 bill which is of pretty much no use
to me except for the fact
that it contains hidden guitar picks
that is pretty much
my edc there's also some keys you can
get these at your local hardware store
though they probably will not
be identical to mine at least that's how
i would like it
and i know i kind of rushed through
everything in this video so
over on nebula i actually have a collab
with my friend elia dahl where each of
us go through our daily gear in more
detail
and that is live on nebula now so if you
want to get that video
plus ad free versions of my youtube
videos before they go live here on
youtube you are going to want to get on
nebula if you haven't heard about it it
is a streaming service that i built with
some of my awesome creator friends
brian from real engineering sam from
wendover productions marques brownlee
from
mkbhd and tons of other creators that
you know
and love on nebula you get ad-free
versions of our videos before they go
live here on youtube but you also get
exclusive videos that are only on nebula
and that is because
nebula is a platform that we the
creators actually own and that allows us
to experiment
and branch out from our normal content
bubbles which makes nebula the best
place to follow my content along with
the content from tons of other great
creators
and the best way to get nebula is
actually to get curiosity stream because
we have teamed up with the folks over at
curiositystream to offer a bundle where
when you use the link in the description
down below you get a full year of both
curiosity stream and
nebula together for over 26 off the
normal price less than 15
bucks a year and for that price not only
do you get access to nebula but you also
get access to all the high quality
documentaries on curiosity stream there
are thousands of them curiosity stream
is the best place on the internet to get
documentaries
and one that i have to recommend this
week is actually nick offerman's history
of
the home number one nick offerman is my
home's patron saint i've got a picture
of him over my fireplace
so always got to give a shout out to my
boy nick offerman but also
i've been doing a lot of work on my own
home studio recently so i thought it
would be a great recommendation for you
and in addition to that documentary
there are thousands of others covering
history nature science technology so it
is a great
platform for expanding your knowledge
and again once you get that you also get
access to nebula so once again use the
link in the description
down below to sign up to get a full year
of both curiosity stream and nebula
for 26 off and in doing so you'll also
be supporting my channel and a ton of
other great
educational creators thanks as always
for watching hopefully you found
something interesting in this video it's
always a pretty interesting format to do
and maybe you found something that
you're going to be adding to your bag or
edc
or maybe i convinced you to try biking
to work or biking to school or wherever
you have to go
because that's something that i'm pretty
passionate about getting more people to
bike
and drive less often anyway thanks again
for watching and i will see you in the
next video stay cute