if you've been following my channel for
any length of time then you probably
know already that I am a sucker for a
good quote I love putting them in my
scripts I love building little
animations for them so today I'm going
to double down on that love of quotes
and share five quotes that are very very
meaningful to me some of these Quotes
come from people that I know personally
some come from just public figures and
famous people that I admire but each
quote on this list represents an idea
that has helped me to make a big
Improvement to some area of my life be
it my work ethic or my ability to make
decisions or my ability to update my
beliefs these are all things that I try
to live by and that's why I want to
share them with you today and to start
things off let's just jump immediately
to my favorite quote of all time which
comes from Bruce Lee and his book The Da
of Jeet kundo research your own
experience absorb what is useful reject
what is useless and add what is
essentially your own this quote from
Bruce Lee is a constant reminder of the
fact that as we go through life we are
essentially building a library of stuff
that works in our brain which means that
not all the advice we receive from other
people as we go through life is going to
be useful to us not all advice is
applicable in every single situation or
to every single person and if you want a
great example of this picture the CEO of
a giant corporation like Mark benof of
salesforce.com or Jeff Bezos talking to
a brand new entrepreneur somebody who's
maybe 19 years old just getting their
start if Jeff Bezos or Mark benov said
the best thing you can possibly do right
now to help your company grow is hire a
bunch of assistants so so you can
delegate all of your work well that
would be terrible advice for that person
who was just getting started because
somebody like Jeff Bezos has a lot of
money has a lot of capital resources but
doesn't have a whole lot of personal
time given all the responsibilities and
projects he's got going on so for Jeff
Bezos or Mark benof or some powerful CEO
delegation hiring people that makes a
lot of sense but for that Scrappy
firsttime entrepreneur who's just trying
to get their business off the ground
they probably don't have a whole lot of
capital in the bank but what they do
have is time maybe some time after work
every single night where they can work
on their thing so for them being Scrappy
having that DIY mindset is a much better
course of action to take than to attempt
to use what little funds they have to
hire someone all right so the second
quote on my list actually comes from my
friend Charlie hoopert who runs the
excellent Channel Charisma on command
and it's very very simple he told this
to me I think two years ago at VidCon he
simply said what is your art and what is
your ego and he said this in response to
me kind of telling telling him how I was
having trouble delegating the editing
duties on my channel which I have since
done but back then I had a lot of work
on my plate editing videos took way more
hours than it should have and I had
other projects that I was kind of
letting kind of go to the back burner
and I had this feeling at the time that
me editing my own videos and basically
you know having my hand in every single
element of the production of my videos
was what made my channel successful but
of course this is entirely ego talking
I'm not the only person in the world who
can edit video and in fact there are
many more talented editors out there
than myself and that is a statement that
is true for basically every other part
of the production process there are
better writers there are better hosts
there are better editors animators
whatever role you can think of there's
somebody out there more talented than me
and Charlie understood this before I did
and better than I did which is why he
told me ask yourself what is your art
what is the thing that you can
contribute the best to the thing that
you're creating and what is just your
ego what elements in the process are you
doing just because you have this false
belief that you need to be doing them
and I sat back and asked myself what is
my art what is my ego and I came to the
conclusion that well what I really
contribute what I really bring to the
table more than anything else is my
ability to do research to maybe combine
it with jokes and references and things
that make the overall script
entertaining and then my hosting the
actual filming of the video so those are
the areas where I should really be
focusing my time and energy and
attention and anything else should be
outsourced to somebody who could do it
better than me now if you're not an
entrepreneur if you're not running your
own business then you might be asking
yourself how does this apply to me
because I have a boss who delegates
things to me I have to do what they say
I'm the
boss I'm your boss and that's true but
you might have built this identity up
for yourself that you're the best person
for your particular role and a lot of
people get this into their heads and
then they don't actually want to move up
or Branch out or accept new responsib
abilities because they think that
they're the only person who can deal
with the current thing that they are
doing in their job so this isn't advice
that's only for entrepreneurs or
business owners this is really for
anybody because we can all come to
conclusions we can all hold ideas in our
head that are in fact supported only by
our egos and when we really challenge
the foundation of those ideas we may
realize that what we're doing actually
isn't the best use of our time or
attention or energy and speaking of time
and energy the third quote on my list is
one that comes to mind anytime that I'm
feeling lazy and it's the one that has I
think more than any other helped me to
develop a strong work ethic so this
quote is from the actor Will Smith and
it goes the only thing that I see that
is distinctly different about me is I'm
not afraid to die on a treadmill I will
not be outworked period you might have
more Talent than me you might be smarter
than me you might be sexier than me you
might be all of those things you got on
me in nine categories but if we get on
the treadmill together there's two
things you're getting off first or I'm
going to die so this isn't one of those
quotes that dos out some sort of wisdom
you never really knew about before it's
kind of obvious we all know we need to
work hard but I love having reminders of
the fact there are people out there who
understand that hard work beats Talent
when talent doesn't work hard your high
school coach has probably told you that
a zillion times I know my wrestling
coach told me that but I have to be
reminded of it every so often because
sometimes I find myself leaning on my
talents or leaning on what I've already
built in the past and I realize that
that is just resting on my Laurels and I
need to actually be working furthermore
this is a reminder of what we can
actually control even if you start from
a less advantageous place even if you
come from a less wealthy background or
you have less innate Talent quote
unquote or not as good-look as somebody
out there what you can really control is
how hard you're willing to work how much
you're willing to focus how much you're
willing to push out distractions how
much you're willing to prioritize what
you really want these are the things you
truly have control over the things that
you should focus on improving all right
that brings us to quote number four on
the list and this comes from my previous
boss at Iowa State University back when
I was a student but also a new student
orientation assistant and she was
basically the director of the entire new
student programs uh department and I
remember this very distinctly we were
getting ready to build this entire event
for all the new freshmen coming into
campus and we were writing in a golf
cart over to the next thing we needed to
do and we happen to start talking about
this whole idea of it's the thought that
counts right actual gift you give
somebody or the presentation or whatever
doesn't matter so much as the thought
right and I will never forget this she
turned to me and she said it's not the
thought that counts presentation matters
and then she continued to tell me that
if I couldn't rrap a present correctly
then I needed to go learn how to do it
my grandma was good at it and it would
be unacceptable for me to be terrible at
it and for most of my life I never
thought this way I did think it was the
thought that counts it doesn't matter if
I wrap a present terribly I'm giving a
present to to the person that I like
which means that I love them right they
should know that it's the thought that
counts but listening to her I realized
it's the thought that counts is kind of
like the whole saying like that person
has a heart of gold it's an excuse for
what would be considered unacceptable
Behavior by people who don't already
maybe know you or love you or excuse
that behavior because of that Foundation
of love so this really stuck with me
it's not the thought that counts the
presentation matters and in fact if you
love somebody if you're giving them a
gift or doing something to show your
appreciation for them then it should be
immediately apparent from the
presentation of that gift from the gift
itself that you do care you shouldn't
have to make an excuse like oh it's the
thought that counts it should be readily
apparent so anyway hurt telling me that
much like Charlie telling me to examine
my ego was something that made me really
challenge my beliefs and I had to change
them afterward because I knew what she
said was true and that actually brings
me to my fifth and final quote on the
list which comes from the artificial
intelligence researcher and rationality
writer eleazer owski do not flinch from
experiences that might destroy your
beliefs the thought you cannot think
controls you more than thoughts you
speak aloud submit yourself to ordeals
and test yourself in fire relinquish the
emotion which rests upon a mistaken
belief and seek to feel fully that
emotion which fits the facts to put this
in some simpler words essentially think
like a scientist in everything you do
science scientists follow the scientific
method where they form hypotheses but
then they test those hypotheses and they
use the evidence they gather to update
their beliefs they don't fall victim to
Dogma but instead they are constantly
seeking objective truth now this
specific quote from yudkowsky was
something that I came across a little
bit after I really started to learn
about rationality and about these ideas
my original exposure to them was his
fanfiction called Harry Potter and the
methods of rationality which is frankly
a pretty well-written story at least for
fanfiction standards but it's also a
pretty thinly veiled attempt to teach
people about rationality and heris STS
and biases and all these kinds of things
and I read this back in I think 2013
right around the time I was about to
graduate from college and it was kind of
a revelation to me I mean in the past I
had always thought of myself as rational
but really digging into these ideas and
challenging some of my long-standing
beliefs asking myself why was I afraid
to go down certain uh Avenues of inquiry
really showed me that I wasn't quite as
rational as I had thought and uh this is
now sort of part of my core beliefs of
how I should act as a human being I
should constantly be seeking out points
of view or perspectives or Avenues of
inquiry that do challenge my beliefs
that have the potential to shatter them
because if my beliefs aren't rooted in
truth then I shouldn't have them in the
first place now if you're also
interested in learning about human
rationality and heris discs and biases
well you are in luck and I've got two
specific recommendations for where you
might want to start one is something
written by eleazer owski himself and for
a really long time he really only wrote
directly about these topics on l.org in
blog post form but he recently took all
those blog posts and turned them into a
book called rationality from AI to
zombies now while I have benefited
greatly from many of the essays in that
book I will say that if you were to say
listen to it it is 49 hours long and
it's still not the most cohesive thing
in the world so there's some real gems
in it but if you want to really good
place to get started to start learning
about these topics then I would suggest
Dan Ariel's book predictably rational
and the great thing is you can start
listening to either of these titles
completely free today by starting a free
30-day trial on Audible and you can do
that by going to audible.com Thomas or
by texting Thomas to 500500 on your
phone audible is the best place on the
internet to get your hands on audiobooks
they have an unmatched library of titles
across all the different genres that
you're going to want they've got
biographies psychology titles science
fiction fantasy all the best sellers and
lots of more obscure books including one
that may or may not have been written by
yours truly with your membership each
month you'll get one credit that is good
for any title in their Library plus two
audible Originals that you cannot get
anywhere else and access to audio
workout programs additionally you'll be
able to use their excellently designed
app which in addition to many other
features has the ability to add notes to
specific timestamps in your audiobooks
so if you come across a great quote that
you want to remember you can easily do
that so to get started with a 30-day
free trial of their service and one free
audiobook download of your choosing
doesn't have to be the ones I
recommended but it could be headed over
to audible.com Thomas orex text Thomas
to 500 500 on your phone big thanks as
always to Audible for sponsoring this
week's episode and being a huge
supporter of my channel and as always
thank you guys so much for watching as
well you can subscribe right there to
get new videos when they come out and
also click right there to get a free
copy of my book on how to earn better
grades you can also watch one more video
on this channel right here or you can
listen to the podcast episode that we
did a few weeks ago which inspired this
video on six very powerful quotes that
changed our lives I highly recommend
going to listen to that one if you
enjoyed this video so that's it
hopefully you found something useful in
this video and I will see you in the
next one