there are three simple steps that you
can take whenever you sit down to work
that will reliably help you feel focused
and be able to avoid distractions but
almost everyone skips them in this video
you're gonna learn exactly what those
steps are and how to use them but before
we get into the steps themselves it'll
be helpful to answer this question first
why do so many of us find it so hard to
focus in the first place it feels like
you should just be able to pick a task
sit down and do it but more often than
not you find your attention wandering
and there is a reason for this getting
to that focused dialed in state of mind
is a lot like mining for gold see gold
can technically be found anywhere
panners find it in streams and on very
rare occasions some lucky soul will find
gold under just a few inches of dirt but
most gold the vast majority on earth
sits much deeper beneath the surface in
south africa for example the deepest
gold mine in the world goes down more
than two miles into the dirt and with
most the world's gold setting under
millions of tons of rock much of a gold
miner's work doesn't actually involve
moving that gold because first they
gotta get to it gold miners understand
intuitively that much of their work
involves moving tons and tons of useless
dirt and rock simply so they can
position themselves in the right place
and that focused dialed in state of mind
where you do your best work is just like
gold sometimes you get lucky and it
comes effortlessly but that is the
exception and if you think it should
always work this way you're going to
find yourself falling victim to
distractions and being a lot less
productive instead just like those gold
miners you should realize that you
usually need to dig deep and work to
find your focus
so now let's equip you with the shovel a
metaphorical one because this real one
isn't going to be quite as useful in
this case and because i can't actually
hand it to you through the camera so as
it turns out there are some proven steps
that you can take to do this digging
down process and more reliably reach a
state of focus when you're doing your
work and they're actually pretty easy to
take but
most people skip them and if you want to
more reliably get into that flow state
you shouldn't be one of those people who
does the skipping so the first step is
to get truly clear on the very next
action that you need to take and most
people don't do this if you look at the
goal lists and the to-do list of most
people you're going to see goals like
eat healthier and to do's like write the
paper or work on the sales page and the
problem with goals and tasks like this
is that they don't give you any kind of
direction they don't make it obvious
what the clear very next action the vna
if you want to make a tla out of it is
and when you don't have this direction
you'll tend to procrastinate a lot more
or you'll bounce between different tasks
in your project and get caught up in
multitasking so instead first try to get
that direction and a very easy way to do
this is to go through an exercise that i
like to call a five minute prep true to
its name this doesn't involve any actual
work on your task instead what you want
to do is try to get that direction so
take five minutes or maybe even set a
timer for five minutes and soak in the
details of your task specifically you're
looking for a few things number one
you're trying to break the task down
until you have a clear obvious very next
action number two you want to make sure
that the estimated time to complete this
action is something reasonable it's
gonna take all day try to break it down
even further and finally soak in the
details of the task itself but also any
important context in the larger project
as a whole so here's an example of a
five-minute prep that i went through
yesterday initially my task was write
the script for this very video but i've
been doing this long enough to know that
writing a video script takes me a really
long time so the first thing i did was
break it down i knew that there were
several sections of the video namely the
three steps that were going through here
plus that intro section about gold
miners so i broke my task down to draft
not finished but draft that intro
section about how gold mining is similar
to achieving focus in my work and i knew
that i could do that in a single session
at least get a couple of paragraphs
written so that defined my very clear
very next action once you have this
direction the next step very well may be
to simply buckle down and start working
on it and if you feel motivated you feel
focused then that is exactly what you
should do but that is actually step
three in our process and we'll get to it
later because sometimes you're not in
the right state of mind to sit down and
focus on your work this is because your
brain has two important modes of
thinking and you spend time in both of
them and it's important to do this in
her book a mind for numbers the author
barbara oakley calls these the focused
and the diffused modes of thinking now
focused mode is exactly what it sounds
like it's the prefrontal cortex heavy
mode that allows you to logically work
through problems it's great for getting
work done but it's not so good at
letting your mind relax and it's also
not very good at thinking creatively yet
sort of stepping back and making
connections between seemingly disparate
elements this is the domain of the
diffused mode in the book oakley likens
this to a pinball table where the
bumpers are really well spaced out and
this allows the ball which in this case
is your ideas to bounce all around the
table and get exposure to basically
every area by contrast the focus mode is
more like a very tight cluster of
bumpers that keeps the ball in one tiny
little area namely your prefrontal
cortex so by stepping back and getting
into the diffuse mode ideas can sort of
background process they can bounce
around to all different parts of your
brain and that's how you make more
creative connections and my favorite way
to do this is very simple go for a 20
minute walk or maybe take a nap or clean
your room do something that lets your
brain relax and not have to intensely
focus on any one thing doing this will
get you into that mode and you're gonna
make some more connections that you
often wouldn't make in that focused mode
now once you're done with that walk or
whatever you did to get into the
diffused mode it is now time to come
back and actually get to work and it's
here that i want to share one of my
all-time favorite quotes which is
attributed to the author william
faulkner i only write when i'm inspired
fortunately i am inspired every day at
nine o'clock i love this quote for two
different reasons first and foremost he
mentions nine o'clock as his start time
for the work day which is another piece
of evidence to prove that you don't need
to wake up at five a.m in the morning
and have some kind of hustle crush at
morning routine to be successful you can
get up at a normal time and still be
perfectly productive but secondly i love
his mention about how he is inspired
every single day at nine o'clock
faulkner understood exactly what those
gold miners understand that to get to a
focused place to get to where the
rewards really are you have to put in a
little bit of prep work first or to
phrase it the way i did on twitter the
other day and this is pretty corny but
i'm standing by it don't wait for the
muses to smile upon you tell jokes until
you get them to laugh and the most
reliable way that i have found to do
this is to use a timer now you already
have your clear very next action defined
from step one so at this point just set
a timer for 25 minutes and commit to
working only on that task as best as you
can this is the classic pomodoro
technique and it works so well because
you're reframing the task and reducing
the amount of resistance that your brain
feels to starting it instead of i have
to finish this entire task no matter
what it's all i have to do is work for
25 minutes and the benefit here isn't
simply getting 25 minutes of work done
it's getting into the middle of that
focused session as a writer i know after
writing 200 video scripts 300 blog posts
and a book that the most effective and
the most useful writing always comes at
least 10 or 15 minutes into a writing
session now there is an inconvenient
truth here which is that the first 10 or
15 minutes is usually useless and i have
to throw it away but that's the price i
pay to actually get my brain into a
state where the good stuff actually
comes out and using a timer is what
helps me get there most reliably it
externalizes my self-discipline and
makes it much easier to simply start
working now there are a ton of pomodoro
apps out there so you don't have to use
a regular kitchen timer seriously there
are more than you can shake a shovel at
but i have the sneaking suspicion and i
guess i'm gonna be holding this shovel
here like a a staff or something but i
have the sneaking suspicion that the
best pomodoro timer in the world is
actually a very old school hourglass and
this is because an hourglass lets you
set a timer but that timer never goes
off or at least it never goes off in a
way that gets your attention and this is
actually quite useful because i have
found through years of doing pomodoro
sessions that i almost never stop
working and take a break when that 25
minute timer goes off really the point
of the pomodoro session is to simply
convince my brain to start working and
get to the point where i am mining that
metaphorical gold and once i'm there i
can work for a lot longer than 25
minutes so experiment with doing this
either get yourself an hourglass or
experiment with simply silencing the
timer when it goes off and see if you
can push yourself just a little bit
further now it's worth noting that while
these three steps are very effective
they may not be the only things that you
need to do because everyone has their
own unique challenges and problems when
it comes to focus and creativity so you
may want to analyze what yours are and
try to come up with some new solutions
that are tailored specifically to you
for example i have found that as a
writer i have a lot more writer's block
and i find it much harder to get into
the zone when i feel like i'm writing on
what is the final draft of the project
i'm looking at the script right here a
notion and trying to write on this is
difficult for me so a lot of times i'll
open up a brand new document where i
feel a lot less pressure and i can just
sort of brain dump my thoughts then i
can clean them up later and bring them
back into that final draft it's
something that works very well for me
and this applies to any other problem
you want to solve as well instead of
always sticking to the established
methods it's often better to dig into
the details yourself and figure out a
brand new solution this type of problem
solving is a useful skill that can
benefit you in both your professional
and your personal lives and it's also
something you can practice and one great
resource for getting that practice is
brilliant who have kindly sponsored this
video brilliant is an interactive
learning platform that helps you master
math science and computer science and
all of their courses are filled with
interactive puzzles and quizzes that
ensure you're learning actively the
entire time instead of just watching
long videos or reading walls of text and
when you're learning like this not only
are you constantly working on your
problem-solving skills but you also have
more fun and you retain what you learn a
lot more easily in brilliant library
you'll find more than 60 different
courses including their calculus and a
nutshell course which breaks down
calculus and makes it a lot easier to
understand and you'll also find science
courses like this one on gravitational
physics and computer science courses
like their algorithm fundamentals course
so if you want to start learning today
and also support this channel you can go
over to brilliant.org thomasfrank to
sign up or use that link on screen that
should be right there and if you're one
of the first 200 people to use that link
with this video you're even going to get
20 off their annual premium subscription
if you're looking for something else to
watch you might like my video on the
five levels of self-discipline right
there which is a great follow-up to this
video and last but not least leave a
like for the algorithm and if you want
more bite-sized content you may also
want to follow me on twitter over at
tomfrankly thanks as always for watching
hopefully you found this helpful and i
will see you in the next one