hey what's going on guys so this week's
video is going to be a little bit
different than most the other videos
that I've done on this channel because
for the most part the videos that I do
have a pretty set in stone topic I try
to keep a pretty narrow focus on
whatever I'm talking about but for the
last four months I've been keeping a
note in Evernote just called five
self-improvement tips and I put that
number there arbitrarily but um I came
up with something that I thought was
interesting to me there was just
something that I felt was like a mindset
change I made a long time ago and it's
really improved my life and that gave me
an idea for a video where I would just
sort of list out some of the subtle or
maybe not so subtle mindset changes that
I've made over the last decade or so
since I graduated high school that have
really improved things for me on a daily
basis and I was going to wait until I
had a longer list to do a video on these
sort of mindset hacks but I think the
four that I have now which I've just
sort of added over time as I thought
about them uh make up a pretty good list
So today we're going to go over four
mindset hacks or mindset changes that
I've made slowly over the past 10 or so
years that have really improved my life
and if you can adopt even just one of
these into your own life I think you're
going to notice a marked improvement as
well so let's get into it mindset hack
number one is to become okay with being
the worst person in the room and by that
I mean like the worst person at whatever
skill you're trying out this fear of
being labeled as the worst person in the
room or of looking bad in comparison to
everyone else keeps people from pursuing
the things they want to do or it keeps
them from increasing the difficulty or
moving to the next level in something
they're already pursuing and if you can
become okay with being bad at something
or comparatively bad or if you can
become okay with being worse than
everyone else in your peer group then
you start to compete in a higher league
and when you are the worst person in the
room that means that there's nowhere for
you to go but up and everyone else
around you is somebody who you can learn
from so example of putting this mindset
into action that immediately comes to
mind for me is from last summer when I
started doing downhill mountain biking
now downhill mountain biking especially
the lift access version where you
literally put your bike and yourself on
a ski lift and you go up to the top of a
mountain and then ride down is a pretty
difficult and risky discipline in
mountain biking in fact my friend Martin
actually broke his finger doing it uh
back in the fall uh I started this in
the summer and I started off being
pretty bad and I noticed that all these
people kept passing me up on the trails
and I kind of felt self-conscious about
my abilities at first then I realized
that if I just challenged myself to
follow these people who were better than
me I actually would get better more
quickly and I found that this actually
did happen I was more afraid to do
things like go off of jumps or take the
trails at a higher speed when I was
alone but when I was following somebody
there was like this competitive Instinct
that kicked in I found myself pushing
myself a little bit further and really
challenging myself to keep Pace with
this other person who was better than me
and this mindset actually paid off on
the very first day that I went mountain
biking cuz I went with my cousin to a
bike park in Boulder Colorado and there
was a jump that I just could not get
myself to do every single time I would
go up to the jump I would hit the brakes
I would stop and I have to take my bike
lift it up and walk down uh past the
jump I was just too scared to do it and
my cousin who was a little bit better at
mountain biking than I was not a ton but
a little bit said all right this time
we're going to go you're going to follow
me I'm going to hit this jump and you
are going to hit it with me and watching
him do it and knowing there was this
expectation that I was going to have to
rise to the challenge because he was
doing it as well forced me to do it and
I actually hit that jump and afterwards
it became easy so again if you can
become comfortable with being the worst
person in the room even if it's a
self-perception kind of thing then you
are going to allow yourself to compete
in a higher league and you're going to
expose yourself to people who are more
skilled and who can bring you up to
speed more quickly and one last thing
that I do want to note when it comes to
this mindset is that for the most part
people are kind of self-absorbed so say
if you go to the gym and you are out of
shape or you're lifting the least amount
of weight out of the gym people aren't
going to make fun of you because they're
there to do their own thing they aren't
there to judge you so just keep that in
mind when you start a new hobby or you
start trying to improve yourself in any
way if you're around other people who
are doing the same thing they're
probably focused on their own goals and
their own efforts all right mindset hack
number two is to treat real life goals
kind of like video game levels and the
reason that I have this on the list is
that when we play video games at least
when I play video games I am 100 % okay
with dying or failing because I know
that in just a few seconds after dying
I'm going to restart the level I'm going
to try again and the process of dying
over and over and over again in some
cases is part of the experience it's
part of the fun one of my absolute
favorite video games in the world is
called Celeste which is in my opinion
one of the best Platformers ever made
and if you go look at my death stats for
every level in the game they are
ridiculous in fact I think in one of the
levels I have over a thousand deaths but
because I've gone through that level and
died a thousand times I can now
basically speedrun it and the process of
doing so looks really cool and is really
fun to do and I know that all those
deaths are part of the learning process
every single time I made a mistake I got
a little bit better I got a little bit
more knowledgeable about what to do in
that situation I made an adjustment now
in real life a lot of times we feel like
we have to get things right the first
time whether it be out of embarrassment
or whether it be out of the fear of
wasting too much time but that's not how
things are it's just like a video game
if we can treat things as a learning
process even if they're failures then we
become more open to going through that
learning process and we become more able
to gain those skills the fear of failure
is something that really holds people
back so if you can start viewing
yourself as a video game character at
least in so far as you're allowed to
fail certain things maybe not allowed to
fall into pits of spikes but you can
fail certain things then you're going to
sort of move past that mental roadblock
mindset hack number three is to become
okay with confronting harsh realities or
bad news and this is a mindset hack that
I got from the book good to Great by Jim
Collins this is a fantastic Business
book I think anybody who is in the
professional world or an entrepreneur
should read this book and there is a
quote from an executive of the company
Pitney Bose his name is a Fred Purdue
that really stuck with me after I read
this book in fact I think this might be
the concept that stuck with me more than
any other from this book and I want to
read the quote to you here the quote
goes when you turn over rocks and look
at all the squiggly things underneath
you can either put the rock down or you
can say my job is to turn over rocks and
look at the squiggly things even if what
you see can scare the hell out of you
the sad thing is a lot of people would
rather avoid looking at bad news avoid
looking at harsh realities than confront
them and this causes a lot of problems
some people know they probably didn't do
well on a test so they avoid looking at
the test results until they realize
they've been kicked out of school or
some people know their bank account
balance is probably a little bit lower
than they'd like it to be so they just
don't look at it until there's an
overdraft or until there's a bill that
isn't paid in our quest to avoid pain we
often avoid looking at things that cause
us mental pain just because they are
like the bearer of bad news the
harbinger of bad news to come but the
people who are truly successful are the
ones who can confront these harsh
realities because when you do when you
don't shy away from them or pretend they
don't exist then you can after you get
over the emotional pain or the shock of
seeing them formulate a plan for dealing
with them so become okay with
confronting these harsh realities yes
it's tough yes you kind of never really
get totally used to it cuz you always
have that little part of your brain that
just sort of wants to go do something
else but you have to become able to push
through that mental resistance finally I
want to talk about the one mindset hack
that I think has improved my life more
than any other and it's simply building
a sort of background Loop in my head
that constantly asks where am I wrong or
how am I wrong I'm always looking for my
own blind spots this mindset hack was
kind of forced upon me when I was a
teenager When A girlfriend of mine
actually broke up with me and she told
me the reason that she left me was that
I always had to be right every time we'd
get into an argument or even just a
conversation I always had to be the
person with the last word I didn't
really realize this at the time but when
that happened the pain of being dumped
was so great that I was forced to look
at my actions to look at the way that I
thought and I realized that yes I did
have this implicit assumption that I was
right in all things even if I would have
never admitted it even to myself and I
think a lot of people are like like this
especially people who are generally
successful in a lot of the things they
do there's this sort of huis or Pride
that develops in the back of our minds
and sort of squashes any humility we
have and it causes us to miss a lot of
our blind spots or to assume things that
aren't true so even though that
experience was very painful I count it
as a blessing because it sort of forced
me to develop this assumption that I'm
probably wrong in a lot of areas even
when I think that I'm right about
something there might be a blind spot
there might be something that I'm
missing so I ask myself what could I
possibly be missing and a lot of times I
try to put myself in the shoes of the
person that I'm talking to and ask what
is their perspective on this what could
they see that I might not be seeing now
I don't think you have to go through a
super painful experience to develop this
ability and I would say that a lot of
its refinement came from reading books
like Harry Potter and the methods of
rationality or thinking fast and slow by
Daniel conman or even some of the
individual blog posts over on less
wrong.com which was one of the original
resources where I started learning about
human rationality learning to notice my
own confusion and my blind spots
regardless of how you go about
developing this ability once you do get
better at using it and making it more
habitual you're going to become a much
more likable person because people will
see you as not arrogant as open to
noticing your own flaws and your own
blind spots and aside from that it's
also going to make you a better Problem
Solver as Barbara Oakley talks about in
her book A M for numbers there's this
concept called aalong where the work
that you've done to learn something
earlier can sort of block the ability
for you to consider new information
because you have these very well-worn
neural patterns that are pretty
difficult to break out of but if you can
build this metacognitive skill of
constantly challenging your beliefs and
looking for your blind spots you're
going to be far less susceptible to this
einon so going forward start trying to
consciously challenge your beliefs start
asking yourself how could I be wrong and
in doing so you're going to become a
much better Problem Solver of course if
you want to boost those problem solving
skills even further then the best way to
do it is to practice problem solving on
a daily basis and a great place to do
this is at brilliant.org brilliant is an
excellent learning platform for anyone
wanting to improve their skills in math
science and computer science and they
take a very active approach to building
all their courses meaning that whether
you want to take a course on calculus or
on math for quantitative trading in
finance or on computer memory computer
algorithms or gravitational physics
you're going to find yourself
immediately thrown into challenging
problems that stretch your problem
solving capabilities and stretch that
lateral thinking ability that we've
talked about in earlier videos
additionally you're not going to find
yourself bored by tons of introductory
lecture material you're getting right
into the problems right away so your
interest in the subject is going to
remain high the entire time and you're
going to learn much more efficiently as
well now in addition to their library of
in-depth courses they've also released a
new feature called daily problems where
every single day they're releasing new
problems that can wet your appetite and
get you interested in new subjects such
as how prehistoric humans track time or
how you can cut amobia strip in half
these problems take about 5 minutes
every single day so you can build them
into a habit and not only do they
improve your problem solving abilities
even further but they can get you
interested in new topics that you hadn't
considered before so if you want to try
out that daily problems feature or you
want to dig into one of their more
in-depth courses and start learning
right now you can go over to
brilliant.org Thomas Frank to start
learning for free and if you're one of
the first 83 people to sign up with that
link you're also going to get 20% off
your annual premium subscription big
thanks to brilliant for sponsoring this
video and being a big supporter of my
channel hopefully you guys enjoyed this
video if you did definitely give it a
like you can also subscribe right there
to get new videos every single week on
this channel plus go right there to get
a free copy of my book on how to earn
better grades you can also follow me on
Instagram at tomf frankley or last but
not least click right here to get one
more video on this channel thanks so
much for watching and I will see you in
the next one