so here's the thing about waking up
early if I have to do it if I have a
event that I have to get to then I can
easily get myself out of bed at like
3:00 a.m. if it's a early flight or or
6:00 a.m. if I have to be to work by
7:00 but if I'm left to my own devices
getting up early is only going to happen
if I'm forced to do it if I have to be
somewhere at a certain time maybe you're
just like me in that respect and maybe
you also want to be able to get yourself
up in the morning before you have to be
somewhere so you actually have time to
do some things like eat breakfast or
maybe workout or even just read a book
well I definitely wanted that for myself
so in this video I'm going to show you a
technique that I've been using that 100%
absolutely gets me up at 6:00 a.m. every
single morning during the week
completely crazy you say well it's been
working for 6 months so here it is the
basis of my system uses an app called
buffer which is a social media scheduler
and I have a tweet set up in buffer that
goes to my Twitter account which
basically says hey I'm sleeping in
because I'm lazy if you reply to this
tweet TW I will give you $5 via Paypal
assuming that my alarm did not
malfunction the Tweet is scheduled for
6:10 a.m. so I have to get up every
morning before that goes out get over to
my computer and set it to go out the
next day instead of today I also have
the hashtag sleeping in on that tweet
and I'm using an app called if it to
watch for tweets that have that hashtag
from my account if if it sees a tweet
like that then it'll send an email over
to beinder which is a service I've
talked about before which tracks your
goals and actually charges you money if
you fail on them so if I sleep in I will
guaranteed be charged five bucks from
be- minder and also be charged $5 from
anyone who sees my tweet and wants me to
pay them and an added incentive that
comes from offering to pay people if
they reply to me is that there's a
threat of social shame and embarrassment
if I have to do it so I'm essentially
using the threats of both monetary loss
and social shame to force myself to get
up every morning and I've been doing
this for about 6 months now and 100% of
the time that I have set the tweet I
have gotten up on time and only one time
did I actually forget to move the tweet
I probably got distracted by my email or
something and I did pay $5 to the person
who responded so since then I have
always remember to move my tweet forward
I have a reminder set up in habit RPG to
do it and every single morning I'm up on
time doing my morning routine so if
you're looking for a method that will
actually make you get up in the morning
without having to rely on an actual
obligation try my method out I just have
one warning that I'll give you before
you actually start using it you have to
be 100% honest when you use this method
because if you let the Tweet go out and
then lie about it later you're
essentially breaking the method for all
future instances if you know that you've
broken it in the past then you're
probably going to break it again in the
future so if you try to adopt this
method realize that it's kind of a
nuclear option for getting yourself up
and respect its power if you want to
know more about how I use this method I
actually wrote a blog post about it over
at college infogeek with a little bit
more detail and this video serves as a
bit of an update to let you know that
yes it's been working for about 6 months
now check that post out and if you want
to get more videos every single week on
being an awesome college student and
building better habits then hit the
Subscribe button below otherwise I will
see you in the next
video well hello there and thanks for
sticking around to the end of my video
on how to wake up early if you plan on
putting my system into action then I
would love to hear about it and you can
follow me on Twitter over at tomf
Frankle and let me know that he did it
I'll be up tomorrow morning at that time
so I will definitely respond to you if
you want to stay up to date and get new
videos every single week then hit the
Subscribe button right there and you can
also get links to any resources and a
summary of this video over at the
companion blog post which you can get to
by clicking the orange button right
there if you missed last week's video
there's a clip of it playing and you can
click that clip to watch it and also if
you would like to get a free copy of my
book 10 steps to earning awesome grades
just click the picture of it and you can
get it right there thanks for watching