hey what is going on guys so the
semester just started for most of you
and today I wanted to share a really
quick tip that can help you retain a lot
of that motivation that we get when we
start new semesters and keep it going
throughout the semester's entirety
because I know you know when you start a
new semester you're kind of turning over
a new Leaf all these new classes are
coming into your schedule and you're
really excited to learn them and
honestly you haven't yet realized just
how much work they're going to be so you
are naturally fired up and you've
probably got your task management
systems your organizational systems
calendar all that stuff cleaned out
reset and ready to go so today I want to
tell you about a habit you can adopt to
keep these systems in order which is
going to keep your motivation levels
high and that habit is to establish a
weekly review day now on this channel
before I've talked about how it's a
really good idea to have a weekly
planning day where you kind of sketch
out what's going to come in the week
ahead you kind of know exactly what you
need to do all the doe dates and all the
events that are coming in the coming
days but I think it's also a good idea
to take this particular day which I
think Sunday is a really good day for
this to also review the previous week
now here's why I think this is a really
good idea in my case and I'm sure that
many of you have the same exact problem
I find that my task management systems
get kind of crufty maybe that's the word
for it they get a little bit
disorganized some tasks don't get
checked off some things just don't get
done and after a few weeks I find that
my task management system is not a
perfect onetoone representation of
everything that I need to get done and
that is a huge problem because that
means I can no longer trust that system
as well as I could before and as the
productivity researcher David Allen once
said your brain is for having ideas not
for storing them I shouldn't be storing
anything up in here my system should be
well taken care of and be the place in
which all those ideas are stored and
perfectly updated and this is what a
weekly review does so what exactly goes
into weekly review process well this is
largely up to you but I do want to make
a few specific suggestions for you guys
here number one I think it's a good idea
to ask what exactly did you get done
last week and what didn't get done so
look at your plan for the last week and
ask yourself out of all these things
which ones did I actually accomplish and
you can make this even easier on
yourself if you adopt a daily habit of
writing an accomplishment Journal now
this isn't a big long Journal where
you're pouring your deepest feelings
into some secret book with a lock on it
no this is just a simple habit where you
write down exactly what you got done on
a day-to-day basis in something really
simple like an Evernote account or
notebook or just your arm whatever and
I've actually found that doing this can
increase my motivation and make me feel
like I'm kind of on a roll in the days
that come afterwards so this kind of you
know boosts your motivation as a
singular habit but it also helps with
your weekly review because you can
simply go back look at your
accomplishment journal and say yeah I
was really really productive this week
or on the flip side this wasn't such a
good week after all and that allows you
to do something really really important
with the weekly review and that is to
make course Corrections and small
changes to to your habits and to the way
that you work so say you've been
studying in your dorm room and you find
that friends keep coming in and they're
really really persuasive when they ask
you to go to you know get something to
eat or to play guitar hero or to do
anything other than studying well that's
something that's going to stick out like
a sore thumb when you ask yourself
during your weekly review why you didn't
get things done and from there you can
fix that by changing your study location
or by putting a sign in your dorm room
or texting your friends that you're busy
what have you the point is if you're
doing the weekly review you're noticing
the problems on a weekly basis and then
you can fix them now in addition to
mentally running through the past week's
accomplishments giving yourself a pat on
the back giving yourself that little
productivity score and making those
course Corrections and habit changes the
last part to this weekly review process
is simply to reset your task management
systems in your calendar back to where
they should be so make sure that all
events have their due dates updated make
sure you check things off that you maybe
forgot to check when you actually got
those tasks done and make sure you
update any details with updates from
your professor or group members from
group projects just basically make sure
that across the board your systems are
where they should be and that they're an
accurate representation of everything
you have to do that way you never start
to feel overwhelmed or confused about
what's on your plate so I really hope
you guys found this video to be useful
and for those of you who use habitica
I'm hoping that after watching this
video you're going to log in and add
weekly review to your Daily's list and
set it to once per week because that is
going to remind you to do this process
and that will help it become a habit if
you have comments or questions
definitely leave them down below and if
you liked this video you can leave it a
like to support this channel also if you
want to get new videos every single week
on being a more effective student you
can click your mouse button on that big
red subscribe button right down there
you can also get yourself a free copy of
the book I wrote on earning better
grades by clicking the picture of the
book right over there and if you missed
last week's video we talked about how to
get over the fear of starting college so
if that's something that's still on your
mind check it out if you missed it and
as always you can find the full article
for this video by clicking the full
article button right there if you want
to connect with me you can do so on
zanga by going over to eBay and buying
the one time machine that work works
it's the one with the pink crystals and
then adding me as a friend there I
looking forward to discussing your
favorite My Chemical Romance album see
you there