i got a question from a reader a few
days ago that i really want to address
i really want to read more books but i
dislike reading what do i do and as
somebody who definitely enjoys reading
but also who has gone through periods of
life where reading hasn't been the
biggest thing that i want to do
i wanted to address this question
especially since the answer is very
simple and very easy
first thing you're going to want to do
is read thinking fast and slow by daniel
common it's a very very light easy
breezy read only about 497 pages of
research findings
and after that you're going to want to
follow things up with the owner's manual
for the brain
by pierce j howard phd again an easy
read only about a thousand and 97 pages
and once you read these two books you're
going to understand your brain and
you're going to be able to change it
on command and just tell yourself to
like reading
sound good all right video over okay i
do kind of wish that i could end the
video like that because it would be
pretty funny but
as it turns out i do have some actual
tips that will be helpful if you want to
become the kind of person who likes to
read or at least the kind of person who
doesn't absolutely
dislike reading and who can get through
the occasional book once in a while
so let's get into it so the first thing
that i want to mention here which is
something that comes from my own
personal experience is that reading is a
habit that gets easier to do and more
pleasant to do
the more you do it a couple years ago i
made a bet with my friend martin that i
was going to read 25 pages a day every
single day
for three entire months and to really
force myself to stick to this bet i told
him i was gonna give him a hundred
dollars
if i failed to read those 25 pages even
once
and during the first month sticking to
that goal was difficult and the threat
of losing that money
and being embarrassed was my main
motivator but about a month into the
challenge i started to notice something
profound which was that i found it
easier to start reading and i also found
it easier to keep reading for longer and
longer periods
of time so i discovered through this
challenge that
reading is very akin to working out
actually when you start doing it it's
very tiring it's exhausting it's not a
lot of fun
but when you get into the habit of doing
it it gets easier to do
and it gets more enjoyable that being
said i'm not just going to leave you off
with a tip to brute force reading habit
by making a bet with a friend because
there are definitely some other things
you can do
one of which being to start with
material that's easier
to get through and i do have a few
suggestions so on the really easy end of
things
are comic books and stick with me even
if you're not typically into comic books
because these can really help you get
into the habit of reading overall
comic books are number one usually very
easy to finish in one sitting an issue
of a comic book is not very long
and because of all the art on the page
there's really not a whole lot of room
for a ton of text now if you walk into
your average comic store you're going to
see a lot of stuff on the shelves and
you're probably not going to know where
to start so let me give you a couple of
recommendations here
first and foremost i'm going to
recommend the avatar last airbender
comic series which actually pick up
right where the series left off avatar
is one of my favorite tv shows of all
time if you haven't watched it you
probably should and the comic series is
just as good
as the television series so that would
be a great place to start
also there is an app called comixology
which i believe is owned by amazon now
and they have a ton of different comics
from marvel dc dark horse
lots of manga as well and one thing that
i discovered after i went and watched
elita battle angel in the theaters and
wanted to read the manga afterwards
is that you can get a free 30-day trial
with basically unlimited reading
without even putting a credit card into
the app so that's a great way to at
least
start doing things you didn't have to go
to a comic book store and buy
paper comics you can just read them on
your computer and that can get you into
the habit
of reading you don't even have to stick
with comics afterwards it just builds
that habit
now if comics just aren't your thing
there are definitely other options out
there that don't come with a whole lot
of pictures one of which being
short story anthologies so one of the
things that i have found has been sort
of a roadblock to getting back into my
reading habit at times
is the fact that books are usually very
long and if i
stop in the middle of a book i often
feel like i have to go back and read the
entire thing again just to figure out
where i was
and that could be discouraging so the
great thing about short story
anthologies is that again you can sit
down and you can usually finish an
entire story
in one sitting and that feeling of
accomplishment that feeling of
sitting down and finishing something can
encourage you to keep
reading in the future now just as with
comics there are a
ton of short story anthologies out there
and you might not know where to start so
i do want to give you at least one
recommendation in this video and that is
going to be for the anthology called
rogues which was edited by george rr
martin and which actually contains a
brand new game of thrones story
alongside other stories by authors like
patrick rothfuss and
neil gaiman and again just like with
comics treat these
as an entry point to building your
reading habits you don't have to always
stick to short story anthologies or
comic books they can just get you back
into that daily habit of reading books
and then you can move on to bigger
and possibly better things one of which
would be fiction books
that are still novels but that are
written for easier consumption so the
one book that comes to mind for this tip
is
the hunger games because a few years ago
i remember reading an article by the
blogger jeff goins about why the hunger
games was so successful
and one of his main arguments is that
the book uses very short
packed sentences it doesn't use crazy
frilly prose it's kind of written for
today's more easily distractible
audience here's just a quick snippet of
what he said about her writing collins
writes short sentences that pack
a punch they are disturbingly terse like
a hemingway novel this way of writing
builds
suspense which works perfectly with a
culture addicted to constant
interruptions
now some people might interpret that as
a criticism against her writing but i
see it a little bit differently yes it's
not the most amazing prose ever written
it's not war and peace but suzanne
collins knows her audience and she knows
that choosing to write in this way is
going to help them get through the books
more clearly and keep coming back
for more and to a somewhat lesser degree
i've noticed this in the books that i've
had an easier time getting through
as well for example i binge read the
entire mistborn series by brandon
sanderson
and while that series is amazing the
writing is a little less complex
than other series like the name of the
wind by patrick rothfuss or especially
anything by neil stephenson both
authors that i really really enjoy but
who have had a little bit of a harder
time getting
into than with sanderson's work now i do
want to stress that i'm not advocating
you avoid
more complex books but if you are the
kind of person who believes that you
dislike
reading or the kind of person who has
been out of the habit of doing it for a
while
starting with easier or more digestible
books is again a way
of building that habit building that
base and once you have that base
then you can branch out into the more
difficult material and in addition to
that more difficult material realize
that you could also branch out into
areas that you don't think at first
glance
are for you for instance young adult
novels or middle grade fiction novels i
remember a few years ago i was on
goodreads.com
and i noticed that patrick rothfuss the
author of the name of the wind and
mizeman's fear had reviewed and given
five stars to a children's book called
the girl who circumnavigated fairyland
in a ship of her own
making and due to his positive review i
went and read the book
which i found to be fantastic i also
found it to be full of a lot of vocab
words that i did not understand so
not quite sure how this made it into the
children's categorization but that
should just be more evidence that books
that are considered to be
for children or for teenagers might be
for you
as well the categorization is to help
people who are in those groups to find
more things that they might like to read
or that might be at their level but it
is not meant to exclude people who are
outside of those groups
so from all that i want to move on to
talking about something which may
potentially have killed your love of
reading at an early age
and you might be able to guess what it
is because it's school
i remember back when i was in high
school i used to have english classes
and composition classes and reading
classes where i was assigned reading
sometimes fiction reading where we were
assigned specific chapters every single
week and were actively discouraged from
reading
ahead now i get what the teachers were
trying to do they were trying to keep
the entire class at the same pace but
here's the thing
if you have 50 kids in the classroom not
every single one of them is going to fit
into the same exact specific
mold for how they should learn to read
and yes we should be teaching people how
to read analytically how to critically
think
but more importantly we should be
teaching a love
of reading so if your experiences in
school
made you kind of not like reading like
they did for me in certain cases
then realize that there are other ways
of reading and the way they force you to
read in school isn't the way that you
have to read
yourself so give it a try again and one
last but
important tip that i want to share here
which i think is going to apply to a lot
of you
because it definitely applies to me and
it definitely applies to my best friend
martin who helped me write this
video is to ditch your tbr or to be read
list
if it is becoming an obligation i know
that on many occasions in the past i
have seen a really interesting book on
the bookstore shelf or library shelf
and thought i really want to read that
but i've already got a bunch of books on
my to be read list over on goodreads
that i gotta read first
so i dutifully put that book on the
bottom of the list
and then proceed to of course never read
it so instead of doing that instead of
holding yourself to this really
non-essential obligation to go through
books in the order in which you
discovered them
follow your interest if something looks
really interesting right now then pursue
it read that book now and go to the tbr
later don't put it at the bottom you
have to remember that interest is really
tied up in emotion and emotions are
really tied up in the moment
and it's kind of a delusional belief to
think that you can just put a book
on a to be read list and conjure that
same level of interest that same level
of emotional attachment later on
when you get down to that position on
the list so realize that while the tbr
concept is not an inherently bad thing
and that it can be useful in some
circumstances
it can really hinder your emotional
attachment to things that you are
interested in
right now and if that's the case then
you should probably ditch it at least
temporarily
now earlier in the video we talked about
how starting with bite size content
comic books short story anthologies
things like that can really help you to
graduate to the more in-depth and
lengthy
books out there and this is a concept
that doesn't just apply to reading books
it can apply to everything for instance
if you want to learn
math or science or you want to get
better at solving complex problems
a great way to get yourself into the
habit of doing that is by starting with
bite size problems things that you can
solve in 5 minutes or 10 minutes
and that is exactly what you can do with
the daily challenges feature on
brilliant every single day they publish
new problems in math
science and computer science that you
can sink your teeth into that you can
solve in five or ten minutes and that
might possibly pique your interest in a
new subject that you haven't considered
before and once that flame of interest
is lit you'll be happy to know that
brilliant also has a ton of in-depth
courses that you can use to continue
learning ranging from calculus to math
for quantitative training and finance to
gravitational physics to python
programming to computer algorithms and
much
much more the best part is that
brilliant builds all of their courses
and their daily challenges with the
principle of active
learning in mind you're not just going
to be sitting there passively and taking
material the entire time you're going to
be actively encouraged to solve
problems on your own and because they're
bite-sized when you get stuck which will
happen from time to time you're going to
easily be able to go find the
information you need possibly from their
very
in-depth and detailed wiki with lots of
concept explanations and example
problems
you'll be able to find that information
come back and solve the problems with
minimal frustration now with brilliance
free tier you get new daily challenges
every single day along with access to
that wiki and their community discussion
area where you can talk with lots of
other learners and if you do decide to
go for their premium subscription you'll
also get access to the entire daily
challenges archive along with full
access to all their in-depth courses so
if you want to start learning for free
today
and building that learning habit and
growing it in the future then head over
to brilliant.org
thomasfrank to get started and if you're
one of the first 83 people to use that
link and sign up you're also going to
get 20
off your annual premium subscription big
thanks as always to brilliant for
sponsoring this episode and being a
supporter of my channel and
also thanks to you for watching if you
enjoyed this video maybe give it a like
to support this channel and also click
right there to subscribe so you don't
miss out on future videos you can also
click right there to get a free copy of
my book on how to earn better grades
click right here to get one more video
on this channel or check out our latest
podcast episode right over here thanks
again for watching and i will see you in
the next one