all right so how many times have you
woken up just in time to get out the
door and rush off to class or or a
part-time job or whatever it may be and
you go through your day and then you get
home and you realize that yeah you got
everything that had to be done done you
got your classes done you went to work
you did all that but you ended up
leaving a lot on the table still you had
lots of tasks and goals and little
things you wanted to do and they just
kind of piled up and never got done and
you know day after day this keeps
happening and all it's doing is causing
you dress well a lot of people have that
problem I had that problem and today I
want to share with you a four-step
process that I've been using to set
myself up for a more productive day and
you can use this just practice it every
single day and it gives you momentum it
makes the rest of your day more
productive and as you get better at it
then every day gets more and more
productive uh along down the road so
let's get into it number one plann the
night before so youve probably already
got everything that you need to do in a
task management system like Trello or
one list or whatever it may be maybe
just a notebook where you write down due
dates and projects and everything and it
kind of just it's a big long list of
everything that you've got coming up in
the next few weeks or months uh Etc and
that's great but realistically on any
given day on a day scale very you know
very magnified scale you can only get
one you know two or three things done uh
two big projects three two or three big
projects
so uh looking at this big task
management system is just kind of a you
know a stopper you just look at it and
you freeze up and doing that is uh not
very good for your productivity so it's
better to have a separate daily list
where you keep two to three things that
you know you need to get done that day
and you make this every single day and
rather than making this in the morning
when you've already got your morning
routine to do and you've already got
classes to rush off to do this the night
before when you're relaxed when you can
sit down and you can have a clear vision
of what needs to be done the next day
write it down and whatever system you
like I honestly like to use a whiteboard
it's right on my wall I can wake up I
can see okay it's Tuesday I need to do
this this and this I'm going to get
these things done anything else is extra
it's icing on the cake and uh that's
cool but I'm going to get these three
things done and if you plan that the
night before it helps you to stay calm
when you wake up in the morning it helps
you to get everything else done and you
know what you need to do and honestly I
almost feel like I'm beholden to my past
self when I wake up uh if I wake up and
I try to set everything I need to do in
the morning then I'm like oh it's just
you know me planning and I I can get
very stressed and very confused by it
but if it's already set up the night
before I'm like these are things that I
set in the past and I am almost
obligated to my past self to get them
done so it helps with my motivation so
number two the second step in the
process that helps you have a more
motivated uh productive day is the clear
to neutral technique and this is a
technique developed by my friends over
at Asian efficiency. comom which if you
find the link in the show notes to the
blog post that goes along with this
video you'll find a link link to their
blog which is very good but the clear
neut neutral technique or CTN is
essentially a technique that helps you
clear everything from your plate it
helps reduce the friction that is
involved with getting into any new task
so the big one for me is closing down
all the tabs in my browser when I'm
finished working for the day because if
I don't do this then the next day I wake
up I sit down on my computer to work and
I realize oh crap I have 15 open tabs
and every single one of them represents
something I could be doing usually all
of them are research for projects or
people I could be contacting or cool new
tools I want to try out and if I have
them all up in the morning it just sort
of creates a jumble in my brain and all
the planning I did the night before all
that productive planning is sort of lost
because I'm now confused and I want to
jump into 15 other different projects so
clear to neutral is a technique that
helps you avoid this problem and you can
use it for anything else you can use it
for like cooking uh after you finish
cooking at night you can make sure to
wash the dishes right away so when you
wake up in the morning the kitchen is
clean spotless and ready for you to cook
breakfast without any friction so that's
the second technique and those two
techniques are usually practiced the
night before so these are sort of end of
the day techniques that help you
translate into the next day the last two
techniques on the list are things you do
in the morning and the first one is
waking up early now you don't have to
wake up arbitrarily early but I think
it's a good idea to wake up early enough
that you have some time to relax some
time to sort of get your bearings for
the day and practice a morning ritual
which is the fourth technique but I want
to talk about waking up early first so
if you can uh convince yourself to get
up early in the morning have some time
to relax you won't find yourself rushing
out the door stressed and just trying to
catch the bus now how do you get up
early this is a question I've been
asking myself for years and I tried tons
and tons of different techniques and
sometimes they would work for a few days
and eventually I would sort of my my
sleepy self would hack the way through
them and I would stay in bed but I have
found one that works 100% of the time
and I've been doing it for about 5
months now and I actually use Twitter to
force myself to get up so this is a
technique you can steal from me if you
like I use a Twitter scheduler called
buffer which you can find at buffer
app.com and every night I schedule a
tweet that is set for 6:10 a.m. that
says hey it's 6:10 I'm still in bed I'm
lazy if you reply to this tweet then I
will send you $5 and then there's a
little disclaimer that says you know
limit five and if my alarm clock Mal
malfunction I have the right to uh you
know say that I was honestly going to
get up but this is a technique that has
been working for 5 months so I would
never lie because I know that that would
forever break the technique and my alarm
has never malfunctioned they make sure
to check my phone so for 5 months
straight I've been getting up at 6:00
a.m. on every single weekday and having
some time in the morning to be
productive before I get into my work so
this is a thing that you can try if you
want to get up in the morning and the
fourth technique which I mentioned
earlier is having a morning ritual
getting up early gives you you time to
have a morning ritual in which you can
practice some productive habits that
sort of give you a little bit of a
momentum boost to like push you into the
harder work of the day but also help you
uh also help you make some progress on
some smaller goals so what I do in the
morning is I get up I make sure to make
breakfast to make a healthy breakfast
with some spinach and some eggs I go for
a walk and listen to a podcast so I get
a little bit of exercise get some
sunlight and also listen to a podcast
and educate myself a little bit and then
I come back and do some pull-ups and
push-ups I read for about half an hour
take my vitamins and I'm good to go so
once I've started my work for the day I
already have all these things behind me
they're all very productive habits and
they've given me uh a bit of momentum to
start working on the really hard stuff
like writing or making videos or
whatever it might be so try that out and
if you want a a good tool for tracking
these little habits and sort of giving
yourself a little more motivation to do
them I recommend using habit RPG it's
sort of a a geeky tool that lets you
level up a character and get experience
points but I really like it especially
for the reason that you can partner with
other users and go on quests and if you
don't do your habits then they lose
health and then they come yell at you so
I use it with my roommate and it's
actually a really good motivational tool
so that is a four-step process uh four
different things you can do to at night
the night before and then two first
thing in the morning that give you sort
of a foundation for having a productive
day so uh if you want to get the links
for any of the apps that I mentioned in
this video or read like The overview for
each part of the process then in in the
show notes for this video or below in
the description you'll find a link to
the blog post that goes along with it uh
if you happen to be on YouTube and you
can check that out if you like this
video then subscribe to my channel
because there will be lots more videos
coming uh in the future on making you a
more productive
[Music]
student