when's the last time that you played
slide 2 Band of Thieves for the PS2
huh all right actually I'm not expecting
you to play that exact game except for I
do really like it what I do want to talk
about in this video really quickly to be
honest is that you should be having fun
seriously you should be having real fun
and in this video I want to emphasize a
specific type of fun that I like to call
high density fun so here's the common
problem I hear a lot about and let me
know if you're having the same problem
cuz I hear it a lot from friends so
basically they will say oo I want to
play this new game or I want to see this
new movie that's come out or I want to
do this fun thing fun thing X or fun
thing Y and fun thing X or fun thing why
takes you know a little bit of
investment like a moderate amount of
time to step away from your work and
since they're busy and have a lot of
homework and all that kind of stuff they
just go ah man I just don't have time to
do that thing now I would be inclined to
believe them but the only problem is the
very next minute I see them scrolling
through Facebook or checking Reddit or
spacing off or just something that isn't
actually work so here's the problem that
they're facing they are filling too much
of their day with lowdensity fun fun
that they think is still part of work uh
you could call it distractions and fun
that takes away your ability to have
high density fun fun that actually is
fun and here's the problem with this low
density fun it's not actually fun it's
just a distraction from whatever work
you're trying to get done at the moment
it doesn't reduce stress it doesn't give
you any fond memories it just sort of
takes your your attention away from
something that you don't want to do for
the moment unfortunately it also
drastically extends the time that you
feel like you're working and takes away
what little time you have for actual
relaxation at night so instead of
succumbing to this curse of lowdensity
fund distraction whatever you want to
call it my suggestion for you is to
actually be deliberate about having
highdensity fun which means scheduling
it meaning that you need to actually be
serious about having your high density
fund during the day now this could be
something as simple as saying yes at
8:00 I'm going to play slide two band
Thieves for the PS2 and I'm not going to
work at all for the rest of the night
once I start or it could be something
that requires an actual commitment maybe
you tell your friends that you're going
to go bowling with them and you actually
have to show up doing this is good for a
few reasons number one it puts a little
bit of time pressure on you you're
actually going to be more efficient
during your working hours because you
know that they are limited number two
high density fund reduces stress and I
will talk about this in a later video
but essentially you can think of your
stress as a bucket with a faucet pouring
stress into it constantly and a hole at
the bottom pouring some out well fun
widens the hole and keeps the bucket
from overflowing or in other words
making you go absolutely crazy and
number three scrolling through Facebook
stupid stop it so that's it for this
week's video real simple message but
seriously schedule some highdensity fun
into your life use it to make yourself
more efficient and stay away from the
low density fund it's really not that
useful at
all hey there and thanks for watching my
quick and simple video about high
density fun now if you want to find more
videos on how to be a better college
student every single week you can hit
that big red subscribe button right
there and if you also want to get a free
book that's over a 100 pages on how to
get awesome grades while studying less
then click the picture of the book you
can also find the companion blog post
for this video by clicking the orange
button right there and if you missed
last week's video it's over an hourong
lecture called study less study smart
that I distilled down into 6 minutes so
click the thumbnail to watch it lastly
if you want to suggest topics for new
videos or just connect with me I'm on
Twitter at tomf Frankle or you can leave
a comment on this video and I would love
to hear from you so definitely do that