if you can't tell by the abrupt set
change I have moved and I am currently
in the process of building a new studio
but right now it's well kind of a mess
so bear with me for a while I've got
this temporary set for a couple of days
and then once I get this video out I
will have time to build a proper set
once again but in the meantime we got to
talk about some things that I did right
in college now a few months ago I did a
video called eight mistakes that I made
as a student and that is a pretty big
number of mistakes and I certainly made
more than that but I also did a few
things right so today to sort of create
a compliment to that video I wanted to
go through eight things that I think
that I did correctly as a student and I
think that you might want to apply a few
of these lessons to your own life if you
are a student and some of these might
even be applicable to you even if you're
not a student so let's get into them all
right so the first thing that I want to
go ahead and Pat my 18 year old self on
the back for is taking jobs that existed
outside of my area of focus or my major
now when I went into college I majored
in something called management
information systems which is basically
the IT major my goal originally was to
become a network technician so I was
looking for jobs specifically in the IT
area and my first job in college was
actually working for the campus tech
support department where I removed
viruses from people's computers and took
support calls and answer emails and
basically told people to turn it off and
on again have you tried turning it off
and on again but during that same exact
year I also got a job that was at my
school called being a cyclone aid
because we were the Iowa State Cyclones
and this job was basically working as a
Student Orientation assistant so during
the summer I gave campus tours I set up
in front of tons of parents and students
and answered all kinds of questions
about the college experience and I also
helped set up basically the entire
freshman orientation program we booked
speakers we set up event areas it was a
job where I had to wear a lot of hats
and I also think it was the most useful
part-time job that I worked in college
now I did all kinds of other stuff as
well I worked as a web developer both
freelance and employed I was an RA and I
had lots of other jobs on the side but
that job in particular gave me
leadership skills gave me communication
skills both interpersonal communication
skills and in the realm of public
speaking and in general it made me
it forced me to become a more organized
person and these qualities organization
and leadership and communication and
lots of others employers are looking for
these qualities in addition to
domain-specific experience so yes your
major is important and getting
experience in that major area is
something that I definitely recommend
you do as soon as you possibly can but
also be looking for other jobs and
experiences that give you the
opportunity to build those other
qualities they're really really
important secondly I got really really
serious about using my calendar
correctly during my freshman year and
this was something that was kind of
forced on me because right when I came
into college I got a job at the campus
IT Center like I just said and every
single week this free-for-all calendar
of hours would open up and it was kind
of a first-come first-served thing so if
you were there the moment the calendar
opened up you could get whatever hours
you wanted you can kind of tailor it
around your class schedule which was
awesome
but if you waited too long usually we
were just picking up the scraps and
working midnight shifts or 7:30 a.m.
shifts which you know what those are
kind of okay for me but still it was
nice to have a choice and the moment
that I would grab a slot on that work
calendar I would go and replicate that
work slot on my personal Google Calendar
and this was really important because my
work schedule is changing every single
week as a result and I also had a pretty
complicated class schedule but that
wasn't all I was doing with my calendar
and the tip that I want to share with
you here was something that I started
doing really early on which was looking
ahead at the academic calendar and at
other calendars for organizations and
other things like that and putting
events on my calendar well in advance
for example I went and found the date at
which I could sign up for the next
semester's classes and I got that on my
calendar and made sure I was awake and
ready to sign up for classes the moment
I could again it was kind of a
first-come first-served thing and I
wanted to be first all right Adam number
three on list I optimized my time and my
schedule for extracurriculars rather
than a heavy course load now there are
going to be people in the comments who
are really gung-ho about double majoring
and I'm sure many people have had a
great experience doing so or compressing
their classes into fewer semesters so
they could cut the cost of college but
for me I viewed college as a
concentrated bundle of opportunities I
was basically placing myself in a
geographical space where there was just
all kinds of opportunity around me and I
realized that class
worth the only kind of opportunities I
knew that if I dedicated some of my time
towards extracurriculars towards
participating in clubs and being in the
leadership boards of those clubs towards
personal projects like building my
website college info geek which
eventually became my career or even
part-time jobs on campus I knew that it
would get a much more well-rounded
experience in college plus I knew that
employers were looking for real-world
experience they were looking for
impressive projects where the student
took initiative and you can get those in
classes but you can get a lot more of
them outside class so I think that it's
a good idea to have a balance between
coursework and extracurriculars now
we're moving on to item number four it's
a brand new John Cena poster for my door
of course actually I'm number four was
that I kept applying for scholarships
all throughout my college career now a
lot of high schoolers go really hard on
the scholarship application train up
until they get to college a lot of
people think that scholarships are
something that you worry about when
you're in high school and then you don't
worry about funding once you're in your
university experience but there are a
lot of scholarships out there for
current college students and even for
graduate students and in fact I won far
more scholarships during my college
career than I ever did in high school
during college I went to different
entrepreneurship scholarships one I
think was for my freelance web design
business and then the second one later
on was for college info geek and aside
from those which obviously did involve a
lot of extra curricular work I also
applied for general College of Business
scholarships where I just had to fill
out a basic application and I won a
couple off of that as well so I think
that it would be advisable to follow the
path that my 19 and 20 and 21 year old
self took keep applying for scholarships
all throughout your educational career
unless the funding is completely taken
care of you kind of owe it to yourself
to do it
alright item number five as often as I
could I introduced myself to my new
professors and teachers assistants at
the beginning of each semester classes
and I also went to office hours and I
didn't just go to office hours to ask
for help I would occasionally drop by
office hours just to chat with the
professor because I wanted to build
relationships now looking back on all
those efforts I don't have ongoing
relationships with every single
professor that I ever had in college but
I do still stay in contact with a few of
them every now and then and a lot of
really good stuff came out of those
relationships as well some of them were
happy to write letters of
datian for internships and scholarships
when I asked them because they knew me
and they knew a little bit of my work
and I was even invited to speak at the
classes of a couple of them after I
graduated from college so I know this
takes a little bit of effort but
everything worth doing it does whenever
you start a new semester make it a point
to at least introduce yourself to your
professors and try to build that
relationship
alright item number 6 which might be a
bit of a controversial item but I at
least stand by it I chose to live on
campus in the dorms for my first two
years of college and I have this
decision on the list because it wasn't
my original plan back when I was in high
school I had plans to get an off-campus
apartment with one of my friends from
high school we were both gonna get
part-time jobs on campus and we were
just gonna pay the monthly rent to live
off-campus which was a little bit
cheaper than the dorms and which would
have allowed us to pay monthly rather
than all upfront each semester and that
was big because we didn't want to take
on loans and I kind of had this entirely
debt-free mindset going into college
which was why I was gonna you know move
three miles off campus was gonna get the
part-time job all that stuff but then
during the summer leading up to my
freshman year I decided to go and read
every college prep book my public
library had and one of those books was
the naked roommate by Harlan Cohen and I
remember one of the pieces of advice in
that book being to live on campus for at
least the first year and his
justification for that was that it puts
you in the middle of the action all the
opportunities are so much closer to you
if there's an event on campus you don't
have to do the mental calculus of
whether or not it's worth it to drive 30
minutes there and back all that kind of
stuff you are just there and also if you
live in the dorms you can have your door
open all the time and a lot of people
will just end up wandering in and that's
how you make friends
so I took that books advice and yes I
did end up taking a couple of student
loans to make that work in hindsight I
probably could have paid for it with
part-time job earnings anyway so I would
count that as a little bit of a mistake
but I'm very glad I lived on campus I
met friends who are still some of my
best friends today and that book was
right I was placed right in the middle
of the action and at the drop of a hat
I could go take advantage of an
opportunity which I did many many times
now again I realized this particular tip
might be controversial both for the
financial aspect of it and for the fact
that many campuses do things differently
my campus was a very
insular environment some campuses are
just in the middle of cities and it
makes sense to get an apartment that
isn't affiliated with your school so the
lesson that I really want to share here
isn't to make sure you're living in
on-campus dorms per se but it's to do
whatever you can to put yourself in the
middle of the action
put yourself as close to the potential
opportunities as you can especially
during that first and second year when
you haven't really figured out what you
want to do you haven't made as many
friends yet you're still kind of trying
to establish yourself item number 7
which is quite related to item number 6
I was constantly keeping my eye out for
opportunities a lot of the buildings on
my campus had bulletin boards that I was
constantly looking at and I also went
and proactively followed a lot of the on
campus departments and clubs on Twitter
and Facebook and I kept tabs on the
things that were going on but I didn't
just keep tabs mentally and what I want
to share here is to keep an eye out for
opportunities but then put them on your
calendar and if you're not sure whether
or not you want to do them or if you
have time just mark them as TBA and
maybe even put them on a specific
calendar for on-campus events that way
on a day to day basis you can go and
look at what's going on on your personal
calendar or where it's all nice and
collected and decide whether or not you
can actually make it to the things that
you put on that calendar alright finally
number eight I went to every single
career fair that I could I've put this
item on the list because I remember
distinctly during my freshman year a lot
of my friends said I don't need to go to
the Career Fair this year because I'm
only planning on getting an internship
after my sophomore year after my second
year of college so what's the point of
going to the career fair now it's just a
waste of my time right but I saw it
differently I too only intended to get
an internship after my sophomore year
because I was doing that Student
Orientation job the summer after my
freshman year but I wanted to go to the
career fair to meet people as early as I
could because I figured if I met
recruiters during my freshman year then
I would go to the Career Fair during my
sophomore year again and they would
recognize me and the more they
recognized me the more rapport we
established the higher up I was probably
going to be on the short lists of the
hiring managers that they talked to
additionally going to every single
Career Fair meant that I was getting a
lot more practice talking with
recruiters pitching myself telling them
what I wanted to do when my skills were
well my experience was this is
kind of difficult when you don't have a
whole lot of practice doing it so by
going to every single career fair every
single networking event that you have
access to within your major and
otherwise you're gonna get a lot of
practice and even if you end up talking
with recruiters at companies that you
don't really care about
you're gonna one make a connection but
two you're gonna get practice that will
be applicable for the recruiters and the
companies that you really do care about
so my suggestion is to go to every
career fair that you can even if you
aren't intending to get a job or an
internship for a couple of years it's
just good practice now in the first tip
of this video I talked about a few of
the qualities that hiring managers and
recruiters are looking for beyond simple
major level or domain level experience
things like organizational skills or
communication ability and in addition to
those these hiring managers are also
looking for things like adaptability and
problem-solving skills they want to know
if you can independently apply yourself
to a new and novel problem and solve it
because if you can then you are
advancing their business and they're
probably gonna want to hire you and
luckily problem solving and adaptability
these are traits that you can learn and
get better at through practice and if
you're looking for a great resource for
building those skills you should check
out brilliant brilliant isn't
excellently designed a learning platform
for anyone who wants to improve their
abilities in the areas of math science
into computer science and what I love
about brilliant is they approach their
course design process with the principle
of active learning in mind this means
that from the moment you start one of
their in-depth courses you are gonna be
solving the problems you won't be
sitting back passively in taking
information you're gonna have to sink
your teeth into something that you might
get stuck on now these problems are
bite-size so they're not designed to
frustrate you but they are designed to
keep your interest level high and
they're also designed to improve your
problem-solving skills along the way
within their library you're gonna find a
ton of different courses that you can
take from calculus to statistics to
waves and lights to even computer
science fundamentals but this year they
also watched a new feature called daily
problems this is a section of the
website where every single day they
publish a few new problems in broad
areas for you to sink your teeth into
such as this one on whether or not sound
travels farther in the cold or this one
where you have to figure out what
happens did you cut a mobius strip in
half these problems don't take up a
whole lot of your time so they're great
for building a daily learning habit and
most importantly they're from a broad
array of subjects so if you're stuck
within a couple of subjects within their
in-depth courses this can be a great
feature for expanding your horizons and
maybe finding something
knew that you might be interested in it
so if you want to try your hand at some
of those daily problems or get into one
of their in-depth courses then go over
to brilliant org slash Thomas Frank and
to sign up and if you're one of the
first 83 people who does so you're also
gonna get 20% off their annual premium
subscription big thanks to brilliant for
sponsoring this video of being a huge
supporter of my channel and the work
that I do and as always guys thank you
so much for watching if you like this
video definitely hit that like button so
more people can find this channel and
you can also subscribe right there if
you wanna get new videos every single
week when they come out you can also
click right there to get a free copy of
my book and how to earn better grades
watch one more video on this channel
right over here or follow me on
instagram at Tom frankly thanks for
watching and I will see you guys in the
next one bye