hey what's up guys so today we are going
to talk about your morning routine now
there is a ton of stuff out there on the
internet about morning routines there's
tons of books there's tons of blogs
there's tons of podcast episodes but it
seems like the majority of those are
focused on what you should be adding to
your morning routine what you should do
I want to take a little bit of a
different tack today and focus on what
you should stop doing in your morning
routine so today we are gonna break down
eight different things that you should
stop doing when you wake up in the
morning if you're doing them right now
the first item on our list has to do
with that magical little rectangle of
plastic and silicone in your pocket if
you wake up in the morning and
immediately check social media on your
phone you need to stop doing this for
two important reasons first and foremost
if you make checking social media the
first action of your day then the first
action of your day is giving in to a
craving for novelty and that counteracts
all the work that you've been doing to
build your focus muscle by contrast if
you wait a little bit before you check
those feeds and maybe do some other
things like having breakfast or working
out or reading a book for a bit you are
telling your brain that yes you have to
wait before you can go check all those
novelty inducing social media feeds and
that's gonna make you much more able to
focus on your work later on in the day
reason number two why you should stop
checking social media in the morning is
because if you're anything like me you
tend to just grab the phone and start
checking your feeds in bed and you
intend to only check your feeds for
about five minutes but you end up
looking at them for twenty minutes
sometimes and from personal experience I
can tell you there is no healthy
position to be looking at a phone in bed
your eyes are looking at it with your
arm above your head or your propped up
on one elbow either way you are putting
your body in a bad postural position and
if you do this enough you can actually
end up causing nerve damage
I've actually caused a nerve damage at
my own arms before and it is really
painful and impedes my work and it takes
a surprisingly long time to heal so in
short use your bed as a place for
sleeping check your social media when
you're out of bed and do it a little bit
after you wake up item number two on our
list is eating an unhealthy breakfast so
I'm actually reading Jordan Peterson's
book twelve rules for living right now
and in this book he actually talks about
how eating a protein and fat heavy
breakfast can actually decrease feelings
of anxiety even putting that aside and a
lot of people like to wake
and they eat a breakfast full of sugar
or simple carbs and neither of those
things is going to set you up for a
sustained healthy energy throughout the
day and this is not me getting on a high
horse here this is yet another area
where I actually struggle with
temptation because it can be very easy
for me to fall into a pattern waa wake
up every single day convince myself that
I need to work right away and then go to
Starbucks and get a breakfast sandwich
and those things are not healthy so you
might be asking yourself how do I make
sure that I'm eating a healthy breakfast
on a regular basis and one of the
easiest ways to do this is to bulk prep
your meals
this basically means taking one or two
days a week to bulk cook a bunch of food
in advance so it's really easy and quick
to grab it in the mornings the great
thing about this is that it's efficient
you don't have to get up the pots and
pans seven different times you'd have to
clean them seven different times it's
just one or two times and you reap the
time-saving benefits one really great
candidate from prepping is hard-boiled
eggs because if you have a pressure
cooker you can cook them really really
quickly and the shells are very easy to
peel off and if you don't you can easily
do it in a pot it's a little harder to
peel the shells off but still pretty
easy and saves you a lot of time or you
can do what me and my girlfriend love to
do which is making egg bakes in a
casserole dish item number three on the
list is hitting the snooze button on
your alarm and you knew this was coming
on the list so aside from the fact that
hitting the snooze button is basically
denying yourself good quality sleep that
you could have had because you are
interrupting your sleep cycle and then
attempting to get into a new one which
is going to be inevitably interrupted
early again hitting the snooze button is
also a terrible idea because doing it is
admitting defeat as your very first
action of the day if you hit the snooze
button on your alarm it means that you
had set an intention to wake up at a
specific time the night before and then
you failed so do yourself a favor and
get out of bed the moment your alarm
goes off now this might sound a little
bit weird but I've actually found it
pretty helpful to picture myself setting
this intention and telling it to a
specific person and the person who
always comes to mind for me is Jacko
willing who is currently a podcaster and
author but was a Navy SEAL and to be
honest is somebody that I would
definitely not want to disappoint in
real life of course if that's not enough
I've also devised a system for basically
forcing myself to get up in the morning
you
scheduled tweet and if you're curious
about that I will have a link in the
description down below and on screen
right now now we're moving on to item
number four it's brand-new John Cena
poster for my door just kidding it's
complaining seriously a lot of people
love to wake up in the morning and
complain they complain about how early
it is they complain about having to go
to work they complain about how tired
they feel and the problem with
complaining is that the words that you
choose to use the way that you choose to
express yourself actually has a tangible
effect on your state of mind and your
level of motivation so instead of waking
up in the morning and complaining why
not think about what you have to be
grateful about or you can be positive
about if you dwell on these things
you're gonna be an overall a happier
person
alright item number five is cleaning up
your living space and your work area now
this is definitely not a bad thing to do
but I'm putting it on this list because
I think it is much better to do it the
night before you might have heard me
talk in the past about a concept called
clear to neutral
this basically means setting your work
area or your living area back to its
neutral state after you're done using
this and the reason that you want to do
this is that the next time you come to
use it which in the case of your living
space would be the next day when you
wake up you want to be in a state that
is already usable when your living space
to your work space is ready to be used
immediately when you start the day you
don't have to waste any of your
willpower or your time getting it ready
it's just ready to go so when you're
building your before bed routine build
in a little bit of time for cleaning
your space up and clearing it back to
neutral your future self is gonna be
very appreciative on a similar note item
number six is planning your day now
planning your day in the morning can be
very useful for some people some people
love to have that as part of their
morning routine but for other people it
can actually be a lot better to plan
their day the night before personally I
find that when I wake up to a concrete
plan that I set up the night before
I almost feel kind of beholden to my
past self and I'm much more clear on the
direction I'm going to go in immediately
it's kind of similar to how Barack Obama
used to outsource the decision for what
outfit he was going to wear during the
day because he didn't want to deal with
that decision he already had a ton of
other decisions and that was just going
to make him less focused item number
seven is starting your day with negative
news
and if you're the kind of person who
likes to check reddit or the news app on
your phone this is something that you
need to be worried about as somebody who
likes to browse reddit I mean heck I've
even got my own subreddit for college
info geek I am well aware that many of
the default subreddits on reddit.com are
filled with tons of negative news and
yes you might want to keep up to date on
world events but if you're waking up
every single morning and bombarding
yourself with a ton of negative stories
that's gonna put you in a negative state
of mind and it's also likely to send you
down rabbit holes that end up wasting a
ton of your time so if you are going to
wake up and check news check your feeds
if that's something you like to do
tailor those feeds to be full of
positive or interesting information not
negative news or if you wanna do
something even more effective just read
a book in the morning make that part of
your morning routine and then check your
feeds later on during the day again if
you wake up in the morning and you start
your day with some long-form content
that's building that focus muscle and
that brings us to our final item on the
list which is getting up at different
times every morning if you don't
currently have a at least somewhat
consistent time you wake up in the
morning if you're getting up really late
in the weekends and really early during
the days or you have totally different
wakeup times during the week then you
are negatively impacting your body's
circadian rhythm and negatively
impacting the quality of your sleep so
as best as you can try to establish a
consistent wakeup time for yourself and
I know a bunch of you are gonna ask me
can I still sleep in on the weekends and
biologically speaking you would be best
off by having a consistent wakeup time
that includes the weekends your body
doesn't have like a special magical
weekend mode it doesn't switch over all
of its biological processes because
you're not in school or work but that
doesn't mean that you are going to ruin
your life by sleeping into the weekends
and to be quite honest I actually sleep
in about an hour later on Saturdays and
Sundays than when I get up during the
week so if you want to be like me you
don't want to be completely over
efficient then go ahead and do that but
from a scientific perspective a
consistent wake up time is better than
an inconsistent one now in future videos
we are definitely going to talk about
things that you can add to your morning
routine to further improve the quality
of your daily life but the nice thing
about the items on this list is that
well they don't take a lot of effort to
put into practice so earlier in the
video we talked about how it might be a
good addition to your morning routine to
read a book and this is something that I
like to do myself but because I am very
committed to having some form of
exercise in my morning routine as well
whether it be going to the gym or going
for a bike ride or for a long walk I
typically listen to my books and my
favorite app for finding those books is
audible audible has an unbeatable
selection of audiobook titles in a ton
of different genres ranging from
psychology to science fiction the
biographies so no matter what's sitting
on your reading list you are most likely
going to be able to find it in their
library now in the past you've probably
seen me talk about how you can use
audible on your phone but today I wanted
to show you how you can also use it on
an Amazon echo and it's really easy all
you do is ask Alexa to read an audible
book Alexa really Elon Musk's by Ashley
Vance getting the selection from Thomas
audible library resuming Elon Musk and
from there you can easily listen while
you're cooking dinner which is what I
usually use it for or while you're doing
anything else at home also as a guy who
sometimes likes to listen to audiobooks
well I'm going to sleep I love the fact
that you can ask Alexa to set a sleep
timer so your book doesn't get too far
ahead once you actually do fall asleep
and of course you can also use voice
commands to ask Alexa to pause or go
backwards just get forward and at any
time you can pause what you're listening
to on your echo device and pick up right
where you left off on your phone so if
you've already got an echo device you
can try this for free right now and when
you're ready for more you can go over to
audible.com slash Thomas or text Thomas
to five hundred five hundred on your
phone to get a free one-month trial that
also comes with a free audiobook
download of your choosing now as you can
probably tell from all the b-roll here
the book that I'm gonna recommend for
you guys this week is the Elon Musk
biography by Ashley advance which covers
Elon Musk's early years as well as the
development of Tesla and SpaceX and if
you saw my recent video on Elon Musk a
lot of lessons about how productive he
is came straight from that book so if
you want to start listening to that book
for free or any other book of your
choosing once again you can go over to
audible.com slash Thomas or text Thomas
to five hundred five hundred on your
phone
big thanks to audible for sponsoring
this video and helping to support this
channel and as always thank you guys so
much for watching you hit that like
button if you enjoyed this video and
also subscribe right
if you don't want to miss future videos
when they come out you might also want
to pick up a free copy at my book on how
to earn better grades right there or
check out one more video on this channel
right around here
thanks for watching and I will see you
in the next video