Hello friends and welcome to my day five
accelerated Japanese challenge learning
overview thingy from Osaka Japan we just
got here and uh yeah so I wanted to tell
you a little bit about what I did in the
first half of my learning challenge
basically I relearned all of hiragana
and Katakana two of the more simple
slaveries or alphabets as you can call
them in Japanese I also went through the
first two chapters of texu the online
Japanese textbook that I talked about in
the last video just to kind of give
myself a refresher and the most
important thing I did was created a list
of sentences in Evernote that I wanted
to be able to say and that's what I want
to recommend to you to do if you're
learning a language in this video so
basically I created a big list of all
the things I wanted to say I made it as
varied as possible but I also tried to
make the sentences things that I would
actually need to say in Japan things
like iura how much is this um things
like where is the bathroom how much is
it to stay here things like that things
that I would actually want to be able to
talk to Japanese people about and uh
learning these would enable me to
actually be functional in the country
and it's also a very fast way to learn
the language so basically if you want to
do this just create a list in Evernote
start using Google Translate to get a
starting point as to how to put the
grammar and sentence structure together
and then maybe even hire a tutor on a
site like I talking to get some
instruction now this isn't something I
had done within the first 5 days of the
challenge but I did do it in the next 5
days and I'll talk about that next time
now this is just kind of an extension of
the active learning concept it's just
active recall and forcing yourself to do
things with the inent of actually using
it and if you want some more detail on
this idea Tim Ferris actually did a talk
on his uh his method for Rapid skill
acquisition and basically he
deconstructs a skill then selects a
little bitty parts of it that he
actually wants to use and that's how he
learns things rapidly so if you want to
see that I've actually embedded that
talk in the blog post for this video
which you'll find linked down in the
description below and we're going to go
see the aquarium in Osaka so see you in
the next
video
[Music]
why does he go back
[Applause]
like