thanks to brilliant for sponsoring this
video and supporting my channel hi my
name is thomas frank and i am in the
market for some new noise cancelling
headphones because after about four
years of use my trusty bose qc35 gen
ones are finally dying on me the battery
is running out quicker and quicker these
days and there are some
new models on the market so in this
video i'm going to be testing out and
deciding which of these noise-canceling
bluetooth headphones are the absolute
best ones you can buy here in 2021 for
me budget is not a huge consideration
these are all the models that are the
top of the line as far as all the other
reviewers i've seen are concerned so we
have the bose 700 the apple airpods max
the
sony wh 1000
nice naming convention sony and because
my friend ali abdal loves them so much
i'm also throwing in the 250 microsoft
surface headphones too into the mix and
what i want to do is compare all of
these against my trusty bose qc35s to
see whether or not i should just rebuy
these or go with one of these newer
models so first and foremost i'm going
to give you a quick upfront verdict so
you know what i think and what you might
want to do if you're short on time and
then we're going to dive into the
details going over the criteria that i
care about the most comfort sound
quality noise cancellation quality
portability and cool extra features
finally we're gonna be rounding things
out with a more detailed verdict so for
me after two full weeks of testing i am
going with the apple airpods max yes
these are much more expensive than the
competition about 200 more than anything
else on this table and yes they have
some weird quirks the case that these
come with is absolutely stupid i have no
idea why apple designed it that way but
they sound amazing they connect
perfectly to all of my other apple
devices the transparency mode is a game
changer i'll talk about that a bit later
and their noise cancellation is
absolutely the best out of everything on
this table so these are the ones that
i'm personally going with however if
you're not heavily invested in the apple
ecosystem if you don't have a bunch of
different apple devices or you have
other maybe android or pc devices you
also want to connect to or if you don't
want to spend a ton of extra money for
you know marginal extra benefit what i
would recommend going with is the sony
again wh 1000 xm4s these are about 350
bucks last time i checked they have
amazing noise cancellation just about as
good as these the sound quality is
excellent especially if you like bass
and they have a lot of cool features so
these are the ones that i would
recommend for most people if you are
trying to get the best and you don't
want to go apple's way so that's my
upfront verdict we'll have a more
detailed version at the end but now
let's get into some of the details
behind the criteria that i was looking
for when i was looking for a new pair of
headphones and let's start with comfort
because i think that's actually the most
important criteria of them all i'm going
to be wearing these headphones or
whichever one i pick for multiple hours
at a time so of these which are the most
comfortable well
if you've ever owned a pair of bose qc35
quiet comfort 35 headphones it will
probably be no surprise to you that
these
are still absolutely the most
comfortable headphones you can buy at
least out of this test area here they
basically feel like pillows on your head
and out of everything that i tested
these are the only model that i will
actually sometimes forget are on my head
so if comfort is of the utmost priority
to you these are definitely at the top
of the list even though they do lack
some of the features and some of the
tech that the newer models have beyond
this my opinion may be a little
contentious here because of the other
four that are remaining i actually think
that the airpods max are the most
comfortable and this is where i differ
from a lot of other reviewers i read a
lot of reviews did a lot of research in
preparation for this video and a lot of
people said the airpods max were kind of
uncomfortable and it's not hard to see
why even though apple put a ton of
engineering into this mesh canopy thing
that they're calling the top headband
the fact of the matter is that these
headphones have a metal build which
makes them about 100 or more grams
heavier than everything else here on the
table and yes these metal ear cups these
metal connectors here they do feel very
premium but you can't get around the
fact that they do make them quite a bit
heavier that being said even though a
lot of other reviewers have have kind of
griped about the weight here after
testing these every single day for about
two weeks
they do not bug me at all i've actually
worn them at night to watch movies in
addition to wearing them during the day
for work purposes and the mesh canopy
for me is actually the real deal so this
is definitely going to be one of those
your mileage may vary things but for me
other than these old bows of mine these
are actually the most comfortable coming
in second or i guess third place after
these i'm going to give it up to the
sony i'm just going to call them xm4 at
this point these are nearly as
comfortable as the bose they have a
little bit more rigidity to them a
little bit more clamping force but
otherwise you know they're pretty nice
feeling on my head the bose 700 are
pretty similar as well though i will say
i have kind of an elongated head feel
free to make fun of me in the comments
about that but even with the ear cups
extended to the end of the rods here it
does feel a little bit tight on the top
of my head so i probably give the edge
to the sony's over these bows and then
unfortunately i have to give a
resounding last place to the surface
headphones too in terms of comfort now i
know ali loves these so again i think
the verdict here is really going to come
down to personal preference how your
head is shaped different pressure points
on your head and how those differ from
mine but for me these are the only
headphones that became actively
uncomfortable after about just an hour
of use i started to get this pressure
point spot on the top of my head and no
matter what i did to shift it or try to
adjust these headphones they just
weren't comfortable for me let's move on
to sound quality what sounds the best
well when i was doing research before i
even bought the headphones for this
review a lot of the reviews were saying
yes the hype is real the airpods max
actually do sound better than all the
other headphones that we've tested i
read this on sound guys or this on some
other blogs and in my testing i have to
agree
these are the best sounding bluetooth
noise cancelling headphones that i have
ever tried except for in one dimension
so for me the sound stage here is the
best the clarity of the highs is the
best the overall
quality of the music in general is the
best however the bass in the airpods max
isn't quite up to the level of what
you're going to find in the sony's and
in the microsoft surface headphones too
so if you are somebody who loves bass
over everything else i would go for
either one of these with the edge going
to the sony's because while i found the
bass to be even boomier in the microsoft
headphones the overall listening
experience just sounded a bit better in
the sony's i will also note that if
you're using this with your iphone or
android device there is an app where you
can actually change the eq profiles and
weirdly i found that the classical eq
profile was the one i liked best for
even rock and metal but i won't give too
much weight to that because if you're
using it on like a mac or a pc you're
not going to have that built-in eq and
you can just use a system-wide eq or the
eq and apple music or spotify to adjust
how any of these headphones sound still
these get the edge over these in terms
of overall sound quality and these are
both what you want to go for in terms of
bass uh let's talk about the bose
options here the 700 is the newest bose
headphone offering it is what a lot of
people consider to be the successor to
the qc35 even though they are a totally
different model line and bose is still
making and selling these in their second
generation but given the price
difference between a pair of qc35s 250
dollars and the 700's 380 dollars when i
bought them i was expecting these to
completely blow me out of the water
and what i actually experienced was just
about the opposite and tony verified
this for me when he tested these against
the sony's these kind of sound terrible
to my ears they sound worse than the old
qc35 in terms of sound quality these are
the absolute bottom of the tier list
even compared to the surface headphones
which you think wouldn't sound quite as
good given that they're 250 bucks again
a huge price delta when compared to the
700s so i gotta say the sound quality
here is a massive disappointment and
maybe the kind of music that you listen
to or the kind of ear you have is gonna
be a little bit more favorable towards
these but you know both me and my editor
think that these are woefully
underperforming even compared to their
previous model and definitely compared
to the sony's and the airpods max now to
be fair to these 700s i do think one big
area where they do beat out the old
qc35s is in the area of noise
cancellation and that's going to be our
next detail criteria that we're going to
go through and one of the most important
if you're in the market for a pair of
noise canceling headphones then the
noise cancellation performance is
probably going to be pretty important to
you now to set a baseline all of these
headphones here in front of me do a
really good job at blocking out outside
noise and they do that in two different
ways number one these are all closed
back over the ear headphones which means
that their physical design provides some
isolation already but they also have
what's called active noise cancellation
where they've got an array of
microphones that actually listen to the
ambient noise around you and then
generate opposite sound waves that
cancel out most that ambient noise now
the degree to which these are successful
in doing that is going to depend on a
few things the frequency ranges of the
noise the uh steadiness of the noise so
you know like an airplane drone versus a
loud coffee shop with a baby crying
every once in a while there's going to
be differences there but also the tech
within each pair of headphones and
that's what we're really going to focus
on here which of these actually does the
best job well number one new tech
definitely beats old tech all these new
models that i tested do a better job at
blocking out outside noise than the
qc35s these still do a really good job
and if they hadn't started dying on me i
probably never would have even thought
to do this comparison so if you really
care about comfort and you want these
they still do a pretty darn good job um
the surface headphone too i also say
would do a pretty good job but not quite
on the level of these other more
expensive headphones now among the sony
the bose 700 and the airpods max which
ones perform at the absolute best level
well in my testing in my opinion i think
the airpods max really do take the cake
here and my testing methodology was
twofold i took all these headphones to a
very loud dynamic coffee shop
environment so i was getting lots of
different sounds that kind of came at
different unpredictable times and i also
tested out all these headphones next to
my very loud
hvac system on the opposite side of this
single uh drywall wall here in my
basement i didn't have access to an
airplane for this test but i think that
thing is a pretty good substitute and
sitting here testing things out going to
the coffee shop testing things out i do
think that the active noise cancellation
on the airpods max is just to cut above
everything else in this comparison and i
read several views saying the exact same
thing in fact the sound guys review
shows an interesting graph comparing the
sony xm4s to the airpods max and shows
how the airpods max actually do have
objectively better cancellation in the
lower frequency range that being said in
my anecdotal experience i think that the
xm4 are so close to the airpods max
especially if you're not sitting right
next to an hvac
system they're so close that you
probably wouldn't notice an appreciable
difference over a long period of time
and especially given the price delta
between these two i mean these are
almost 200 cheaper if noise cancellation
quality is your main criteria you're
looking for these are kind of a
no-brainer so what about the bose 700
well i think that they also have very
good noise cancellation if you look at
the sound guys objective tests it's not
quite as good and not quite on the level
of these two but still very good and
noticeably better than the qc35 and the
microsoft surface headphones in my
opinion so if you really want bose again
if you can deal with that objectively
worse sound quality these will be the
ones to go for so now let's move things
on to portability this is a bit of a
less important category when compared to
comfort and sound quality and noise
cancellation quality but it still is
important because if your headphones are
going in your bag then they have to
jostle for space with everything else
you want to put in your bag when you go
about your daily work so which of these
is the best in terms of portability well
the answer is actually it's a tie it's
the sony xm4 and the bose qc35 and the
reason for that is that both of these
headphones have a dual folding mechanism
you can fold the ear cups back but you
can also fold the entire headphone up
and make it take up less space and this
means that the included cases for these
two headphone models take up less space
in general than the other three whereas
the surface headphones the airpods max
and the 700s just have their ear cups
lay flat and they don't fold up in any
other way which means their cases take
up quite a bit more space let's talk
about the case that comes with the
airpods max for a second because it is
the stupidest most idiotic design case
that i have ever laid eyes on when it
comes to premium headphones i have no
idea why apple designed it this way
because you know by my reckoning the
most fragile part of these headphones is
this mesh canopy thing on the headband
and that case does absolutely nothing to
protect this fragile part of the
headphone so if you're going to buy
these like i am then you're probably
going to want to do what i did and
tackle an extra 20 bucks onto your
buying budget so you can go on amazon
and buy a cheap zipper case that
actually protects your headphones and
doesn't add a whole lot to the footprint
since you already have the headphones
taking up a ton of space due to the way
that they fold anyway in terms of
overall footprint in your bag the bose
700 do seem to take up a little less
space than the surface headphones 2 and
the airpods max whereas these two are
the big daddies they're going to take up
more space in your bag than pretty much
anything else so if you want these if
you want these make sure you got room in
your bag one criteria that i didn't
explicitly mention in the intro but that
i probably should talk about now is
battery life but fortunately we can go
pretty fast here because for the most
part you're gonna get around 20 hours of
use per charge on all these headphones
i've got two notes that i can make about
that number one the xm4s are marketed to
have 30 hours of battery life so you
should be getting quite a bit more but
in the sound guys review their tests
found out that they only got 19 hours of
battery life so that kind of brings it
down to the level of all these other
options maybe they worked out some kinks
maybe it's a bit better but that's
something to consider point number two
the airpods max do not have an off
button and a lot of people are kind of
freaking out about that they're like
well what if i don't want to put my
headphones in the case are they going to
die overnight i will mention that quinn
nelson over at snazzy labs his review he
actually left these out on his
nightstand outside of the case overnight
and only experienced three percent
battery loss so i think the uh hubbub
about these dying if you don't put them
in the case is a little bit overblown
would i like to be able to turn them off
for real when i'm not using them yeah
but on the other hand the airpods pro
have gotten me pretty used to being able
to stick the headphones in my ear and
just have them immediately connect so
that's kind of a nice convenience
feature and personally i have to charge
my ipad my macbook every single night so
it's not a huge hassle to just plug
these in right on top of all that stuff
and you know have them fully charged in
the morning so that brings us to maybe
the most fun category in this review
which is cool extra features that these
headphones come with because uh they
have some and you might actually care
about them so first let's talk about
bluetooth multi-point this is a
technology that allows you to connect
your headphones to multiple devices and
then even have them automatically switch
over to a new device when something
starts playing so maybe you're listening
to spotify on your laptop and then you
uh you open up a youtube video on your
phone these headphones can all for the
most part switch over automatically and
start playing that video in your
headphones but there are different
degrees to multipoint and the airpods
max don't actually have true bluetooth
multi-point i'll get to that in a second
among these four models they all have
bluetooth multi-point but i found in my
testing the switching speed was actually
the fastest on the microsoft surface 2
headphones so if you really care about
bluetooth multi-points maybe these are
ones to consider
works really well on these though works
well on these works pretty well even on
these qc35s as well so let's talk about
the airpods max they don't have true
bluetooth multi-point but what they do
have is the ability to switch pretty
seamlessly between all of your apple
devices that you have these connected to
and i believe that all syncs through
your icloud account so if you're a heavy
apple user like i am i do have a desktop
pc for editing but otherwise i'm pretty
much all apple all the time this
actually works better than traditional
bluetooth multipoint i can have these
switched seamlessly between my apple tv
my macbook pro my iphone in very very
little time and it's just it's very nice
and convenient to have but if you have
an android device or you have a laptop
that you're going to want to connect to
that's running windows then you know
these can work but the multi-point is
not going to work so well and overall i
wouldn't recommend these if you are
trying to mix those other non-apple
devices into your workflow auto pause is
another interesting feature that some of
these headphone models have where when
you take the headphones off of your head
they can actually detect that you've
done so and pause the music or pause the
video that you're playing the airpods
max has it the uh microsoft surface
headphones have it and the sony's have
it but if you are a bose aficionado you
are sadly going to be out of luck on the
autopaws front now one feature that the
airpods max have that none of these
other headphone models can boast is
something called spatial audio this is
something i didn't think i would care
about before i bought these and started
testing them out but now that i've tried
it
it is honestly really cool so if you're
using an ios device that has the latest
ios installed or even an apple tv with
the beta tv os 15 you can actually turn
on something called spatial audio which
basically is like 3d audio it mimics
surround sound and the first time that i
tried watching a show on my ipad using
it with these headphones i legitimately
thought the sound was coming from my
ipad i thought these were disconnected
and then i was like wait why does it
sound so good these do a really good job
at mimicking surround sound and honestly
this is kind of like a hidden feature in
terms of what i was thinking about but
if you're living like an apartment or
something and you can't set up a proper
surround sound system because you've got
neighbors who don't want to hear it this
is actually a pretty convincing
alternative and it's going to be
something that i'll probably use quite a
bit when i'm traveling and you know
being on planes watching movies that way
lastly let's talk about transparency or
ambient sound mode all of these except
for my old school bose qc35s have the
ability to let outside noise actually
pass through the headphones and be
amplified past the point of what you
would hear if the anc was turned off
however only one of these headphone
models has a transparency mode that i
actually would want to use on a daily
basis and it is the airpods max in fact
the transparency mode on the airpods max
is so good that i've been using it all
the time i didn't think i would use it
at all but i found out that when i have
these on when i have transparency mode
on it sounds almost indistinguishable
from having no headphones on at all and
it also means that i can listen to music
at a pretty low volume and easily hear
anybody else in the house if they need
me and they want to get my attention so
i've actually been wearing these and
using transparency mode while filming
b-roll or doing work around the house
and if anna needs me or tony needs me
they can easily get my attention i
absolutely love the transparency mode on
these which is a surprise for me because
i don't like the transparency mode very
much on the airpods pro in those it
sounds a little bit too amplified and a
little bit too harsh but here it's like
not wearing headphones at all the
surface headphones the sonys and the
bose all have their own transparency
mode but to my ears the world either
sounds muffled it sounds dull it's just
like it's there if you need it but it's
not something that i think you would
actively want to use it's not pleasing
like it is on the airpods so final
verdict time which of these five
headphone models should you buy well we
didn't talk about price in this
comparison because my aim here was to
identify the best possible headphones
but if price is something that's
important to you the surface headphones
2 and the bose qc35 are a hundred
dollars less than the sony's and the
bose 700 and definitely cheaper than the
airpods max so these might be
interesting options if you're looking to
spend under 300 and honestly i've gotten
a lot of use out of these qc35s they're
great headphones and if none of these
existed i would be perfectly happy to
buy these again they're wonderful but in
terms of the absolute best choice i am
going with the airpods max again i have
a very apple-centric lifestyle aside
from my desktop where i've got wired
headphones so i'm wired into the
ecosystem and they work pretty much
perfectly because of that however the
price is really high compared to all the
other options and in the most important
categories comfort and sound quality and
noise cancellation quality they really
don't beat out the sony xm4 by that big
of a margin there is a margin there i do
think they are the absolute best but
these are in my opinion the best overall
value you get stellar noise cancellation
you get really good sound quality
especially if you like tighter and
bigger bass and you get great comfort
and better portability to boot so these
are the ones that i would probably
recommend to most people but you know
what you could do is try them all out
put them on your head and see how they
feel when you go about your work or you
go about reading or we go about maybe
learning some math science or computer
science on brilliant if you're somebody
who wants to improve your
problem-solving skills which hopefully
you are brilliant is a resource that you
absolutely should check out they've got
over 60 in-depth and interactive courses
that you can use to supplement your
reading material your class work videos
that you watch and to boost your
understanding of stem topics like
calculus like statistics like
probability number theory gravitational
physics classical mechanics even how
search engines work and how computer
algorithms work and recently brilliant
has upped the interactivity levels in
their courses even more for example in
this problem on figuring out how the
pythagorean theorem works you're
actually moving triangles around to
literally prove through spatial
reasoning how that theorem actually
works and this is so much better than
simple rote reading and memorization for
really locking in and understanding how
concepts work and then being able to
apply them in the real world so if you
want to join over 8 million learners
improve your abilities in math and in
science in a computer science improve
your problem-solving abilities which
apply to your career and your personal
pursuits and support this channel go
over to brilliant.org thomasfrank and
sign up to start learning today or use a
link in the description down below
beyond that if you haven't subscribed to
this channel already you can do so right
there or check out one more video on
this channel if you want to keep
watching thanks for watching this video
hopefully you found it helpful and i
will see you in the next one