hey what's up guys so today we are
tackling the age-old question is it ever
worth it to skip a class now you're
probably expecting me to say something
like always go to class eat your
vegetables I'm your dad because I have a
beard and I'm probably a bit older than
you but if I said that this video would
be 5 Seconds long and it probably
wouldn't be worth your click so instead
let's look at this a little bit more
objectively because this is a question
about skipping classes yes but it's also
a more general question about
opportunity costs so let's get this out
of the way right up front if you're in
high school I'm not going up against the
treny laws here you should go to class
just deal with it yeah it sucks
sometimes go to class if you're in high
school if you're in college though the
question becomes a little bit different
because in college now you're an adult
you can make your own choices and you
are choosing to pay money for more
education that is not legally required
of you and that's the big thing here
you're choosing to pay money for these
classes and every class you decide to
skip costs you money and in fact using
some simple math we can break down
exactly how much money you're throwing
away if you decide to skip a class so
let's say you're going to a university
like the one I went to which charges a
flat rate per semester instead of
charging per credit and let's also say
you're taking the standard 15 credit per
semester load which means you're going
to have five three credit classes Each
of which meet three times a week and an
average rate for semester tuition at
this point is about $4,000 for instate
public tuition so we're going to use
that here so breaking all that down your
cost per credit is
$266 67 which means each three credit
class ends up being about $800 and since
you're going to go to each of those
classes 48 times over the course of the
semester that means you end up with a
per class cost of
$16.67 meaning every single time you
decide to skip a class buy the straight
math you are throwing away $17 that you
already paid and you're no longer
getting the value for that example is
the simple math-based way to put it but
it breaks down when we consider a couple
of other things number one being not
every class is considered equal for one
you're going to have general education
classes which you don't care about as
much as your major classes and then for
each individual class you're going to
have certain sessions that are really
important because they're either tests
or the professor is giving away some
Vital Information you need for the tests
or on certain days you're just going to
have classes that go over like edge
cases or case studies or something you
really don't need to know about in the
future so each class is not going to be
worth as much as the other one and
furthermore you need to think about what
the actual value of these classes is
because the value isn't the time you
spend sitting in the seat the value
actually is the signaling value your
degree is going to give to potential
Employers in the future basically saying
this person is qualified to do the job
they want to do and also the Knowledge
and Skills that your classes and your
other college experiences are going to
give you which will help you get those
jobs as well basically your focus should
be on the value of each class as it
applies to your earning potential in the
future because make no mistake about it
college is a business decision it's an
investment on your part you're choosing
to spend thousands of dollars to sit in
classes and take tests and you're also
choosing to sacrifice many years of your
life that you could be otherwise working
and making money and this is where the
opportunity cost comes in you're
sacrificing one thing of value to gain
something else so the earnings you make
in the future from from college
eventually need to outpace what you
could have done otherwise this is the
financial Roi or return on investment
and yeah College gives you other
benefits you learn things you gain
experiences you meet new people but as
Matt Damon so eloquently put it in
Goodwill Hunting you could have gotten
all that for $150 and late fees at the
library so we're not going to get off
into the Weeds about all that stuff
we're just going to keep the focus on
the financial Roi here keeping that in
mind for any particular class what's
going to happen if you skip it well you
might miss some Vital Information that's
going to be really important on a test
test or maybe you miss a test altogether
and that's going to lead to a lower GPA
down the line you also might form a
negative perception in the mind of your
professor if you skip they going to
think you're like some sort of lazy
entitled Millennial and they're going to
shake their fist at you and tell you to
get off their lawn or maybe nothing's
going to happen who knows on the other
side of the equation though you have to
ask what am I gaining by skipping class
because money isn't the only cost
there's another cost to your classes and
that's your time yeah you're paying
tuition dollars but you're also using 45
minutes of your precious time every day
that you walk into that classroom so
what could you gain if you use that time
somewhere else if you're just feeling
lazy and you really don't want to go to
class I'm not going to sit here and tell
you that's a good decision because
frankly it's not you've already
committed resources and it's a waste of
your money and time to throw away those
resources because you don't feel like it
you probably know how I feel about not
feeling like it but if there's something
else that you can do instead of going to
class and it's valuable to you then that
changes the situation significantly for
example when I was a senior I actually
skipped about 3 days of class to go down
to Texas for an event called finish up
weekend this was basically an event
where lots of creative people came into
one space and they were all working as
hard as they possibly could to finish up
a lot of cool projects and they were
helping each other out and I met a lot
of cool people during that event people
who I still talk to today and I also
learned how to build iPhone apps in one
weekend through a course that somebody
pointed me to and for me that was way
way more valuable than a few computer
networking classes also during my
freshman year I skipped a few of my
general education classes that were just
not useful to me and some days I would
just schedule extra part-time work make
a little bit of extra money and I would
just keep my eye on the syllabus to make
sure I wasn't skipping any important
days though for those of you who are
thinking this is an endorsement of
skipping class and who want to follow my
footsteps here are a couple of caveats
number one I will say that after my
freshman year I made it a point to
always attend class and I never skipped
class again other than those times where
there was a really important thing to go
to like the Texas trip and number two I
really recommend getting to know your
professors introducing yourselves to
them at the beginning of the semester
and if you do this there's a higher
likelihood that your professor is going
to notice if you're gone so if you're
skipping because you're lazy or you just
want to sleep in you're not going to
make a good impression anyway those are
the facts that's all I've really got to
say about this and it really comes down
to your own uh values and priorities and
your own decision if you want to skip
class or not it's an opportunity cost
decision and you need to weigh the costs
and the benefits however if you're going
to skip class at least do it smart have
a friend who can fill you in on any
details or maybe let you copy the notes
and make sure you're staying as up to to
date on the out of class work as you can
so you're not falling behind you also
want to gauge the class to see if what's
on the test is kind of mirrored from the
textbook or if there's a lot of really
Vital Information you can only get in
lectures and lastly make sure you're
paying attention to the syllabus as much
as you can and write down any test dates
quiz dates or homework dates in your
calendar I mean you should be doing this
anyway but if you're going to skip it's
vitally important like doubly so though
I will say that it's not foolproof
because I've had times where the
professors had to change the location or
the time or the date of test and they've
only told the people who were in the
lecture hall so if you're going to skip
a class there's inherent risk built into
it no matter what you do no matter what
you do to mitigate that risk there's
going to be some there so just keep that
in mind and uh one last thing if you're
going to be going to a class where you
have to work on a group project don't
skip Don't Be a Jerk right there yeah
anyway guys thank you so much for
watching if you enjoyed this video give
it a like to support this Channel and if
you want to get new videos on being a
more effective student every single week
you can click that subscribe button
right down there I also wrote a free
book on how to earn better grades and if
you want to get a copy of it click the
picture of the book I'll send one to you
there's also an article for this video
with a little bit more detail and some
more examples I didn't put into the
video so click the orange button right
there to uh watch it and if you missed
last week's video we discussed the topic
of brain enhancing music and talked a
bit about whether or not it works duck
into the science a bit so check it out
if you missed it also I'm Tom frankley
on Instagram and Twitter if you'd like
to connect or you can leave a comment
down below thanks for watching