all right ladies it is this is the
100,000 subscriber bonus video so guys
thank you so much once again for 100,000
subscribers it's just absolutely insane
the Channel's come this far and I'm
hugely grateful for all the support and
I suppose thank you for 125,000
subscribers because I'm rather bad at
getting this out on time but I know last
time when I did a bonus video I asked
for some topic suggestions for the next
one and a lot of people wanted to see my
computer so what I'm going to do in this
video is give you a little tour of my
gaming and video editing computer here
show you some of the parts show you some
of the performance and what I can do and
then at the end of the video I'm going
to give you some recommendations for
resources if you happen to want to build
your own PC and I will just say right up
front you can build a really good gaming
PC for far far less than I paid for this
one so uh stay tuned for those resources
if you're interested all right so
starting out with the case I opted for
the enu Lux with this build now this is
a case that costs only about $100 so
it's quite a bit cheaper than some of
the other really popular full-size cases
out there but it still has all the same
room a lot of the expandability hard
drive Bay and customizable options that
a lot of those higher end cases have and
it doesn't look like Michael Bay
designed it so that's another plus the
CPU running the system is the Intel
i75820k which is a six core processor
and I decided on six cores over four
cores which are usually better for
gaming and cheaper because six cores
works better for video editing
applications cooling that processor is
the noctua NH u14s which is a huge
aftermarket heat sync but will come in
handy if I ever decide to overclock when
it came to the RAM for this build I
decided to get right on that future
train so it's running 32 GB of ddr4 RAM
and that might sound like Overkill but
it comes in handy because I do a lot of
work with After Effects and Premiere and
sometimes one of those programs alone
can use over 20 gigs for the graphics
card I've got the EVGA version of the
Nvidia gtx980 just one because I'm not
Super Saiyan yet but maybe two in the
future and to round out the main
components I've got a 750 W power supply
which is probably too much for this
build but at least some flexibility for
added components in the future now ever
since I've gotten into video editing
I've had to get really serious about
storage for this build I decided to go
with two solid state drives in addition
to a regular hard drive and with this
case it actually keeps the solid state
drives on the back and this is a huge
mess back here you can see one is
mounted here and one is mounted here
this one is a Samsung Pro drive this is
one of their fastest models and I keep
it for my boot drive it's 256 GB and I
put all my programs on there and windows
as well and then down here is one of
Samsung's Evo ssds which are a little
bit slower but still pretty fast in this
I keep my Dropbox files on and also the
cash files for both Premier and after
effects additionally on the other side
like I said I've got a regular 2 TB hard
drive and that is quickly filling up so
I'm going to have to add more drivve in
the future now with this Hardware I can
run new games like The Witcher 3 without
any problems at Max settings but that's
not the reason I got the computer though
it is a nice bonus the real reason I got
the computer is for high performance
blogging high
performance just kidding the real reason
I bought this computer is so I could run
after effects better because after
effects animations are extremely
demanding on a system both to preview
and to render out finally and to give
you an example I want to show you the
Mark Twain quote animation from the last
video so as you can see there's this uh
this light object here over here and if
I turn that off we get a little bit
different lighting and there's a camera
that changes their perspective as you
can see the entire thing is 3D if I turn
it back on you can see that and all
these things actually move so if I turn
the light back
on I actually have the light animating
and moving to cast some different moving
Shadows on the animation as you can see
even with this Hardware the animation
doesn't update perfectly as I'm dragging
the timeline cursor it still struggles
to keep up because there's just a ton of
stuff going on now I learned with this
video that I should apply all my
lighting effects after I do the
animating so I took way longer than I
needed to on that last video but still
the hardware definitely helps make these
animations all right guys well I hope
you enjoyed this video now if you're
interested in building your own computer
either now or at some point in the
future I have a couple of
recommendations for resources that you
should definitely check out one of them
being the build a PC subreddit which has
lots of PC builders that can answer your
questions as well as a Wiki with lots of
useful information you can read up on
and also there's a site called PC part
picker which will allow you to build
your own custom PC and print out a list
of the parts but also shows you the
cheapest place online to buy each one
lastly there's a YouTube channel I'm a
pretty huge fan of called lonus Tech
tips and they often do PC build videos
will they'll set a certain budget and
see what they can build while staying
under it so that might be a useful
resource as well that is it for this
video so the Nerds among you may now go
into the comments and tell me why my
build is terrible and for the rest of
you the next Milestone video will
probably come at a million subscribers
if the channel ever gets there and
beyond that I'm going to start doing
bonus videos basically whenever I feel
like it that way I'm not pressured to do
it at a certain Milestone each time but
rest assured they will be coming in the
future so if you have ideas for future
bonus videos or awkward inappropriate
questions about my life you can leave
them down in the comments and I will
possibly do a video on them in the
future other than that I will see you in
the next video thanks for watching