every day for about the past three
months I have been replacing either my
breakfast or my lunch with one of these
smoothies it takes me literally less
than five minutes to make this including
cleanup it's super nutritious and
nutritionally complete and it actually
tastes pretty good and ever since I
posted about it on my Instagram a couple
of months ago people have been asking me
to go through the process of making it
and asking me what's in it so that is
what I want to do for you guys today now
you might be thinking to yourself this
isn't a nutrition channel this is a
channel about how to do better in school
and how to be more productive so what's
a video like this doing on the channel
and you're right I don't talk a whole
lot about nutrition but I would like to
change that because this is a channel
about enhancing your cognitive
performance and becoming more productive
and I think the foundational level of
doing both those things is improving
your health and when it comes to
improving your health there's kind of a
trifecta of sorts you have your sleep
your exercise and your nutrition and on
this channel we've talked a good bit
about sleep we've talked about how to
get up early in the morning if that's
what you want to do we've talked about
how to get to bed on time consistently
and we've also talked about how to
improve the quality of your sleep we've
also done a video or two about how to
build an exercise routine and to become
more fit we haven't done a whole lot
about nutrition and I'd like to start
changing that now when it comes to
nutrition I am an anti perfectionist I'm
a lot more concerned with building a
consistent routine that you're actually
going to stick to rather than building
the perfect diet and I'm also looking
for ways to on a consistent basis cut
down the time and energy and effort
required to follow a good diet and as I
found over the past few months making a
smoothie every morning is a great way to
do that so without further ado I'm gonna
guide you through the process of making
it and then we'll come back here to
answer a few quick questions about it
welcome to my kitchen there are many
like it but this one is mine here we
have all the ingredients I'll just
quickly go through them and they were
gonna make this so we got back here some
strawberries I have a spinach and kale
mix got some blueberries which we were
almost out of raspberries blackberries
also flax seed and chia seeds these both
have a lot of nutrients in them I'll
talk a little bit about that later
silk unsweetened vanilla almond milk got
your plain old gold standard optimum
nutrition whey protein get that no no to
get swole right natural Jif peanut
butter I know I could do like actual
natural peanut butter but I like this
stuff quite a bit we got our Quaker Oats
last but not least good old bananas so
like I said in the intro this does not
take very long to make so let's go ahead
and make it and the blender that I'm
using to make this guy is the
nutribullet 900 series if you have a
regular blender at home that's gonna do
just fine
the main benefit of a nutribullet in my
opinion is that you can drink right out
of the like serving sized shaker cup
here which I do and that require that
really reduces the cleanup that I need
to do afterwards but if you have a
regular blender and you wanted us to
dump it into a yeti Rambler or a glass
or whatever you have laying around then
no need to buy this thing and I'm
probably gonna have to replace it in the
future anyway because I put a lot of
ingredients in my shake alright so the
first thing I always do get myself a
spoon and do what I think is roughly a
cup of the spinach and kale mix so I
just kind of spoon it in until it's like
roughly at a point that looks pretty
good it's around the cups worth so about
that much you could do a lot less this
is how much I do and then we'll move on
to the strawberries I know you can open
it from the bottom it's kind of like
life hack I've written about before or
read about but I just do this and it
works pretty well too this is not very
ripe but it will work and the nice thing
is like if you have ingredients that
aren't perfectly ripe or you have things
that don't necessarily taste amazing on
their own they're pretty good in the
smoothie so I do about half of a small
to medium sized banana
and then strawberries next usually four
to five strawberries there are a big
volume items so I don't try to go
overboard on those guys and then we'll
do all the berries so blackberries
generally about four to five of those
raspberries pretty much the same story
and finally our blueberries so we have a
fruit base we have the veggies now let's
do the rest of it I like to do a single
serving of flaxseed which is two
tablespoons the one thing I'll warn you
about is that flax is high in fiber and
a lot of people don't get enough fiber
and if you introduce a whole ton of
fiber into your diet really really
quickly you're gonna have some
gastrointestinal difficulties so maybe
start with like half a tablespoon of
this stuff and work your way up slowly
I've gotten to the point where I'm
pretty used to it chia seeds I don't
think there's as much of a warning I
have to put on these guys so I usually
do two tablespoons of these as well both
the flax and the Chia contain omega-3
fatty acids they contain a lot of
vitamin it's and minerals and they also
are decently calorie dense and also add
some protein to the shake so if you're
an athlete or you like to workout and
you're trying to put on some weight or
gain some muscle they're pretty good
sources of protein and calories or
calories I also put in Quaker Oats I
don't really think that there's a whole
lot of other benefits to the oats that
you couldn't get from other ingredients
but again I'm trying to make this like a
true meal replacement and as somebody
gave me a lot of energy when I go to the
gym so I will do just like four
tablespoons of oats in there that is
only half a serving so it adds maybe 75
calories but you can't get the shaker
cup too full and some not naming names
but some would believe that I already
make it oh but hey so with the
nutribullet there is as my camera woman
is explaining there's a max line on the
cup here and I'm using the bigger cup
because I'm a monster and eat a thousand
calorie shake every morning you want to
fill it up to the max line with liquid
you can do all kinds of liquids you
could do regular milk you could do
almond milk you could do soy milk give
water I like doing the almond milk I
found that it tastes really good it is
not as high calorie or sugar dense as a
regular milk and it still tastes really
good and then this is the real calorie
Packer here so if you wanted to make a
lower calorie shake you would probably
just want to leave out the peanut butter
or do a lot less of it but again it's
almost like a mass gainer for me so I
will do probably about two servings of
the peanut butter in there and I love
peanut butter this is the guilty
pleasure in here and I guess maybe the
flavored protein shake is too but it's
so good and finally we got our standard
optimum nutrition whey protein this is
the vanilla ice cream flavor and I'll
just do a single serving of that plop it
in and we are good to go you want to
make sure that your lid which is also
the blades is on real tight and then it
would probably be a good idea if I plug
the blender in now this is really loud
but luckily I have the magic of editing
so it won't be for you
[Music]
probably good oh yes
check out our delicious cup of pinkish
grayish slop there it is I don't have to
put it in a cup because this is
literally a cup I think it's best to
drink it through a straw and because
plastic straws are horribly bad if the
environment and you throw in why all the
time I got just some glass straws from
Amazon
there are also stainless steel straws
but I've heard that those can get a lot
colder and be bad for sensitive teeth so
I got the glass ones I think they're a
bit thicker they don't transfer that
cold quite as much could be bro science
but these work for me so bon appetit my
brands let's answer a few questions
about the smoothie that the whole
process of making it probably didn't
answer first and foremost how does it
taste I actually think that this
smoothie tastes really freaking good
especially given the fact that it has a
ton of ingredients in it and I kind of
almost feel like I hit upon a really
good recipe really early on because I
didn't have to do a whole lot of
experimentation with this and compared
to a lot of the smoothies I've gotten
from places like Jamba Juice and like
grocery stores that make smoothies I
actually like the taste of this one
better it's probably a lot of the fruit
mixed with the peanut butter you kind of
can't go wrong with that combination but
the fact that it tastes really good and
it tastes good enough for me to look
forward to drinking every single morning
is a real benefit because it's
nutritionally complete but it's not
something that I dread in the morning
now of course we have to answer the
question could you make it healthier yes
of course you could I'm sure they're
gonna be plenty of people down in the
comments suggesting changes or telling
me that I am completely idiotic for
including ingredient X or ingredient
line here but yeah you could totally
make it healthier and if this is
something you're gonna start doing
making smoothies in the morning I would
encourage you to experiment with
different ingredients and to try to make
it healthier to try to vary it up from
time to time now to get specific the
peanut butter that I put in my smoothie
is number one peanut butter and peanuts
aren't like the healthiest nut out there
and also it's Jif peanut butter so
there's a little bit of added sugar in
there so if you wanted to make things
even healthier you could go to
completely raw peanut butter
really just peanuts and salt or you
could switch it out for something like
an almond butter you could also instead
of using a flavored protein use a non
flavored protein just like pure whey
protein or you can go to a vegan protein
or you could use a different protein
source altogether and of course you
could change up the fruit to vegetable
rice you putting more greens in there
and less fruit if you wanted to lower
the sugar content even more but again
and I really want to emphasize this
sustainability is the name of the game
I'm not aiming for perfection here I'm
aiming for something that's a lot better
than I would otherwise eat but that I
really want to eat on a daily basis so
I'm consistent in my good diet now
because some of you may be curious I do
want to dig a little bit into the actual
nutritional profile of this movie now I
don't claim to be an expert here and
there are probably ingredients in
vitamins and minerals that aren't listed
on the nutritional facts of each
ingredient but I did do a little bit of
research by looking at the nutrition
labels for the things that had them and
then using a site called Fooducate calm
to look up the nutrition content of the
fruit and vegetables that didn't have
labels on the packaging and I came up
with some data and I'm gonna have a link
to a Google sheet that I created in the
description below
which I will start fleshing out in the
future to add different smoothie recipes
to over time so you may want to bookmark
it though I do want to mention that
drinking one of these no matter what you
put in it is not a panacea you also need
to worry about the other parts of your
diet so if you're just thinking that you
can create a nutritionally complete
smoothie every single day and then eat
nothing but Nabisco crackers and pizza
rolls for the rest of your meals then
you may want to rethink that plan and on
that note I would love to explore
different nutritional ideas in the
future particularly ideas that cut down
again on the time and energy required so
I want to dig into things like batch
cooking like slow cooker cooking things
like that things that give you meals you
can just put in the fridge and have for
days on end instead of having to cook
every single night and I would love to
hear your ideas on that front so
definitely leave some ideas down in the
comments below for videos that I should
do on the nutritional front in the
future but until then if you haven't
tried making a smoothie like this before
definitely give it a try again it's
super quick to do the cleanup is minimal
and once I've made it in the morning
it's really easy to just sit down and
read a book or watch a video or do
something that helps me learn something
new and while we're on the subject of
learning new things if you enjoy my
channel and you're looking for more
educational content here on YouTube you
may also want to check out the cheddar
channel I just finished watching one of
their videos on how one bad business
decision completely tanked Sega's
hardware division back in 1990s and I
found that to be a really fascinating
video and beyond that they have lots of
videos on topics like business and
technology without all the boring parts
so definitely go check out that video by
clicking the link in the description
down below if you liked that consider
checking out some of their other videos
and subscribing to their Channel I want
to give a big thanks to cheder for
sponsoring this video and being a
supporter of my channel and as always
guys thank you so much for watching if
you like this video definitely give it a
thumbs up and I would love to hear your
recipe modifications to my smoothie and
the comments below if you do happen to
change things up otherwise you can
subscribe to this channel to get new
videos every single week right there or
click right there to get a free copy of
my book on how to earn better grades
thanks again for watching and I will see
you in next week's video