hey what is up guys so in today's video
we're going to be covering thirteen
effective study tips that are all backed
by science which you can find linked in
description down below later on if you
are curious now I'm doing this video
right now because we are just about into
final exam season but if you're coming
into this video later on and realize
that these tips aren't just useful for
exam review they're general learning
tips so if you want to study less if you
want to spend less time reviewing if you
want to learn more effectively than pay
attention tip number one space out your
review sessions so in the field of
cognitive science there is this
phenomenon known as the spacing effect
which describes how we actually learned
better if we try to recall material
close to the point at which we are about
to forget it essentially forgetting is a
crucial part of the learning process
much like rest is a crucial counterpart
to strength training if you want to get
physically stronger so to take advantage
of the spacing effect you want to study
with what's called a space - repetition
which involves adding gaps of time
between your study or practice sessions
that get progressively longer and for
most types of information that you're
gonna find on a test like
question-answer pairs vocab terms really
anything that can fit on a flashcard you
can actually get very specific about
these gaps of time by using spaced
repetition apps which include donkey
Quizlet and duolingo z' tiny cards you
can even do this with paper flashcards
by using something called the lightener
system which i details in a previous
video that'll have length and
description it down below now for
everything else that doesn't fit on a
flashcard just try to space out your
practice sessions intelligently instead
of trying to practice all in one session
or following a very rigid timetable and
note that this principle works for skill
practice as well so if you practice one
specific skill on Monday then maybe wait
until Wednesday or Thursday to practice
that particular skill again and in the
meantime on Tuesday practice something
else that's related tip number two is to
use the Pomodoro Technique so research
has found that studying works best when
we do it in short hyper focused bursts
rather than one long drawn-out session
because at a certain point your focus
and your attention really start to wane
and you kind of start wasting your time
the problem with this approach though is
you'd probably know well is that you
have to motivate yourself to start each
and every one of these sessions and
after you do a few well maybe that
motivation has waned a bit so that is
exactly where the Pomodoro Technique
comes in it is a device that helps you
to keep that motivation high and
actually helps you to get into
each session so to use it you simply set
a timer for 25 minutes and pick one task
to work on and it's very important to
actually set a timer don't just set it
in your head use a real timer because
that creates an external motivator
during that 25 minutes work only on the
task you chosen don't switch to anything
else and if something distracts you
quickly write it down so you can either
take care of it later on if you need to
or so you can figure out how to prevent
it from distracting you in the future
and then get back to work now once that
25 minute timer goes off you are
presented with a choice if you feel that
you're in the zone if you feel like
you're still productive then keep
working until you feel your motivation
focus start to wane otherwise take a
five-minute break
go for a walk get some water and then
start a new session now if you don't
want to use a physical timer for this
process then there are plenty of
websites and apps out there that you can
use as a substitute including tomato
timer comm and tide which is my personal
favorite from a door app and is what I
use whenever I do my own sessions tip
number three is to create your own
quizzes out of your study materials and
then take them later on and this is
called the quiz and recall method
essentially you want to take all of your
study materials your study guy if you've
been given one your notes may be the
slides from the class or your textbook
readings specifically the subheadings
and the bolt lists vocab terms and the
review questions at the end of the
chapter if you have them and create your
own quizzes out of them essentially act
like you're your teacher then a couple
of days later go and take those quizzes
this practice testing method is an
active method of learning and it's a lot
more effective than just passively going
over the material tip number four which
is pretty related is to work lots and
lots of problems the more you can
practice the more mastery you're going
to achieve and the more difficult these
problems are the better off as well it's
like I'll just be high each cheek sent
me how you put it this way the best
moments usually occur when a person's
body or mind is stretched to its limits
in a voluntary effort to accomplish
something difficult and worthwhile just
like the muscles in your body grow
stronger after being exposed to a
stressful challenge your mind becomes
more capable every single time you
challenge it to solve a tough problem so
the next time you're tempted to study by
just letting your eyes glaze over your
notes or a slide deck remind yourself
that this is basically the mental
equivalent of showing up at the gym and
using nothing but five pound weights you
have to stretch yourself a little bit
further counterpoint to that though and
tip number five when you find yourself
stuck on a tough problem try working a
simple one that you
is only one of the concepts from the
original this is because the difficulty
in many tough problems comes from the
combination of several different
concepts or ideas that you haven't yet
mastered so when you find yourself stuck
for this reason then go and find or
construct a similar problem that only
uses one of the concepts from the
original master that and then you can
move back to that original and you'll
probably have a much easier time getting
done tip number six is to use mnemonics
and mnemonic is basically a mental
device that binds two different pieces
of information together in a sort of
roundabout way your brain more naturally
latches on to this could include rhymes
acronyms visual devices or even stories
and a great example of that latter
device is one akane which is web app
that helps you learn japanese kanji it
does this by creating ridiculous stories
that bind the way each kanji is
pronounced aloud to the way that it's
written and in addition to all those
devices you can also try to find a way
to turn the information you're studying
into a song or find a way to make it
rhythmically interesting for example the
main reason that I can remember the date
of the Pearl Harbor attacks is the very
specific way that Franklin D Roosevelt
said it in his speech about the attacks
the Samba 7 1941 I usually have a pretty
difficult time pulling it up directly
but I can always remember if I first go
to that speech in my memory and that
line in that speech is actually the
first line of the intro to hardcore
history which is an incredibly
entertaining podcast that has gotten me
very interested in many different eras
of history and speaking of interest
tip number seven on our list is to find
a way to get more interested in your
topic and this is because your emotional
state your emotional attachment to a
topic how much you care about it these
are all very important and how well
you're going to retain the information
when you're learning about it so you
want to find a way to get more
interested now my favorite way to do
this is to find a way to immerse myself
in the topic that's a little bit more
fun or interesting than your standard
textbook readings or lecture slides this
could be a podcast it could be a
documentary
it could be visiting a museum it can
even be a video game as long as that
video game ties back to your topic it
makes you care more about it tip number
eight is to regularly switch between
different types of problems and concepts
while you're studying this is a concept
called
inter lady and helps combat a problem
known as
we're learning we basically hammered
away at one specific concept a problem
for so long but you really kind of start
wasting your time and once again the
Hwanhee County app provides us with a
great example of how to do this well
because when you're reviewing the app is
constantly switching between questions
about radical and kanji meetings about
vocabulary terms and about how to
pronounce specific kanji so you're
constantly being asked to recall what
you've learned in different ways so when
you're studying for a test you're doing
a homework assignment you can basically
replicate this by switching between
concepts or different sections of a
problem set at regular intervals tip
number nine is to do at least one study
session in the classroom where you're
going to be tested or a very similar
classroom if you can and this tip
leverages what is called a context
dependent memory research and cognitive
sciences found that people are better
able to recall information when they are
present in the same environment in which
it was encoded so if you learn in the
classroom or at least spend some time
with viewing in the classroom then when
you're sitting in that same classroom
for the test you're gonna have an easier
time remembering what you study
additionally if you can study in the
classroom then that makes it a more
familiar place and when you're taking
the test being in a familiar place can
actually cut down on test anxiety as
well that brings us to tip number 10
which is to go for a walk after a long
study session so when you're thinking
your brain uses two different types of
primary neural networks what are called
highly attentive States and then resting
state networks and crucially both of
these types of networks are very
important for learning effectively in
the book Emine for numbers dr. Barbara
Oakley labels the use of these two
networks as the focused and diffuse
modes of thinking respectively and notes
that it's important to switch between
them in order to encode new material now
using the focused mode is pretty
straightforward as it's activated
anytime you actively work on a problem
so to get over into the diffused mode
you just need to step away from that
problem for a bit and let your brain
process it in the background and a great
way to do that while also getting some
exercise which is in itself a great way
to enhance your learning and there's an
entire book on that is to go outside and
go for a quick walk tip number 11 is to
do at least a few of your review
sessions in a group working in a group
can not only expose you to new ideas and
let you come to the problems from a
different angle but it also prevents you
from getting stuck on any one problem
too long the caveat here is that you
shouldn't do all of your work in groups
because it can get to the point where
you start relying on other people to
find the answers for you and you're not
actually solving them for yourself it's
very easy to confuse recognition of the
right path to the answer given to you by
someone else with actual mastery of the
materials so you have to strike an
optimal balance between individual
problem solving time and group work tip
number 12 is to find these study sounds
that work the best for you and I'm very
specifically using the term sounds here
because ambient noises music and silence
can fall work well for studying and make
you more productive it just depends on
what kind of person you are now if you
want to go the route of ambient noises a
great starting resource is noisy which
actually allows you to mix different
sounds together to create your own
custom soundscape but I really like
doing that or you keep things simple by
going with the classic rainy mood for
rain sounds or coffee tivity which is a
website that creates coffee shop
ambience and for music you might wanna
start with my Sunday study post over on
Spotify or my ultimate study music
playlist here on YouTube both of which
have a lot of similarities but also some
key differences and if you do find a
song that you really like because they
are pretty eclectic a good way to find
more music like that would be to use
Spotify as a radio function or to just
find the album's songs from and put that
on now I do want to mention that the
science behind the link between music
and productivity is pretty money right
now there's a lot of research that's
been done but very few concrete
conclusions so this is an area that
really warrants personal experimentation
that being said I will still be linked
in to some resources in the description
so you can dig in and do some reading on
what exists right now if you're curious
and that brings us to tip number 13
which is to protect your sleep now I
know this seems completely obvious but I
also know from personal experience that
sleep seems to be the thing that we most
readily sacrifice when we're dealing
with a looming deadline and this is a
really detrimental choice that we make
because sleep is crucial for keeping
your brain at its optimal levels and
it's especially important for retaining
the information that you've learned and
being able to call it on tests as the
Harvard Medical School puts at when we
are sleep-deprived our focus attention
and vigilance drift making it more
difficult to receive information without
adequate sleep and rest overworked
neurons can no longer function to
coordinate information properly and we
lose our ability to access previously
learned information so no matter how
tight your deadlines are respect your
body's need for
sleeeeep make sure you're getting enough
sleep and also make sure you are keeping
a consistent sleep schedule as well now
all the tips on this list are indeed
useful but I do want to make a final
note that it is not necessary to try to
implement them all at once if you try
you would probably just find yourself
overwhelmed so instead just pick one
area that you know you can improve upon
and focus on that during your next study
session eventually that will become
ingrained as a habit and you can move on
to something else and if you're not sure
where to start or if you often find
yourself overwhelmed with huge lists of
tips or just the sheer amount of options
you have available to you then you might
want to follow this video up by going
and taking Brian sorvino's excellent
course on how to strategically set
priorities you'll find Brian's course
over on Skillshare alongside more than
27,000 other classes that can help to
boost your skills and a ton of different
areas including graphic design video
production digital animation marketing
and lots lots more all skill shares
classes embrace the principle of active
learning and they all include a project
often with sample files that you can
download which can help you to start
using what you're learning each class
also has a discussion section so you can
ask questions and get feedback from both
the teacher and the other students as
well and best of all Skillshare is
really affordable their annual plan is
less than ten bucks a month and in case
you haven't heard about it already that
subscription also gives you access to my
hour-long productivity systems course so
if you want to start boosting your
skills then sign up at a link in
description down below and if you're one
of the first 500 people to do so you're
gonna get a two month free trial with
unlimited learning on the platform big
thanks goes out to Skillshare for
sponsoring this video and being a big
supporter of my channel and as always
thank you guys so much for watching as
well hopefully you enjoyed this video
and if you did maybe consider hitting
that like button and getting subscribed
right there I will also have a lot more
stuff in the description so if you want
to jump off from this video to something
more detail I've got many other videos
you might want to check out otherwise
you can click right there to get a free
copy of my book on how to earn better
grades find one more video on this
channel or listen to our latest podcast
episode over here thanks again for
watching and I will see you in the next
one