this video is sponsored by
curiositystream you can watch a
full-length companion video to this one
when you sign up for the nebula and
curiosity stream bundle linked below hey
what's going on friends so in this video
we are talking about something that i
haven't covered on this channel in quite
some time which is personal finance
specifically in this video we are going
to talk about the single habit that more
than any other allowed me to save up
around 300 000 in my various investment
accounts over the last 10 or so years
since i started investing money back in
college now that number on screen right
there is not intended to be a flex of
any kind and it's also very much not
intended to be something you should be
comparing your own financial situation
against the only reason i am putting
that number on screen right now is to
give a specific and concrete example of
just how powerful the concept and the
habit that we're going to talk about
today is and that habit is called
financial automation or automating your
finances this is something i talked
about in my recent video on seven books
everyone in their 20s should read and i
had a few people asking me to explain it
in a bit more detail so that is what i'm
doing in this video so essentially
automating your finances means first
identifying the habits and the actions
that you need to take to meet your
financial goals be it buying a house or
getting out of student debt or saving
for retirement and then taking those
actions and handing a lot of them off to
a robot or to be more accurate to a
computer or a piece of software or
website that takes care of these actions
for you so in this video i'm going to
teach you exactly why financial
automation is so powerful why i practice
it in almost every area of my life where
i can do it and we're going to go
through specifically how i automate my
own finances in two key areas bill
automation and investment automation so
first let's start with the why why do
you want to go through all the trouble
of setting up financial automations well
there are a couple of key benefits here
number one you get access to a safety
net and to huge peace of mind because
when you automate your finances you will
never miss a credit card payment you
will never miss a bill payment if
there's something you are supposed to
pay it is going to get paid even if
you're on vacation or you forgot to do
it or i don't know for some reason
you're a sentient bear watching this
video and you're going to go hibernate
for the winter and sleep for three
months doesn't matter your stuff is
getting paid additionally when you
automate your savings and your
investments your consistency goes way
way up and as a result you're almost
certainly going to invest and save a lot
more over the course of your life in
fact that is the reason i've been able
to save more than 300 000 over the past
10 years back when i was a sophomore in
college i opened my very first
investment account over at vanguard and
because i had read about financial
automation in that book that i
recommended in a very recent video of
mine your money the missing manual by jd
roth i set up an automatic deposit from
my bank account to that investment
account every single month now at the
time it was very small i think i started
out with 50 bucks a month going in there
just a little bit of money for my
part-time job being invested but over
time i increased those amounts and as i
got into my career they became
significantly larger and the most
important thing is that they were
happening every single month and this
consistency can be incredibly powerful
and i want to give you just a small
example of that say i would have started
investing when i was a baby back in 1991
super smart baby thomas and i was
putting 500 a month into essentially the
entire stock market an index fund that
tracks the entire stock market that's
500 a month which adds up to 6 000 a
year or 180 000 over the course of the
last 30 years from 1991 to 2021 but if
they had done that consistently and they
never took any money out of the market
in the meantime their money today would
be worth 1.6
million dollars imagine saving 180 000
and turning into 1.6 million it sounds
crazy but it's actually something that
can be done quite reasonably by
leveraging compound interest and by
being consistent in your savings and
think about the person who is doing this
manually if they're going in every
single month and making the decision to
invest in the market or to move money
from their checking to their savings
account that's 12 times a year they have
to go in and manually do that which
means that they are potentially setting
themselves up for failure every single
time they might forget they might be on
vacation or they might justify to
themselves that they need to spend the
money on something else this time and
hey i'm just going to get back onto it
next time i totally swear man that's one
month they missed the robot certainly
wouldn't miss so for these reasons i
think learning to automate your finances
is one of the most important personal
finance habits that you can learn but
there is at least one preliminary step
that you should understand and make sure
you have taken before you start doing it
especially when we're talking about
investing and that is establishing what
is called a cash buffer and to explain
that i actually want to show you
something i've been developing in my
spare time called the personal finance
tech tree so i grew up playing games
like civilization where they had these
tech trees you had to learn things like
metallurgy before you could learn
ballistics things like that and i've
always thought about my personal finance
journey in a certain way that's kind of
similar to that i have to do certain
things either learn certain things or
hit certain financial milestones before
i can move on to the next thing so i've
been thinking to myself could i create a
sort of actual map for these different
financial milestones and i've been
working on this in a tool called
whimsical that i'm going to show you
here so basically i have these little
mapped out paths here for things like
savings regular income installment loans
and basic budgeting but the specific
part that i want to zoom in on right now
is the one month cash buffer this is
what i think you should establish before
you start automating your finances and
we can see here that this leads to first
a three month cash buffer and then to
the start of your investing journey but
the real reason you want to make sure
you have a one month cash buffer is if
you are automating your investments you
are automating bill payments you're
automating deposits from your bank
account into maybe an investment account
or a savings account and you don't want
those automations to draw your bank
account down below zero so essentially a
one month cash buffer is a buffer of
cash for one month's expenses beyond
what you're going to spend this month
and when you've established that in your
bank account you can be sure that your
current expenses your bills your
investments your savings your debt
payments are never going to draw your
bank account down to a negative balance
once you've hit that milestone i think
it's a very good idea to start looking
at how you can automate different parts
of your financial life so let's now talk
about how i automate the bill payments
in my life basically anything that is a
regular monthly payment i have on auto
pay if i can do it so that includes my
mortgage that included my rent when i
was paying rent for an apartment that
includes my utilities payments so
internet gas electric uh water and that
includes every credit card that i have
and to go on a bit of a tangent about
credit cards for a second i do not use
credit cards as credit cards so your
credit card gives you access to credit
which you might even be able to tap even
if you don't have that much money on
hand i do not view credit cards that way
for me a credit card is simply a
pass-through vehicle for money that i
already have and i was already going to
spend i simply use credit cards to get
access to airline points and different
perks and to build my credit score over
time and i always always always always
pay off my credit cards balance in full
every single month i have never once
paid a cent of interest to the credit
card companies and i think that is a
goal that all of us should aspire to the
credit industry calls people like us
deadbeats because we don't make the
credit card companies a whole lot of
money and i think everyone should aspire
to be a deadbeat that being said maybe
you have some credit card debt right now
that you can't pay off in full but what
you should at least do is what i do go
into your credit card and enable auto
pay at the very least for the minimum
payment and the huge reason for this is
that your credit score is determined by
several different factors but one of the
biggest is your percentage of on-time
payments and even one missed payment can
be a huge ding to your credit score so i
always auto pay my credit cards because
it is a safety net even if i get knocked
out for two months for some reason or i
get lost in the jungle for some reason
my credit card is going to get paid
because the auto payment is set up the
other area where i use financial
automation in my life is with my savings
and my investments so i have some
automatic rules with my bank account to
have money transferred from my checking
to my savings every single month and
then i have some different investments
that are automatically funded and
deposited every single month as well the
main one is my 401k through my company
that money goes into the 401k account
before i even pay myself my payroll and
if you work for a company that offers a
401k it's a very good idea to do this
especially if they offer matching
because that's essentially free money
and then i also have a few different
taxable investing accounts basically
non-retirement accounts that i
automatically invest into as well now
there are some good habits to practice
in addition to financial automation that
are going to make sure you don't run
into problems in the future and i think
the first one is to put bill due dates
on your calendar you at least want to
know when your bills are going to be
charged even if they are automatically
being taken out of your account you
basically want to stay on top of your
finances and the second big habit
actually kind of goes into the exact
same idea here it's to do what's called
a monthly review of your finances
essentially the robots are taking the
actions for me but every single month
i'm coming in and i'm staying on top of
all of my accounts i'm making sure i
know where all my accounts are how much
money i have and overall i'm making sure
that i have a clear picture of my
personal financial health i think only a
fool sets up machines and then doesn't
check up on them every once in a while
so by checking up am i making sure i
know everything that's going on i
prevent myself from getting blindsided
in fact i take this one step further i
don't just check over my balances i
actually have a custom built spreadsheet
that i made to do some financial
planning to actually look over my
average income my average expenses my
average savings and investing goals and
i even have formulas that will show me
how much roughly i'm going to pay in
taxes what my take-home pay is going to
be and my percentage is split between
how much money i'm spending on my car my
housing how much i'm saving and how much
i'm investing i even turn this into a
completely free template that anybody
else can download and use but what i
haven't done up until this point is
actually make a video showing exactly
how i use it and how it works so i have
finally done that i've made a complete
and full length companion video to this
video going into how i use this template
and how i plan out my financial
decisions and i've uploaded it to nebula
in case you haven't heard nebula is a
streaming service built by both myself
and a ton of other fantastic educational
creators and on nebula i upload my
videos that you see here on youtube both
early and completely free of ads like
this one it's also a place where we can
experiment with content that might not
work very well on youtube such as oh i
don't know a long and in-depth video on
my budgeting strategy and there's a ton
of other great exclusive content on
nebula as well from a ton of creators
that i personally love my friend ali
abdal for example has a series called
workflow where he goes in depth into the
tools and workflows that he actually
uses in his business and in his work and
real life lore one of my absolute
favorite channels that i have been
absolutely binging lately has a series
called modern conflicts on nebula it is
just as long and high quality as his
normal videos but it covers some more
controversial topics like the history of
the north korean south korean war things
like that that would almost certainly
get demonetized on youtube so he puts
that on nebula and i have been
absolutely loving that series but the
best part about nebula is that it comes
bundled with curiosity stream which has
thousands of high quality documentaries
that you can stream from almost anywhere
and right now when you sign up for the
curiosity stream in nebula bundle over
at curiositystream.com thomas you can
actually get 42 off of the yearly annual
price you can literally get nebula and
curiosity stream for a full year for
less than 12 it is seriously the best
deal you are going to find in streaming
and once you do have access to curiosity
stream one documentary that i've been
enjoying recently that i'd like to
recommend to you is called the ascent of
money which tracks the development of
money and goes into the history of it
it's a really interesting series so i
think you're really going to enjoy it
and beyond that there are thousands of
other documentaries covering economics
science technology nature and tons of
other topics that can expand your
knowledge of the world so to get access
to all those great documentaries on
curiosity stream as well as nebula with
all my early and ad-free videos and all
those exclusive videos on nebula you can
go over to curiositystream.com
thomas or click the link on screen right
there to sign up thanks as always for
watching hopefully you found this video
helpful hopefully you learned something
new and if you did hitting that like
button for the algorithm would be much
appreciated thanks again for watching
and i will see you in the next one