Hello friends a new semester is upon us
and in this quick video I want to give
you a few things that you can do to make
sure that semester goes smoothly and one
of the biggest things I want to focus on
in this video is setting yourself up to
not burn out and lose motivation as the
semester goes on because I know when a
new semester comes Upon Us you're full
of a lot of motivation right you're full
of all this like new refreshed energy
and you really want to do well in all
your classes and get involved and hang
out with people and do all that stuff
and as the semester goes on you start to
lose that motivation right things just
pile on and due dates start to pile up
and your motivation starts to wne so I
want to talk about some things you can
do to make sure that doesn't happen or
at least to let you mitigate those
effects and uh not let them make you
lose steam but first I want to talk
about just the changing of habits so in
Charles Dick's book The Power of Habit
which I have read and highly recommend
he talks about how people are apt to
change their set patterns their regular
behaviors more often during large Life
Changes such as moving to a new house or
becoming a parent or getting married
people who get married or move to a new
house are really apt to change the brand
of coffee they drink or the cereal they
eat and the book mentions that people
going through these big life changes are
actually more vulnerable to marketers
because of these huge upheavals in their
life now this is great information for
marketers maybe not such great
information for you if you want to be a
Discerning Shopper but it is good
information for you if you want to
change your own habits because just just
as those habits are vulnerable to
marketers they're also vulnerable to
intervention on your own part right so a
new semester is the perfect time to look
at your habits and see what changes you
can make see what systems you can build
to become more efficient and effective
as the semester goes on so I want to
talk about a couple of things that can
really help you out in that regard but
first I have some quicker tips that will
help you before the semester starts or
right when it starts to make sure things
go as smoothly as possible number one
you want to know exactly what you
require in terms of gear and textbooks
and all that good stuff before the
semester starts does this mean you need
to buy all of your textbooks right away
before classes start not necessarily um
what I recommend doing is at least
looking at the book requirements maybe
even emailing teachers and saying hey do
I actually need the book do I need the
newest edition can I get a used Edition
and just having that knowledge stored in
your pocket know it in the back of your
mind now if there are books that are
going to take a while to ship you can
only get them in paper you can't rent
them uh as an eext book or you can't get
them from the campus bookstore and a
pinch yes you're going to want to get
those books well ahead of time just to
make sure you can get a good start in
the first week of the semester uh I
always think you know in my opinion that
it's better to spend a little bit of
money on a textbook you're not quite
sure about than it is to lose a lot of
progress in your first couple of weeks
of class while you're waiting for it to
ship because that can derail an entire
semester however for books that you can
rent uh very quickly via Amazon Kindle
or other e textbook methods or maybe
something you can find very cheaply in
town
maybe it's okay to book gamble you know
wait till the first day of class see if
you can share a book with a friend or
something or see if it's actually that
required and if it is you can go pick it
up very quickly if not you've saved
yourself a good amount of money another
tip that I have used a lot uh during my
whole college career was actually put my
professor's office hours on my Google
Calendar now Google Calendar lets you
actually create multiple different
calendars that you can turn off and on
so usually I would only be showing my
class and work and event calendars but I
had this other calendar that showed all
my professor's office hours that I could
turn on at will and that way if I did
need to go see a professor I didn't need
to go digging through the University
website to see when they'd be in the
office I had it all in the calendar I
had that set up before the semester
started and everything got busy and I
could see exactly where their office was
when I could go in what their phone
number was and all that good stuff so
highly recommend doing that it's really
easy just look on the syllabuses that
you get uh syllabi I guess is the plural
word or look on the University website
most professors have their own little
website and you can create that stuff
right there now a couple of other
calendar related tips number one get all
of your classes into your Google
calendar before the semester starts and
a little less obvious tip to attach to
that actually look on the University
website and map figure out what the
locations and room numbers of your
classes are and put that in the detail
section of Google Calendar I actually
wrote an article last year about how I
every semester before classes started
would go around campus making sure I
knew exactly where my classes were
especially if I had multiple classes
that had a very small Gap of time
between them that way I wasn't wasting
time getting lost and uh it was just a
better way to start the semester I think
but having that information Google
Calendar even if you don't go looking
for your classes locations personally In
the Flesh before the classes start
you'll actually have that information
and you can look up a diagram I would
also link to the campus maps and
building diagrams like floor plans in my
Google Calendar just in case I got
really confused and needed to see where
something was on in more than one
occasion I actually was able to help
somebody else who was lost and needed to
find a classroom on the same floor that
I was going to and lastly on that
calendar front it's good to put the
semester significant dates in your
calendar I'm talking stuff like days
when there won't be school the start a
spring break the start a Thanksgiving
break when finals are that stuff is
usually up on the University website
they usually have a calendar for
significant dates in the semester and
you can transfer that stuff all towards
your calendar the reason this is a
really good idea is because I advocate
every single week looking at your
calendar on Sunday and creating a week's
plan of events and tasks and if those
events are already on the calendar you
can look at say Monday and say oh that's
Labor Day I don't have school I can work
on a new project or I can go have fun
and you don't have to go looking at the
University website for those dates
during that week and you don't have to
be surprised about those significant
dates you'll know well in advance
because you put in the groundwork
beforehand now let's talk about things
you can do to ensure that you don't run
out of steam as the semester goes on you
know you're really motivated as the
semester starts we want to make sure you
can keep as much of that motivation as
the months we on as the assignments and
tests pilot up and the first thing that
you want to do is make sure you have
good study habits and one of the best
ways to build good study habits is to
make sure you have a good location for
studying if you remember in a previous
video I talked about a study done at the
University of Hawaii where students
literally just turn their desk towards a
wall and put a note on a lamp it said
study area and the students that
actually did this were able to raise
their GPA so before the semester starts
or maybe during the first week identify
a good location for you to do most of
your studying in and you can pair that
with set studying time each day or maybe
a time that works for each day on your
calendar so maybe the library is a good
location for you it's quiet there's a
lot of other people working so you kind
of get that good vibe of focused work
and you can put on your calendar that
every day from 2: to 4: or something
like that you're going to go there
you're going to get all the studying and
reviewing and assignments done that you
need to get done and that'll start
building a habit so two months down the
line when you're a little bit stressed
and you've got a lot more assignments
you still have that habit ingrained
you're still going to be at the library
every single day like you said you would
and you're keeping steam going
throughout the semester one final tip
for that first week of classes is to
introduce yourself to your professors
maybe go up to them after the first
class shake their hand introduce
yourself and that's going to make it a
lot easier for you to get over the
initial uh mental blocks for going to
office hours if you happen to need help
during the semester you already know the
professor they're familiar person
familiar face and you won't have as much
trouble going in and asking for help
that's going to help you if you run into
difficulties during the semester which
could otherwise cause you to derail in
your studies the worst thing is getting
behind yes you can can recover from
getting behind with a lot of hard work
but if you can prevent that by seeking
help and assistance when you need it and
if you can make that as easy as possible
then that's going to be to your benefit
so I hope these quick tips helped you
out if you're watching this at the
beginning of a new semester I hope your
new semester gets off to an awesome
start and stays that way thanks for
watching and I'll see you next
week hey guys thanks so much for
watching this video on how to get a
great start to the new semester now if
you want to get new tips on being a more
effective student every single week you
can click that big red subscribe button
right there also I wrote a completely
free book on how to earn better grades
so if you want to get a copy of that
click the picture of the book and if you
want to find a summary blog post with
links to other resources and other
articles I've written with more detail
you can click the orange logo right
there to get to it last week's video was
an absolutely massive video on how to
get better test grades we talked about
things you can do during the test and
also ways to prepare more efficiently
and if you want to connect with me I'm
on Twitter at tomf frankley and you can
also leave a comment below with
questions you might have or other
feedback if you like this video leaving
a like definitely helps the channel out
so thank you so much if you do that and
I will see you next week