I want to show you guys a picture this
was my fridge in my freshman dorm room
and it looks terrible I know for most of
college and for a lot of high school I
had a terrible addiction to energy
drinks and sodas monsters Red Bulls
NASA's and I knew it was unhealthy for
me in fact at one point I remember
tweeting out something about meeting
help quitting these things and somebody
replied have fun with that a regular
heart beat in ten years dude and that's
stuck with me but not enough for me to
quit for a long time I would try and
fail again and again and it was always
this just one more time excuse that
would come up maybe there was a homework
assignment that I had to do late at
night so I'd head to library cafe pick
one up and settle in for a study session
or maybe sometimes I'd just go to the
convenience store with my friends and
now there are six inches away and my
willpower failed me so long story short
this was one of my worst habits and it
took me years to finally beat it but
eventually I did and now it has been
about five years since I have had any
kind of energy drink whatsoever and I
really drink regular soda at all as well
so today guys what I want to talk about
is how to break those bad habits
regardless of whatever the habit is
whether it's drinking one too many soda
pops like me or playing too many video
games and you should be studying or just
compulsively biting your nails you have
the ability to break those bad habits as
long as you take the challenge seriously
as Aristotle said over 2,000 years ago
with some admittedly weird grammar in
the English translation but it lies in
our power to do it lies in our power not
to do but before we dive into the actual
tactics and strategies here it's useful
to ask the question what exactly is a
bad habit well in Charles Duhigg book
the power of habit he defines a habit in
general as an ingrained pattern of
behavior that has three stages there is
the cue whatever triggers the habit in
your mind the routine the pattern of
behavior the actions that you take to
get the reward
the final part and he also mentions that
once a habit becomes truly deeply rooted
and ingrained you've gone through it
several times a fourth component also
comes into the equation and that's
craving when the cue is triggered in
your mind there is an intense craving
for that
ward and it's important to understand
this every habit has a reward otherwise
you wouldn't do it so essentially a bad
habit is really any habit that stands in
opposition to your long-term goals be it
living a healthy life or maintaining
good relationships or earning straight
A's
and the reason that these bad habits
stick around for so long is because they
are ingrained but almost always they're
habits that lead to short-term rewards
and your brain is hardwired to care a
lot more about the short term than your
long term goals even though logically
you know those long term goals are more
important so essentially you're acting
against your own self-interest and in
fact there's a term that originates in
ancient Greece for this called a crazy
and if you want to be able to beat that
a crazy
you want to be able to beat that short
term focus programming deep inside your
brain you need to have a clear
well-defined and compelling reason for
breaking that bad habit and one of his
private journals Bruce Lee once wrote I
realized that dominating thoughts of my
mind will eventually reproduce
themselves in outward physical action
and gradually transform themselves into
physical reality therefore I will
concentrate my thoughts for 30 minutes
daily upon the task thinking of the
person I intend to become thereby
creating in my mind a clear mental
picture for Bruce Lee that compelling
reason that motivation came through
intense meditation and visualization but
you can also create a real physical
reminder of why you're trying to break
that habit as well and that's actually
what I dipped out of all the reasons I
had for stopping my addiction to energy
drinks the main one was my face because
for most of high school and for a lot of
college I had horrible acne my
complexion was basically the Dark Side
of the Moon and it wrecked my
self-confidence it was bad enough that I
would wake up pretty much every day with
blood stains on my pillowcase and my
sheets so I really wanted to fix this
problem and I'd spend hours researching
online trying to find remedies and fixes
and trying to figure out what the causes
were but eventually I realized what I
had basically known all along which is
that sugar especially sugary energy
drinks and soda were a huge cause of
breakouts so one day I decided to
crystallize this reason in physical form
and actually went into Photoshop I took
a picture of myself and I use the clone
tool to create a photoshopped version of
that picture basically an idealized
version of what I want to look like some
day and I put that on my phone and every
time I would get a craving to go buy a
monster or buy a Red Bull I would look
at that picture and I knew if I gave in
to that craving I was pushing that
reality further and further into the
future now that did help immensely but
of course it was still tough to resist
those cravings and one additional thing
that really helped me to stave them off
was actually replacing energy drinks and
soda with something different that still
gave me a very similar reward and that's
actually the second tip here if you can
find a different routine that replaces
the reward with something similar then
you can replace the habit with something
more productive and this is actually
something Charles Duhigg talks about in
the power of habit now for me I replaced
my energy drink addiction and my soda
addiction in part with sparkling drinks
Lucroy tofu Chico's San Pellegrino
because I realized it wasn't necessarily
the taste of the drinks that I was
addicted to wasn't even necessarily the
caffeine it was just the novelty of
having that cool can on the desk and
having some good tasting drink while I
did my boring homework so I asked myself
is there something else where I can get
a similar if not exact same benefit and
when my girlfriend actually introduced
me to Lacroix which is like a lemon
flavored one I was like this doesn't
taste the same but it's carbonated it's
in a can it's got a dead novelty to it
so it kind of replaced soda in that
habit and my experience is actually
pretty similar to the author of the
power of habit Charles Duhigg because at
one point he found himself in bad habit
where he would go every single day and
buy a cookie and he asked himself like
this is not healthy for me why am I
doing this
is it because it tastes good it's
because I need the sugar because it's
the afternoon or is it something else
and eventually he realized the real
reason that he was getting up every
single day leaving his desk and going to
buy a cookie is that it gave him excuse
to take a bit of a break and socialize
with his co-workers so that was really
the reward sometimes you have to dig in
figure out what's the actual reward I'm
getting from this habit and are there
several words and if so is there a
primary one that I can find a way to
replace with a healthier behavior
[Music]
another crucial step you need to take
from breaking a bad habit is to remove
as much access to that habit as you
possibly can in the Odyssey when
Odysseus and his men are sailing past
the island of the sirens he actually has
his men bind him to the ship's mast with
ropes and then put beeswax in their own
ears that way they can't hear the siren
song at all and he can still hear to
navigate the ship but he won't be able
to give in to the temptation because
Odysseus knew when he was removed from
that temptation he was able to think
rationally and logically and he had
enough willpower to set up a
pre-commitment which made it so that
when his willpower failed in the face of
temptation he was unable to give in to
it anyway so use this tactic when you're
trying to break your own bad habits and
I do this as well I actually have a
pretty bad habit of looking at analytics
on YouTube or social media sites like
Twitter or Facebook when I should be
writing so I actually have a program
that completely blocks all access to
those sites basically binding me to
doing my writing and making it
completely impossible for me to go
distract myself essentially if I have no
access to that habit I'm not going to be
able to give in to it
[Music]
lastly if you find the prospect of going
completely cold turkey and quitting your
bad habit forever daunting try a 30-day
challenge I find this to be useful
because a lot of people can't moderate
their bad habits they can't say I'm just
going to do this every once in a while
as a treat they have to give it up but
thinking about giving it up forever
especially when it's a fun habit like
playing video games or having the
occasional soda is kind of daunting it
kind of sucks but anybody and I mean
anybody can do a 30-day challenge
abstaining from that thing for just 30
days and the way that I do this is I
create a Google sheet and I give the URL
to my friend Martin every day I will go
in I will log my progress and I tell
them check on my progress and if I fail
even once I'm going to give you $100 so
I don't want to fail it'll hurt my pride
it'll hurt my wallet and I know I've got
somebody invested in my success who is
going to keep me accountable and hey
it's just for 30 days so again anybody
can do it
alright so quick recap here you want to
break a bad habit number one has a
compelling crystallize well-defined
reason in your mind for why you want to
break it and try to create a physical
reminder of that reason number two was
number two I don't know what number two
identified the reward and try to replace
the routine with something that gives
you a similar word also remove as much
access to that habit as you possibly can
and finally start out with a simple 30
day challenge instead of trying to go
cold turkey permanently now a lot of the
tips from this video come from my own
personal experience but several the
other ones also come from the book the
power of habit by Charles Duhigg and
this is one of my absolute favorite
books and it has a pretty high position
on my essential books list for students
which you can find over on my website
college info geek whether you're a
student in high school in college or
you're beyond traditional education I
think that you should read this book
because habits define so much of our
behavior when you understand how to
break the bad ones build more productive
ones and understand the structure of
habits in general and how they make your
brain tick you're going to be a lot more
successful now if you have the time you
can definitely sit down and read this
book in its paper form or pick it up on
your Kindle but you can also read this
book with your ears you
I'm talking about audio books audiobooks
are a great way to get through books
while you're cooking or while you're at
the gym or going to work and the best
place to find audiobooks and my personal
source for them is audible audible has
an unmatched library of audiobook titles
and a ton of different genres they also
have a great app for managing all those
and one of my favorite features of that
app is the ability to make notes at
specific time stamps in the book so say
you're cooking up a pie a or something
and something really insightful comes up
in the book you're listening to you can
just pause it add your note and go on
with your day so if you'd like to give
audible a try you can get a free 30-day
trial over audible.com slash Thomas that
trial also comes with a free audio book
of your choosing be it power of habit or
really anything you want and the nice
thing is you can keep that book forever
whether or not you decide to become an
audible subscriber which is pretty nice
so head on down the link in the
description below if you want to give it
a try and thanks so much to audible for
sponsoring this video thank you for
watching and if you haven't subscribed
yet definitely click that subscription
button right there to get videos every
week when I upload you can also get a
free copy of my book on earning better
grades right there eventually I'm hoping
to get an audio book version done so hey
maybe at some point you'll see an
audible ad with my own book in it that's
pretty conceited anyway you want to
listen to our latest podcast episode on
procrastination check it out right there
and if you want another video on this
channel there's going to be one right
there thank you so much for watching and
I will see you next week