okay now you are live and this time it's
for real and actually public oh is it
really whoa it works this time yeah I
think it's actually going to work this
time all right which
means I still can't see it but I'll
figure it out that the what like hour
plus of testing has finally paid off
kind of yeah yeah see look at all this
there's a lot of chat coming in hello
everybody on the chat you all are very
very
early oh my oh my God see okay it's all
highs right now which is good but we
already have a question such as why am I
Ginger um I could say genetics or I
could say maybe you fell into a vat of
red dye Fair things like that do happen
like the Joker you know that's not
genetic all right it says three are
watching I don't believe that because
there there's a lot of people in the
chat oh my gosh okay but yeah I do I do
think we need to wait a little bit
before we like start doing things and
there is a different URL I bet you the
one that I gave you works but apparently
there's also youtube.com C Thomas Frank
SL live oh so that's pretty cool sweet
all right we now have 550 people
watching right now so that's pretty cool
I'm going to go ahead and toss this link
over on
Twitter um just in case people don't
happen to have notifications I may just
tell them hey all' doing a quick live
stream and some Q and A all right there
will be both q's and A's yeah so your
job is to help me get questions and
maybe like save them in a note or
something because yeah the chat is like
insanity right now I'll get a little
text editor I'll get a text
editor yeah I'm gonna I'm going to bring
up a little text edit window as well
just so I can maybe oh wait yeah maybe
pull a few out and Save them cuz things
think these things take a
while
anyway Skyrim or Fallout 4 has a
question for you um I like Skyrim better
but I personally don't like fallout's
aesthetic yeah Fallout is very it's all
it's all so Bleak it's like the bleakest
grayest thing and I don't know about you
guys but I'm it makes sense I like happy
Sunny fun adventure like Venture full
bright games I like some Vibrance to my
games yeah like I'm playing um DSX
mankind divided right now and even that
while a pretty bleak game and its
subject matter the world is filled with
neon and bright screens and just like
the most I don't know it's it's super
cool looking yep pretty colors anyway
okay so hi guys uh we're going to do
some Q&A today but I just want to make
clear this is like an absolute test
stream and we're doing this because
Martin really wants me to do live
podcasts it's all your fault actually
yeah I would just like to sit like a
kudin in my room and record things and
let people hear it for I don't know eons
afterwards long after I've become a dead
skeleton yes
but YouTube seems to like life things I
like trying new things and you're up for
live things so yeah um since this is on
the main Channel I think a lot of people
don't actually know who you are unless
they're podcast listeners so do you want
to introduce yourself I'm uh good sir
hello I'm Martin I do stuff I'm on the
podcast you should check it out I used
to say you're my roommate but you're
actually not anymore yeah I'm not but
you're my apartment building neighbor
howdy neighbor yeah howdy neighbor and
uh I guess like partner in crime over
here at College infogeek lots of crime
so yeah he helps me edit my podcasts and
he helps me do this now and host a
podcast and I guess we're going to try
out some live stream stuff I think what
we may do with this video we actually
have it recording on another camera
behind the webcam so I'm thinking I
might upload this to some Channel at
some point in better quality and then
we're mainly going to use it as a test
for a potential live streaming podcast
solution at some point and we'll see
what happens so let's see here what are
there's an easy question what are you
guys drinking water that's easy question
I'm drinking winter chai there's a yes
there's a cool Tea House what's it
called coocha yes T chai tea house in
Boulder Colorado and they sell four or
five different kinds of chai and um I
wanted to get the spiciest one that they
sell so oh yeah we do look out of focus
I don't think we can get close enough to
the webcam yeah I think the webcam is
built for the second camera is going to
be in Focus this is this is a test we're
working on it we're basically using what
we have I'm doing what I what you doing
what I can with what I got and I'm
pounding out new sounds I never stop um
if this works out well I may just go buy
better streaming cameras my camera back
there dude my good one does not o I want
to write that down my good camera can't
do live streaming because it doesn't
have like this clean HDMI outport so oh
yeah I'm out of luck there yep well okay
never mind it can
but you there is no way to not have all
like the you can see the gunk right like
the all the words and text and the
little blinking red icon and that like
will always be on the output even if you
try to turn it off on the LCD it'll
always be there so we can't turn off the
HUD for yeah so I basically need to get
a different um a different camera that
will work uh so there's a there's a
question here that I think is pretty
good from Oli what is your educational
background I get this question a lot and
I think people might be interested in
what yours is as well okay so people
sometimes think that I'm like a
Psychology major or an education major I
actually graduated in something called
Mis which is management information
systems so I wanted to be an IT guy like
I basically wanted to run the networks
at a big Corporation and then I did that
during one summer as an intern and I
hated it so I decided to do this instead
and um I have really no formal
background in education but a lot of
good stuff is on the internet and Google
is your friend and I know where to find
scientific studies so I was able to just
kind of create things
up um on my own yep yeah the same exact
thing same thing yeah but you took a
pretty different approach to it cuz Mis
wasn't your initial intention right no I
started out majoring in French and then
I changed to Mis and then I was just
going to learn French on the side and do
all that stuff because I figured a
degree in French wasn't I wanted the
degree in computer stuff because I knew
I could very easily pay off my loans
with the computer stuff I knew how to do
yeah so and weren't you going to do
Linguistics before French or something
like that I considered that a lot but I
didn't end going with it m
and I ended up you regret that now that
we know our Linguistics friend
well I maybe I wouldn't know our
Linguistics friends had I done that
that's true actually yeah Butterfly
Effect right there but yeah Mis uh
language stuff and web development
that's pretty much so yes the uh know
about the two study guys on YouTube did
not ma major in education at
all um all right so here here's a good
question I'm an older student I'm in my
mid-50s do you have any recommendations
for adults returning uh to Student Life
as full-time workers so and I guess this
is this is good for any student that's
also working part-time full-time how do
you balance full-time work with your
studies is this full-time studies and is
it at a university or Community College
these are things that that change the
equation a little bit because I know a
lot of older students at Community
College much more so than in my
University it does change the equation a
bit in terms of the intensity I think
but there's still some general
guidelines we can probably give for how
you balance work and studying yeah and
you worked right right off the bat right
in college I worked after 3 months first
three months I was getting used to it
and then I got a job I had a job before
College started at my college yeah at
the college you were going to before you
started yes because um so I had in my
head that I was going to be a bus driver
for the college because bus drivers make
I think like 14 or 15 bucks an hour and
my conception of college kid job was you
flip burgers or you sack groceries or
you mol lawn or something like that and
I was like those all pay basically
nothing so I'm going to go be a bus
driver and then my friend was like hey
did you know that the It Center on
campus hires students to fix computers
and I was kind of like I can sit on my
butt and fix computers and get paid for
it as a student so I applied I got my
job and they hire a bunch of new
students every single semester before
the semester starts to help with every
one else coming in because all the new
freshmen aren't going to know how to
hook their XBox up and they all forget
their password every 5 minutes so they
need all these kind of people and so I
started that and it was really helpful
for me because the job did not have set
hours they had like this crazy calendar
that would open up every single week and
it was like a Shark Feeding Frenzy
everyone could go in claim as many hours
as they wanted and once they were
claimed like they were gone so not
stable at all it was yeah absolutely not
stable I was like sitting on my computer
hitting refresh
over and over and over again right
before the calendar would open and what
that ended up doing was I wasn't able to
get the same hours every week I wanted
them for the most part but I couldn't
get them so um I had to get like super
serious about Google Calendar and right
off the bat I had colorcoded calendar
which I definitely recommend doing with
my work hours and then I would my class
schedule in there and every day at a
glance I could see all right I'm working
from this time to this time and I've got
class from this this time to this time
so I can plan in advance when I need to
do my homework and when I need to maybe
batch smaller tasks together so I
actually have time for homework yeah
yeah when I was running when I was doing
a job and I was studying a bunch of
languages on the side and I was taking
my classes I also had like Google
Calendar has very specific times here's
a study time for this language here's a
study time for this language here's my
homework for this class it's very
specific because otherwise it's really
easy to get overwhelmed by like the 40
things you could be doing and then do
none of them instead and then hours have
passed while decide what you're supposed
to be doing so time management via
calendar is helpful yeah I think the
other thing I want to mention here is
something online classes are pretty
great yeah actually when you're in
University there are at least our
University had a lot of online classes
you could take as part of being at the
University which seems kind of
counterintuitive because you don't get a
class or like well there were some where
like you take the tests you go yeah you
go to the proor test area but you know
and you you meet like the online classes
I took at Iowa State I did have a
professor so I could physically go to
office hours so the only thing I really
lost out on was time in class with um
other people other students yeah I
didn't have that so that was good but
the other thing I wanted to mention is
that I've noticed a lot of my friends
who have part-time jobs now or full-time
jobs sorry they come home and they're
too tired to do any of the things they
aspire to do so I kind of view going to
University as like that side project to
your full-time job especially if you are
fulltime and yes you may have to put a
lot of that work after your work hours
but if you can maybe wake up when you're
like a little fresher in the morning and
do an hour of work or something like
that yeah so that you're not already
like done thinking for the day yeah
because it's easy to feel drained
exactly like in my case I do my reading
every morning before I start my work
because I don't want to read after my
brain is all drained from all the day's
work so I do it in the morning when I'm
fresh all my good habits are first thing
mhm then I work I think if you can take
anything that has more structure and
control to it external to like your own
willpower and put that later on in the
day then that structure motivates you to
get things done whereas the things that
are more up to you you want to give
yourself as much mental energy to deal
with those and to discipline yourself to
do them yeah and I found that when I was
working and I had stuff to do afterward
even at school if I if I was working I
knew I had homework or I knew I had some
stuff to do later while I was working I
would read the homework and stuff coming
up a lot more just because I'm like I'm
already tired now I've got to work
another 3 hours and there's that stupid
paper I did not write yet so it just it
feels worse and kind of emotionally
drained me prior to doing the homework
which wasn't helpful mhm so we have um
some eggplant emojis in in the chat and
some contr is is healthy yeah uh yeah
and just so you guys know um anybody
who's come into the chat like later on
our camera literally cannot Focus far
enough to get our faces in focus and
that's just if I I could do this but
it's gonna hurt me if I just like come
forward like that there you go is that
what you guys want from me yeah I suffer
from my art anyway it's a webcam and we
wanted it to be like we wanted to be
further enough back from the computer
that we'd both be in view So eventually
I will invest in a better camera and
also if the audio and video are out of
sync we did spend about 20 minutes
trying to get them in sync by adding
delays to the audio but it's tough to
test so we'll keep working it's a work
in progress it'll get better this is a
very much a work in progress um we
didn't even know we were doing this
until like this morning when we were
like let's just do it I don't know
somebody in the chat said is Martin the
the Mison plus dude Mis
yes dude and yes I am looking at the
chat guys but the chat is going really
fast so it's very tough for me to see
anything here yeah I have noticed couple
of questions on meditation here and I
know we talked about this on the podcast
recently but because a lot of people
don't listen listen to the podcast um
let's talk about that okay what do you
how do you meditate and what do you get
out of it how do I meditate well I
meditate when I get right out of the
shower because I have these cool
meditation pants and I feel when I feel
cleaner it's easier for me to like throw
out all other feelings I can't meditate
and like have really gross hair or
something at the same time so I get out
of the shower I put on my cool Thai
fisherman pants that I meditate in
they're really comfortable I I just
looked up meditation pants on Amazon I
didn't specifically look for Thai
fisherman pants but they're really
comfortable and then I I go out and I I
sit on my zafu which is a little a
little cushion that you sit on so that
you can you know you'll see like on TV
or in video games people meditating or
they'll have their legs crossed up on
each other in full Lotus position or
you'll have one leg on the other in half
Lotus and aafu what that cushion does is
makes it easier for you to sit like that
while maintaining balance because if you
do it straight on the floor it's going
to be harder on your joints yeah and
zafu are very traditional so I sit on
the zafu and then sometimes I'll use
brain FM because I really like the brain
FM music and the the noise cancelling
headphones that I have because then I
can explicitly drown out everything else
in Focus but if I do they have specific
meditation tracks okay I only use their
focus tracks so they have meditation
stuff they have a it might be under
relaxation I'm not sure but I also do
the one where you can pick your theme a
lot yeah so I'll do like Chimes and
bells or stuff like that but they've got
a meditation section and I'm either
doing that or I'm just enjoying the
silence of the morning and I'm usually
just focusing on my breath noticing the
positions of all the parts of my body
and or if I want to ahead of time I'll
decide this is one where I'm going to
think about a problem and I meditate on
a specific thing and so in one way I
gain peace and relaxation it relaxes my
muscles and it helps me separate between
two tasks so if I've just done all of my
habits in the morning morning shower and
then meditate it gets me I clear out all
the habits I did that morning and now
I'm mentally more ready to get to work
you do it after the morning routine then
like after everything else yeah for the
most part I'll I'll prefer to do a lot
of things before that and then that will
help me separate things I like to use
meditation to separate two different
topics so that my brain isn't yelling
about what I just got done doing yeah so
serious question here what's all like I
mean what's the point of like the the
pants and the zfu and like all the the
pants is just Comfort because I was like
I don't I don't want to wear shorts it's
not as comfortable for me and I don't
want to wear jeans meditating that's
definitely not comfortable when I'm
sitting on the Z does sense the pants
are just for comfort the zfu is there
because it's the way I'm sitting is
important because I like sitting half
Lotus okay so you just personally enjoy
sitting I personally prefer it and I
meditate better that way you can
meditate just laying down or sitting on
a regular chair or doing whatever yeah I
think a lot of people have this View
meditation is like if you're not I don't
know sitting on the edge of a mountain
watching the sunrise with your fingers
in like this position and sitting
cross-legged then you're like doing it
wrong now we were we were saying on the
podcast the other day um it's not about
looking like a Tibetan Buddhist monk it
is mostly about reentering yourself and
sometimes you're training yourself to
focus you're explicitly trying to focus
on one thing or nothing so that you get
used to not picking up distractions
every 3 seconds yeah but def not about
being um doam you don't need to be dose
and shoot yoga Fireballs I I have tried
a lot of techniques none of them work
for shooting yoga Fireballs out of my
mouth or hands yeah so I'll get back to
you guys if I ever figure that out
there's a dream shatter um yeah I just I
want to point that out because I think
like there's a lot of things you can do
meditation for like a lot of reasons and
some people literally just want to be at
peace and maybe just take a break from
all like the external stimuli that they
indulge in like YouTube or video games
or whatever for me it is purely to train
my focus muscle essentially it's
basically just be like you're
doarian style can I focus on one thing
that is boring that isn't like a video
game or music for um a period of time
and for me it's just five minutes and I
find that tough because my mind is very
active so I sit on the couch sometimes
sometimes I'll sit crossle on the floor
but I'm not as flexible as you or oh
yeah you said you don't you don't feel
comfortable doing that no I'm you don't
like I'm not a flexible person no I I
hate medit it so we're good we're good
counterbalance I'm into all the like
peace half Lotus nonsense but Tom just
wants to sit on the couch and train his
Focus muscle that's all it is it works
for both of us I just like breathe
slowly and I did I remember reading a
study once um where this woman went out
and she actually observed people in
coffee shops and she noticed that when
people are on their computers they're
doing their work or they're doing
whatever they tend to breathe shallowly
um unconsciously they just start
breathing a lot more shallowly and
they're not taking deep in deliberate
breaths and that shallow breathing is
tied to um anxiety in the central
nervous system which can cause all sorts
of stress problems and she she did
notice that like trained musicians
especially ones like that played
woodwind instruments or any sort of like
breath instrument or trained athletes
they tended to not have this problem
where even when they were engrossed in
YouTube or engrossed in their work they
would breathe deeply and normally that a
lot of sense so you're accidentally
getting all anxious because you're
breathing shallowly exactly or you're
just not thinking about that and I
notice like whenever I play OverWatch
I'll start breathing very shallowly and
I'll get really stressed out well yes
cuz you're playing OverWatch I'm yeah
I'm just constantly getting killed and I
it's terrible so I consciously try to
breathe while I play that game but also
during meditation it's all about slow
deep deliberate breaths in yoga class
they taught us yogic breath which is
fill the diaphragm let the chest rise
both things and let them all come out
sounds a l like flame I'm going to be
honest I'm trying to get the flame to
come out my mouth like seriously that is
a cool superpower and I need it um
honestly like everything I've done so
far has just been secretly to get
superpowers somehow and I feel like if I
get famous enough I can meet all like
the secret superpower givers that
probably work for the government yeah
that's what I'm trying to say here but
um I focus on my breath and so it's a
dual purpose thing train that deep
breathing that can apply to my work
later on in the day and also Al train my
ability to focus on that breath which is
boring yeah like my work a lot of the
times a lot of times writing a script or
editing a video or whatever it is is
boring and I want to train myself to be
okay with that and not feel like I have
to go over to Twitter every 5 seconds or
watch the next you it's going to help
you work better or focus better on
anything even just a TV show so that you
don't feel the need to I'm going to
check my Twitter while I'm watching a
movie I really wanted to watch if you
teach yourself to focus you can actually
enjoy just relaxing too
it it frustrates me to know end when
people pull out their phones during a
movie yeah especially if it's a movie
that I ask them to watch with me oh is
not really watching it exactly yeah oh
no I watched I saw that scene oh that
was that was important yeah exactly um
we we have a lot of questions um and I
have I have a cool question that I
wanted to pull out of the chat but a lot
of people are asking about exams and
stuff
um I've got if you just go to the
homepage of the channel I've got a whole
playlist on exam prep so check that out
and actually that reminds me we have a
whole page on the site for exam prep
don't
we pretty sure we have I don't remember
yeah we do I believe you it's actually
on the front page of the website right
now oh yeah that I'll throw it in the
chat uh it'll probably get buried in
like two seconds but yeah yeah um bam
somebody asked work for money or work
for
love
um well it's a good question I guess I
do run a money podcast that's that's a
tough question for me personally
I would be okay doing a job that wasn't
my favorite if it enabled me to do stuff
that was my favorite on the side if you
can do both at the same time obviously
that's awesome and some people obviously
sacrifice money for their what they want
to work on but yeah like what wasn't
there some like really well-known artist
that said that recently that I was I
shared to you I can't remember I don't
remember I don't remember who it was and
I don't want I don't want to like have a
bunch of dead air from us trying to
think of it but I do remember they there
was some pretty well-known AR artist who
they make their living making art so
they are in that camp but they did say
like you don't necessarily have to get
paid and make a living doing what you
love to do you can have a job that maybe
you enjoy maybe you get some fulfillment
out of you feel competent or have some
autonomy in but that just pays the bills
and enables you to do what you want to
do yeah like making videos isn't always
what I want to do I do like doing it but
I mean I've been doing it for three
years at this point and I do have other
interests on the side
like right now I'm playing guitar and
I'm learning game development and I have
zero
intention becoming a musician or become
a game developer or like becoming a
dancer or anything I don't want to
become like a pro DDR player I love
doing those things yeah he does but he
does doesn't know yet I what that I'm
going to be you're going to be a pro DDR
play player I know you you want it I
think the DDR scene is basically dead at
this point so I think there's no way to
easiest way to become the
best
um so I guess like there isn't a hard
and fast answer to that question but I
do want to say that I want to put a
Counterpoint out there to all the people
who say like you have to follow your
passion and do what you love for living
it depends on what your passion is if
it's something that doesn't really have
like a
clear-cut monetary path like yeah you
don't have to go for it now I don't want
to discourage anybody who's like really
gung-ho about that you know my cousin
was like super into music and he spent a
few years of his life touring the
country playing in a metal band and now
he's not doing that for a living but
like he got like a pretty cool life
experience out of that yeah but you
don't have to and I guess like the point
is you don't have to feel bad if what
you do for a living isn't what you love
to do no I don't think it's bad because
if if everybody only did what they love
to do there'd be plenty of jobs that
weren't filled anyway plenty of skilled
positions that you need I know you know
I don't think every welder out there
loves to weld it's like their passion
but they go and they do a good job
they're probably proud of the work they
do you know or like repairing air
conditioners you might not like have a
passion for repairing air conditioners
but you might like enough um of like the
mechanical tinkering process to get some
fulfillment out of it yeah or let's say
you're you're a web developer but you
don't like programming but web
development allowed you to work remotely
which allows you to travel and you
really love traveling yeah ex you learn
the skill that enabled what you want
okay so um and I've been looking at the
chat but I can't look at the chat you
know what we should do we should like
hire a moderator or something to pull
good questions out at some point that
may be like a good note to put down for
future episodes um we have three and a
half minutes left before that camera
will turn off so I want to be able to
like end the the stream before the
camera turns off so we have the good
audio and video so I'm going to do one
more question how do you make yourself
enjoy cooking how do I make myself enjoy
cooking yeah cuz I had this problem for
a long time and I've just started to get
into cooking and enjoying it so I have
some thoughts but I used to hate it
yeah I guess you probably have more
relevant thoughts I started the love
cooking when I was a vegetarian in
college and I loved it because I was
learning about so many new foods okay
but that's that I haven't cooked much
recently since moving everything's still
being set up but you just learned to
like to cook and you hated it before
which is different so I went from like
neutral I'm lazy to liking to cook but
you went from hating it to liking to
cook so what what are you doing I think
the big thing is um mental commitment
UPF front because I think the main
reason I've always hated cooking is
because it takes a long time there's a
lot of steps uh part of it is with a lot
of recipes you just have to wait but
it's like it's like a it's not the kind
of waiting where like with lasagna I can
throw it in the oven 45 minutes I don't
have to do anything so I can go do what
I want that's fine but the first step of
lasagna is constantly modering the sauce
you might have to like cook it for 30
minutes but you're you know you're
stirring it every minute so it's just
coming back to it but I found
that before the main reason I hated
cooking is because I would want to be
doing other things and I never really
committed to like I'm going to spend the
next three hours cooking it was more of
like a maybe I can make dinner in 20
minutes and then go back to playing
OverWatch or go back to working or
something so when I decide that all
right the work day is finished at 6 I'm
going to go cook dinner and you know
what I might not get to do anything else
tonight I might not get cooking is its
own activity I might be able to like
watch one episode of Avatar with Anna
later on like 9:00 it might take me 3
hours to cook this meal and that's fine
and once I did that like setting my
intention allowed me to be a lot more
meditative about the process of cooking
and now I'm finding that I actually
enjoy it because I'm picking recipes not
based on their quickness but just based
on them being a challenge for me and
then when they turn out well it's like
whoa I just made something that is
really good like that's that's a lot of
good positive reinforcement and then the
other thing that we've been doing is we
don't cook every night because it gets
exhausting so we just cook in that's
fair so I made a uh Ukrainian recipe
called borch and I ended up with enough
of that for a week and then we also make
big lasagnas and that's also probably
enough food for a week so I can cook
Sunday and then be good yeah so you can
you can afford to give the time to cook
something Fancy on Sunday if you know
it's going to save you time the next
several yeah and again it's that
batching concept if you batch your tasks
then you can concentrate on them in one
block of time and free up a whole lot of
other time so if I'm batching one giant
cooking session where I get a week's
worth of food that's 7 days worth of not
washing dishes that's 7 days worth of
not chopping up vegetables mining up
herbs and spices and stuff like that
it's all concentrated in one period of
time so I can tell myself you only got
to do this once you have the entire rest
of the week to play video games or
practice guitar or go hang out with
friends or whatever yeah because the
food that you make in that several hour
period maybe on Sunday is so much better
than the divided What could you have
made in 20 minutes 7 days a week exactly
yeah so we are just about out of time I
think that is where we're probably going
to end of this stream I know like oh PS
I saw some Zelda or Mario if you have to
pick Zelda but Mario Kart's also great
just saying yeah Mario Mario Kart 8 is
amazing and we are both like yeah we're
playing that right now obsessed with it
you have to pick though but um Zelda
breath of the wild is like one of the
greatest games I've ever played so sorry
we can't do more questions once I get a
camera that can record for more than
half an hour we can boost the length of
these and that's a big thing because the
the podcast is actually usually longer
than half an hour but if you look down
in the description of this video you'll
find a link to our podcast or just go to
youtube.com/ thee colge infogeek podcast
and we have I don't know what like 60
some episodes on the channel there's a
100 past episodes on our feed that we
haven't put on the channel so oh and a
couple questions I saw running through
there that we don't have time to answer
right now are in my plans for the next
several podcast episodes so just saying
so yeah so guys thank you for watching
you'll also find both of our Twitter
accounts down in the description below
so check those out and uh we'll see you
next time we go live so thanks for
[Music]
watching