today's video is brought to you by the
French philosopher Voltaire to whom is
attributed the aphorism perfect is the
enemy of good it's a good reminder for
this video because I'm going to give you
ten specific tips that you can use today
to both prepare for your exams more
effectively and also perform better on
those exams when you're actually taking
them the thing to remember here though
is that 10 tips are lots taken at once
and if you try to execute on all ten of
these at once you're not going to have
good results so when you get to the end
of this video pick one or two that you
think can help improve your specific
test taking abilities and then try to
put those into action let's get started
the first tip has to do with the few
minutes immediately leading up to your
exam and it's to do a test preparation
ritual now in my mind this ritual has
two specific components number one if
you're prone to test anxiety then the
first thing you're going to want to do
is pull out a piece of paper and write
out the specific things that are
worrying you as we talked about in my
video on test anxiety a study done at
the University of Chicago actually
proved that students who did this got
better grades on their tests now the
next component of the ritual is to brain
dump any important information you have
loaded into your brain right now onto a
piece of scratch paper or the margin of
the test if you can this includes
formulas measurement conversions and
other important facts that you're afraid
you might forget during the test but
that you think you might need the second
tip is to be on the lookout for later
questions in the test that might provide
insight or answers to earlier questions
I've actually noticed tests that I've
taken in previous classes where this has
happened later on to the test
I'll find a question that references
something in earlier question and it
might actually flat-out give the answer
to put this tip in more general context
simply go back and look over your
answers after you're done with the test
that way anything that references
anything else in the test is going to
catch your eye tip number three is to do
a cheat card exercise now in some
classes a teacher might let you bring in
a cheat sheet or index card filled with
notes to assist you on the test but
usually this isn't going to happen still
go the exercise of making this cheat
sheet going through the exercise of
forcing yourself to try to condense all
the material you're studying for the
test into one little summary is going to
help you learn the most important parts
of the material even if you're not
allowed to bring that resulting cheat
card into the test you've now gone
through an exercise that has really
efficiently encoded the information in
your brain now your brain basically has
that cheat cards stored inside of it and
this is just a simple way to exploit the
fact that the
learns best through active recall it
learns best when you have to work hard
to pull information out of your head at
the same time you're also forcing
yourself to think critically about what
information is the most important what
is going to fit on that little 3x5 index
card when you combine those two factors
together you'll find that you're
studying the most important information
in the most efficient way with tip
number four we're staying on that active
learning active recall train but this
time the tip is to create quizzes out of
your notes and lecture materials and
then force yourself to take them just
with like the cheat card exercise you're
forcing yourself to condense the most
important information your studying into
a more compact format but then you're
also bringing some pressure into the
situation by forcing yourself to take
that quiz now speaking of that the next
tip is to try to simulate the test
conditions as best as you can when
you're studying this means going to the
testing room to study actually
simulating the time constraints of the
test when you're taking your quizzes and
also getting your hands on old practice
tests that you can study from basically
do whatever you can to make your study
sessions near the actual test tip number
six has to do if you find yourself stuck
on a question during a test and if this
happens try to visualize your study area
now the reason you'd want to do this is
because research has shown that learning
is context dependent for example in one
study half of the research participants
learn something on land while the other
half learned something while underwater
and scuba gear when tested on the recall
later the students who learned with the
scuba gear on underwater actually were
able to recall the information better
when they were back underwater instead
scuba gear what I'm trying to tell you
here is that you should study underwater
now this is not a new discovery another
good example of this comes from
philosopher John Locke who wrote about a
young gentleman who having learned to
dance and that to great perfection there
happened to stand an old trunk in the
room where he learned the idea of this
remarkable piece of household stuff had
so mixed itself up with the turns and
the steps of his dances that though in
the chamber he could dance excellently
well it was only whilst the trunk was
there nor could he perform well in any
other place unless that or some such
other trunk had its due position in the
room now the English is a little weird
in that passage but I'm sure you can get
the point this all comes back around to
visualizing your study location when
you're stuck though because other
research has shown that people who do
this are sometimes able to overcome the
effects of context dependent learning
basically that means that if you happen
to study in the library and then you
visualize library their memory of that
study location might help you forge
connections to the material you're
trying to recall tip number
is to try doing at least one of your
study sessions while out on a walk
if you're having trouble grasping a
certain concept and try going on a walk
and reviewing it while you're outside
now many people actually find that when
they're doing physical activity in their
outside their brain makes better
connections but you're getting an
additional benefit as well while you're
outside you're looking at the problem
from a different perspective Barbara
Oakley's book a mind for numbers points
out that doing this helps you review a
concept and learn it while independent
of any environmental cues of one
specific place my eighth tip is to apply
Hofstadter's law to the act of studying
now house letters law states that it
always takes longer than you think even
when taking into account Hofstadter's
law encoding the information needed to
earn a certain test grade is almost
always going to take you longer than you
expect it will yes I know you're
absolutely certain that later on tonight
you're gonna study really really hard
core but then your friends are going to
come in and want to do something or a
five-minute study break is going to turn
into a Netflix binge this is just simple
reality and smart people plan around
reality so take the date that you're
planning on starting to study for your
test and try moving it back a week that
way you're giving yourself ample time to
review and revise even if things get in
the way that you didn't anticipate tip
number nine is to be deliberate about
taking all your small tasks and grouping
them into as few small concentrated
blocks of time as you can this will free
up timing you're scheduled to create
large uninterrupted blocks of study time
now when you're doing this as a general
rule of thumb try to put those
uninterrupted study sessions as early as
you can in the day this is because your
willpower is a finite resource and if
you use it all on small tasks earlier in
the day you're not going to have as much
left over for that big study session you
need to get to this is where the saying
eat your frogs first came from do the
hardest things when your willpower
reserves are as high as they can go and
we are finally to the last tip and it is
simply to appreciate test taking as part
of the learning process
viewing tests only as assessment says
basically judgments makes them scary and
causes undue stress instead try to see
your tests as beautiful concentrated
bursts of recall and application and you
can also reduce further stress with cats
so that is it for this video if you
found it helpful you can always leave a
like down below to help support this
channel and if you want to find more
videos with more additional tips on how
to do better on your tests then this
channel is absolutely full of them on
the screen right now you'll see
thumbnails for videos on finals tips how
to deal with test anxiety how to not
make stupid mistakes on your exams and
also whether or not you should change
and
your exams if you feel like changing
them whichever one fits your fancy click
it right now and hopefully it'll teach
you something new lastly if you have
questions that are still unanswered or
maybe you saw something in this video
that picked your curiosity and now you
want a more in-depth video in the future
then leave those questions down in the
comments those comments are super
helpful for me because they let me know
what to make next and somebody might
actually answer your question in the
mean time so that's it thank you so much
for watching and I will see you next
week hey guys thanks so much for
watching to the end of this video on
test prep now if you want to get more
tips on being an effective student every
single week you can hit that big red
subscribe button right there I also
wrote a book on how to earn better
grades which is absolutely free so if
you'd like me to send you a copy click
the picture of the book and I'll get one
to you you can find a summary for this
video along with links to a lot of the
research I mentioned other resources at
the companion blog post which can be
accessed at the going to logo right
there last week's video talked about how
to craft a good sleep schedule when the
rest of your schedule is hectic and
fittingly I created that video at 4 a.m.
we're going to VidCon but check it out
anyway and also if you'd like to ask
questions or just connect with me i'm on
twitter @tomfrankly or you can leave a
comment below also all these links are
down in the description so if you're on
your phone check that out you can click
them there thanks we'll see you next
week