our culture seems to have a fixation
with mourning books like the miracle
morning and websites like my morning
routine love extolling the virtues of
waking up super early and building a
strong morning routine with lots of
healthy habits in it like meditation and
of course putting lots of butter in your
coffee but what about the evenings
here's the thing nothing exists in
isolation and this is especially true of
your mornings if your lacs about your
evenings if your lacs about the time
when you go to bed or you do at night
and your mornings are probably gonna be
pretty lackluster as well so here are
seven things you need to stop doing at
night because you can fix your nights
then your tomorrow morning's get better
as well number one stop going to bed at
inconsistent times and note that I
didn't say stop going to bed late
because that actually works for some
people everyone has a different
chronotype which is a biologically
hardwired propensity to go to sleep and
wake up at different times some people
do really well going to bed super early
waking up at 4:30 in the morning doing
the whole jockle willing thing and some
people do well working late into the
night and then sleeping in to compensate
but regardless of the exact time the
reality for most of us is that we're
trying to get up at a consistent time
and when that's the case going to bed at
an inconsistent time the night before it
leads to inconsistent in amounts of
sleep so to fix this first figure out
how much sleep you need the guidelines
put up at the National Sleep Foundation
or a great place to start and you can
also use apps like sleep cycle to figure
out your own specific sleeping habits do
you want to be more accurate once you've
got that data then establish a bedtime
that fits with it and stick with it
which of course is easier said than done
so the question then becomes how do you
go to bed on time consistently well
that's the focus of my next suggestion
stop doing your main activities working
hang out with friends watching TV shows
playing video games well before your
bedtime in my experience this is the
main reason that I tend to push my
bedtime off I'll be playing a video game
or watching a TV show and notice that
it's getting near my bedtime but then
tell myself that I can just go to bed
right after I'm done I can just roll
right into bed which is of course a lie
I've got to do stuff before I can go to
bed brush my teeth clean up all that
good stuff and that keeps pushing my
bedtime it later and later so the
solution here is to set a wine downtime
at least 30 minutes before your bedtime
this is the point we should stop doing
whatever it is you're doing start
getting ready
bed and getting ready to go to bed once
you're ready for bed it's fine to go and
do something else until your bed time
actually rolls around maybe you play an
instrument for a while like I like to or
read a book or maybe even watch some TV
there's actually conflicting research
out there about the harmfulness of TV at
night so it might work fine for you but
whatever is you pick it should be
something that's relaxing and that's
easy to put down when it's actually time
to go to bed which brings me to my third
item on the list stop using the internet
before bed
nothing has a greater ability to trick
you into staying up later and later then
the Internet
sure binge where the TV shows can be a
temptation as well but at least before
you start an episode of one of those you
know beforehand you're gonna dedicate 30
minutes or an hour to that and it's
often possible to talk yourself down
but with Reddit and Twitter and
Instagram and all these social media
sites it's so easy to tell yourself that
you're just gonna spend one or two
minutes scrolling and then get to bed
which is almost never the case so when
your wind down time rolls around the
first thing that you should do is fully
shut off your computer and put your
phone somewhere where it's not going to
distract you and if you're one of those
people who uses your phone as your alarm
clock then that deserves scrutiny as
well and I say this is somebody who does
use their phone as alarm clock if you
find yourself reaching for your phone
when you're in bed if you find yourself
not going to bed when you should because
it's on your nightstand
then maybe it'd be a good idea to get
yourself an old-fashioned digital alarm
clock and keep your phone in a different
room all right next up stop drinking
caffeinated beverages before bed which
should be obvious but also even in the
late afternoon now you probably already
know that having a coffee or energy
drink right before bed is going to harm
the quality of your sleep but research
has found that caffeine consumption even
up to six hours before bedtime can do
the exact same thing now this is the
point of the video where I'm going to
say your mileage may vary because I know
from personal experience that I can have
coffee at 7 p.m. 8 p.m. and go to sleep
just fine with no problems but if you're
having trouble getting to sleep or
you're waking up in the middle of the
night if the quality of your sleep is
suffering then cut off the caffeine
consumption in the early afternoon now
that may leave you coffee and tea lovers
wondering what do I drink at night and
my personal suggestion is herbal tea
which actually isn't tea at all because
tea always has caffeine unless it's
decaffeinated which makes it gross but
there are herbal tea blends out there
that are delicious and non-caffeinated
my personal favorites are fireside
vanilla spice and Bengal spice a lot of
people also like to go for chamomile and
while there isn't a whole lot of
scientific evidence out there that
chamomile is actually a sleep aid it is
indeed a relaxing drink and well that's
pretty good for going to sleep too that
brings us to item number five which is
admittedly a bit of a departure from
everything else on this list but I did
want to include it stop going to bed
angry this is a rule that I set for
myself back when I started dating my
girlfriend and it's been very helpful
ever since I guess the way that I look
at it is that each day is its own
self-contained journey and I don't want
to end that journey on a sour note I
don't want to be angry at her I don't
want her to be angry at me so if I can
help it and I can I want to at least
address the situation make my apologies
because often I do need to make an
apology and make sure that the emotions
have simmered down and cooled off a
little bit before we go to sleep and
maybe work on it some more the next day
all right
item number six maybe stop working out
late at night so back when I was in
college I would often do just that when
I live in the dorms I would often wait
until 9:00 p.m.
sometimes even 10 p.m. to go to the dorm
gym and get a workout in and then go to
bed and that worked out pretty well for
me however and again this is a your
mileage may vary thing if you do this
you might find it difficult to go to
sleep and the reason for that is that
working out especially if you do a hard
cardio workout II go really really hard
raises your core body temperature and
that body temperature doesn't come back
down to normal levels for quite some
time and of course as anyone who's ever
slept in a hot room knows going to sleep
with an elevated body temperature isn't
really the easiest thing in the world to
do so if you're used to exercising in
the evenings but you're finding it
difficult to fall asleep then maybe try
moving your workouts to the mornings now
one thing that I do want to note is that
things like yoga and light stretching
these are probably not gonna raise that
body temperature very much so those are
totally fine to do before bed and I
often like doing some light stretches
before I go to bed personally that
brings us to the final item on our list
which is to stop leaving messes for
yourself to clean up in the morning you
probably know this just as well as I do
it's so easy to go to bed and tell
yourself that you're gonna clean up the
mess in the kitchen or on the desk in
the morning because you're gonna have
more energy then you're gonna have more
time but here's the problem with doing
that when you wake up the next day
instead of being able to roll right into
your morning routine or get right to
work you are immediately interrupting
your momentum by having to clean up your
mess from the night before and I know
from personal experience that this
interruption to momentum can often have
knock-on effects it can make my entire
day less productive as a result so
instead use party or wind down time to
reset your space do the dishes clean off
your desk so close any programs at the
computer do whatever it is that you need
to do to make your space immediately
usable the next morning that way you can
wake up and immediately get into the
habits in your morning routine one of
which could be spending some time at the
start of your day working to broaden
your base of knowledge like we talked
about in my previous video about
Leonardo da Vinci one thing that can
really help you become a better
problem-solver and boost your job
prospects is working to become a
t-shaped person someone with the deep
knowledge of an expert in a few specific
areas along with a much broader base of
shallower knowledge they can draw upon
to solve problems creatively and a great
place to start building that base of
knowledge is curiosity stream which has
over 2,400 high-quality documentaries
that can broaden your knowledge in
science nature technology history and
lots lots more including ones from
Stephen Hawking and Sigourney Weaver
though if you want a personal
recommendation I'm gonna recommend you
start with a documentary called order
and disorder which traces the
development of communications technology
and how we transmit information across
the globe you can get access to all
these documentaries for just $2.99 per
month which is really really affordable
but since you watch my channel you can
also get your first 31 days for free by
going over to curiosity Stream comm
slash Thomas and using the promo code
Thomas when you sign up big thanks as
always goes out to curiosity stream for
sponsoring this video being supporter of
my channel and thank you as well for
watching if you enjoyed this video hit
that like button and get subscribed
right there so you don't miss out on
future videos and also click right there
to get a free copy of my book on how to
earn better grades if you haven't done
so already you can also watch one more
video on this channel right over here or
check out our latest podcast episode
right over here if you want to listen to
something that is you know more than
eight minutes long thanks for watching
and I'll see you in the next one