hello my name is thomas frank and i have
a browser tab problem i just can't seem
to help myself from having 50 or 80
browser tabs open at one time and
completely taken up all my computer's
ram
which is why i now have this little
extension that automatically hides the
browser tabs i'm not using and groups
them into
projects and that's not all today we're
going to break down 10 of the best
browser extensions out there for
boosting
your productivity and this video is
sponsored by hover so we're going to
focus mainly on chrome in this video
since it is the most popular browser out
there and it's the one that i happen to
use but if you're using something else
like firefox or safari
fear not a lot of these extensions are
on multiple browsers so when i call each
one out you're gonna see some icons to
show which of the major browsers that
extension is also on
so with all that out of the way let's
get into our first extension the one
that i teased in the intro called
wercona this is probably my new favorite
extension on chrome because
to make a bit of a mission here i'm a
really bad tab hoarder my friends love
to make fun of the fact that i often
have
50 or 100 tabs open but that's just my
nature i always have multiple research
projects going on
and before i know it the browser header
bar on my computer screen is just this
unintelligible mess of tiny slivers of
tabs i can't even see what they are at
that point
and that's the problem that workona
helps people like me to solve
it basically gives you this dashboard
where you can create multiple projects
and then group your tabs into those
projects now if you've watched my past
videos you've probably heard me talk
about an extension called tab copy which
lets me basically copy all the tab links
to my clipboard
but i gotta say this is better in
addition to letting you do that if you
wanna just paste your links somewhere
else it also saves all of your tabs
in organized projects and you can even
close those tabs after saving them as
resources so you can keep
a bunch of different websites in a
specific project without having to keep
them open
you can also switch between projects and
work on it actually suspends the tabs
that you're not using and
hides them if they're not in the open
project so you only see what is relevant
to the project that you're working on
so basically workona makes context
switching a lot better within chrome but
it also encourages you to be working on
one specific project at a time
because you know the grouping of tabs
you have open are only related to
that project our next extension is
called habitica pomodoro
sight keeper which is kind of a mouthful
but it is now my pomodoro app
of choice so if you're unfamiliar with
the pomodoro technique i've got a whole
video on it i'll link to that down in
the description below
but in short it is probably the most
effective and easiest to use
productivity technique out there you
simply pick a task you want to work on
set a timer an actual timer for 25
minutes and work on
just that task during the duration then
you take a break
and because you're using an external
timer to guide you
and because you're reframing your task
as work for just 25 minutes
it's an extremely effective way to get
over the resistance you feel to doing a
tough task
i use pomodoro sessions all the time to
get myself doing things that i don't
want to actually do
and i've tested a lot of pomodoro apps
out there this is now my favorite one
because i use a habit tracker called
habitica
now if you haven't used hibika before it
uses rpg and video game elements to sort
of build a habit tracking app that keeps
you a bit more motivated to track your
habits
especially if you're a nerd like me but
i will note that even if you're not the
rpg stuff habitica is a fantastic habit
tracking app
possibly one of the best out there
because it's open source which means it
has a ton of advanced features that
don't cost anything
where other apps that have similar
features always want you to pay which is
pretty nice
and in keeping with that way of doing
things this extension for pomodoro
timing
has a lot of cool features that a lot of
other pomodoro apps that i've seen
want you to pay for like tracking your
pomodoro stats a lot of them want you to
pay for that this one does it
for free and it does a few other cool
things as well namely it connects to
habitica and adds pomodoro-based habits
to your habit tracking it also has a
site blocker so you can add whatever
sites you want to its block list and
during pomodoro sessions
all those sites are going to be blocked
you can also add costs
to websites and if you add a cost to a
website it's going to be blocked
all the time even outside of pomodoro
sessions and you can get into them for a
limited amount of time by paying gold
from habitica now personally i love
having this extension connected to
habitica since i use the crap out of it
but if you don't happen to use that or
you want something a little less nerdy
there is another extension called tide
which has a pomodoro timer it's got the
stat keeping for free it's got the sight
blocker
so it's very similar but it doesn't have
the habitica connection so check that
out
as an alternative next up on our list is
an extension called
audioblogs which translates written
articles into
podcast narrations that you can send to
your phone and which are narrated by
a scarily good ai narration algorithm
this thing is
way better than has any right to be and
i have never heard a text-to-speech
algorithm that works anywhere near as
good as this thing
sometimes it gets inflections wrong
sometimes it's a little wonky but
95 of the time it's perfectly listenable
this guide was originally published in
march 2012.
since then hundreds of students and even
non-students
have created their own personal websites
using it and the reason i have this
on my list is because for me one of my
top priorities and values in life
is daily low-level movement walks and
bike rides in addition to my sessions in
the gym and more intense exercise for me
this is a non-negotiable priority in my
life
and when i go for these walks and bike
rides i love to listen to
usually audio books so i can keep
learning or keep myself entertained
while i'm out
on them right now i'm actually listening
to a book called walkable city
which is kind of making me hate the way
that we americans design our cities but
i digress
sometimes i'm on my computer i come
across an article and i want to read
that
but i also want to go out for a walk or
a bike ride so audioblogs lets me turn
that article into a podcast narration
and listen to it while i do that next up
on our list we've got ublock origin
which is a great
lightweight ad blocking extension for
most browsers there are a lot of ad
blockers out there i like ublock origin
because it is again lightweight it
doesn't use a lot of resources
and if you want you can add sites to a
white list so you can support them and
see their ads
if you don't trust them but i have long
held that an
ad blocking extension is almost as
necessary for computer security as an
anti-virus program and here's why a lot
of website owners do
not place their own ads they have
third-party ad placement extensions that
they put on their pages
and they trust a third party to place
those ads and there have been many
instances where those third-party
networks have placed ads that contain
malware or exploits so i am not going to
trust my computer security to
every website in the world that i happen
to go to i use an ad blocker as a
default and then i
whitelist sites if i trust them and one
other really nice thing that you block
origin lets me do is add filters which
can block
certain elements of websites for
instance that what's happening section
on twitter is always full of these like
sensationalist headlines that just suck
me in
and waste a ton of my time i never want
to see what's happening on twitter
ever again and luckily in the my filter
section of ublock origin i can paste
this little line of code
and that is exactly what happens it gets
hidden and that is just
read wise the next extension on our list
is read wise and if you've seen my
previous videos you will know that i
absolutely love raidwise this is a
wonderful
highlighter app that allows you to make
highlights from kindle books from
podcast episodes
from actual print books if you use their
phone app with the camera and the
built-in text recognition feature
and in anything that you read on the
internet with the extension installed
all you need to do
is highlight some text right click and
send that highlight to read wise this is
a great way to keep a collection of the
things that you want to remember
if you saw my ipad productivity video
from a couple of months ago you will
know that i talked about an app called
command
on the ipad which is a browser that lets
you make highlights that actually stay
on the web page even if you refresh and
then automatically sends those
highlights over to read wise which is
freaking sweet and i really wish that
command was on desktop browsers
unfortunately it's not but for now we at
least have the read wise extension which
while it won't leave those highlights on
the web page
will send them to your read wise account
and if you have one of their sync
options turned on can send the
highlights over to rem note or roam
research or if you're like me
to notion and while we're talking about
read wise we also have to talk about
pocket which is the next extension on
our list unlike read wise
pocket is an extension that just lets
you save web pages read wise really
wants you to make a selection and kind
of
save a snippet of text pocket is just
for like i want to save this cool web
page that i found
for later that's exactly what i use it
for if i come across an article that i
don't have time to read and want to read
later
or if i come across just like a cool app
that i want to share with my audience
i will hit that pocket button in my
browser and it saves it to my little
pocket list which i can go
and review later on and another cool
thing about pocket is their mobile apps
have the ability to download articles
for offline reading
so if you're somebody who commutes on
the subway or you take a lot of flights
or
you somehow have a lot of time or you're
offline pocket can be a really really
useful app and extension combo
next up on our list we have an extension
called notion
boost so as you probably know if you
follow this channel or my other channel
thomasfrank explains i am a huge user of
notion i basically run my entire
business through it i've got my task
management in it and i write all my
articles and do all my research in it
i absolutely love notion but there is a
feature that i have wished notion would
add
for a really long time and it's a
feature that's in a lot of other
note-taking and writing apps
that is a floating sticky outline i want
to be able to see
all of my headings and be able to zoom
to them and a lot of other apps have
this
google docs has it dropbox paper has it
obsidian has it slight has it
unfortunately notion does not they do
have the table of contents block but
when you put that somewhere it just
stays where you put it
and you have to scroll up to find it not
that useful so notion boost adds notion
at least in the browser
to that hollowed collection of apps that
have the beautiful
uh sticky floating outline on the
sidebar it does a few other things as
well but that is
absolutely the coolest thing for me that
it does i've got a lot of really long
articles i read in ocean i've got huge
research documents and having that
sticky sidebar
is really really nice for being able to
zoom to different sections next up we
have web clippers there are web clippers
for notion for evernote and for onenote
and these extensions basically take the
entire content of a web page release the
you know text part
and port it over to the note taking app
that you're using now personally i don't
use web clippers very often because i've
got a combination of other apps that
basically do the same thing for me if i
want to make sure a bunch of tabs are
saved in my resource section well i've
got work on it for that
if i'm reading an article and i want to
highlight something i've got read wise
for that and if i want to just you know
put something in my big
jumble of stuff that i can go look at
later i've got pocket for that
but for some people a web clipper is
going to be the thing that fits the bill
so we're mentioning it here and i'm
going to mention specifically the ones
for notion onenote and evernote because
they're the ones that i know about
before i move on to the next extension
on our list which might possibly be the
most
useful one for most people watching this
video i do want to say that if you're
enjoying this video maybe consider
hitting that subscribe button i've
actually got a brand new best
note-taking apps video in the works
that's going to compare some of the
newcomers like
rome research and obsidian with our old
standards so if you like these kind of
videos
that one is coming in the very near
future and you're going to want to be
subscribed so you don't miss it
plus according to my analytics only 30
of you are actually subscribed when you
watch my content and i know
every youtuber says that these days it's
kind of a trope but subscribing really
does help support the channel and push
it out to more people on this platform
so if you do enjoy this content and you
want to help support it you want to help
support me as a creator uh consider
hitting that subscribe button and thank
you
if you do all right next extension on
our list is called news feed
eradicator for facebook even though it
says for facebook in the title this is
an extension that can eradicate the news
feed
in a ton of different social media
websites in youtube and twitter and
linkedin
and facebook instagram may not be in the
list there but uh most of the
distraction usual suspects are and all
you got to do is hit a little check box
and the feed on that website is going to
be
deleted essentially it's going to be
hidden so that allows you to use social
media if you're somebody like me who
needs to make posts on social media or
you want to check your mentions and
engage with your audience
without getting sucked into your feed
it's something that i keep on almost
all the time only turning off if i
really want to check the feed for a
specific
reason and that brings us to our last
extension of the day which is called
reader view and read review like the
reader view on mobile safari
takes a page full of distracting
elements and boils it down to its
essentials
namely the content that you want to read
it also gives you typography options
which is
pretty sweet you can change the font
size you can change the line height
it's pretty nice now some web designers
like yours truly design our websites so
extensions like this
aren't needed if you go onto any of my
websites college info geek thomas j
frank
we've got single column minimalist
distraction free columns of text it's
designed
for pleasurable reading but designers
like me seem to be in the minority it
seems like almost every website out
there these days has a pop-up asking you
to subscribe their email newsletter
there's a sidebar
there's mid-content ads all kinds of
crap that is just distracting and makes
the page load slower
so an extension like greater view is
really really nice for being able to get
rid of all of that
and just read the thing that you came to
read and there are a couple of other
cool features as well built in there's a
dark mode filter and actually some light
theming options
there is a text-to-speech mode which is
honestly
pretty bad i would just use audio blogs
if you really want that but there's also
a built-in highlighter and like in
command the highlights you make
persist even if you refresh the page now
it's not going to send your highlights
to read-wise as well so there is a
couple of different actions
to take if you want both those things to
happen that's why command is still the
gold standard for researchers as far as
i'm concerned
but it is pretty cool having that
highlighter feature at least
so for all this video we've talked about
extensions that can make you work more
productively on
the internet but what about making the
internet work more productively
for you well that's exactly what happens
when you have your own online presence
where you can connect with people or you
have your own platform where you own
your content and where you can maybe
make connections with potential
employers potential clients people who
you could work with that's exactly what
i do on my website thomasjfrank.com that
shows off my work
and helps me build my personal brand and
if you haven't started building an
online presence for yourself it's
something you should definitely think
about and at least
take the first step to doing which is
getting your own domain name
even if you're not ready to build your
own website yet getting that domain name
locked down is crucial
because if somebody goes out and
registers it before you can get it well
you're kind of out of luck that's how i
am with thomasfrank.com i couldn't get
that so i at least got thomasjfrank.com
but that could have been taken
as well so as soon as you can go over to
hover and register yourself a domain
name
hover is a great place to do it because
unlike a lot of other places out there
they have a completely hassle-free and
speedy check-up process
they're not trying to upsell you on a
bunch of stuff like a lot of other
websites and registers
are they also have over 400 extensions
to choose from your dot coms and dot mis
which are
great for your professional presence but
also more fun ones like
lol dot ninja i use thomas.lol for my
music stuff and once you have your
domain they also have a feature called
connect which lets you easily hook that
domain up to online website builders and
online store builders
so if you're ready to claim your domain
make sure nobody else can take it go on
over to hover.com
thomasfrank to buy it with your first
purchase using that url you're gonna get
off and you're gonna be able to support
my channel i work
really hard to make sure that my content
is research backed and detailed and has
a high production value
and because most of the stuff that i
create is free supporting the sponsors
who support me
is actually the best way to support this
channel if that's something you want to
do and if it is
thank you uh beyond that make sure you
subscribe to this channel if you like
content like this and you want to see
some more in the future like i said i've
got that
note-taking app comparison coming up
that's a much more detailed topic than
this one but i'm hoping to get it
up in the next month or two and if you
would hit that like button
youtube's algorithm absolutely uses
engagement factors like likes and
comments when it's determining how far
to push a video
so big thanks to you if you do hit that
button and if you have other extension
recommendations you want to make let me
know down in the comments let me know
what i missed let me know what's good
for other browsers
and beyond that i've got a couple of
other videos right here and here you can
check out
make sure you subscribe right there or
don't do any of that and go uh i don't
drive a motorcycle off of a ramp through
a bunch of flaming hoops like evil
knievel because as always
i'm not your dad but i will see you in
the next video thanks for watching