so back in 1791 Ben Franklin or at least
his publishing house because he had died
a year prior published his autobiography
and in that autobiography Franklin
actually laid out his daily schedule now
you may have seen a picture of this
schedule online before but what I want
to do in this video is actually go
through the schedule and see what we can
learn from it both in terms of what's
useful in the schedule and what it might
actually be missing that you should have
in yours let's get into it all right so
first things first at least according to
this schedule he woke up at 5:00 a.m.
every single morning which means that he
definitely lived up to his early to bed
early to rise Mantra and this is the
first thing I want to get into because
as I talked about in my video about how
to wake up early you don't actually need
to wake up early to be successful this
is something that Ben Franklin
definitely advocated but there are many
different people throughout the world
who have been successful even if they
wake up at 8:00 a.m. 10:00 a.m. or
whatever hour that they feel like
because we are all different in fact
people have different chronotypes which
are essentially biologically set times
at which they tend to go to bed and get
up so figure out what yours is and live
by that not just some schedule from a
dude who lived 300 years ago so the
first real item of business on this
schedule is the morning question what
good shall I do this day and this is
setting an intention and I think it's a
great Habit to adopt in your own life
because setting an attention allows you
to give yourself direction for the day
and when those urgent tasks or
distractions come up later in the day
you're going to be able to keep your eye
on the prize and avoid them after you
set that intention the next items which
are rise wash and address powerful
goodness which was his personal word for
God and after that he would contrive the
day's business and take the resolution
of the day which is a big fancy smancy
way of saying make a daily plan so this
is another great Habit to start doing
setting the intention gives you some
direction for the day in a general sense
but sitting down and making a daily plan
allows you to make it more concrete you
can break that big task that big
important work down into subtasks that
are a lot easier to understand and put
into action and then you can order them
so you know exactly how you're going to
tackle the day after after making his
daily schedule Franklin would prosecute
the present study and that's some old
English that I didn't know how to
interpret but the popular interpretation
is that he's basically doing some
studying on whatever he's learning at
the time and it's pretty safe to say
that Franklin was a voracious lifelong
learner since according to Wikipedia he
was among other things an author printer
political theorists politician Freemason
postmaster scientist inventor Civic
activist Statesman and Diplomat now this
is a part of his schedule that I really
like because it's something that I do
myself I find it really helpful to have
some sort of learning project that I'm
pursuing independent of my work or a
book that I'm reading at basically all
times and when I wake up in the morning
after I brush my teeth and feed my cat I
read every single day for about 20 or 30
minutes before doing anything else and
my friend Martin does the same thing
with language study he'll get up he'll
do some studying in Spanish or French
and then get into the day's work so if
you have an independent learning project
you know spend some time on that before
you get into the work that's going to
exhaust you and deplete those willpower
reserves and if you don't you should
probably get one next up up we've got
breakfast which is breakfast I eat
breakfast in the morning probably a
pretty good thing to do and then we move
into the main work block of the day and
Franklin split this up into three
different tasks first up there's a
4-Hour block of work followed by a
2-hour block for eating and reading and
going over accounts and then a final
4-Hour block of work and I have a few
comments here so the first thing I want
to note here is that because he
mentioned in this noon segment that he
does some light reading or goes over
accounts I interpret that as doing
shallow work during his noon hour and if
he's doing shallow work during the noon
hour then it stands to reason that he's
at least trying to do his deep highly
concentrated work during those two
blocks of time so it's a good idea to
try to schedule differences between your
intense work that's really important and
the work that doesn't require quite as
much brain power or quite as much
attention secondly at least on his
schedule Franklin did not make time for
breaks during his main work hours and
this is something that you definitely
want to do I made a whole video on why
breaks are important so I'm sure that he
probably did it in real life I mean I
can't go back in a time machine to
verify but working for 5 hours at a time
without a break is pretty tough and
you're going to hit a point during that
work session where your efficiency is
going to go down so make sure you're
taking some breaks going for walks
getting a little bit of exercise and
breaking up those work sessions with
some relaxation so once the work ends
the first thing that Franklin did was to
put things in their places essentially
put things away and reset his space back
to neutral now this reminds me of a
technique a friend told me about a long
time go which is called clearing to
neutral basically you clear your
workspace back to its neutral clean
ready to go State at the end of the day
once you're done with your work and the
reason you want to do it then rather
than before you start the next day's
work is that it's a shallow task it's
really easy to do it doesn't take a
whole lot of willpower and if you do it
then when you come into your work the
next day the workpace is ready to go and
you don't have to waste any time or
willpower getting the space ready you
can just steamroll right into the most
challenging work of the day once you had
everything put away the next things were
supper music diversion and conversation
and I'm sure that because life is
complex even back then he left a lot off
the schedule so I do think it's telling
that he put this on the schedule that
shows that he really did value time with
friends and relaxation and that he
understood the importance of taking
breaks and making time for recharging in
between work sessions and that brings us
to his last true activity of the day
besides sleep which I'll get into in a
second here and that is the asking of
the question what good have I done this
day and asking that question reflecting
on the day's events and what you've done
is just as important as setting the
intention in the morning if you get
yourself into the habit of reflecting on
what you've done during the day then you
can start to pinpoint what went right
and what went wrong and when you know
what went wrong you can start to Target
why it went wrong and then make changes
which will help you improve the next day
now he does have sleep written on his
schedule and he slept about 7 hours a
day and the only real thing I have to
say here is that just because some dude
200 years ago put 7 hours of sleep on a
schedule doesn't mean that 7 hours is
the optimal amount of sleep everyone
needs different amount of sleep so when
you're creating your schedule make sure
you tailor it to the amount of sleep
that your body actually needs remember
your sleep your nutrition and your
exercise are the levers with which you
can control your body's energy levels
and hence your ability to get work done
so don't overlook them all right so to
recap here I want to pull a few of the
best lessons out of his schedule that I
found and share them here and I also
want to mention a few of the things that
were missing that you should think about
when you're creating your own schedule
first I really like how he tried to
start every single day with purpose he
set an intention for the day and he
created a daily plan to make sure that
he carried it out I also like how he
made specific time for shallow work he
had those two work blocks but then he
would look over his accounts and do
easier stuff over the lunch hour and I
also like how he made it a point to
schedule time for clearing his space to
neutral getting everything cleaned up so
that it was ready for the next day's
work now a few things I thought the
schedule was missing include exercise
taking small breaks during those work
sessions and through no fault of his own
since he lived 200 years ago a lot of
the things that we have to deal with in
Modern Life like commuting to work or
school cooking Etc so when you're making
your own schedule take schedules like
this or schedules from other famous
people you read online as inspiration
not as an exact recipe take what's good
add it in and experiment with it and
figure out what works for you also if
you find that you're not perfect at
following your schedule realize that Ben
Franklin wasn't perfect at following his
either in his autobiography right after
he wrote out the schedule Franklin wrote
that I was surprised to find myself so
Fuller of faults than I had imagined but
I had the satisfaction of seeing them
diminish so if you have one crappy day
or you have an interruption that comes
up that messes with your schedule just
accept it forgive yourself and then wake
up the next day and set that intention
again and as time goes on because you've
deliberately built a schedule for
yourself you're going to start building
routines and habits that will make these
things happen less often and in turn
you'll be more successful so guys thanks
for watching this video hopefully you
enjoyed it I'm going to link to that
schedule down in the description below
and if you like this video give it a
like to support this Channel and leave a
comment down below if you have an
additional tip that you'd like to sh
share if you aren't yet subscribed to
this channel you can click right there
to do so and get new videos every single
week and you can also click right there
to get a copy of my book on earning
better grades also our latest podcast
episode is going to be right there so
definitely check it out and if you want
to watch another video with my face on
the camera here then that button right
there is your go-to thanks for watching
I'll see you next week