hey what is going on guys so I think we
can all agree that studying takes far
far too much time so what I want to do
in this video is show you guys how you
can remember more of what you learn even
if you're spending fewer actual hours
studying and the way to do that is by
spacing out that study time this is a
technique called spaced repetition and
to do it you add progressively longer
and longer time intervals in between
each of your study sessions so in this
video I want to show you exactly how you
can do that both with your paper
flashcards and with apps both for
smartphones and computers but first I
wanted to get into into why this
technique is so powerful and also talk
to you a little bit about the history
behind it and how it relates to our
memories in general space repetition
leverages a memory phenomenon known as
the spacing effect which describes how
our brains make better connections and
overall remember things more effectively
when we space out our learning over time
here's how Pierce J Howard the author of
my least favorite book to haul into
coffee shops puts it work involving
higher mental functions such as analysis
and synthesis needs to be spaced out in
order to allow new neural connections to
Sol ify new learning drives out old
learning when insufficient time
intervenes and we've actually known
about this effect for quite a long time
back in the late 1800s a psychologist
named heran ebbinghouse basically
launched the field of memory science
Itself by embarking upon an intense
study where he made himself memorize
long long lists of nonsense syllables
and through that research he eventually
came to develop What's called the
forgetting curve which describes how
memories Decay over time but what he
also learned is that by spacing out his
efforts to memorize these lists he could
put in less actual study time to get
them memorized perfectly for example for
one list of 12 syllables he found that
it took him 68 repetitions on one day
and then seven repetitions the next day
to memorize it perfectly but by spacing
out his studying over the course of 3
days he found he could achieve the same
level of perfection in only 38
repetitions over the past 130 years
since he published his findings lots of
other Studies have been able to
replicate the same positive results
which leads us to the question why does
the spacing effect work well to put it
in simple terms it turns out that one of
the most important parts of the learning
process is actually forgetting now what
forgetting truly is is a subject for
another video that I'll publish in the
future but the most important thing to
note here is that the more we've
forgotten something that is the harder
we have to work to retrieve it since we
last learned it or studied it the
greater the increase in learning will be
to make this a bit more clear here's how
the author Benedict kery who wrote the
book how we learn explains it some
amount of breakdown must occur for us to
strengthen learning when we revisit the
material without a little forgetting you
get no benefit from further study it is
what allows learning to build like an
exercised muscle and that's the main
reason why Carrie calls space repetition
one of the most powerful methods for
remembering what you learn in his book
and I would add to that the fact that
you can do this with basically any other
learning technique it's entirely
complimentary because it's all about
just modifying the time periods in which
you study you can do anything within
those time periods you're just using the
time periods as intelligently as
possible with that being said now I want
to get into how you can put space
repetition into action and implement it
into your own study systems and we're
going to talk about apps and computer
programs that you can use in a minute
here but first I want to talk about a
system that you can use with your paper
flash cards which is called the Lightner
system and here's how it works the first
step is to decide on a number of boxes
that you're going to use to hold the
cards in your system now I don't
actually own little boxes so I've just
substituted rubber bands and sticky
notes that say box but that actually
works just as well and actually makes
the system more portable so that's
pretty cool and from there each
individual box is going to represent a
different study time interval so box one
might be studying every day box two
might be studied every other day and so
on and when you're studying your cards
in the boxes every time you get a card
right it's going to graduate to the next
box so you're going to see it less and
less often but if you get a card wrong
it's going to go all the way to box
number one no matter where it was and by
using this system you get two main
benefits number one you're maximizing
your learning through the spacing effect
but number two you're also studying more
efficiently because you're spending more
time in the cards that need the most
attention and less time on the ones you
know really well rather than studying
every single card equally now this paper
system works really well for both of
those goals but if you want to take
advantage of more advanced scheduling
algorithms and other features you're
going to need to find yourself a space
repetition app and there are a lot of
contenders in this area but I want to
focus first on what is probably the most
popular one right now and that is called
Anki Anki has a huge Community it's
insanely customizable and best of all it
has apps for almost every platform out
there and almost all of them are free
with the exception of the iPhone app
which oddly costs a whopping $25 now I
think the price is that high because
it's their way of basically letting
people support the app since it's free
everywhere else but if you're on an
iPhone and you don't want to pay that
much fear not because Anki also has a
companion web app called eny Web which
is accessible from mobile Safari so you
can use that for free if you want now
with Anki creating cards is really
really easy and I really like the fact
that you can add basically any kind of
media you want to your cards including
pictures which is awesome because adding
pictures to your flash cards can really
help increase retention however the
killer feature of Anki is the ability to
rate cards based on difficulty when
you're studying them so essentially when
you turn a card over you can tell the
program how hard it was for you to
dredge the answer up from the depths of
your memory and it will use that data to
decide how long it's going to be before
you see that card again and that's
really the main strength of space
repetition apps versus a paper system
each individual card can be tracked can
have a difficulty rating and can be
adjusted in the algorithm so you're
getting the most benefit of the spacing
effect Anki is definitely not the only
space repetition app out there though so
if you're looking for Alternatives I've
got a few things in mind for you to take
a look at number one one being an app
called tiny cards which I showed off in
my previous video on how to make better
flash cards now tiny cards is only for
the iPhone unfortunately but there
should be an Android version coming soon
and honestly when compared to Anki I
think it's a lot more simple a lot
prettier and the process of making cards
is more fun and faster because they have
an excellent system for adding images to
your cards aside from Tiny cards there
are also apps like flashcards Deluxe
memorize super memo nemosine tic Quizlet
and probably a bunch of others that I
don't even know about right now but but
I'm sure you will let me know about down
in the comments so before I wrap this
video up I have a couple more things I
want to mention number one being that
the script I wrote for this video is
actually about half the length of the
blog post I wrote so if you want a lot
more detail especially pertaining to the
memory bits and how the spacing effect
works you can click the blog post Link
in the description down below or on the
card on screen right now and read to
your heart's content also and I have
been really excited to announce this for
quite a long time now there is now an
official college infogeek t-shirt on
dftba.com and I am super super stoked
about this I've already ordered mine and
there's going to be a link down in the
description also a card so if you would
like to get your very own shirt which
may or may not Grant superpowers you can
click either of those links and order
one now one cool thing about the shirt's
design is it was actually created by the
college infogeek Community my good
friend Ashley did the handletter design
itself but the Mantra or the saying on
the shirt was actually decided upon by
people in the college and vate community
over on Reddit which I think is really
really cool and I would love to continue
to play up this community aspect so if
you get a shirt I would love to see you
tweeting awesome pictures of you wearing
it so just send them to me over on Tom
Frankle and I will probably retweet them
you can also put them in the Reddit as
well if you like and other than that
that's all I have for this video guys so
thanks so much for watching if you found
it useful give it a like to support this
Channel and you can also subscribe with
that button right down there if you want
to get new videos on being a more
effective student every single week you
can also get a copy of my book on
earning better grades by going to the
picture of the book right there and
clicking your mouse button you can find
the previous video right over there
which was about how to use flashcards
more effectively and if you want to find
that awesome article which is way more
detailed than this video was go to the
full article thing right there if you'd
like to connect with me you can use the
social media links down below but
there's also a nonzero probability that
you can connect with me by yelling into
a con shell so maybe give that a try too