hey what's up guys so this is another
episode of Five Lessons which is a
little mini show here on this channel
where I take useful lessons from a book
that I have read recently and share them
with you and on today's episode I'm
going to be sharing some lessons from
the productivity project which is a book
that tries to cover productivity in kind
of a general sense now I haven't read a
whole lot of other books that are huge
overviews of productivity I've
definitely gotten into more specific
books on things like habits but I
haven't really read any of the other
General productivity books out there so
I can't really make a comparison here
that being said I really enjoyed this
book and I wanted to provide you with
five of the best lessons that I took
from it starting with the first one
which is actually the subtitle of the
book accomplishing more by managing your
time attention and energy and that's
really Chris's main idea in this book
which is that productivity is the
product of managing your time attention
and energy equally and these three
resources are vitally important and they
are all equally important now in past
Generations where people worked in
factories or when they worked on Farms
time was the most important element you
punched into the right time you did work
that wasn't incredibly mentally taxing
didn't require a whole lot of creativity
and there weren't a whole lot of
distractions to kind of pull you away
from that work so time really was the
most important aspect but today more of
us are doing creatively demanding work
that requires a lot more knowledge
requires a lot more brain power and
because of that our energy and our
attention are just as important as our
time and I think this is really
important to think about deliberately
because time management is probably the
aspect that is most asked about and most
focused on but when you have a
productivity problem it's just as
important to ask yourself am I managing
my energy correctly am I managing my
attention correctly or am I trying to
put in too many hours and trying to
brute force my way to more productivity
and learning this and kind of
integrating into your life will help you
to do things like take more regular
breaks to pay more attention to your
health to sleep to get more hydration to
go exercise even though these things
take away from the raw amount of hours
you can work they're going to make you
more productive so lesson number one
this is the big overview of the book
when you're trying to make yourself more
productive try to consider all three of
these factors so the second lesson that
I wanted to share with you from this
book is that there are six
procrastination triggers basically
facets or aspects of a task that make
your brain more averse to doing them so
the six triggers are whether a task is
boring difficult frustrating
unstructured or ambiguous lacking in
personal meaning and lacking in
intrinsic value such as it's fun or it's
intriguing to do so the next time you
find yourself procrastinating you can
sit down and ask yourself for this task
that I don't want to do which of these
triggers are present is it boring well
maybe I can change my location and go to
a coffee shop that makes it more fun to
work on is it frustrating or is it
unstructured well maybe I can break it
down into some concretely defined steps
and then tell myself this is the very
next step to work on I have a very clear
Vision in my mind of what the road is
forward and now I can start working on
it the third lesson that I took from
this book is that each of us has our own
individual time during the day where
where both our energy levels and our
ability to focus are highest it's not
the same across the board and Chris
calls this the biological prime time and
he discovered his own biological prime
time through the results of two
different experiments first he took the
often sighted advice that the early bird
gets the worm and tried an experiment
where he woke up at 5:30 a.m. every
single morning thinking this will
obviously make me an all powerful
productivity robot and the results of
that experiment were diametrically
opposed to those expectations Chris
found that number one he absolutely
hated getting up at 5:30 in the morning
and hated going to bed as early as he
needed to to get up and get enough sleep
but also it really didn't make him any
more productive than he usually was so
he scrapped that experiment and did a
second one where he recorded his energy
levels at each hour throughout the day
for a certain number of days and what he
found that was for him between 10:00
a.m. and noon and then 5:00 p.m. to 8:00
p.m. his energy levels and his ability
to focus were highest so as a result he
now considers that time sacred and he
tries to schedule his most important
most challeng in and most rewarding work
during those hours he doesn't put
meetings there he doesn't put any sort
of like maintenance tasks there all
those tasks are relegated to the other
hours when his ability to focus is a
little bit lower now the fourth lesson
from this book is a really interesting
one that I had actually not heard of at
all before and it's that our future
selves are actually the same as
strangers to our present selves
perception Chris talked to a UCLA
researcher who put people in brain
scanning machines and asked them to
think about strangers and then to think
about both their present selves and
their future selves and what he found is
that when people think about strangers
they actually have the same brain scans
the same activity in the same brain
regions as when they think about their
future selves and by contrast when they
think about their present selves their
brain scans are quite different which
shows that when we think about our
present selves we do not consider the
same limitations the same stresses the
same stuff we're going through right now
even though logically we can tell
ourselves that the future version of
oursel will probably be going through
those same things so what Chris actually
did is he used an app called Aging Booth
to create an old looking picture of
himself basically himself in several
years and he put it up on his wall now I
did that and I'm probably not going to
put this on my wall but it did teach me
to start to deliberately think about
what my schedule is going to look like a
few weeks in advance because if I don't
think about it deliberately I can think
Oh My Future Self is going to be you
know totally Carefree there's nothing
going to be going on sure I'll take that
meeting in you know two months or 3
months even though logically I can look
at my calendar 3 months ago I can look
at my calendar now and I know that my
schedule does not get less busy over
time the opposite is true and the fifth
and final lesson from this book is
actually something that Chris learned
himself from David Allen the author of
another book called getting things done
and it's to have in addition to your
task list you know your to-do list a
waiting for list basically a list of all
the things that you're waiting on
someone else to do before you can take
action on it or before it can be
finished so if somebody owes you money
or you're waiting for someone to respond
to an email or maybe you're waiting for
a package to be delivered these are all
things that kind of weigh on your mind
they're things that have sort of a a
part in your life but you can't do
anything to resolve them right now so
it's good to have a separate list of
those things and to check it maybe once
or twice a month at least just to make
sure that for everything where the ball
isn't currently in your court it does
come back and it doesn't slip through
the cracks so those are five of the
lessons I learned from the productivity
project overall I really enjoyed this
book and I found that it was a pretty
good overview of many of the different
problems we face when trying to be
productive if you want to see other
recommendations I have for books that I
think every student should read you can
check out my Essential books for
students list which you can get to by
clicking the card on the screen right
now or the link down in the description
otherwise hopefully you enjoyed this
video if you did and you found it useful
you can give it a like to support this
channel also if you want to get new tips
on how to be more effective student
every single week you can click the
Subscribe button right down there and if
you'd like to get a free copy of my book
which is about how to earn better grades
and study more effectively you can click
the picture right there and I will send
one to your email if you'd like to check
out the last video in the Five Lessons
series you can go right there it's a
video on The Power of Habit by Charles
doig which I absolutely love and if
you'd like to find the full article for
this video with some more tips and extra
resource links click the full article
button right there if you want to
connect with me I am most responsive to
smoke signals so you're going to want to
build a big bonfire but don't do it in
the middle of a forest otherwise Smokey
the Bear is going to have some Choice
words with you anyway thanks for
watching and I will see you in next
week's video