hey what's going on guys so as you can
see the set is finally rebuilt and along
with it to my new studio slash office is
coming together quite nicely over the
past couple of days I've been able to
check off many different items in my
little studio rebuilding project in my
to do list and speaking up to-do lists
well we got to talk about those because
I get a lot of questions about which a
poor tool out there is the best one for
managing your tasks so in today's video
I want to try to answer that question
and to do so I'm gonna be sharing my top
three to-do list applications that I
think are gonna be the best options for
most people and I'm also gonna throw in
one kind of oddball recommendation that
doesn't really fit in with the other
three but might be useful for certain
viewers so let's get into it all right
so the number one app of my list which
you've probably seen if you've ever
looked at the resources page in my
website or asked me about it on Twitter
is todoist now back when I was in
college I used to use a task management
app called wonder list and I absolutely
loved it but a few years ago Microsoft
actually bought it and they made the
announcement that I was eventually going
to be going away and as a result I moved
over to todoist and just to kind of
spoil this video a little bit for you I
think that to duyst is probably the best
to-do app out there in terms of features
and capabilities and the number one
feature that offers something that I
find invaluable in my workflow is
natural language processing which means
that you can add tasks along with all
the details needed for those tasks such
as tags and due dates and assignees and
things like that
just by typing what you want in the main
task bar or by saying it I'm also a big
fan of the quick add feature when I'm
using the app on my desktop or in the
browser I can just hit the letter Q or I
can just hit the plus button on my
iPhone and I can easily enter a task in
seconds and that reduces a lot of
friction in my system additionally I'm a
big fan of its integration with voice
assistance it's got Siri integration and
it's also got Amazon echo integration
and don't worry I'm not going to say the
a-word in this video but if I want to I
can easily tell my echo to add a task
and it gets automatically added to my
inbox and I love that since I have
several of them in my house
that being said not everything is
perfect with the duyst I do think of the
way it handles subtasks is a little
dated I'm not a big fan of how you just
indent things in your main tasks list
instead of having a real subtasks view
and additionally the Windows app doesn't
work quite like the dust
app the Mac app or even the mobile apps
it's got kind of a different UI and it
doesn't work quite as well additionally
to do us is not the cheapest app in the
personal productivity space especially
since they just raise their prices to
four dollars a month so that might be a
bit of a turn-off though it is worth
mentioning that there is a student
discount though they did make the
baffling decision to require people to
sign up for a business account before
asking for it but even still it reduces
the price down to about a buck fifty per
month so if you are a college student
that is an option for you however if you
are a price conscious person or you're
just somebody who doesn't want to pay a
monthly subscription fee for your to do
list app then there's something else
that you're gonna want to look at and
that is Microsoft to do so let me level
with you here if you're somebody who
just does not want to pay for to do list
application and you have simple needs
then I think Microsoft Sidhu is the
absolute best option on the market right
now a couple of years ago I would not
have made this recommendation as when it
came out as the replacement for
wunderlist there are a lot of missing
features but over the past couple of
years Microsoft's team has added a lot
of needed features to the app and
honestly it's pretty darn good
especially for having absolutely no
premium tier whatsoever you've got the
ability to make multiple projects you
can color code those projects subtasks
actually work like they're supposed to
and unlike to do it's free plan you can
add comments and file attachments to
your tasks in Microsoft to do without
paying anything this is actually the
main reason why I recommend Microsoft to
do over to do is to free plan if you
just don't want to pay
I do think to do is this more powerful
overall but I think a lot of people are
gonna want the ability to add
descriptions and comments to their tasks
like say if you want to set up a p.o box
need to put the address at the post
office box in the task you have to pay
for that to duyst now granted Microsoft
to do does not have natural language
features so you do have to set your due
dates and stuff like that manually but
if you want something simple I think it
really works and it also has some pretty
cool features that you're not gonna find
in other apps such as the my day feature
which doesn't pull tasks based on due
dates but instead lets you manually add
tasks from your lists now of course
there are some things with Microsoft to
do that I don't like for instance there
isn't a dedicated mac app right now so
just like to do it on the windows side
I've got to use Microsoft to do in the
browser
additionally like I said earlier it is
not quite as powerful as other apps like
to duyst you don't have the net
our language features you don't have
tags and filters and smart lists and
things like that but again if you don't
want to pay and you want something
simple I think it is a very compelling
option that brings us to my third
recommendation on this list just now
called ticktick and if you've ever used
tik tik before you probably know that it
is your really similar to todoist just
like to do us it's got those natural
language features which allow you to get
tasks into your system very quickly and
have it just parse all the information
you want instead of having to set it
yourself it's got tags you can add your
tasks and it's got something called
smart lists which function basically the
exact same way that filters do in
todoist but there are some features in
ticktick that you're not going to find
in todoist for example there is a
built-in calendar view so if you want to
look your tasks on a by week or by month
basis you can actually do that
there are start times you can add to
your tasks which I don't personally use
but some people find to be very useful
there is a built-in Pomodoro timer which
can actually be tied to your tasks so if
you want to do Pomodoro's throughout the
day and actually bind them to the tasks
you have in your system you can do that
and subtasks actually work the way that
they should you click into a task and
you can see your subtasks along with all
the related information like file
attachments and comments beyond that
there are even more features in tick
ticks such as desktop widgets which I
kind of irrationally love not sure why I
like them so much but it's kind of cool
to have like a semi-transparent box on
my desktop with all my tasks and on the
mobile side there's a feature called
plan my day which helps to intelligently
plan out what you want to get done on a
given day given all these features and
the fact that tick tick is cheaper than
todoist at $28 a year versus their $36 a
year it might seem like tick tick is the
better option and for some people it
might be but there are a few caveats for
one tick tick does have those natural
language features but they're not as
strong as the ones found in todoist
for example I can't use T om for
tomorrow I actually have to type out the
entire thing and when I'm using a really
complex request like having a task with
a specific first due date along with a
recurring option it can't really parse
it to do is handle it like a champ but I
have to go in and manually set that kind
of thing up in ticktick additionally
there is no two way google calendar sync
and tick ticks so while you do have that
built in calendar view if you want to
actually look at it on your Google
Calendar you can't quite do that as well
as you can on todoist
and perhaps most importantly of all
their free plan is there
you can only have nine lists that brings
us to my oddball recommendation which
really isn't that odd it just kind of
exists outside of the realm of these
simple to-do list style apps that most
you guys are probably familiar with so
my final recommendation for this video
is something called click up which is an
app that you would probably categorize
as project management software instead
of a simple to-do list app project
management apps which don't really
include the tools we've already talked
about but do include tools like asana
and JIRA and click up are a little
better suited for managing really
complex projects with lots of moving
parts different tasks statuses and for
managing teams now for a long time I was
a big asana user mainly because my
friend Matt got me on it and it was
pretty useful but after testing click up
I think it is probably the most useful
and most full-featured project
management app that I've ever tried and
it might also work for personal
productivity hiccup gives you eight
hundred ways to look at your tasks
you've got a normal list view you've got
a board view which is kind of Trello or
Kanban style you've got a calendar view
or you can go full project manager and
even look at Gantt charts when it comes
to creating tasks you basically have all
the options there's a full-fledged
hybrid markdown editor for descriptions
that rivals notions or slights there's
the ability to add subtasks and
checklists and you can generate these
checklists from templates in fact you
can generate entire tasks from templates
and of course you get your due dates for
current due dates with more options and
you can shake a stick at there's task
Watchers and you can even assign
multiple people to one task and then
there are the tools there's the ability
to minimize tasks to a task tray which
kind of gives you the ability to make a
little daily list of tasks you're gonna
work on there's a notepad feature built
into the app for making just scratch
notes and possibly my favorite
additional tool is their Chrome
extension because it lets you take a
screenshot of a web page and append it
to an existing task or make a new task
out of it and when Martin and I were
working on fixing some bugs on the
college info geek website this was
actually really really useful so if you
were the kind of person who wants
incredibly fine-grained control over
every aspect of your life or you want to
take heavy advantage of templating and
team features then click up might be
something to look at
that being said after testing click up
extensively for a couple of weeks with
my team I ended up making the decision
to move us all back to duyst and the
main reason for doing that is that click
up just gives us too many options and we
found that there was
friction involve and adding new tasks to
the system and figuring out where they
should go
whereas in todoist we can use those
natural language features to get
something into the system really quickly
however during that testing period I was
really impressed with all the different
features they're offering and I do think
that it offers a lot more flexibility
and capabilities than similar apps like
asana so for a certain kind of person
it's going to be a pretty compelling
option so that brings us to the final
question which is which of these apps is
the best one and it's kind of hard to
answer that question objectively since
everyone has different needs so I'm
going to give you a couple of different
recommendations first and foremost if
you don't want to pay for your task
management software then Microsoft to do
is really compelling if you really want
the natural language features then maybe
to do as free planets for you otherwise
if you want something simple you want
something that works and has some pretty
cool features all of its own then
Microsoft to do is pretty cool if you
are willing to pay a few bucks a month
for a subscription though for my money
at least todoist is the best general
task management app out there for most
people
now ticktick is really compelling it's
quite similar and it does have a few
additional features like that Pomodoro
timer but at least for me the superior
natural language processing which allows
me to get tasks into my system more
accurately and more quickly gives
todoist at the edge now regardless of
which task management at the end up
going with one of the tasks that you
should put on it and do as soon as you
possibly can is getting yourself a
domain name it's no secret that more and
more companies are relying on the
internet to find their job candidates so
if you want to position yourself as the
best possible person for that job you're
looking forward then you should be
looking to establish a strong personal
brand online and a really important part
of that process is building yourself a
website where you can communicate your
skills show off your portfolio and make
it really easy for people to contact you
and of course the first step to doing
that is securing a domain name for
yourself something that you can link to
from your online profiles and even put
on your resume and business cards and
the best place on the internet to get
that domain name is hover unlike some
other places however makes the process
of getting a domain name is super easy
in fact I just bought one this morning
and the process took less than 30
seconds there are no annoying upsells
nothing to get your way just a
frictionless and streamlined at checkout
process plus with over 400 different
domain extensions to choose from like
the classic coms and dot meas just some
more interesting ones like lol and ninja
you've got
a lot of choices and once you've got
that domain name you can easily set up a
professional email address for it or use
their connect feature to automatically
hook it up to different website builders
like Squarespace and Shopify so head
over to hover.com slash Thomas Frank to
get your domain name before somebody
else does and if you use that link which
you'll find in the description down
below you're also gonna get 10% off your
first purchase
big thanks to hover for sponsoring this
video of being a big supporter of my
channel and as always thank you guys so
much for watching if you enjoyed this
video hit that like button you can also
subscribe right there to get new videos
every single week when they come out or
click right there to get a copy of my
book on how to earn better grades for
free if for some reason you don't want
to click on either of those boxes you
can go follow me on instagram @ Tom
frankly or click right over here to see
one more video on this channel thanks
for watching and I'll see you in next
one