hey what's up guys so today we're going
to talk about textbooks and I want to
bring to bear all the knowledge that
I've gained both as a recent college
graduate and also as a quite Adept user
of Google if I do say so myself to help
you pay as little money as possible for
these things and before we get into the
thick of it I just want to mention that
I wrote an article a little while ago
that goes into uh more in-depth detail
on each of the tips that I'm going to go
through in this video and also provides
links to many of the resources that I
talk about so if you want to check that
out after watching or maybe just right
now you can click my Faceook or the card
or the thing down in the doo Bibby Bop
or if you have telepathic Powers you can
just go to it with those either way
let's get into it so in my experience
the process to getting the best possible
deal in your textbooks starts by getting
the list of the books you need as early
as you possibly can as with most things
in life giving yourself ample time to
prepare will result in the best possible
outcome by getting the list of the books
you need early you give yourself time to
hunt for bargains but you also give
yourself time to email your professors
this is what I did as a student what I
recommend doing just email them
introduce yourself briefly and ask them
two different questions number one how
often is the book going to be used and
number two is it okay to buy an old
edition of the book or do you absolutely
need the current edition and when you
email just make sure you're polite and
let them know that you're just trying to
be budget conscious in my experience
most professors completely understand
and once you have these two pieces of
information you can start doing a couple
of different things number one if the
book is not going to be used very often
then you might actually be able to just
go to the library and find a version
they have for free or you can decide to
share a copy of the book with somebody
in your class second if it turns out you
don't need the current edition then that
means you can buy an old Edition and in
my experience I've gotten old editions
of textbooks that cost like $87 for the
newest edition for a dollar on Amazon so
it really can be worth it and let's face
it a lot of textbooks do not need a new
edition every couple of years like if
you're taking a French history class as
a genm then you don't need to know about
all the minute discoveries about the
Napoleonic Wars that have happened since
2013 if you're really that curious you
could just go to the Wikipedia page and
look at the citations for new books but
you're not that curious now the the
alternative to emailing your professors
and asking about books or the plan of
action if they don't reply is what I
like to call book gambling and this is
the act of simply waiting until the
semester begins to buy your books to
figure out if you really need them or
not and as a student my policy with book
gambling was this if I could get the
book within one day if I really needed
it then I would go ahead and book gamble
otherwise I took the safe road and
bought the book as cheaply as possible
before the semester started because some
classes really get into the thick of it
during the first week and to me it
really wasn't worth the stress of
falling behind just to save a couple of
bucks all right for the next step of the
process let's talk about the library if
you go to a big enough University
there's a good chance that some of your
text books can be found at your library
however I really wouldn't trust copies
of the book that can be checked out by
other students because when it comes
test time or when it comes time that you
really need the book it's likely to be
gone so what you want to look for are
Reserve copies which are copies of the
book the library will let people use in
the building but not check out and with
those you have a much better chance of
getting your hands on one when you do
need it aside from using the library the
other way to absolve yourself from at
least some of the financial
responsibility of buying books is to
share them with other students and the
best way to do this is to wait till the
semester starts and to find a group or a
partner in class that you can share with
but this requires book gambling so one
thing you can do if you don't want to
book gamble is to use Facebook groups to
potentially find students who you can
share books with to do this you can just
search for your University class of 2016
or whatever your graduation year is and
then you can probably find many
different official groups for that year
and in there you can make a post just
asking if anybody is taking your class
and would like to share a book also it's
a good idea to search for other
graduation years since lots of different
students from different years might be
in your class all right so now we have
finally made it to the point in the
process where you actually have to start
buying your books and in a moment I'm
going to talk about several different
websites and online resources you can
use to get the best deals but before
that I want to talk about what might be
the absolute best deal in your area
getting books from other students there
are probably a lot of students on your
campus who have already taken the
classes you're going to take and the
ones that still own their textbooks
might be willing to sell them to you for
cheap if you can make these kind of
deals happen they're usually win-win for
both parties since on their end they're
going to get more than the campus
bookstore would give them which is two
pennies and a pile of leaves and on your
end you're going to pay less than the
campus bookstore would charge you if you
live on campus and you happen to live
around a lot of people at the same major
as you then these deals are usually
pretty easy to put together otherwise
Facebook groups are once again a good
option and if you have any specific sort
of on-campus messaging system or
bulletin board then you can try those as
well in the case that older students
refuse to sell you their textbooks and
instead they give you a swirly and steal
your lunch money well then here are your
other options and I want to start with
the Oddball ones starting with one
called Bounce
now this is actually kind of the wrong
section of the video to put boundless in
but it fits because it's a website
boundless doesn't actually charge you
for their textbooks instead they make
open- Source online textbooks which use
open source Creative Commons data but
they structure it in the way that many
popular textbooks do so if you don't
need a specific textbook for your class
but you do just need a general outline
of the information in detail then a lot
of their subjects may be suitable for
your needs the second Oddball site I
want to talk about is called packback
books and this is going to be useful for
those times when you have a textbook
that's required but is not used very
often basically what packback does is
allows you to rent digital textbooks for
five bucks a day so instead of having to
rent it for an entire semester and pay
like 40 bucks or 50 bucks or whatever if
you just need the book for two different
tests throughout the semester then you
end up paying just 10 bucks for two days
of renting now if those sites don't work
for you then there are plenty of
traditional textbook sites out there and
the ones that I used as a student
include Amazon CH and textbook rush but
there are plenty of others like a books
book renter textbooks.com and many many
others and because there are so many of
these I recommend using a price
comparison tool to compare the prices
across all of them and the ones I know
about specifically include student rate
textbooks slug books and bigw with any
of these tools you can just put in the
book's ISBN number or the title of the
author and then it'll pull up the book
and query all the different sites out
there to figure out which one has the
lowest price it's also good to note that
you have several different options for
the formats of the books you want to get
for instance you can buy or rent you can
go physical or digital or you can get
combinations of both for instance as a
student I made use of digital rentals a
lot and you also might be able to find
International additions of the books you
need these are often black and white
instead of color or paperback instead of
hard cover but usually they have the
exact same content and are much cheaper
two last things to note here number one
don't discount brick and mortar stores
if you have like a secondhand bookstore
in your area or if your campus bookstore
sells used editions then you might
actually find a better price there than
you can online and secondly if you're
going to plan on selling your textbooks
at the end of the semester then go on
Amazon and see what the buyback prices
are right now because you might actually
come out ahead if you buy and
subsequently sell than if you rent all
right so that is the point where we're
going to wrap this video now I know you
might be in a weird situation where
maybe your school forces you to buy new
books or maybe you have to buy one of
those books that comes with an online
code that can only be used once which I
absolutely hate those kind of books but
in any case hopefully you found at least
a couple of useful tips in this video
that can save you money on at least a
few of the books you have to buy in the
future once again if you'd like to dig
into the article I wrote for this video
that has even more detail you can click
the card or link down in the doob Bobby
bop and if you you have tips that I
didn't mention in this video share them
Below in the comments so other people
can benefit from them that's all I've
got for this week so if you enjoyed this
video and you found it helpful then give
it a like to support this Channel and I
will see you in next week's video thanks
for
watching hey there guys thanks so much
for watching this video now if you want
to get new tips every single week on how
to be a more effective student you click
that big red subscribe button right
there and also if you want a free copy
of my book on how to earn better grades
you can click the picture of the book
and I'll send you one if you want to
check out the article that goes along
with this video click the orange logo
right there and if you missed last
week's video we talked about how you can
bounce back failure so check it out if
you missed it lastly if you want to
connect with me I'm Tom Frankle on both
Instagram and Twitter or you can leave a
comment down
below