this video is sponsored by skillshare if
you want to make better first
impressions with people you meet build
good relationships over time and in
general live a more successful life one
of the simplest things you can do is be
punctual be where you're supposed to be
when you're supposed to be there of
course that's easier said than done
because most of us live pretty complex
lives we've got class we've got work
we've got meetings we've got secret back
room deals to get to so it's not always
the easiest task to keep a perfect
record of your schedule up in the three
pounds of mushy cranial material inside
your head and honestly you shouldn't
even be trying as david allen the
original productivity guru once wrote
your brain is for having ideas not for
holding them so today you my friend are
entering calendar bootcamp now your
calendar is a part of what i love to
call the productivity system which is a
combination of external tools that come
together kind of like voltron robots to
form this cohesive real world source of
truth for everything going on your life
that includes tasks ideas contacts and
of course events so today i'm going to
teach you how to set up the calendar
part of that system so that it never
fails you and accomplishing that goal
means following three simple rules
number one set up your calendar in a way
that suits you number two add events and
relevant information to those events and
number three get information out of your
calendar at the right time and the right
time might not be what you think it is
so let's kick this off with rule number
one set up your calendar in a way that
suits you and that starts with choosing
a calendar system in the first place
leading us to the inevitable age-old
question what kind of calendar is best
physical or digital and if the answer is
digital what's the best calendar app
well in the world of fitness there's
this old adage the best workout program
is the one that you will actually stick
to the most hyper-optimized program for
olympians is going to be useless to you
if you don't enjoy it or if you don't
have time to stick with it that's
actually why i work with lifting coach
if i have a super busy week or if i'm
traveling matt can just adjust my
programming accordingly and i stick to
my workout and the same is true for
calendar apps and productivity apps in
general the best one is the one that
you'll actually use and stick to now
personally i like google calendar some
of my friends like apple calendar better
my mom actually sticks with an old
school wall calendar that works for her
these are all legitimate choices because
a calendar is really a personal tool
that has one main job acting as that
external source of truth for your life's
events so as i mentioned earlier google
calendar is my personal calendar app of
choice that's because it is free i can
pull it up on my computer and my phone
which is always with me and that's nice
even my watch and it also has some
integrations with other apps like
savvycal which i use for scheduling
meetings with other people and not doing
email tag so for that reason we're going
to be using google calendar as the
visual example in this video but i do
want to mention that there are some
other great apps out there i've got a
companion article for this video and
you'll see them listed there and in
general i will note that again for me i
do think that digital calendar apps have
some very compelling advantages over
paper calendars namely recurring event
support and reminder support which is
very nice but if you want to use a paper
calendar or paper planner like this one
that's totally cool too and there are
some advantages to paper calendars as
well do you always carry that calendar
in your pocket
yes for one it's pretty hard to get
sucked into instagram or tick talk when
you're adding an event to your paper
calendar and also you can use markers
and highlighters to make your paper
calendar
now one thing that i like to do when i'm
setting up my calendar is divide the
different types of events in my life
into groups that i call life buckets and
this was especially helpful when i was a
student and had a much more chaotic life
because i had work shifts i had class i
had exams i had on-campus events i had
scheduled study blocks with study
partners and friends tons of different
things going on in all kinds of
different categories and i think a lot
of you are going to be in the same boat
we live very complex multifaceted lives
in many cases so doing this just gives
you some visual separation on your
calendar and just gives you a better
bird's eye view of everything you have
going on in your life now in google
calendar you can easily choose the color
of each event and you can divide your
events up into life buckets that way but
i like to go one step further and create
an actual separate calendar for each of
these buckets that gives me a couple of
different advantages number one i can
set a default color for every single
event type but number two and more
importantly i can set up default
notification preferences for each of
these different calendars and that's
very useful because i sometimes do want
to get notified about events like for
appointments but i don't need
notifications for every single event on
my calendar like scheduled self-study
time in the morning i don't need to be
notified about that i know i'm gonna do
it rule number two is to add events to
your calendar kind of obvious but also
add relevant information to those events
so in order for your counter to be that
trusted external source of truth you
have to actually add events to it but
for a lot of people especially over the
long term that's kind of easier said
than done because a lot of calendar
systems have a lot of friction and when
there's friction involved in a system
especially a productivity system we
start getting tempted to just try to
remember things we go against that david
allen advice from the beginning of the
video we're trying to hold ideas in our
head instead of externalizing them and
that's not good so what we're going to
do in this section is go over several
different tips for getting events into
your calendar painlessly and with less
friction but also how to make those
events more useful to you as well and
let's start with optimizing for quick
capture in the world of productivity the
idea behind quick capture is that the
faster you can get something into your
system be it a task an event an idea a
contact the more likely it is that
you're actually going to do so and there
are a lot of tools out there that try to
optimize for this there are gtd style
inboxes a single default place where you
basically just dump everything when
you're on the go and then process it
later my ultimate tasks task manager
notion template has one built in for
calendar events there are also some
quick capture tools out there the one
that i use personally is an app called
fantastical now earlier i said that i
use google calendar as my calendar
system but what i actually do is import
those calendars into fantastical which
is both an iphone app and a mac app and
what that gets me access to is
fantastical's natural language
processing for adding events and if
you've ever used todoist you're probably
familiar with this in todoist you can
type out all the details of a task in
the quick ad bar and if you have like a
project tag or a due date to do this
we'll parse that information and add it
where it's supposed to be and
fantastical has the exact same feature
pulls out details like location date and
time so basically i can just type or in
many cases speak the event right into
the title and it's going to get all the
information and put it in the right
place which is really really nice i also
keep fantastical's widget on the front
page of my home screen so i can just tap
in there and tap the add event button
and that's a tip that works for pretty
much any calendar app that does have
widgets our next tip is a pretty big one
here and it's to use recurring events
this is another area where like i said
earlier digital calendars have a huge
advantage over physical calendars if you
have events that repeat like something
that happens every single day or every
week or heck the third wednesday of
every other month in a digital calendar
app you can go and set up a recurring
event so all you have to do is put in
the events details once specify how it
repeats and if it ends and that's always
going to be on your calendar at the
right time so those are a couple of tips
for getting events into your calendar
more quickly but what about making those
events more useful to you well one thing
that i love to do is add relevant
information about an event into the
description field of that event i do
this all the time because when i'm going
to an event when it's about to start my
calendar is the most relevant piece of
my productivity system with respect to
that event i don't want to be digging
through my email i don't want to be
digging through my note-taking system if
there's information about an event i'm
just going to open up my calendar and
find it there another useful tip is to
add optional events to your calendar
your set in stone schedule isn't the
only thing that can be on your calendar
you can also basically give yourself
options so as an example i'm currently
taking a course to get my professional
barbell coach certification and the
course comes with optional coaching
calls that i can get on every week with
higher level coaches who answer
questions and go through different
topics and i'm really busy i've got
these videos to make i've got notion
templates to make i can't always make
these calls but i always put them on my
calendar in a special life bucket called
edu opportunities so that when the time
comes if i do happen to have time i can
choose whether or not to attend and
another tip that's kind of along the
same lines here create reference
calendars for useful information useful
schedules so back in college my
professors like most professors had
office hours so at the beginning of the
semester i would get all the office
hours from my professors and i would put
them in my own calendar called professor
office hours and normally this was
hidden by default i didn't want to gunk
it up my own schedule but in the case
that i needed to see a professor i could
easily just turn the calendar on and see
when their free time when their office
hours coincided with me having some time
on my schedule and this is also very
useful for things like basketball court
schedules open gym schedules anything
that you want to reference and
cross-reference with your own schedule
make a reference calendar for it and
finally this is a tip that i shared over
on my twitter the other day and it's
more of like a general personal
development tip but if you find yourself
with your long-term goals at odds with
your short-term desires if you find
yourself skipping workouts or not
cooking when you're supposed to start
scheduling things start scheduling time
to work on your goals whether it's
instrument practice or workouts or
cooking dinner because when you schedule
something you remove ambiguity from the
choice and a lot of times when we are
trying to do things that we know are
good for us we are dealing with a lot of
ambiguity and that contributes to the
resistance and the likelihood that we're
just gonna go play video games so when
you schedule it when you put it in your
calendar you're basically saying i want
to be beholden to my past self and i'm
adding some specificity to this goal and
it's gonna make it much easier to
actually do it and it should boost your
motivation a bit and now we move on to
rule number three get information from
your calendar and get it at the right
time i've got two big tips that you're
going to want to follow so you actually
get stuff from your calendar number one
check your calendar every day this is a
very simple tip but a lot of people skip
it a lot of people don't look at their
calendars even if they're adding offense
to it and that doesn't make the calendar
very useful so right when you wake up in
the morning check your calendar make it
part of your morning routine and in
doing so you're going to prime your
brain and you're going to get a
bird's-eye view of everything coming up
in your day and be much less likely to
have something blindside you and throw
off your plans secondly set up
notifications if you are using a digital
calendar app you can set up
notifications to remind you before an
event happens and i highly recommend
using these especially for very
important events like interviews and
exams and the destruction of the
universe by zorp the surveyor hails or
but hang in a second when should you set
these notifications to hit well that is
going to kick us into a bit of a
discussion on human psychology see we
humans with our mushy brains and all are
susceptible to something called the
planning fallacy which describes how we
are very over optimistic when we are
estimating how long things are going to
take this is partly because we basically
can't distinguish between the best case
scenario in the average case scenario so
you know best case like you hit every
single green light there's no traffic
average case there's a few red lights
there's some traffic but our brains
conflate them we're making estimations
there's research on this and there's
also the segmentation effect if i broke
down a task like go to work into a bunch
of different mini tasks and had you
estimate how long each one would take
you would be much more accurate than if
i asked you how long is it going to take
to get to work that's the segmentation
effect and we are very susceptible to it
so when setting up our notifications we
should be cognizant of these facts we
should know that we vastly underestimate
how long it's gonna take to get places
to do things to get ready and we should
set up our notifications accordingly now
one way you can do this is go very
simple and just say i'm gonna make it an
hour before but sometimes it takes more
than an hour to get ready so you can
also do is use a fudge ratio take your
initial estimate of how long it's going
to take to do something and add a
multiplier to it 1.5 is a good starting
point so if your initial estimate for
getting ready for work let's just say is
30 minutes then add 1.5 x on that and
let's just set your notification for 45
minutes in advance one additional note
here is that most calendar apps let you
set up multiple notifications so for
especially important or infrequent
events i would recommend having an
additional notification that comes much
further out and this is especially
important for things like birthdays or
anniversaries where you're gonna need
some prep time to find a present or book
a venue or whatever it is so to quickly
recap here first set up your calendar
system in a way that suits you it can be
digital it could be analog it's all cool
just pick something that you're actually
going to stick with secondly add events
to your calendar and relevant
information to those events use quick
capture techniques and apps like
fantastical to cut down on the amount of
time it takes and also make your events
more useful add reference calendars
optional events and schedule time for
goals and things that are important to
you and finally third get information
from your calendar at the right time
check your calendar every single day
make it part of your morning routine and
also set up notifications so that you
have ample time to prepare and actually
get to your next event so you're not
freaking out and stressed all the time
now as i mentioned earlier your calendar
is just one part of that productivity
system if you want to learn how to set
up the entire thing and optimize it
including your task manager the way you
take notes your file organization system
you should take my productivity systems
class over on skillshare in this class
you're gonna learn how to set up each of
these systems but more importantly
you're gonna learn some techniques for
optimizing the way that you keep it
organized so it doesn't get messy and
unusable over time which happens to a
lot of people they end up ditching their
systems over a hundred thousand people
have already taken this course and you
can join them for free because right now
skillshare is offering the first 1 000
people who clicked link in the
description down below a one month free
trial with unlimited access to the
platform which means once you get into
skillshare you don't have access just to
my classes but to thousands of other
classes from expert teachers who can
teach you how to make great youtube
videos like mkbhd class they can teach
you how to do 3d animation they can
teach you how to mix music and tons more
and even after that trial skillshare is
a very affordable platform and new
classes are being released all the time
so click that link right there if you
want to start learning today and support
this channel or you'll find in the
description down below and thanks for
watching you can also find two more
videos right here and here hit that like
button for the algorithm if you enjoyed
this video and found it helpful and i
will see you in the next one