a great man once said that time is an
illusion lunchtime doubly so but despite
the apparently illusory nature of these
two things time can certainly seem like
something that's tangible and like
something that is constantly slipping
through our fingers not least of which
because of the fact that we tend to
waste so much of it yes it seems that
most of us are perpetually racked by at
least a little bit of guilt over the
amount of time we spend scrolling
through netflix or browsing the dankest
of memes or just refreshing instagram to
see how many likes we got on that latest
post in the last 30 seconds though it
also bears mentioning the amount of time
we tend to waste on things that don't
seem to produce as much guilt things
that seem justified like taking on too
many commitments and having an overly
busy schedule where we're stretched thin
stressed out and producing low quality
work as a result and as francis crick
once said a busy life is a wasted life
so what i want to do with this video is
take a broad view of time management and
give you five useful tips for managing
your time more effectively whether you
already know you're wasting it because
you're a couch potato or whether you
like me to be honest have simply deluded
yourself into thinking you're already
managing it pretty well because of how
busy you are let's get into it
the first tip that i've got for you guys
today is to try using a time tracking
tool now i recently did a video on apps
that forced you to work which listed
several different options in this
category so i'm not going to restate
them all but what i do want to do here
is give you a little bit of a deeper
look at one that i'm going to recommend
you at least give a try and that is
toggle so unlike automatic time trackers
like rescuetime that just log the time
you spend in each app or program on your
computer and then give you a report at
the end of the week toggle is a manual
time tracker which means you actually go
into their dashboard and record the time
you spend on each task throughout the
day and the reason that i recommend at
least giving this tool a try is that
tracking your time manually makes you
think harder about it and you start to
realize more accurately how you spend
your time on a daily basis and that lets
you make changes going forward now
within toggle's dashboard you're going
to find two different modes manual mode
and timer mode with manual mode you can
record the amount of time you spent on
each task after the fact but what i'm
going to recommend you use instead is
timer mode this is a real-time method
where you hit a start and stop button so
you can be timing your work as you
actually do it and this has a couple of
key benefits first it's more accurate
since you are tracking time in real time
you don't have to go back after the fact
and try to remember how many hours and
minutes you put into each task and
secondly and more importantly you'll be
less likely to waste time or switch
tasks because you'll subconsciously want
your time log to accurately reflect what
you actually did now long-term manual
time tracking like eating a bowl of
nails in the morning is not for everyone
you might find that after you do it for
a week or two you kind of want to move
on and just not worry about it anymore
and that's fine but i do think that
doing it for a week or two as an
experiment is very useful because it
gives you a more accurate picture of how
you're using your time and it'll make
you think a little bit more deliberately
about how you're going to use it in the
future
tip number two is to get clear on your
priorities and to do this very
deliberately maybe even sit down and do
it on a piece of paper or write it in
your journal because when you aren't
clear on your priorities and what they
represent on your schedule it can be
very easy to take on too many
commitments and to become that overly
busy person now i think prioritizing can
be a topic for a video all its own but i
do want to give you a couple of
questions that i ask myself whenever i'm
trying to nail down what my personal
priorities are and whether a new
commitment is worth it number one to ask
a very in the details type of question
what does my schedule look like without
this on it answering this means taking a
hard look at my current list of
commitments my schedule how much free
time i have and whether or not i'd be
willing to give something up to take on
this new commitment or not and in
addition to that question i also like to
ask a more bird's-eye view question
which is when i'm on my deathbed will i
regret not doing this and this is the
question that actually got me to finally
start taking singing lessons and this
could be a question that would also be
useful for getting over your fear to
start doing things but as a time
management question it can also be very
useful because it helps you to
prioritize things from a bird's-eye view
from a life values perspective and if
you want to be really clear on your
priorities and on your values and on
what you're doing it may also be useful
to have a written record of what you're
doing at the moment and to update it
quite frequently and i actually do this
if you go to my website
collegeinfogeek.com now you can see what
i'm doing and what my priorities at
least should be ideally
all right tip number three is to learn
how to batch your tasks effectively and
batching basically just means taking a
bunch of your tasks bundling them
together and knocking them all out in
one session and when you do this you
free up lots of time for more intense
projects later on or if you're me
probably playing more beat saber but
more importantly batching lets you take
advantage of economies of scale when you
decide to do a bunch of tasks in one big
batch you eliminate a lot of the setup
costs that you would have to deal with
if you did them all individually now in
terms of tasks that make good candidates
for batching i'm gonna go ahead and
suggest number one any and all errands
if it's a low energy task and you have
to leave the house to do it go ahead and
take care of all those in one big batch
in one afternoon number two tasks that
require low mental energy and that are
done at home so cleaning things up
organizing papers fighting that ninja
that's hiding in your closet clearing
out your email box all that kind of
stuff and number three any kind of small
tasks that surround your main work and
for an example here every single time
that i have to make a video i need to
create a project over a notion with a
sponsor tag and a publishing date and i
also have to create a research document
in evernote these are little tasks that
could be done individually when i start
the project or i could come up with 10
video topics in a row and do all these
things in one big batch now one little
tidbit before we move on if you're
already using todoist or a similar task
manager you may want to start using
their labels feature as it can be very
helpful for batching since across all of
your projects you can apply labels that
correspond to say your energy levels
like low or medium or high or the
location at which a task has to be
performed like home or work or an errand
and then when you have time for a batch
you can look at the label that's most
relevant to you right now and see what
there is to be done
next up we have to talk about how to get
better at saying no this is an integral
skill in time management especially for
people who are overly busy those of us
who are perpetually over committed seem
to be the kind of people who just can't
say no to new opportunities whether
they're people coming to us because they
want something from us they want our
help or whether it's something that just
seems really cool that we want to do
either way we have to learn how to say
no if we want to be able to prioritize
the things that are actually important
and give them the time that they deserve
so how exactly do you get to the point
where you can say no well there are
definitely tactics there are ways to
gracefully let people down there are
ways to sort of push off things that you
might want to do for yourself but i
think the first thing you have to do is
just become mentally okay with saying no
and this can be hard a lot of times
saying no feels like letting an
opportunity slip through your fingers
forever like you're only going to get
one shot because this opportunity only
comes once in a lifetime like having the
ability to seamlessly integrate m m
lyrics into a video script which i
didn't say no to but remember that every
time you say yes to an opportunity you
are incurring an opportunity cost
because the act of saying yes to one
thing means you are implicitly saying no
to something else you have a limited
amount of time energy and attention and
you can't devote it to everything and
this can be a useful way to reframe your
thinking remember that every single
decision you make incurs an opportunity
cost now that brings us to the question
of how to properly let people down if
you have to say no because there is a
graceful way to do it and then there is
an abrasive way to do it you could just
yell no and why would you ever ask me to
do that in their face but you could also
do it a little bit more tactfully and
here's an example of how i personally do
it so one type of opportunity that i
have deliberately chosen to say no to
for the most part is public speaking
this is something that i do like doing
it definitely can advance my career but
i've realized that if i travel if i
speak if i take time to write talks i
can't make as many videos and i can't do
the other things that are valuable to me
so nine times out of ten when somebody
reaches out to me wanting me to go speak
at their school or their event i have to
say no my priorities dictate it but i
try to say it in a way that respects the
fact that they even reached out to me
that says that i'm honored that they did
so and that tells them i have other
commitments right now i'm not saying no
because i don't want to do it i do but i
have other priorities that i have to
respect and you can also take it one
step further by trying to anticipate
their next step and then trying to help
out with that so if somebody comes to
you with an opportunity and you have to
say no it's likely that they're gonna
have to go to somebody else or look
elsewhere for a solution since you can't
provide it and if you have anything that
you can do quickly again that doesn't
interfere with your priorities or take
too much time then anticipating that
need of theirs and trying to fill it is
going to help them along in their
process but it's also going to make this
interaction a positive one even though
you had to say no so to go back to my
previous example if i get a speaking
request and i have to say no to it i'm
going to do so gracefully i'm going to
inform them as to why but i might also
follow that up with a recommendation
that they contact my friend chris bailey
over to life productivity because i
happen to know that he does take
speaking gigs he's really good at it and
his area of expertise is pretty similar
to mine so even though i had to say no i
might have been able to provide them
with a solution and this practice the
practice of anticipating the needs of
the other person when you say no or
anticipating the next step in the
conversation is a very very useful life
skill to build so don't think of it just
as a time management tip think of it as
a life tip in general
all right we have arrived at what is
possibly my personal favorite time
management tip which is to use the
pressure created by deadlines to your
advantage a few years ago i had to learn
the hard way just how useful deadlines
are and how terrible for your
productivity a lack of them can be so
back in my junior year of college during
the first semester i was incredibly busy
i had so many commitments i was an ra i
had a second part-time job i had classes
i had clubs basically i had very little
time to work on my side project which
was my site college info geek so second
semester that year rolls around and i
have the bright idea to quit basically
everything except my classes and devote
the rest of my free time to working on
the blog and i thought that this would
give me so much more time and energy to
get articles done that i would basically
triple my productivity overnight
but instead i spent most of that
semester playing marvel vs capcom 3
getting very few articles written and
generally wasting a bunch of time and
that experience taught me a very
valuable lesson which is that we need
structure we need deadlines we need a
little bit of a framework to operate
within otherwise we just don't do
anything we tend to take the path of
least resistance now there may be some
rare souls out there who are so
passionate about every single element of
what they do that they need absolutely
no structure no deadlines no nothing
they just get up and work like a madman
every single day but i'm not one of
those people i love the work i do but i
don't love every single element of it
and i'm prone to procrastination unless
i have a deadline it's like the ex-navy
seal jocko willink always likes to say
discipline equals freedom when you have
a little bit of discipline when you have
a little bit of structure you're able to
operate within that there are fewer
decisions to make and you have a little
bit of time pressure with which to get
your work done and that actually gives
you more free time overall so if you
work for yourself or your student who
has a lot of free time a lot of kind of
flexibility with your homework i would
encourage you to set some deadlines
maybe make some mini goals within your
task management system give yourself a
little bit of time pressure now speaking
of deadlines one unspoken deadline that
i do want to remind you about is the
unknown amount of time before somebody
else out there goes and grabs the domain
name that you are eventually going to
want for yourself and that is why as
soon as you possibly can i would suggest
you go over to hover and get your domain
name now if you've been following
college info geek for a while especially
some of our career content you'll know
that one of the most important things
you can do for advancing your career and
making connections is building an online
presence for yourself and one of the
most integral parts of doing that is
securing a professional domain name for
yourself this allows you to create a
personal website where you can have a
portfolio and also link out to your
other social profiles now i was
unfortunately born just a little bit too
late to get the domain that i really
would have wanted which would have been
thomasfrank.com but i was at least early
enough to get thomas jfrank.com which is
just about as good and which i used to
create a portfolio website that i shared
with recruiters and freelance clients in
college so if you don't want to miss out
on your chance to get the best possible
professional domain name for your online
presence then head over to hover and get
it today hover is the best place on the
internet to get yourself a domain name
not least of which because they have
over 400 domain extensions to choose
from ranging from com dot me to dot
ninja and pizza and now you probably
know which cartoon i spent much of my
childhood watching but beyond that they
also have an incredibly streamlined
sales process it is super easy to buy
domain there are no annoying upsells no
annoying pop-ups and if you have an
account like i do you can literally get
your hands on a domain in less than 30
seconds which is pretty cool and once
you've got your domain hover also has
tools for easily setting up a
professional email address like mine
which is thomas at collegefulgeek.com
and you can also use their connect
feature to easily hook that domain up to
website builders like squarespace and
shopify of course the best part is that
if you go over to hover.com thomasfrank
which you will find in the description
down below you can get 10 off of your
first domain purchase so head on over
there get your domain and show your
support for this channel big thanks to
hover for sponsoring this video and
being a big supporter of the work that i
do here and of course guys thank you as
always for watching if you enjoyed this
video and you found it useful then
definitely hit that like button and you
can also subscribe right over there if
you don't want to miss out on new videos
when they come out every single week you
can also click right there if you want
to get a free copy of my book on how to
earn better grades follow me on
instagram tomfrankly or check out one
more video on this channel by clicking
right there or smash your face into your
phone's home screen that works too
thanks so much for watching and if you
want to connect with me further i
respond best to morse code chest taps
i actually have no idea what i'm doing
right now