some of you guys have asked me to do a
video about the stuff that's in my
backpack and my answer to that is
okay so let's talk about the bag first
before I get into what's inside of it
this is the manal carryon I actually
backed it on Kickstarter a little while
ago and for traveling the world and
going places I think this is a fantastic
bag I'm able to fit everything that I
need to carry with me inside of it it
opens up in a clam shell fashion I
absolutely love it that being said now
it retails for around 300 bucks and for
daily campus use it's probably overkill
for comparison this is the bag that I
use for most of college it's the uh
Synergy I think it's called from Swiss
Gear I got it from Best Buy for about 60
bucks and it's a quality backpack it
hasn't fallen apart in six years uh and
I think that's a thing that you should
keep in mind when you're buying a
backpack but also it's not Overkill it
doesn't cost hundreds of dollars and it
has enough Pockets to hold all your
stuff all right let's dig into this
thing first up is my MacBook Air this is
probably the thing in my backpack I use
the most because I'm always writing and
going to coffee shops and working on
stuff I love the air absolutely amazing
computer if you're looking for a Windows
computer that's very comparable the Dell
XPS 13 is an awesome option beyond that
I am not a laptop expert but I can link
to some laptop recommendations in the
blog post for this video also got an
iPad Mini this is the first edition so
no R in a screen but I mainly just use
this for reading books it's an upgrade
from my Kindle and I always keep it in
the bag I also usually have a print book
because I like books I guess and right
now I'm reading a book called think
smart it's a neuroscientist's
prescription for improving your brain's
performance I'm hoping to learn some
cool stuff from this book that I can
build into new videos uh so keep an eye
out for that kind of stuff also got a
couple of paper notebooks this is my
main one nothing fancy it's an
environotes recycled paper notebook I
think it costs about 65 cents but if you
watch my video on my task organization
system you'll know that a lot of what I
do is on paper and this thing is my
catchall when I'm taking notes from an
online course they all go in here when
I'm doing my daily or weekly task lists
they go in here or when I'm creating
b-roll lists for the uh graphics and
animations I want to put in my videos
they go in here everything's in here uh
it's not very organized it's probably
not the best way to organize your notes
if you're a student and have lots of
classes but it works for me I've also
got a cheap Sketchbook in here for when
I want to create drawings or
illustrations for my videos and if
you've seen my video on how to Ace your
finals you probably remember this
drawing so keeping it in my bag at all
times is a good way for me to be able to
draw things when I get inspiration if I
don't happen to be here by my desk
lastly I've got a single purple folder
is my catchall for things like airline
ticket stubs and anything else that
needs to be put in a folder that's made
of paper um if you're a student and you
have a lot of classes I actually
recommend those accordion binder devices
with the flap that can snap shut it
works better than a Trapper works better
than stuffing lots of folders into your
backpack but uh these days I don't
really have a whole lot of papers that I
need to keep so one folder carries them
all pretty well moving on to the small
stuff I've got a Logitech presentation
remote because occasionally I go speak
at schools adapters for the MacBook I've
got the VGA one for the same reason I've
got the presentation remote to hook up
to projectors when I want to do a
presentation and also the ethernet one
just in case there's no Wi-Fi but there
is for some reason an ethernet cord
business cards I always recommend having
at least a few of these in your backpack
just in case you meet somebody and you
want to leave them your contact
information and also leave a good
impression and if you want to get them I
recommend using moo I've been using them
since I was a college student and they
make really good high quality cards pens
and pencils not that interesting I don't
use anything crazy I just use what works
but I will say that I do keep two pens
in my backpack at all times just in case
I'm out somewhere and someone needs to
borrow a pen I can be the cool person
who lens went out and actually at VidCon
I made a new friend by doing this so uh
thumbs up for friendship umbrella this
is actually a really cool thing to keep
in your backpack I always have one on
hand because you don't know when you're
going to get caught in a rainstorm and
this has come in handy for me more times
than I can count so this thing is
staying in my bag and it makes for kind
of a cool back trop
too a really thin hoodie to deal with
crazy air conditioning in coffee shops
laptop charger because I don't like
sadness iPhone charging cable because
same reason micro USB and mini USB cords
I used to have legit reasons for keeping
these camera and uh pocket Wi-Fi I think
but now I just keep them in here because
people with Android phones always forget
their phone chargers and then they're
very happy when I happen to have one USB
battery actually picked this up in Japan
came really in handy when I was out all
day my phone would tend to die I don't
use it too much here in the states when
I'm just going about my business but it
keeps a spot in the backpack because it
can come in handy and of course
headphones and lastly a canteen for Te
and water because this thing doesn't do
so well in a backpack now that's
generally what I keep in my backpack on
a daily basis today but since I'm not a
student anymore and there are other
things I used to keep in the bag I
wanted to show you a few other items you
might find useful first up is actually a
plug strip I don't keep this in my bag
on a daily basis but whenever I travel I
do make sure to keep it along with this
little two-prong to three-prong
converter this basically makes it so
that even if all the outlets are taken
in a coffee shop or an airport or a
hostel I can make more outlets and
that's always a good thing when I lived
on campus I always kept a skate tool in
my bag because my main way of getting
around campus was a skateboard book
Flags these come in handy for marking
your place in books that you don't want
to highlight I always kept my clicker in
my bag because I had classes that
required it now if you go to a school
that requires this thing yes you should
keep it in your bag all the time but I
think that schools are actually starting
to move to smartphone clicker apps which
would be pretty cool but either way this
thing always had a spot in my bag as
much as I don't like it a pick four
notebook now this is actually a pretty
cool goal tracking device basically it
has you commit to doing daily practice
on four different goals for a six- week
period and every single day you write
down your progress on each of your goals
I've used several of these in the past
and they've helped me make progress on
goals like learning Japanese building my
own iPhone app and lots of other things
and lastly my trusty graphing calculator
for math classes so that ends this tour
of my backpack hopefully you enjoyed it
and if you did you can leave a like to
support this channel now I actually want
to know what kind of cool stuff you keep
in your backpack so let me know down in
the comments below that's all I got so
thanks so much for watching and I will
see you next
week hey there guys thanks for watching
this video now if you enjoyed it and you
want to get new video videos on being a
more effective student every single week
you can click that big red subscribe
button right there I also wrote a book
on how to earn better grades and it's
absolutely free so if you want to get a
copy click the picture of the book and
I'll get one to you you can find more
detail and links to some of the things I
mentioned in this video at the companion
blog post and you can find that by
clicking the orange logo right there in
last week's video I covered 20 different
websites that I think are really useful
for students so check it out if you
haven't seen it and if you want to
connect with me or ask questions I'm Tom
frankley on Twitter or you can leave a
comment below thanks for watching
[Music]