hey what's up guys so we did it another
year is on the books and we are one step
closer to the inevitable robot uprising
possibly two or three steps closer if i
can just find that bug
in my code anyway about 365 days ago i
put out a video rounding out 2017 with
10 productivity tips that you could use
to make 2018 a more productive year
and if you saw that video hopefully you
were able to implement some of those
tips and this year was a more productive
one for you
and i wanted to do something similar for
the end of this year but instead of
focusing on productivity this time
around we're going to focus on the topic
of
stress in addition to all the emails and
tweets and dms that i get about
productivity topics like how to focus
and how to not procrastinate as much
i get a lot of questions from people who
feel that they're overly stressed on a
daily basis that they're overwhelmed and
if you find yourself in a similar
situation then hopefully one of the five
tips i'm going to share in this video
will help you go into 2019 feeling a
little bit less stressed and like your
life is a little bit more
balanced first up we've got a useful
planning hack that i try to use whenever
i'm taking on a future commitment
something that's next
week or maybe even further into the
future and it's to ask myself
if i had to take on this commitment this
week would it have actually
fit with everything else that i've
already had to do or that i know that's
coming up
as we discussed in my procrastination
series we human beings have this
tendency to view our future selves as
basically superheroes we think that our
future self like next week or two weeks
from now
is gonna be able to handle a lot more
than what we're dealing with right now
we think that that person in the future
is not going to have to deal with the
same procrastination tendencies the same
distractions
and when we look at our calendars
usually next week or the weeks
afterwards
don't seem as full as this week and of
course
every single week when you find yourself
in that present moment there's always
things that come up right so when you're
thinking about taking on a commitment
next week and you feel like oh that's
super easy i can easily fit that in
ask yourself would that have actually
fit into
this week with all the surprises that
popped up with all the tired spells you
found yourself in and
see if that would have actually worked
if it would have then
maybe it would be a good idea to
actually add that into your next week's
schedule but if it wouldn't have you may
want to give it a second thought
all right tip number two which is
something that i have used for a
long time to great effect be a
contrarian
do things at different times or in
different locations than everyone else
tends to do them one of the biggest
causes of stress in our lives is the
fact that
resources are limited there's only so
much food to go around so much money so
much internet bandwidth
but certain resources are only taken up
at certain
times of the day and at other times of
the day they're basically free or at
least they're a lot less busy
so if you can be a contrarian if you can
commute to work at a different time of
the day
or if you can go grocery shopping at a
different time than everyone else
typically does then you're going to run
into a lot less
friction and that cuts down on your
stress now of course there are going to
be varying degrees to which you can be a
contrarian based on your schedule if
you're an entrepreneur you can be a
contrarian in basically any way that you
want whereas if you have a full-time job
your options are a little bit more
limited but regardless of what your life
situation looks like there are probably
areas where you can exercise a little
bit of control and change your schedule
up just
a bit you could wake up maybe an hour
earlier and drive to work and maybe work
out at a gym near there
or you could go to the grocery store on
a saturday morning instead of after work
on thursday afternoon the typical times
at which we do things
are in part dictated by our schedules
and our obligations but they're also set
in part by our habits and by the way
that everyone else seems to do things
so and this kind of calls back to a tip
in yesterday's video about organization
if you can ditch the dogma if you can
stop doing things the way other people
do them just because they do them and be
a bit of a contrarian
you can really cut down on the stress
that you experience in your life
all right tip number three this is a bit
more of a specific tip but
be ruthless about your inbox in 2019
and this tip is on the list because
email can be a huge
stress creator for a lot of people most
of us are being constantly bombarded
with tons of emails on a daily basis and
a lot of these emails frankly are
completely
unnecessary and even for the ones that
you do actually need to look at you
might not need to look at them
right at the time that they come in or
you may need to receive them but not
actually
see them so as you go into 2019 start
taking some steps to tame
your inbox a little bit and i've got a
few suggestions first ruthlessly
unsubscribe from newsletters daily
digests marketing emails
anything that doesn't bring you value
and i realize this is kind of an ironic
tip coming from somebody who literally
has an email newsletter but hey
if you get my email newsletter and it
doesn't bring you value then i
actively encourage you to unsubscribe
from that and that counts for anyone
else's newsletters as well you might
think that it's not a big deal to just
delete the emails when they come in but
realize that every single one you have
to delete represents a little bit of
work you have to do represents a
decision you have to make and over time
as the day goes on
that creates mental fatigue secondly
start using filters and rules to
automate the email that you do need to
keep for example i get a lot of receipts
sent to my business email for all kinds
of transactions that go on
in my business and i need to keep these
receipts for good record keeping in case
i ever get audited
but i don't need to see them all when
they come in like every single time i
make a video here on youtube i have to
order captions for it and when i do that
there's an email receipt that gets sent
to my inbox
but i don't need to see that i just need
to have it in my records in case i ever
need it down the line
so a long time ago i created a filter
that will automatically add the receipt
tag to that email so i can easily find
it if i need to
and that automatically archives it that
way it's there
but i don't have to see it or deal with
it that brings us to tip number four
which is going to sound like
more work but hear me out in 2019
i suggest that you start keeping a
journal now the astute viewers among you
might realize that in my previous
year-end video i advocated keeping an
accomplishment journal and
i do still advocate doing that but for
this video i'm going to recommend
keeping
a normal journal a record of your
thoughts and experiences and the things
that go on on a day-to-day
basis and yes this does create a little
bit of work for you especially if you're
making it a daily habit but it has a
hugely important benefit which is that
it crystallizes your thoughts about the
experiences you're having
in the moment and it's really useful to
have this record to look back on because
we're really good at rationalizing
things and we are especially good at
looking at the past
with rose tinted glasses and if you
don't keep a journal you might find
yourself in a situation down the road
where you're looking back at the past
wishing that you could kind of go back
to the situation you were in because
where you are right now
is stressful but if you have a journal
you can go and look at how you were
actually feeling
during that time and you might realize
that the way things are now
are actually better than they were back
then finally if you want to feel less
stressed in 2019 and in the years
afterwards
then stop rushing so much a few months
ago i was browsing reddit and i found a
thread from a guy who had remodeled his
house and he was showing all the
pictures and the job was honestly
excellent but he was kind of lamenting
the fact that
a lot of the rooms were now empty
because they didn't own a whole lot of
stuff
but he also said that his dad gave him a
really good piece of advice which is
that
you've now got the house and now you
have an entire lifetime
to fill it up and for me that one line
is a great encapsulation of the fact
that
we don't need to rush as much as we
think we do we have a lot more time
than we think we have and the reason
that a lot of us take on
so many commitments is that we feel like
we have to rush
through all these stages of life that
society sort of expects for us
to go through there's all these things
that we're supposed to achieve right we
have to graduate from college
buy a house start a family do all these
things and
social media makes this worse because
we've got all these friends who
in past decades we would only see once
in a while maybe at reunions or family
things or something like that
but now we can see them posting about
all their life milestones
this person started a family this person
bought a house this person got a new job
and we feel like we are falling behind
if we're not doing
all of those things so if you are an
ambitious person like me
there's this really strong temptation to
keep taking on things
because you feel like you have to get to
that next stage as soon as possible but
just like the guy who remodeled his
house now has a whole lifetime to fill
it up
you and i have time to do the things
that we want to do you have time
to achieve your goals and whenever i
feel the temptation to rush
i try to remind myself of what's really
important by asking myself the question
am i truly that unhappy right now
usually the answer is
no i'm content right now and i was
content five years ago even though i
hadn't achieved
nearly as much as i have now and i'm
hopefully going to be content five years
in the future
as well it doesn't mean i'm going to
stop working doesn't mean i'm going to
rest
on my laurels but it does mean that i
can afford to be methodical in my
approach
and that i shouldn't be sacrificing my
mental health or my time
just to get to that next stage as
quickly as i possibly can
so stop rushing so much if you are
constantly stressed out then pull back
and assess the expectations you've put
on yourself it might actually be a good
idea to edit them and to allow yourself
a bit more time to meet them
because when you have that time you'll
feel less overwhelmed and you'll be able
to put more care
into your work plus when you're not
always rushing to finish an overwhelming
task list
you've got free time time to go on long
bike rides time to cook healthier
dinners
and time to actually keep your house
clean and since none of these things
requires a ton of concentration in the
moment
you can also use that time to learn
something new with audible which is the
best place on the internet to get your
hands on
audiobooks audible has an unmatched
library of audiobooks in a ton of
different genres from science fiction to
biographies to psychology they've got
tons of obscure stuff
and they have all the best sellers
including my recommendation for this
week which is the laws of human nature
by robert greene
if you're interested in becoming a more
rational thinker and making better
decisions and in controlling your
emotions more effectively
especially in your interactions with
other people then this is a fantastic
book to go through and i highly
recommend it
and you can actually get it for free
along with a 30-day trial of audible by
going over to audible.com
thomas or by texting thomas to 500 500
on
your phone once you've got that
membership you're gonna get one credit
every single month good for any title in
their library plus
two audible originals that you can't get
anywhere else and access the audio
workout programs plus your personal
library of audiobooks that you've
downloaded is yours to keep forever even
if you end up canceling audible you're
going to have those books as long
as you want so once again go over to
audible.com
thomas or text thomas to 500 500 on your
phone
to get that free 30-day trial and a free
audiobook download of your choosing
as always a huge thanks goes out to
audible for sponsoring this video and
being a big supporter of my channel in
general and thank you guys so much for
watching both this video and everything
throughout 2018
and possibly further back if you've been
watching for a while if you enjoyed this
video definitely hit that like button to
support this channel and i also want to
hear from you down in the comments what
do you want to see from me in 2019
both on the academic side the student
focus side but also
in a broader sense what do you want to
see from me that maybe doesn't have to
focus on academics and productivity
and all those kinds of topics i'm
looking forward to hearing from you down
below and hopefully you had a great
2018 hopefully 2019 is awesome for you
as well
as always you can subscribe right there
to get new videos every single week when
they come
out you can go right there to get a free
copy of my book on how to earn better
grades in school whether you're in high
school or college i think you'll find it
helpful
follow me on instagram right there or
last but not least watch one more video
on this channel by clicking
right here or smashing your face into
your phone screen thanks for watching
and i will see you in
the next one