hey what's up everybody I'm Thomas from
college infogeek and today we are not
going to be talking about probability
Theory we will be talking about reading
assignments so the question of the day
is should you do all of your assigned
reading and there are a lot of different
answers you'll find out there some
people will say no it's useless some
people will say yes obviously you should
do all your reading it's the stuff
you're supposed to be learning and you
are stuck in the middle trying to figure
out which one of these answers is right
so hopefully in this video I can give
you a little bit of guidance to make
that decision for yourself based on your
own set of specific circumstances so
here's the thing about reading reading
assignments help you learn the material
that your professor wants you to learn
obviously however when you're in college
your time is very limited and your class
work and reading are not the only things
that you should be doing with that time
you've also got part-time jobs building
relationships with other people
networking extracurriculars all this
kind of stuff and you can't really
afford to sync all of your time into
reading and studying and specifically
only learning activities so here is my
initial tip for figuring out how much of
your reading to actually do triage your
assignments now triage is originally a
medical term and it's used by doctors
and field Medics and Wars to assess the
number of patients they have at any
given time and figure out which one they
should focus on first however triage is
applicable to many different fields and
you can use it when gauging your reading
material because it's really just
prioritization with an emphasis on doing
the most important things first and
possibly having to let certain things go
so the thing about reading assignments
is that not all of them are required for
you to get a good grade in a certain
class for one a lot of the reading
material will be covered in class on
lecture slides and you can learn it
while you're sitting in class during the
time you've already dedicated to
learning by paying for classes and for
other classes there's just a lot of the
reading material that will never be
covered on tests so you don't need to
learn it in order to get the grade now
unfortunately not every class is like
this and a lot of classes do require the
reading material so the tip here is to
gauge your classes throughout the
semester learn which classes require a
lot of reading and which classes you can
safely skip a lot of the material for
and when I say skip sking it's not just
a binary choice between skipping and
reading there's actually a spectrum of
focus that you can apply to your
assigned readings and for Simplicity
sake we can break this spectrum down
into three specific choices skip skim or
read when I took my marketing class
during my junior year I started the
semester off by reading every single
assignment however I quickly realized
that I could just go to the back of
every chapter note down the vocabulary
and study that and do just fine on the
tests so that's what I did for the rest
of the semester and I got a great grade
in the class so if that's what you can
do for a specific class it's going to
save you a lot of time in other classes
just skimming the material alone isn't
going to cut it so you're going to have
to find time to dedicate close reading
to that material but the key here is to
remain mindful when you're in class
gauge the amount of effort you need to
put into the class and the readings as
the semester goes along and adjust your
effort accordingly another thing that
you can focus on is the type of readings
that are assigned so each of your
classes will most likely have a primary
reading source and this is usually going
to be the assigned textbook primary
reading sources should be a high
priority item for you and you should do
most of your reading assignments in them
those however a lot of classes have
secondary reading sources maybe articles
that the professor finds interesting or
historical documents things like that
and a lot of times these readings are
not actually that important so if you
find that you don't have time to do
reading beyond the primary sources you
can usually safely skip these however
you decide to prioritize those readings
the one thing I will say is to always
have that material available in class if
you're able to dig into your primary
sources while you're learning from the
lecture slides then you're going to be
able to solidify Concepts in your mind a
lot better also the professor might want
you to look in the textbook every once
in a while so just make sure you have it
with you and the last thing I want to
cover in this video is the idea of your
time so reading assignments are so
numerous that they often get the excuse
of I don't have time to do all of these
and often that's valid but I want you to
think about it specifically I want you
to make sure that you're not
interpreting a lack of efficiency as a
lack of time if you're just trying to
read straight through all of your
reading assignments then you might not
be tackling them in the most efficient
way and that may be the true problem
when you think that you don't have time
to get them done next week's video is
going to be all about strategies and
techniques you can use to do your
assigned readings more efficiently so if
you want to get that make sure you
subscribe to this channel but for this
video The Main Idea here is to be
mindful of each class's required
readings as you go through the semester
try to decide which ones require your
attention more than others and then
adjust your investment of time for each
one
accordingly hey thanks for watching my
video If you enjoyed it then you can
support me by giving it a like on
YouTube or sharing it with a friend if
you want to get more videos just like
this every single week on being a better
college student then click the Subscribe
button right there if you missed the
last video a clip of it is playing right
below there and you can click that to
watch it also you can get a summary and
links to anything I mentioned in the
video by going to the companion blog
post which you can find by clicking on
the orange logo right there lastly if
you want to get a free chapter of my
book when it comes out then you can
click that book and subscribe to the
college infop newsletter you'll also get
notified when new podcast episodes and
blog posts come out every week lastly if
you have ideas for new videos or you
just want to connect with me you can do
so on Twitter or leave a comment on this
video thanks
you