yes friends as the incredibly hyperbolic
title of this video implies you can
indeed organize your iPhone home screen
in such a way that it will transform you
into an ultra powerful work robot with
superpowers of productivity if that
weren't the case why would I and so many
other supposedly productive people on
the internet spend so much time
organizing their iPhone home screens it
just wouldn't make sense so let's begin
before we jump into my current setup I
think it' be good to contrast it with
the previous one so here's a shot of my
old home screen not terrible but not
really great either aside from the game
sitting in the home screen that
shouldn't be there there's a lot of
visual clutter all right let's move on
the main thing you'll notice about my
current iPhone setup is that it consists
of only one screen I've chosen not to
fill the whole screen up with apps
instead I've realized that leaving some
space looks a lot nicer instead of
trying to fill every single slot with an
app I've narrowed my choices down to the
16 apps that I use most or that are most
useful to me the rest of the apps live
in one of four folders work play go and
sift choosing these four categories took
a lot of thought my conclusion after
thinking about it for a while is that
besides the many apps I have related to
Transportation or travel most perform
actions that either help me get things
done or help me have fun the ones that
don't fit live in the sift folder which
I thought was a better word than junk or
other my home screen app choices are
also set up to maximize my efficiency
and keep me from playing with my phone
more than I need to on the productivity
side I have apps like todoist Google
Calendar and Pomodoro by the way the
specific Pomodoro app I use is called
Pomodoro Timer though there are a lot of
other ones to choose from the second
ideal reducing phone time is why you
don't see Safari on the home screen I'm
trying trying to get in the habit of
writing down ideas of things I want to
look up so I can do more concentrated
research later rather than interrupting
whatever is I'm doing right now that's
why an app called drafts lives in my
dock it allows me to open it and
immediately start writing after that I
can easily export my note to Evernote
and process it later I also don't keep
Facebook or other social media apps on
my home screen I found that keeping them
in the folders actually discourages me
from using them too much tweetbot and
Instagram are the only ones that get a
place on my home screen as I post on
them regularly but I don't really find
myself scrolling through them very often
a couple of other things I've done to
reduce distractions for one no apps are
allowed to have badge notifications
except for the text message and phone
apps I've also massively cut down on
actual notifications my phone will send
me and lastly my phone goes into Do Not
Disturb mode from 11:00 p.m. to 6:00
a.m. so absolutely nothing will get a
hold of me unless it's somebody calling
for the second time all right so maybe
you watch this video and you're thinking
to yourself wait a minute that guy made
a speed reading video last week and he
promised me another speed reading video
this week so where is the speed reading
video mhm explanation so this being
Wednesday as I record this tomorrow
morning I'm hopping on a plane to go
down to North Carolina for a conference
called fincon and unlike most of the
conferences I go to at this one I happen
to be speaking given that most this week
has been dedicated to designing that
presentation creating my slides
practicing it because unfortunately
unlike YouTube I can't just do takes
over and over again until I get it right
and hence there wasn't enough time left
over to make that follow-up video at a
level of quality that you guys deserve
so hopefully you enjoyed this shorter
video I'll have the next video in the
speed reading series out next Thursday
when I'm back from North Carolina I'm
going to get back to practicing my
speech before my plane takes off and yes
before you ask there will be a video
coming soon on how to make better
presentations so look forward to that
and in the meantime if you got tips of
your own on setting up your smartphone
in a more productive way or you have app
recommendations leave them down in the
comments below and I will see you in the
next
video hey guys thanks so much for
watching this video If you want to get
new videos every single week on being a
more effective student click the big red
subscribe button right there you can get
a free copy of my book on earning better
grades by clicking the picture of it and
also if you'd like to see the companion
blog post for this video with a and
links to any of the apps and resources I
mentioned you can click the orange logo
right there last week as I mentioned was
the first video of my series on speed
reading so if you didn't happen to see
it click the thumbnail to watch it and
also if you'd like to connect with me
I'm on Twitter @tomfrankly or you can
leave a comment down below thanks for
watching