even if you are normally a happy
motivated and generally high-energy
person it's likely that at some point in
your life you're gonna find yourself in
a rut you know a period of time where
you feel listless and demotivated you
feel burnt-out you don't know what to do
with yourself and you don't really feel
like doing anything and now you're
wondering to yourself how did I get here
and more importantly how do I get out of
this rut well I have certainly gone
through my fair share of ruts and
listless periods in my life before so
what I want to do with this video is
share a few of the things that have
helped me get myself out of them now
before we get into it I do want to note
that I think there is a big difference
between a temporary rut and actual
depression and if you feel like what
you're experiencing is actual depression
well the tips in this video may end up
helping you but I don't want to come off
as saying that they are the be-all
end-all solutions because this is
obviously a much more complicated and
serious condition so in addition to what
I'm going to share in this video and
also gonna have a link in the
description down below to a resource
written by a much more qualified person
that you might want to check out the
first strategy that I want to talk about
here and so that almost never fails to
lift my spirits and get me out of the
ruts that I sometimes find myself in is
maintaining relationships with people
who inspire you this is something that
all of us need to be doing and to
punctuate that I want to share a passage
from radios excellent book principles
meaningful work and meaningful
relationships aren't just nice things we
choose for ourselves they are
genetically programmed into us the
meaningful relationships we get from
social cooperation make us happier
healthier and more productive social
cooperation is also integral to
effective work it is one of the defining
characteristics of being human and one
thing that I want to point out here is
that you might not be getting these
types of interactions from your normal
everyday friend group one thing that I
realized about my friend group in
college is that well I loved my friends
dearly a lot of our interactions
basically boiled down to playing video
games together and sharing references
and inside jokes that we'd said a
million times before and those kind of
interactions while fun and a good
reminder that you're inside your comfort
zone that you're safe are not
challenging they're not inspiring they
don't really give you that sense of
purpose that keeps you from falling into
a rut when all of your interactions on a
day-to-day basis are only of
kind it's almost as it you've locked the
part of your brain that craves growth
and challenges into solitary confinement
and a lot of studies have conclusively
proven that solitary confinement like
the real kind has really bad
psychological consequences can cause
brain damage now obviously we're not
talking about the exact same kind of
thing here we're just kind of making a
metaphor but you can see how locking
that part of your brain away denying it
those types of relationships
interactions for a long time can
negatively impact your mental state now
if your friend group is like mine does
not mean you need to go ditch your
friends and try to find friends who are
super productive all the time
but what it does mean is that you need
to spend at least some of your time
seeking out interactions with people who
are doing inspiring and challenging
things the kind of things that are going
to motivate you to go stretch your own
capabilities I'm reminded of this every
single time I go to a professional
conference like VidCon or even when I
just get on skype and chat with one of
my entrepreneur friends I always come
away from these conversations feeling
energized and brimming with new ideas so
if you find yourself in a rut one way
that you can start to get yourself out
of it is to seek out these types of
conversations and interactions with
people who are going to challenge you
and inspire you one way it can be to go
to events whether it's something across
the country like VidCon or just a local
organization in your town or a club at
your school but something even easier is
just to reach out to a friend you
haven't talked to in a while and ask
them to catch up my friend Ben Altman
who's one of the guys who runs the
charisma on command channel actually did
this to me a couple of weeks ago he
emailed me he said hey we haven't caught
up in a while let's set up a time to
chat on the phone and then last week we
had a great conversation and I came away
from that conversation really motivated
and I bet he did too and if you want to
get the benefits to these types of
conversations on a regular basis then
one thing you can do is set up what I
like to call a Jedi Council now if
you're the kind of person who's into
reading all those other personal
development blogs and books out there
and you listen to all the other gurus
quote-unquote then you're probably gonna
hear this called mastermind groups but I
think that term is kind of cringy and
way too businessí so I'm going with Jedi
councils basically this is a pre-planned
conversation that happens maybe every
week or every two weeks or maybe even
every month with people who inspire you
people who have the same values people
that may be the same level of
professional development people with
whom you can swap feedback on projects
and stay mutually accountable actually
have one of these set up every single
week on Thursdays with my friends Andrew
and Matt and these conversations are
incredibly useful for both my businesses
success but also my level of personal
motivation but even if you don't want to
go as far as setting up a Jedi Council I
do encourage you to call a friend
sometime this week and just have a
casual conversation all right the next
strategy we're going to talk about is
giving yourself permission to take a
break or a vacation and I want to put
emphasis on that word permission see I
think one of the biggest culprits for us
falling into ruts is that we put too
much on our plate we expect too much of
ourselves and then we find ourselves
constantly behind and constantly
stressed this is incredibly common for
students and it's incredibly common for
anybody who's really ambitious in their
career and when we are constantly in
this state we are putting chronic stress
on our bodies and our minds this can
lead to burnout and this can lead to
feeling like we really don't have any
motivation to do anything and I think
the solution to this problem is to take
an actual planned break something that
you again give yourself permission to do
and this is something that I kind of
ignored for a really long time I didn't
take a real actual vacation from halfway
through 2016 until halfway through 2018
a period of two years now during that
period I did definitely travel a lot but
it was always for business and anytime a
travel opportunity came up I would only
take it if there was a business reason
for it
you get flying out to speak at a
conference or going to New York just a
month ago to record my audio book it was
always business business business when
it came to travel for me I took little
small breaks but I never really gave
myself permission to take an extended
break from my work so finally in May of
last year my girlfriend hounded me
enough and we booked an actual vacation
to San Diego for about a week and other
than one day where I took the
opportunity to see somebody out there
who were really liked and looked up to
we spent the rest of that entire time
just relaxing I surfed eight of
restaurants I hung out played video
games that was about it and when I got
home from that vacation I was reminded
of just how useful vacations could be
because I found myself having a lot more
motivation both for my work but also for
staying consistent on my daily healthy
habits I found it much easier to
consistently go to the gym and work out
to read more often to go for bike rides
so I get my Straubel miles and to follow
a healthier diet and the reason for this
which I will now take much more
seriously in the future
is that we operate under can dressed
just like on a daily timescale we need
to work and have waking hours and then
go to sleep on a larger timescale we
need to have periods of work and
intensity and then periods of relaxation
so we can basically recharge our
batteries so if you're in a rut and you
believe the reasons that you're burned
out from chronic stress give yourself
permission to take a break and it
doesn't have to be something big or
crazy like flying out to San Diego for a
surfing vacation my best friend Martin
just a couple of months ago actually
booked a hotel room in our city of
Denver for one night just so he could
get out of his apartment and be near a
bookstore that he really liked and while
that was much less expensive and didn't
require him to take any time of work he
still got the same benefits all right
the final tactic I want to talk about
here is exploring a new interest because
whenever I find myself in a rut it's
usually because I feel like I've
stagnated I haven't learned something
new in quite a while and I don't really
know what I'm doing with myself and life
kind of feels boring but the moment that
I kind of pull on a thread of interest
and let it take me somewhere that's when
life starts to feel exciting again
that's when I start learning new things
and I'm really really motivated and just
basically psyched about life in general
so to give you guys an example for this
idea let's rewind the clocks about a
year because last July last August I
found myself in a pretty bad rut I felt
listless I felt like I didn't really
know what to do with myself and it was
kind of weird because I had moved to
Denver about four months prior and
because then I kind of had this feeling
like life was supposed to be awesome all
the time since I lived in this awesome
city but that wasn't the case now
luckily around that time my friend Alex
flew up from Texas to visit me with
another one of his friends and of course
we did all the cool Colorado things we
went hiking we went to all the cool
restaurants here in Denver but at one
point during his visit we also ended up
talking about something that was a big
interest of his at the time which was
blockchain and cryptocurrency and this
was an area that I really had no
interest in myself at the time I had
never really dabbled in it it seemed
really complicated but because I wanted
to have a good conversation with my
friend I heard him out and after the
conversation I started getting a little
bit interested in the subject not a lot
but a little bit and I know from
experience when I get a little bit of
interest I should pull on that little
thread because again you don't have
innate passions right you have little
bits of interest that you explore and
and maybe that turns into something
bigger interest is like a little fire
right you have to fuel it you have to
feed it so it can get bigger until it's
eventually something that is burning
very brightly so I went and did some
reading I started reading some tutorial
articles some basic stuff and I got a
little bit more interested and then I
went and read the original Bitcoin white
paper and got a little bit more
interested and it didn't even stop there
my interest eventually grew to include
cryptography as a general subject I went
read books like the code book which made
it onto my 20 17 favorite books list
fantastic book by the way and I even
remember at one point trying to code my
own encryption algorithm and JavaScript
one afternoon just because I was curious
and I wanted to see if I could do it now
I'm not trying to say that the way
you're gonna get yourself out of a rut
is to go learn about Bitcoin and
cryptocurrency that's just one
particular thing that caught my interest
and I honestly have a lot of interests
later that year my interest in
cryptocurrency and cryptography
eventually faded and then I got really
into cooking and I spent a ton of time
learning how to cook learning the
science of cooking learning tons of
recipes and that was yet another time in
my life where I was not in a rut and I
was very motivated and very happy all
I'm trying to say here is that when you
find yourself in a rut one of the likely
causes of it is that you're stagnating
you haven't learned something in a while
so if a thread of interest presents
itself in any shape or form tug on it no
matter how thin it is because it might
take you somewhere really interesting
and it's worth noting that learning new
things on a constant basis could also
lead you to a useful new skill that
could even change the trajectory of your
career like maybe you have an interest
in learning how digital animation works
well why not learn how to go out and do
that yourself as someone who dabbles in
digital animation personally with
programs like After Effects I've learned
that this is a really useful skill that
not only helps me make higher quality
videos but could also help me land a job
if I ever needed one and with the skill
like digital animation and an
increasingly large number of others you
don't have to go to school or enroll on
a big formal program to get really good
at it there are a ton of great resources
online that you can use to start
learning and one of the best ones out
there is Skillshare well they have a
huge library of over 20,000 courses
spanning 800 different skill areas skill
sure selection of digital animation
courses is particularly strong one of my
favorites is Jake Bartlett's course on
animating with light and After Effects
which teaches you these really cool neon
lighting techniques that seem impossibly
difficult to pull off at first until of
course you learn the relatively simple
techniques behind them you'll also find
more comprehensive animation courses if
you're a beginner
and complementary courses on skills like
video editing and mastering vector
illustration and naturally with such a
big library you'll also find courses on
photography and programming and business
and marketing and a ton of different
skill areas the best part is that almost
all their courses include hands-on
challenges sample projects and an area
where you can get feedback and ask
questions so if you wanna start learning
new skills then skill share is the place
to do it and if you are among the first
500 people who click the link in the
description down below and sign up
you're gonna get a two-month free trial
with unlimited access to their library I
want to give a big thanks to Skillshare
for sponsoring this video and being a
continued supporter of this channel and
hopefully you enjoyed this video and if
you did definitely give it a like to
support this channel and you can also
subscribe right there if you don't want
to miss out on new videos when they come
out every single week you can also click
right there to get a free copy of my
book on how to earn better grades or
click right over here for one more video
on this channel last but not least you
can follow me on Instagram if you have
not done so already right over there and
I will see you in next week's video