if your desktop looks like this then you
and I need to have a chat and well even
if not you're gonna want to stick around
for this video because remember what I
said my paper file organization video is
the most exciting video you were ever
going to watch well that is a thing of
the past because everyone knows that
everything gets cooler when it makes a
transition from analog to digital so
buckle your seat belts once again
because this week we are talking about
how to organize and systematize the
files within your computer so organizing
your computer files is simultaneously
easier and harder than organizing your
paper real-world files it's easier
because computer files don't weigh
anything don't take up any physical
space so they can't really create a mess
on your desk or on your living space but
it's harder number one because well we
were never taught how to organize
computer files I don't know about you
but I remember being in elementary
school middle school and having teachers
tell me to put things in you know
separate folders to have a trapper
keeper all that kind of stuff but when
it came to my computer files no one was
ever around to teach me how to organize
my folder structure where I should save
things all that kind of good stuff and
secondly we create much more on the
computer than we do in the real world
these days we have so many different
documents pictures music files so it can
easily get out of hand much quicker than
a can in the real world and for that
reason I think it is crucial to create a
usable logical structure from the get-go
with your computer files this is much
more important that it isn't paper files
because well in the real world there
just isn't a whole lot to have to
reorganize if you realize that you've
made a mess but if your computer is a
mess you might have hundreds of files
sitting on your desktop so step one is
to create an organizational structure of
folders that makes it easy to find
anything you're looking for quickly
there's a couple different rules here
number one every single file in your
system should be within a folder that
represents it well a specific folder
nothing should be sitting out on the
desktop and nothing should be sitting in
random folders like documents or
downloads everything should be in
something that makes sense but number
two you want to have a structure that
makes it easy to find those folders
themselves now you could just have one
long list of folders on one particular
level of your system but
that's gonna make things pretty
cumbersome pretty quick so instead you
want to follow in the steps of that
great philosopher-king exhibit and start
putting folders inside of folders I call
this a tree structure if you think of a
tree at the bottom you have the trunk
and then that trunk eventually branches
off into main branches which in turn
branch into smaller branches and that
splitting process keeps going on and on
until you reach the leaves and actually
if you look closely at a leaf you'll see
that the branching process even
continues with vane splitting off from
the midrib but you didn't think you're
gonna learn some tree anatomy in this
video huh and if you look elsewhere
you'll find this structure replicated
both in nature and in man-made systems
take your body's circulatory system for
example all the blood goes through
arteries from the heart but from there
it splits off into smaller and smaller
blood vessels until it finally reaches
the smallest then the capillaries and
gets delivered to the exact right place
in the body and Road systems are very
similar any two points in a city
separated by a lot of distance are going
to be best reached by first making your
way to a highway or freeway or main road
and then branching off into smaller and
smaller residential Road and just as the
branching paths of trees blood vessels
and road systems provide the most
efficient way of moving resources around
a tree structure provides the most
efficient and usable way of organizing
your files so the first thing you're
going to want to do is to create this
tree structure which starts with what's
called the root essentially the trunk of
the tree and in my file system which I'm
gonna show you for the rest of this
video as an example the root is called
Google Drive and the reason for this is
that I use Google Drive which actually
just recently changed its name to Google
one to sync all my files up to the cloud
and between all my different computers
but we're gonna talk about that a little
bit later within the route I think it
makes the most sense to organize your
main files by kind of the main
categories of your life or as I like to
call them life buckets so the buckets of
my life include college college info
geek learning for learning projects my
life which is all my personal files like
taxes and you know apartment files
things like that now I do want to note
that this is not the only way of
organizing your file tree and that is
something that could be repeated for
every single level of the file tree in
fact if you go look at
date a curator file tree project on
github you will see that the top level
of their suggested file tree actually
has folders split up by media type audio
files documents literature video etc
personally I like to keep anything that
isn't a document in a specific media
folder within my file system and that
brings me to kind of the main point here
your file system should be expandable it
should be flexible it should maintain
its logic when it does expand but most
of all it should represent the way that
your brain organizes files assuming you
are the only person who's going to be
using this folder because I know a lot
of you guys are gonna go into the
professional world start working in
companies and start using shared
directories so with your own file system
you can kind of query your brain a
little bit more often but with shared
directories you're probably gonna want
to adhere to some agreed-upon rules and
conventions so I want to go over just a
couple here first one is organizing by
category which is exactly what I'm doing
in that main folder of my file tree and
it's the structure that I adhere to for
most subfolders as well and to give an
example let's go into my college info
geek folder this is where basically any
file related to my business goes whether
it's LLC paperwork or the thumbnail for
this video so once we drill into that
folder we're gonna see subfolders like
business content courses projects
speaking and tools and within the
content folder to go a little bit deeper
we're gonna see other folders like
articles email lists graphics podcast
and videos and with this structure it is
easy to find pretty much anything that I
need really really quickly and just to
give you an example I'm gonna throw the
path of a random file onto the screen
right here so you can see the logical
sequence of steps that I would take to
get to it and again it's very easy to
find this file and pretty much anything
else
that being said organizing by category
isn't the only way you can organize your
files and you're gonna get into certain
subfolders where it makes sense to adopt
a different structure such as organizing
by date and I find this particular
structure to be very useful when the
files that I'm trying to organize would
fill so many different category based
folders that would end up with a huge
long list and a great example is my
college classes during my college career
I took over 40 different classes and
while I could just shove every single
class full
into my college folder that would be
kind of messy I'd be looking at a list
of 40 different folders every time I
needed to go save or open a file and
most importantly during every single
semester I would go into that College
folder and I would see a bunch of very
irrelevant folders from previous
semesters so instead of just organizing
by category I instead created another
level of organization by splitting
things up by year so I've got freshman
sophomore junior and senior if we go in
to say sophomore we're gonna see all the
classes I took during my sophomore year
then once we drill into a class based
folder such as English 313 we're gonna
see all the files that had to do with
that class but also project specific
folders as well so if you have a project
with lots of different files I think it
absolutely makes sense to group those
files into their own folder but anything
that's kind of like an individual
handout for the class just keep that in
the class folder and you'll be able to
easily find it as long as you name it
intelligently and speaking of naming
your files that is actually step two in
this process which is honestly an
ongoing process because you're always
gonna be naming files but I do want to
talk a little bit about how you should
name your files and we don't have to
talk a lot here because the main
principle is that your files should be
named relatively specifically you should
be able to know at a glance what it
means within the context of a cloak
ation in your file tree and I make this
point because there are a lot of other
productivity gurus and organizational
gurus out there who have these overly
complex file naming conventions they're
putting the date in their file name
they're putting like every bit of
context they can and honestly I think
this is a waste of time because as long
as you were being vigilant about where
you're saving your files in your file
system then each file really only needs
a little bit of specificity for you to
know at a glance what it is
so obviously don't name your homework
just homework docx or paper doc X give
it a name that at least jogs your memory
as to what it should be but don't worry
about being overly specific item and
that brings us to step 3 in the process
which I referenced earlier in the video
I think that you should absolutely use a
cloud sync app like Google 1 slash
Google Drive as the root of your file
tree so if you don't know in a cloud
sync app is basically it's an app like
Dropbox Google 1 Microsoft onedrive
cloud drive there are some other ones
out there as well they basically sit on
your computer and they upload anything
within the sync folder to the cloud and
then sync it to any other computers that
you have as well and using an app like
this gives you several different
benefits number one all of your files
are kept up-to-date across your entire
system so if you make a change to a
Photoshop document or a word document on
one computer that change will be
dutifully synced up to the cloud and to
any other computer that you have
secondly you have access to your files
wherever you are you've got access on
your laptop you got access on your phone
I'm actually reading the script for this
video off of this phone right now even
have access on any computer in the world
as long as you can log into your Google
or your Dropbox account and download
those files so that brings us to a
question which cloud sync app should you
use which one is the best well I'm gonna
go ahead and recommend Google one for
most people now there are a lot of
different competitors out there again
Microsoft onedrive box sync Dropbox
iCloud Drive but I think Google one
makes the most sense number one because
they give you 15 gigabytes of free space
which is much more than any other
competitor and I think that unless
you're a content creator or photographer
or graphic designer you're gonna take a
long time to fill up that 15 gigabytes
of free space so that just keeps you
from having to spend a whole lot of
money right upfront secondly if you do
need more space with a competitor like
Dropbox you have to immediately go up
there to terabyte plan for 10 bucks a
month whereas with Google One or Google
Drive or whatever you want to call it
it's just two dollars a month for a
hundred gigabytes and again I really
don't think most people need a whole lot
more than 100 gigabytes but what you do
need regardless of who you are even if
you don't need a ton of extra space is
to make sure that your files are
adequately backed up and secured now if
you are using a cloud sync app like
Google one then you do have some measure
of protection for at least hard drive
failure on one computer right so if I
have all my files just on this one
computer just on their hard drive not
synced Google One or anything like that
and this goes down the toilet well this
probably won't fit down the toilet but
someone tries to force it down with
toilet right or someone steals it or low
key comes out of a portal and cast a
spell on it that gives it legs and
away from me right I would lose all the
files because they're only on this hard
drive but if they're synced to the cloud
then all I lose when this thing runs
away from me and goes to frightened
children is the hardware itself and this
computer can be replaced with money but
all those files they cannot be replaced
so at least with a cloud sync app you
have some measure protection against
hardware failure but we don't have
protection against is people who are
malicious right if someone goes in and
like hacks your Google account and
deletes all those files then you have a
whole lot of protection against that now
with Google 1 and a lot of cloud sync
apps you can go back in time and restore
files out of the trash but you usually
have like a 30-day time limit on that
but again somebody could go in there and
empty the trash or you could
accidentally change a file and not
realize it until a month down the road
and realize oh wow I needed the old
version that file and now it's gone
forever so I think you should have a
backup strategy that extends beyond
cloud sync and there are a couple of
different options so the option that I
use personally and the one that I
recommend for most people is to use a
separate cloud backup app like Backblaze
or CrashPlan and I mean these back
layers here because the one that I use
but for about five dollars a month or 60
bucks a year they will backup an
unlimited amount of data on your
computer across any hard drive connected
to it with the exception of any like
network attached storage but the other
thing is that provides some measure of
redundancy if something gets into your
Google Drive and messes with it or
someone deletes all those files they are
also backed up in Backblaze and for me I
want to have my data in multiple
different places this is kind of a pain
in the butt to do but if there ever
comes a time where one of those you know
one of those data silos goes down you're
gonna be very happy you took the
precaution and had a backup now the
other option which i think is a little
less robust and good cloud backup but
it's still useful is to just get your
hands on a small external hard drive
plug it in once a month and copy your
data over to that hard drive and then
just keep it um plugged from your
computer keep it stored somewhere that's
secret and safe and then actually
remember to plug it back in once a month
and make that backup and that brings us
to the final step in this process which
is to make use of shortcuts to more
quickly access the most used folders and
files in your
because here's the thing when you have
this beautifully organized tree
structure sometimes you're gonna have
files that are six seven eight levels
deep from the root and if you need
access those files a lot you're going to
be clicking through eight different
levels of folders and then is not very
efficient but luckily computers allow
you to create shortcuts or aliases these
are kind of interchangeable terms to
access those files quickly but even more
efficient than shortcuts in my opinion
is the quick access and favorites areas
of the finder and Explorer on both Mac
and Windows so on Windows it's called
quick access you can easily pin any
folder or file to it on the sidebar and
in Mac OS it's called favorites and it
gives you the exact same functionality
so if you see my Explorer here you'll
see that I have pinned many different
folders that I access on a regular basis
some are permanently there but you're
also gonna see folders related to the
individual video that I'm working on any
given time so right now you're gonna see
172 computer file organization since
that's the video that I'm currently
working on so start using quick access
start using favorites start creating
shortcuts and you're gonna find yourself
navigating your file tree much more
quickly and then as long as you maintain
the integrity of that file tree as long
as you maintain vigilance when saving
new files and creating new folders
you're never going to lose another file
again and you're gonna be so much better
organized of course the best way to stay
organized is to be very deliberate about
the projects that you take on about the
files that you create in the first place
about the content that you consume this
is called being an essentialist and
involves being very in tune with your
priorities and your values in life and
if you want to get better at doing this
I have a book recommendation for you
essentialism the disciplined pursuit of
less by Greg McEwan is one of my
absolute favorite self-improvement books
it's one of the most useful that I have
found in my personal experience and if
you want to actually listen to that book
for free you can do so by going over to
audible.com slash Thomas or by texting
Thomas to 500 500 on your phone doing
that will get you a free 30-day trial of
audible service which comes with a free
audiobook download which can be anything
you want but of course I'm going to
recommend essentialism but it also comes
with two audible originals you cannot
get anywhere else along with tons of
audio workout fitness yoga and
meditation programs and of course
audible is the best place on the
internet to get your hands on audiobooks
they have an on
library with all the bestsellers lots of
obscure stuff and things from basically
any genre that you could want and they
also have an excellently designed app
with a lot of great features including a
sleep timer for using it at night the
ability to add notes at specific time
stamps within your book and easy
controls for jumping forwards or
backwards just in case you want to fast
forward or if you didn't catch something
you can easily go back and listen to it
again so once again if you want to get a
free trial of audible service for 30
days that comes with a free audiobook
download to audible originals that you
cannot get anywhere else and all those
audio workout meditation programs go
over to audible.com slash Thomas and
sign up or text Thomas to 500 500 on
your phone big thanks as always goes out
to audible for sponsoring this video and
being a big supporter of my channel and
thank you as well for watching hopefully
you found this video helpful hopefully
it was a great complement to that paper
organization video which I'm going to
put right here in case you didn't see it
and of course you can always subscribe
right there if you haven't done so
already and you want to get
notifications of new videos click right
there to get a free copy of my book on
how to earn better grades or if you
haven't seen my latest collaboration
video with my friend Matt to give Bella
I'm gonna have that linked right here so
definitely check that out thanks again
for watching and I will see you in the
next video