but the loss of her Aristotle once said
that we are what we repeatedly do
excellence then is not an act but a
habit and this reality is reassuring
because it reminds us that achieving our
goals requires lots of little manageable
steps over time rather than one giant
Herculean effort but it's also stressful
because it means committing to changing
our behavior on a day-to-day basis for a
long period of time and whether you're
trying to increase your endurance or
learn to play an instrument to read more
or even do something as simple as take
care of a plant every day you probably
know from experience the process of
adding new habits into your day-to-day
life is a difficult one now I wanted to
know what exactly makes this process so
difficult for different people so a
couple of days ago asked over on my
Instagram what was the biggest thing
that prevents you guys from adding new
positive habits to your day-to-day life
and I got some pretty interesting
answers including some funny ones like
pizza an evil twin of Jorgen von
strangle that hits me with the whip
every time I'm trying to do something
useful but a lot of the answers seem to
be variations on two key problems one
actually remembering to do the habit and
the other one which was by far the most
common answer pure unadulterated
laziness so today I want to share a
little hack that I've been using for
quite a while which can help with both
of these problems this is something that
can help you both remember to do those
habits and actually make them easier to
do and it involves using if-then logic
to bind those habits to things that you
already do every single day if then
logic crops up everywhere from math to
computer programming to game design and
it's usually implemented in what are
called conditional statements so let me
briefly explain exactly what these are
and how they work using one of my
favorite games Magic the Gathering in
magic you have two different types of
abilities activated abilities and
triggered abilities activated abilities
or ones that require you to take action
to use them so for example take this
card birds-of-paradise
this little symbol here is telling me
that I have to tap the card in order to
use the action printed on it
by contrast triggered abilities or ones
that automatically happen when something
else happens so in the case of a card
like Man O'War the ability on the card
is going to be triggered automatically
when it enters the battle field you
don't have to do anything it's a
conditional statement if it enters the
battle field then you bounce something
back to your opponent's hand
then your opponent probably flips the
table so let's move on from there and
look at how these conditional statements
might be used in a computer program say
YouTube's recommendation algorithm now
this is an incredibly complicated piece
of software even YouTube's engineers
don't know exactly how it works it's
kind of black box but one thing we know
that it does do is change up the
recommendations you see on your homepage
based on your behavior
so for example if you were to click the
like button on this video then some code
would automatically go into effect to
show you more videos like this one and
likewise if you were to click the
dislike button you would see fewer
videos like this by the way that's an
invitation to Clint blind button so
here's how all of this relates to habit
building what we want to do is set the
if part of the statement as something
you already do every single day or
hopefully multiple times a day and then
set the then part of the statement to
the habit that you want to start
building in an ideal world this would
mean that you would start to do your new
habits automatically regardless of what
they were going to the gym more often
actually remembering to oil your
cybernetic augmentations just meditating
every single day whatever it is there
will be absolutely no conscious effort
involved it would be like that triggered
ability on the magic card but
unfortunately at least in this context
we aren't automatons our brains don't
run on computer code and as a result
there's no 100% foolproof way to build
this triggered ability into our minds
the best that we can do is try to set
things up so that the habit that we're
trying to build is more like that
triggered ability like that Man O'War
card then that activated ability like
the birds-of-paradise
and this actually works out really well
cuz I freakin love jellyfish and my
friend had a parakeet in high school and
I hated that thing anyway the best way
to accomplish this is through
environmental design you want to start
looking for ways that you can set up
your living space and your tools so that
the things you do every single day both
remind you to perform your habits and
make it easier to do so and with that it
is time for some examples I'm gonna
start with a thing that actually gave me
the inspiration for this whole
conditional statements idea in the first
place which was putting a door frame
pull-up bar in my office doorway that
way every single time I walk into my
office I do five pull-ups and I get
really good at pull-ups as a result and
I gotta admit this is not an original
idea my dad used to be in the military
before I was born and he once told me
that to get into the mess hall where
they actually ate lunch dinner and all
those other meals of the day breakfast
second breakfast elevenses all those
things you had to do five pull-ups
before you
actually go in there and as a result all
the cadets got really good at doing
pull-ups and doing pull-ups is something
that I personally want to get really
good at hence the door frame pull-up bar
to my office I also applied this idea
back in college to the task of doing
push-ups every single morning and
getting up early on a consistent basis
and I did this by putting my alarm
underneath the coffee table in my room
not only did that require me to get down
on my knees and reach for the phone to
actually turn it off in the morning
which was more moving around more action
that would actually wake me up but at
that point I was now down on the ground
and I might as well do some push-ups
since I'm down there and this example is
a great illustration of how our brains
are not like computers because I could
easily just get up and not do the
push-ups so it's really all about
putting yourself in the position to make
doing the habit easier it's not about a
foolproof method now so far all I've
talked about our habits that improve
your physical well-being but what if you
wanted to write more often what if you
wanted to get into a journaling habit or
do NaNoWriMo or write the next great
Harry Potter fanfiction that dethrones
the current greatest one which is
clearly my immortal well what if you
went into your computer's startup
settings and said to automatically open
up your favorite writing program every
time you turn your computer on and you
can pair that up with the application
blocking properties of an app like
freedom which could lock down your
browser and your games making writing
the obvious choice whenever you turn
your computer on now putting all of
these ideas aside you could of course
use a task manager or a calendar app to
create reminders to do your habits but
this only solves the reminding half of
the problem changing your environment
and your tools to create these little
if-then pairings to create these
conditional statements actually solves
both halves the problem it both reminds
you to do the habit and combats the
laziness problem that's so many of you
cited by making it so much easier to do
now there are lots of other methods out
there for building strong habits but for
me using conditional logic was a
creative solution that helped me get
even better at doing it and it's worth
remembering that for any problem there
is almost always a creative solution out
there that hasn't been found yet so
instead of sticking to the established
methods be they online lists or even
videos like this one it's often better
to analyze the details the problem
yourself and try to come up with a
creative solution doing this is a skill
that can benefit you both in your
personal life with things like how to
building but also in your career and if
you're wondering how you can start
improving that skill one you
full tool you should check out is
brilliant org at its core brilliant is a
tool that can help you learn math
science and computer science much more
effectively than with traditional
methods but along the way it can also
help you become a more creative and
capable problem solver as well all
brilliants courses prioritize active
learning and problem solving right from
the get-go so you'll find yourself
immediately improving your analytical
and creative capabilities whether you're
learning calculus figuring out how
gravitational physics works breaking
down sorting algorithms and computer
science or tackling any of the other
courses in their library this also means
that you won't find yourself bored
because unlike traditional lecture style
classes you'll be using what you learn
right away I am a huge fan of brilliance
learning philosophy which prioritizes
active learning and curiosity and
allowing failure so if you want to start
improving your problem-solving skills I
definitely recommend you give them a try
to start learning for free you can head
on over to brilliant org slash Thomas
Frank which you'll find in the
description down below and if you're
among the first 83 people to click that
link and sign up you're also going to
get 20% off of your annual premium
subscription I want to give a big thanks
to brilliant for sponsoring this video
and being a huge supporter of this
channel in general and as always guys
thank you so much for watching this
video if you enjoyed it clicking that
like button is appreciated as always as
we talked about that conditional logic
will start to kick in and it helps both
you and my channel and if you haven't
subscribed yet definitely do so right
there so you don't miss out on future
videos you can also click right over
there to get a free copy of my book on
how to earn better grades or click right
here to see one more video on this
channel also while you're here don't
forget to follow me over on Instagram
where I'm doing IG TV videos answering
DMS and posting all the time so
definitely do that
thanks for watching and I will see you
in the next video