let's get right to it so you're taking a
test you're looking at a question you've
already written an answer for and you're
not quite sure about that answer should
you change that answer conventional
wisdom says no but I'm going to spoil it
right up front for you yes in most cases
you should change your answers many many
Studies have been conducted on this
question over the past 70 years and the
data from those studies is clear most
answer changes are from wrong to right
that means students who actually do
change their answers on tests tend to
score better and get better grades this
documented fact goes completely against
the advice that test takers have been
given for years we're often told to go
with our gut you know stay with your
instincts go with your first answer cuz
if you want to change it you're probably
just worriedly second guessing yourself
teachers parents and even SAT prep
guides have been giving out this advice
for years and here's the most
interesting part of this and also the
most sad even though I'm giving you this
data even though I'm telling you and
showing you and even if you believe it
you're not likely to start changing your
answers you're actually likely to keep
sticking with your initial answer in
future tests so we're really trying to
explain two things here number one why
people tend to stick with their original
answers in the first place and number
two why even when presented with the
data to show they should change them
they tend to not do it now out of all
the research that's been done on this
topic specifically and all the
information out there on cognitive
biases the brain bugs that form the
underlying foundation of the problem the
most succinct answer that I found was in
a book called Why We Make Mistakes by
Joseph T henan I'm going through this
book right now and so far it's a
fascinating overview of many of the
mistakes we make in our everyday lives
and the cognitive biases that cause them
for the specific mistake of sticking
with your first answers on tests though
Palin identifies two underlying causes
of the problem number one the power of
First Impressions and number two the
fear of regret first impressions are so
powerful because our brains can look at
a situation and make a snap decision on
it very quickly in addition we also tend
to take limited information and then
fill in the gaps with conclusions of our
own this phenomenon is explained pretty
well in Daniel Conan's book Thinking
Fast and Slow where he outlines the
differences between the brain system one
and system two system one being the one
that makes the snap decisions the big
player here though is the fear of regret
and specifically people tend to regret
mistakes that come about through action
rather than those that come about
through inaction essentially if
something's going to go wrong we would
prefer that it happened because we
didn't do something rather than because
we did something these feelings of
Greater regret from actions actually
cause a memory bias and in studies done
on this topic students tend to
overestimate the amount of times they've
changed answers from right to wrong and
underestimate the opposite it's this
memory bias that leads people to
continue sticking with their original
answers even when they're presented with
the facts that show that changing them
is probably a better course of action so
if there was any real advice here is
that if you feel like you should change
an answer in a test and you feel
justified in doing so you should
probably do it additionally if you're
feeling resistance towards changing that
answer realize that it's probably caused
by your own cognitive biases now this
doesn't mean that you'll always be right
when you change your answer on a test
but statistically most of the time you
will be so that's it for this video
hopefully you find these tips useful on
your next exam and next week's video
will be the start of my accelerated
Japanese challenge review which will
actually be coming to you from Japan so
look forward to
that hey guys thanks so much for
watching my my video on whether or not
you should change your test answers if
you want new videos every single week on
being a more effective student then
click the big red subscribe button right
there you can also get a copy of my book
on earning better grades for free and if
you want one just click the picture and
I'll will send you one if you want to
get links to the book I mentioned or any
of the other research I did for this
video then head over to the companion
blog post by clicking the orange logo
right there if you missed last week's
video it's over how to avoid making
stupid mistakes on your exams so if you
haven't seen it definitely check it out
and if you'd like to connect or suggest
ideas for new videos I'm on Twitter at
tomf Frankle or you can leave a comment
on this video thanks for watching
[Music]