we have talked a lot on this channel
about how to do well academically how to
study effectively how to Ace your tests
and how to crush those homework
assignments even when you have barely
any time to do them but of course
successful students don't just do well
academically they do well all around so
that begs the question what separates
truly successful students who have it
all together in all areas of their lives
from everyone else well that's what I
want to talk about in this video and
today we're going to cover eight habits
of successful students and yes this is
definitely a riff off of Steven Cub's
excellent book The Seven Habits of
Highly Effective People people which I
have read and loved but these eight
habits are unique these come from my own
observations of people that I know who
are successful and things have tried to
cultivate in my own life and I think
every single one of them is going to
help you in the upcoming semester so
let's Dive Right
In to start things off successful
students are forward thinkers J.R tolken
wrote In The Hobbit that it does not do
to leave a live dragon out of your
calculations if you live near him and as
a student you have a lot of live dragons
to contend with not just on the academic
side of things but on all fronts you've
got your career plans you've got
relationships you have your living
situation errands you need to run there
is a lot to keep track of and when I was
in college I had a lot of friends who
always seemed to be scrambling to get
these things done at the last second
they were basically letting life sneak
up on them but if you can build a
Forward Thinking mindset this isn't
going to happen to you and you'll also
position yourself for opportunities that
would pass others by so if you're not
already a natural forward thinker if
you're not automatically thinking of
things that are coming up in the near
future how do you become one well I
definitely think it is possible because
I didn't used to be one but now I am
when I was a kid I remember my mom would
just like look up from whatever she was
doing often times and ask me Hey Thomas
have you brushed your teeth today and I
remember thinking like how do you think
of stuff like that I wasn't talking
about brushing my teeth you weren't
brushing your teeth it just popped into
your mind and eventually I realized it
was because she cared about the health
of her sons and she was simply being
mindful about it and I worked to become
that kind of a person myself so if
you're like I was back then you don't
already have this mental Machinery put
into place the first step is to build
some structures into your everyday
routines that remind you to think in a
Forward Thinking manner one good way to
start doing this is to create a reminder
in your task management system or your
calendar to sit down once a week and
think what do I have coming up in the
near future do I need to sign up for
classes well then I should make a
reminder for the exact time that the
class scheduler opens so I can get in
there and get my classes before everyone
else takes the good ones or do I need to
get an apartment soon if you live in a
college town like I did then it's likely
that every apartment complex is going to
have their leases start around the exact
same time and because of that everyone's
going to be signing leases all in one
big drove so do yours early otherwise
come next semester you're going to be
living in a van down by the river and
while you're going through this mental
exercise also think about your
relationships maybe you have somebody
who has a birthday coming up soon or you
have a friend that you haven't talk to
in a while I find that when you actually
think about these things and when you
apply a Forward Thinking mindset to your
relationships you tend to maintain them
better and this is important because as
people get older they start to get
busier and they start to have less time
for their friends and it's only people
who are deliberate about maintaining
their relationships that actually keep
them the second habit is that successful
students deliberately move towards
adulthood they don't let adulthood sneak
up on them and by that I'm not talking
about becoming a person who hates fun
and tells kids to get out their lawn but
every human is going to have skills they
need to build and challenges they need
to face at some point in their lives and
a lot of people try to push those things
off as much as they possibly can but if
you can become the kind of person who is
willing to take on those things early
I'm talking about things like having
your own bank account doing your own
taxes or filling out your own financial
aid forms or like learning how to iron a
shirt or do your own laundry then once
you have to do those things you've
already got that base of skills to apply
to
them habit number three successful
students strive to become what I like to
call solution finders they're the kind
of people that when faced with a tough
problem that doesn't have an immediately
apparent solution they are willing to
push through and figure out how to solve
it and sadly a lot of students aren't
like this a friend of mine named Matt is
a web developer at a pretty big company
and this company values this solution
finding mindset so much that they have a
rule for people who get stuck on
problems they call it the 15 minute rule
essentially if an employee gets stuck on
a problem they have to spend 15 more
minutes working on that problem before
they're allowed to ask for help and
during that time they have to document
everything they do and write down what
didn't work so that way when they do ask
for help they're able to give context to
the person who's helping them
additionally once they hit that 15minute
Mark they must ask for help help and
this rule creates a nice balance it
makes them be independent and solve
problems on their own but also ensures
that they're not being so stubborn that
they never ask for help and that ensures
that they're not wasting the company's
time and adopting this rule will
actually prove very useful to you as a
student because if you're willing to
solve problems independently you're
going to solve a lot of them that you
would have originally asked for help on
and if you do have to ask for help
you're going to show your teacher that
you take the problems seriously and that
you're not just crying out for help the
moment things get tough
habit number four is to start actively
building relationships with your
teachers with your professors and with
other faculty members at your school or
university when you do this you start to
build a network of people who aren't
just in your immediate age group or at
your same level of progression and it
also has a couple of other very good
benefits number one these people are
going to be able to tell you about
opportunities that you would have
otherwise missed and if you ever happen
to need a letter of recommendation for a
job application or a scholarship those
are going to be the people who you can
go to because now they know you and they
trust you and they're going to be
willing to do it and you probably
shouldn't ask for a recommendation from
your roommate Jimmy so how do you start
building this network well a great first
step comes at the beginning of a new
semester go up to the teacher at the end
of each class introduce yourself briefly
shake their hand and just tell them
you're excited to be there that makes a
really great first impression
additionally in your free time if you
happen to come across like an article
that you think one of your professors
would be interested in email them that
article just say hey I read this and I
thought of you I remember back in 2011 I
was taking my first marketing class in
college and this was right around the
time that Val was getting ready to
release Portal 2 and they did something
really weird with the marketing for
Portal 2 they had this weird convoluted
game setup where people could buy games
on Steam and play lots and lots of hours
in those games and that would all
contribute to making Portal 2 release a
couple of days early so essentially they
found a way to let all these other games
that weren't selling all that well ride
the coattails of this big anticipated
game and I thought that was a brilliant
marketing strategy so I found an article
about it I sent it to my marketing
professor and said hey I think you'd be
interested in this and the next week he
actually talked about it in class so
doing that definitely helped to build
that
relationship the fifth habit is that
successful students are always trying to
learn outside of class they're trying to
learn from a variety of different
sources and they are branching out into
different areas that aren't on their
narrow major path and I think this is
really important to do because once you
start getting interested in a variety of
different subjects and you start
dabbling in different areas you start to
build this diverse web of Connections in
your brain that allows you to be more
creative in your main work plus when you
take just a little bit of time to Branch
out from your major path you might
stumble onto something that actually
proves to be a huge Boon to your future
career prospects one great example is my
best friend Martin he's always been
really interested in language learning
but he majored in Mis in college but
that didn't stop him from creating a
Blog all about how to learn new
languages and that actually got him some
recognition in the language learning
community he was actually on a list of
language learning experts pretty
recently not to mention the experience
he got building that website actually
led directly to him getting hired at a
web development agency in our city right
after graduating who usually didn't like
to hire recent graduates because he had
a lot of experience that most people
didn't
have habit number six is to constantly
be keeping your ear to the ground for
opportunities here's the thing when
you're in school or especially when
you're in college and university there
are a ton of opportunities around you
but you have to be willing to look for
them and know where to look one great
thing to do is to be keeping your eye
out for bulletin boards around your
campus or in your school because a lot
of opportunities are going to be posted
as flyers on those bulletin boards
additionally follow your school's social
media accounts and I'm not just talking
about the main social media account
follow your professors and your teachers
follow departments that you're a part of
because a lot of these departments and
professors they're going to post
opportunities that they think their
students would be good fits for and this
habit is actually directly related to
how I got my first internship because I
was following my school's Career Center
on Twitter and they posted a tweet about
a big company in our area that was
putting on this freshman leadership
seminar so I saw the tweet I signed up I
got accepted and at that event I met a
mentor who was instrum mental in getting
me hired at that
internship the seventh habit is that
successful students put a lot of effort
into keeping themselves both physically
and mentally fit when you're a student
who's ambitious there's often this
General mindset that you should be
spending all of your time studying or
pursuing opportunities and when a lot of
students do this they often let their
nutrition habits their exercise habits
and their sleep go by the wayside and
what's worse they'll often work
themselves to the point where they
mentally burn out or they become
depressed or have a lot of anxiety and
the sad thing is when they're letting
their physical and mental health go by
the wayside they aren't able to perform
in the things that they really want to
do in the first place and truly
successful students know this which is
why they make time for exercise they
make time for making good healthy meals
or getting them at the dining Center and
they also get enough sleep every single
night and one little side note that I'll
make here successful students are
willing to ask for help if they need it
if they're dealing with mental burnout
or anxiety or depression they will go
ask a professional if they can't deal
with those issues themselves
and that brings us to the final habit on
the list successful students try things
before they think they're ready I want
to underline this idea with something
that Neil picha talks about in his book
The Happiness equation in the book he
talks about how people generally
approach new skills or challenges and
how they do it in a linear way they feel
like they have to be able to do it first
and then they'll want to do it and
finally they'll do it but when you think
this way you never actually get to do
the thing because you never gain the
skills to do it in the first place so
Neil encourages you to take that linear
model and make it circular do which
leads to can do because you're gaining
skills through doing that leads to want
to do and the circle repeats and
enforces itself plus you're often much
more qualified than you think you are a
lot of students and a lot of people in
general deal with impostor syndrome they
think who am I to do this I don't have a
certification I don't have a
qualification but in many cases you
don't need it I'll give you an example
when I was a freshman at College I
really wanted to join a club on campus
called Business Council these were
basically like the leaders of the
business school at the University but
they had a rule they only let people in
who are sophomores and above very rarely
would they make an exception for a
freshman so what did I think I didn't
think I'm just going to wait I'm just
going to you know wait till a sophomore
I thought I'm going to apply because
what's the worst that's going to happen
they're going to reject me and I'll try
again next semester so I applied I put
my best foot forward and I got accepted
and what's more during my first semester
as a member I also got elected to the
leadership board so if something seems
exciting to you but it also seems a
little scary try it anyway because that
is what successful students do that
brings us to the end of my list but if
you have additional ideas or habits you
think I left off of it I would love to
hear from you guys in the comments down
below so definitely let me know what
you're thinking if you like this video
if you found it helpful definitely give
it a like to support this channel if
you're not subscribed yet you can
subscribe right there to get new videos
every single week and you can also get a
free copy of my book on how to earn
better grades right there you can check
out our latest podcast episode right
there where we go over 10 of our
favorite fiction books or if you'd like
another video on this channel click
right there or smash your face into it
or whatever it'll probably work
especially if you're using a phone and I
will see you guys next week