this is a hobbit but we're not talking
about Hobbits today we are talking about
habits now you may have heard the old
adage that it takes 21 days to form a
new habit but you might be interested to
learn that there are some researchers at
the University College of London who
figured out in their studies that the
average participant took 66 days to form
a new habit concretely now whether the
actual number is 21 days 66 days or
something else the gist of it is this
building a new habit is difficult and
you probably know this yourself if
you've ever tried to get into the habit
of running every day or getting into a
reading habit or anything of the sort
building habits is hard and when it
comes to building them we could use all
the help we can get so today I'm going
to show you a tool that I've been using
that can help you build really really
strong habits and have a lot of fun
doing it the tool is called habit RPG
and it's a web app that helps you get
the motivation to build habits and get
things done by taking Concepts from
video games specifically RPGs now maybe
you're wondering how can Concepts from
role playing games applied to the real
world well let me give you an example as
a kid my absolute favorite RPG was
Pokémon Red for the Game Boy now I know
this wasn't a typical RPG since you make
these little critters fight gain levels
and take performance- enhancing drugs
instead of doing the work yourself but
deal with
it aside from that one little
distinction the mechanics are all there
you've got your ultimate goal of
becoming the Pokémon League champ and
you've got to get into the habit of
finding countless battles against all
manner of weird looking things to get
there seriously what is this thing the
game does a fantastic job of motivating
you to keep this habit up by providing
your Pokémon with experience points for
each battle one eventually they'll gain
levels get stat boosts and even evolve
all the while you're getting other
rewards like a bicycle new powers that
let you explore new places and a
complimentary gambling
addiction it all comes together into one
fantastically engineered package
designed to keep kids from ever knowing
the layout of the areas their parents
drive them through throughout dozens and
dozens of hours you put into the game in
order to reach the end you almost never
feel your motivation waning battle after
battle is fought without draining an
ounce of the willpower to go on and this
can be attributed to two main factors
number one the game is just damn fun but
number two the makers designed smart
reward mechanisms to keep you going
these reward mechanisms experience
points leveling gear upgrades they're
all built right into habit RPG the only
difference is that you have to practice
your daily habits and get things done to
earn them rather than telling a small
Mouse to shoot lightning at a turtle
so let's go through the main features of
the
app once you sign in to Habit RPG you'll
be graded with an interface consisting
of a few key features first and foremost
is your character you'll notice that
he's got a couple of bars right now one
of them is for experience and the other
one is for health below that you'll find
four different columns habits dailies
to-dos and rewards the habits column
lets you track habits that you're trying
to build or break when you create a new
one you can decide whether it's a
positive habit a negative one or both if
you want to eat more vegetables for
example you'd make a positive one and if
you're trying to stop drinking soda then
that' be a negative one the Daily's
column is for tracking habits that you
want to practice at least once per day
for me this is the main attraction of
habit RPG I have my entire morning
ritual here along with several other
habits and that ritual helps me get a
productive start to each and every day
by the way if you'd like to learn about
how I build my morning ritual and go
about it then the description will have
a link to my blog post on the subject
the to-dos column lets you track one-off
tasks so you can actually use habit RPG
as a task manager as well if you like
and finally there's the rewards column
this column is a place where you can
reward yourself for consistently good
behavior at first you only see custom
rewards things you can create for
yourself like watch an episode of Game
of Thrones but eventually you'll find
gear and spells for your character here
as well rewards are paid for with money
and unless you're getting money from
Obama or or the Tooth Fairy then usually
you got to work for it and in habit RPG
that's the case every time you practice
a habit and check it off your list
you'll gain two things experience and
money with the money you can buy
upgrades gear for your character and
lots of other things and the experience
will eventually let you level up which
unlocks more things and lets you pick
things like classes and other Advanced
features down the line eventually you'll
be able to join parties with other
players and for me this is the reason
that habit RPG is such a motivating tool
when you're party with somebody else and
you go on a quest your actions have
consequences that affect both you and
the other people in your party that
means if you don't do it daily not only
will you lose health but your friends
will lose Health as well and if they
lose all their health and die they'll
actually lose a level and a piece of
gear so if you don't do your dailies
you're going to be hearing about it from
your friends this entire process is
called gamification and for me gamifying
my habits has been incredibly useful
especially since I'm held accountable to
my roommate and will actually harm his
character if I don't do my dailies every
day the apps not just for desktop
browsers either you'll find apps for
both the iPhone and Android platforms so
if you're looking for a new tool that
can amplify your habit building
abilities then give habit RPG a try also
if you're interested I'm going to be
setting up a guild for college infog
geek readers on habit RPG so if you
check the link in the description below
you'll find the companion blog post for
this video and there you'll find the
link to the guild once it's
up hey there thanks for watching my
video tutorial on using habit RPG if you
found it useful I'd absolutely love it
if you can give the video a like and
share it with a friend if you want to
get more videos on being awesome at
College every single week click the
Subscribe button yeah that one below
that you'll find week's video so check
it out if you haven't seen it yet you
can also find notes and links that go
with this video by clicking on the
orange logo right over there and if
you're interested you can also get a
free chapter of my book hacking
productivity by clicking to cover if you
want to connect ask questions or suggest
a topic for a future video leave a
comment or you can connect me on Twitter