this is a copy of my tax return from
2010 just eight short years ago and it
says that during the course of that year
I made a grand total of nine thousand
two hundred and twenty six dollars
contrast that to last year 2017 where I
made easily more than ten times that
amount and with that increase in income
came some lifestyle upgrades back then I
lived at a cramped dorm room and I had
to share it with another person and
beyond that I had to share a bathroom
with 43 other guys in my hall compared
to today where I've got a two-bedroom
apartment where I actually got my own
bathrooms pretty fancy I know and I've
got a pretty good view as well also back
then a all my meals in the cafeteria or
I made microwave chicken nuggets yes I
know those are very unhealthy
whereas today I can actually buy pretty
much whatever I want I can cook fancy
food I can go out to eat more often so
there has been a big improvement on the
dining out front as well when I look at
my life now versus back then there is no
question that things have improved
across the board yet in many ways I'm no
happier now than I was back then I'm
certainly a happy person but then again
I always kind of have been so what's the
deal here I've made all this progress I
put in all this work but for what
exactly this is a question that deserves
a closer look as my experience is not at
all uncommon in fact it's near universal
in general people do not find themselves
happier on a day to day basis as a
result of getting promoted making more
money or making other life upgrades like
buying a bigger house or getting a
better car instead we find that as our
lives improve our desires tastes and
expectations rise to match the result is
a sort of happiness equilibrium this
effect has been called at the hedonic
treadmill or hedonic adaptation and a
lot of psychological research has gone
into this concept in the recent past but
it's definitely not a new thing as st.
Augustine put it a true saying it is
desire hath no rest is infinite in
itself endless and as one calls it a
perpetual rack or horse mill that quote
has over 400 years old
and honestly we've probably been
thinking about this concept for as long
as our brains have been capable of
introspective thought still it's easy to
forget it to get caught up dreaming
about just how awesome life would be if
we had just
little bit more money or just a bit more
space and of course the modern world is
all too eager to bolster these kinds of
thoughts as Daniel Kahneman the father
of behavioral economics and the author
of the book Thinking Fast and Slow puts
it people are exposed to many messages
that encourage them to believe that a
change of weight scent to hair color or
coverage car clothes or many other
aspects will produce a market
improvement in their happiness our
research suggests a moral and a warning
noting that you focus on will make as
much difference as you think but what if
you actually do want to maximize your
happiness or to phrase that question in
a way that appeals to me more how do you
improve your average day if getting a
bigger house or making more money or
getting more awards and accolades won't
do it then what will well this is the
kind of question that will get you a
million different kinds of answers some
will recommend minimalism some will
recommend different life philosophies or
religions and some will recommend
spending more time jumping on
trampolines which I heartily agree with
but here I simply want to suggest five
changes that you can start making to
your life that and my experience
actually do improve the average day to
day experience and make it a happier one
first and I think most importantly give
yourself time to tinker explore and play
or protect that time if you currently
have it one thing that a lot of people
start losing as they get older is this
unstructured time where they can tinker
and explore and this is something that
has happened to me for sure in the past
few years as I move further into my
career become more successful made more
money all these kinds of things I found
that my schedule has a lot less time for
this kind of exploration I have a lot of
things that are pre-planned that I have
to do and there's certainly lots of
external rewards for doing those things
but I found that I don't feel I have the
time anymore to spend an afternoon
figuring out how to set up an Arduino or
I to code something just because it
seems interesting and when your entire
daily schedule is pre-planned and you
feel like you're just some sort of
regimented robot things can start to get
a little bit depressing so protect that
time I actually read an article in QZ
just the other day saying that doctors
are now prescribing a play for children
because parents are in this mad dash to
over schedule their kids lives they got
them signed up for school and music
lessons and sports and all kinds of
stuff to the point where
there's never any moment where the kid
can just go outside and do whatever they
want and I don't want to knock the good
intentions of these parents they think
that what they're doing is going to
prepare their children for the future
and give them a leg up but as science
has found recently play is very
important so if you are a parent give
your kid unstructured time but even if
you aren't protect your own play isn't
something that benefits only children it
also benefits adults it's useful at any
age
secondly make sure that you're staying
physically active and make that physical
activity fun we are built to move we are
built to exercise we have these bodies
that are adapted for working and moving
through an environment so if you're
constantly sitting around whether it be
through work or they'll be coming home
and watching Netflix or playing video
games at the end of the night you're
naturally going to start feeling less
and less happy now when people are told
to exercise their brains usually go to
things like running on a treadmill or
getting a gym membership things that
feel like an obligation so what I'm
going to suggest for you here is to find
something that you truly enjoy doing
that's fun but it still gets your heart
rate up for me right now that's rock
climbing and mountain biking and I still
also love going to the arcades to play
DDR I found lots of ways to exercise
that I'm truly excited to do every
single day and that makes my day-to-day
experience a much better one so you
should do the same all right
tip number three is to work to minimize
things in your daily life that you don't
like instead of asking yourself how do I
get the bigger house how do I get the
better car how do I get that next thing
that seems like it's going to improve my
life exponentially ask yourself what do
I have to do every day that kind of
annoys me now I could probably make an
entire video listing off examples here
so I'm just going to give you one if you
have a long commute and bumper-to-bumper
traffic that you absolutely hate doing
then how could you kind of take that out
of your life or at least make it better
one suggestion would be to actually
change the time at which you make that
commute a lot of people commute during
rush hour because they want to get up at
a certain time they might want to work
out at home then go to work but what if
you got up maybe an hour earlier and
then you drove to work at 6 a.m. when
there's nobody else on the road or maybe
instead of driving to work you ditch the
car altogether and bike to work we
actually just got an office a couple of
weeks ago and I found that it took me
about 15 minutes to drive to work in
regular traffic but only 17
my bike there so really just a two
minute difference and if you factor in
the time it takes me to drive through
the garage and find a parking spot
biking is actually faster not to mention
more fun so whatever it is analyze the
things that annoy you and start to look
for ways that you can either remove
those things from your life or optimize
them and make them a bit more bearable
tip number four is to take the
occasional big break this could be
taking a vacation or inviting a friend
to come stay with you and doing some
different activities in your own home
but you need to break yourself out of
your routine every once in a while and
this is something that I am pretty bad
at I get a lot of things on my plate and
I feel like I don't have time to take a
vacation or that I need to optimize
travel by you know scheduling a bunch of
business trips instead of just vacations
but when you actually take a vacation
you get a mental reset and that mental
reset sort of revitalizes your brains
ability to work effectively and makes
you overall happier so if you have the
time or even if you don't feel you have
the time find the time to take these big
breaks they don't have to take a lot of
money they don't have to involve a ton
of travel they just need to get you out
of your normal routine and have you do
something different now we've got one
more tip that I want to share with you
here which is really really important
but before I share it I do want to also
share an observation about something
that is not going to make you happy so
if you think about the hedonic treadmill
if you think about the fact that these
increases in your life in whatever areas
they may come from aren't going to make
you happier on a day-to-day basis
then it becomes pretty clear that a lot
of the reasons that we use social media
for such as broening or follow or count
or getting more retweets or likes or all
these things aren't going to make you
happy and I think this bears mentioning
because the people the engineers the
product designers who are behind these
companies are paid huge salaries to
design these apps in a way that makes
them essentially addicting that makes
them feel like they are going to make
you happier but from personal experience
I can tell you that your average day to
day happiness is not going to change
when you go from two likes per tweet to
a hundred likes per tweet it really
doesn't make a difference
so yes use social media to bring about
certain benefits you can make new
relationships through it you can bolster
your career through it but don't be
chasing those advantage
metrics the likes and the retweets and
the followers because they will not make
you happy but what will make you happy
which is our final tip here is face to
face interaction with other people on a
daily basis I really want to mention
this explicitly because a lot of people
are content to have digital
relationships - I am people I talk to
people over Skype or play games together
and these things are all great and they
can Forge good friendships but nothing
replaces actually seeing people face to
face and doing things with them in real
life now with all this talk about the
hedonic treadmill and how all these
progressions aren't going to necessarily
improve your day to day life in the way
that you think they will I do think it
bears mentioning that I am NOT
suggesting you abandon all of your goals
sell your possessions and go live in the
mountain as an ascetic unless you want
to I mean that could be pretty cool I
think Martin would want to do it but
seriously the fact that increasing your
income or getting a promotion at your
job or getting a better house won't
necessarily improve your day to day
happiness as much as you think it will
doesn't mean that these goals aren't
worthwhile for one achieving those goals
might lead to opening doors that
actually could lead to day to day
happiness improvements but a more
important point is this I believe that
an integral part of being happy is the
very process of evolving and progressing
human beings are built to explore to
test their limits to constantly try new
things we are not happy being stagnant
as Ray Dalio put it evolving is life's
greatest accomplishment and its greatest
reward now one area where progression
and evolution tend to bring pretty quick
happiness improvements is in creative
expression in fact I find that I'm much
happier when I figure out how to say
film something really cool like this
slow motion shot or learn a new editing
technique and the great thing is these
improvements in creative expression tend
to come a lot more frequently than big
career jumps so if you want to further
improve your average day find a way to
get creative you could do it the way
that I do it through making videos or
playing music or the way that my best
friend Martin does it through macro
photography or in many other fields out
there that you probably haven't
discovered yet and if you want to
accelerate your skill development in the
field that you choose and master new
techniques quickly check out Skillshare
Skillshare has an expansive catalog of
over 20,000 courses in tons of different
topic areas like digital animation video
editing drawing in business
lots more their courses are also hands
on almost always including a sample
project that you can sink your teeth
into so you can start learning actively
now one course that I want to highlight
for you this week is the fundamentals of
DSLR photography by Justin bridges
photography has a ton of disciplines yes
there is macro photography there's
landscapes and portraits but all of
these disciplines rely on a fundamental
foundation of camera skills aperture
lighting ISO shutter speed and Justins
course goes through all these different
techniques along with recommendations of
what camera gear you should buy in the
first place and the best settings to use
so if you wanna start working through
Justin's course or any of the other
courses in scale shares catalog then
click the link in the description down
below and sign up and when you do you're
going to get two months of completely
unlimited access to their entire catalog
of courses absolutely free after that
Skillshare is still very affordable
costing about as much as a Netflix
subscription so this is definitely
something you should try if you want to
start improving your skills I want to
give a big thanks to Skillshare for
sponsoring this video of being a
supporter of this channel and as always
guys thank you so much for watching if
you enjoyed this video and found it
helpful consider hitting that like
button and also hit subscribe right
there so you don't miss out on new
videos when they come out every single
week you can also click right there to
get a free copy of my book on how to
earn better grades follow me on
instagram over @tomfrankly or click
right around here to get one more video
on this channel thanks so much for
watching guys and I will see you in the
next video