hello we are in Boulder Colorado this
week now I will resume your regularly
scheduled study tips and whatnot next
week but today I'm just going to show
you the flat
irons okay here we
go this is what we
want uh rail RAR second third flat irons
Loop to first second flat iron trailer
that's what we
want up we go so
last year I climbed my first mountain in
San Diego Mountain was 1100 FT elevation
gain this will
be400 my next goal is
5,000 in one trip so this doesn't make
it so if you have suggestions for me for
a 5,000 elevation gain mountain that I
should do next let me
know what did you do threw a snowball
what did you threw at me snowball yeah
I found
Stonehenge are you mad that I threw
snowball at you yes okay pretty sure
that's Stonehenge right there we are
going up
there wow
view the district one Hunger Games
announcer in the background over there
something's going
on maybe it's a test this is like the
one thing about Colorado everything that
way is amazing everything that way is
more Iowa basically so I'll just keep
filming this way okay it's time to go up
there 999
88199 9119
725 three slowmo music there's lot of
Boulders here in
Boulder
PR cool
yep are you videoing uh-huh take a
picture it's just been rolling I want
take a
picture oh my God how are you going to
get
down double back flip that's not going
to
work oh my God you're making me so
nervous I don't know where you're going
around there he
is good job so tell me you don't want to
go up
that there we
go areally like the
worst oh this is
awesome this is our new house oh okay
we're going to live here people came and
like
did oh is it Pikachu yeah nice this
Pikachu is drawn by it keeps going men
in 5,000 BC keeps going that way is it a
little bit all right cam all right we're
going to do it
okay took the backpack off it'd be
easier you'd like to see me do that
wouldn't you do things makes
sense you can go out that way oh God I
just looked directly into the
sun survival log day
34 all I've got to eat his
rocks what other kind of art do we got
here we got Sun can't tell what this is
and we got a bear hi hello that's a
pretty freaking cool shot right there so
what do you think of my crib it's got a
skylight built in didn't even have to
pay for it welcome to my new crib my
name is X to the Z exhibit
I'm scared I was going to hit my head on
that you're
good I don't know if I want to go up
there yay okay
hey you did it you did it yeah your help
you're a lot shorter than me and you
didn't start the parkour Club in high
school do you have to like make a waiver
for that club or anything no it wasn't
really like a real club like we didn't
have any
blessings we made a website and we just
like we're like hey kids want to do
parkour okay we'll teach you we had like
three golden rules it's like the three
laws of robotics pretty much it was like
only do what you're comfortable with
with uh ask for help if you need it and
never ever ever do what Eric does cuz
our friend Eric was certifiably insane I
have no memory of this place oh wait we
found the trail
okay hi hello keep filming
me wow I want to climb it she won't let
me got to climbing gear she cares about
safety and stuff
just kidding # lawyers and # liability
and stuff be.com I'm your dad
yeah that giant crossroads right there
is
cool so I thought I'd seen the last of
the cool stuff but
no that's pretty awesome
and
I feel like every good movie or Vlog
should have a
narrative the beginning and a middle and
an end where I stand on top of a
mountain but I don't know if I can get
there apparently there's not a trail
that goes to the top though so I guess I
can't do the closing act
okay maybe end it right here