a writer for The Paris Review once asked
the great science fiction writer Ray
Bradbury where he did his writing his
response I can work anywhere I wrote in
bedrooms and living rooms when I was
growing up with my parents and my
brother and a small house in Los Angeles
I worked on my typewriter in the living
room with the radio and my mother and my
dad and my brother all talking at the
same time later on when I needed an
office and wanted write my novel
Fahrenheit 451 twenty-five years ago I
went up to UCLA and I found a basement
typing room where for 10 cents which you
inserted into the typewriter you could
buy yourself 30 minutes typing time now
this seems a bit surprising at first
especially given all the other famous
writers who had very let's say
particular writing habits for instance
the author Gertrude Stein chose her
writing spots based on whether or not
she'd be able to see a cow walk by but
Bradbury's ability to work anywhere
makes more sense when you hear his
answer to the universe follow-up
question about whether or not he enjoyed
writing yes it's obvious that I do
it's the exquisite joy and madness of my
life and I don't understand writers who
have to work at it if I had to work at
it I would give up because I don't like
working I like to play this is the
kicker Bradbury's intense love of
writing is what enabled him to drown out
all other distractions he wrote because
there was nothing else he'd rather be
doing at the moment and you can probably
think back to things that have consumed
your attention in a similar way for me
at different points in my life those
things have been UI design programming
and most recently playing the guitar
when I'm playing the guitar nothing is
going to distract me because that's
exactly what I want to be doing and I
get into it but there are always less
interesting things that we just have to
do like calculus assignments and ironic
essays about the virtues of nihilism and
crucially as your interest in the work
you're doing diminishes the more
important the optimization of your
environment becomes so today I want to
explore what goes into creating the
perfect study space one where you can
easily slip into the flow state resist
distractions and actually get your work
done fast enough to have some time left
over to play cave story before you gotta
go to bed and when it comes to creating
a great study space the first thing we
need to talk about is context you have a
ton of choice when it comes to study
spots you've got libraries you've got
coffee shops you've got basements of
academic buildings that nobody else
knows about and then there is your dorm
room or your bedroom but wherever you
decide to study you want to make sure
that the place you select is exclusively
for studying and nothing else
that's because context is ever
environmental factors influence a lot of
our behavior so if you put yourself in a
place where the purpose is ambiguous
you're gonna be a lot more likely to
slip into the path of least resistance
which is usually taking quizzes to find
out what your Hogwarts house is now this
is definitely easier to do if you select
the library or the academic basement as
you probably aren't gonna go there for
any other reason but if you happen to
pick your dorm it's much more important
to consider so for an example check out
how my friend Martin set up his study
space he did decide to study and work in
his room but he divided that room up
with a Shoji screen so that way he had a
one isolated area that was only for work
now you definitely don't have to go all
out and buy a Shoji screen like he did
in fact he didn't even buy it was just
laying around but you can use his
example to tailor your own study space
one alternative method would be to turn
your desk into a corner of the room and
make sure that all your fiction books
and your video games and any other
distracting materials are just out of
your field of view that'll make sure
that what you're looking at is
exclusively about the work you're
supposed to be doing secondly you think
about the quality of your lighting
because it really can affect your
productivity now if you can get natural
light that is definitely going to be
your best option
but if you have only artificial light to
work with you can work to control that
because it does make a difference while
I was doing the research for this video
I was especially interested in a German
study that looked at the effects of
color temperature and light intensity on
the productivity of students at the
Colonial University of Applied Sciences
now this study only tracked 50 students
so this area of science could definitely
use more fleshing out but what they did
find is that students were more creative
under warm light at about 3000 Kelvin
and they were able to concentrate better
under colder light at about 6,000 Kelvin
to add to those findings another study
done at Cornell University found that
light that was too dim or too bright
also negatively affected productivity so
with those findings in mind it might be
a good idea to experiment with lighting
in your study area maybe get a lamp for
your desk and experiment with different
color temperature in the bulbs that you
choose for that lamp and on the
brightness end of things you definitely
don't have to go out and buy multiple
bulbs at different levels of brightness
to figure out what works for you
instead for about 10 bucks you can go to
your local hardware store and get a lamp
sight dimmer and if you get a dimmable
bulb you can experiment just by toggling
the switch and seeing what works now in
addition to the color temperature of
your light the actual temperature in the
room that matters a lot as well not only
can an environment that's too hot or too
cold consciously
tract you and make you look up and
daydream and not want to do your work
but it can also unconsciously cause you
to make mistakes while you're actually
working that same Cornell study that I
referenced a couple of minutes ago also
looked at temperature and they found
among other things when temperatures
below 68 degrees or 20 degrees Celsius
employees made 44% more mistakes than an
optimal room temperature 77 degrees or
25 degrees Celsius so if you have access
to the thermostat in your study area
make sure you're setting it to an
optimal temperature for studying and if
you don't maybe try a different location
regardless of where you decide to study
you want to make sure that you have
access to all the things you need for
the particular task that you're doing
that includes notebooks textbooks index
cards if you're gonna make flashcards
for studying and pens and pencils and on
that note of pens and pencils make sure
that what you're writing with is
something that you actually enjoy
writing with now some people definitely
go way further than I would go with this
in fact there's an entire podcast out
there with literally hundreds of
episodes called the pen attic that's all
about pens but I would say don't go for
the cheapest pens that are a pain to
write with because they're just going to
distract you and make process of writing
notes down unenjoyable additionally make
sure do you have a somewhat comfortable
chair to sit in or maybe even experiment
with a standing desk now I've got a
standing desk in my room right now that
cost well it cost a lot of money but
back when I was in college I actually
tried to build a much cheaper standing
desk using tables from Walmart and
screws and a little bit of ingenuity but
I'm gonna be honest it wasn't enough
ingenuity because that standing desk
kind of sucked but luckily there are now
standing desks for about twenty-five
dollars like the smark standing desk
that are made of cardboard and that you
can set up very very easily so that
might be something to try out also one
additional thing that you might not have
thought of having with you while you
study is a notebook or a piece of
scratch paper or maybe an app where you
write down things that come to mind or
distract you one of the things I can
completely wreck my concentration and
absolutely kill a study session for me
is if something comes to mind that I
just can't get out of my head it could
be something stupid like you didn't do
the laundry but if I take the time to
write that down in a system that I trust
where I know it can come back and see it
later that allows me to get back into my
work and let that thing go additionally
that piece of paper can also be a record
of things that distract you maybe your
environment is really prone to having
people come in and ask you to do things
or maybe it's just really noisy if you
write those things
you can start to consciously make
improvements and maybe just select a
different spot altogether now in
addition to the things that you need to
have available to you you should also
consider the things that you shouldn't
have available to you this is why your
room is often not a good study area and
why you have to work hard to make it so
because remember it's context your room
has your videogames your room has your
bed your room has your nine-foot tall
stack a cup ramen it's not always the
best place to study and speaking of
things that you don't need while you're
studying the big elephant in the room is
the thing that you're using to watch me
right now which is the internet now I
know you're gonna say I need the
internet for research I need the
internet to get on MyMathLab and yes
sometimes you do but remember tasks can
almost always be broken down into
individual subtasks or mini tasks this
video that you're watching right now is
a good example of this because to make
this video I had to write a script which
is basically like an essay and writing a
script isn't a singular task it's a
sequence of subtasks there's the
research phase there's idea generation
there's the rough draft writing phase
and finally the editing phase and guess
what I only needed the internet for one
of those phases the research phase so
during the other three phases
especially that rough draft writing
phase where I'm very prone to
distractions and I don't really want to
be writing for a lot of it I will often
turn the internet off or I'll use an app
like cold turkey writer which will
literally block my ability to do
anything else
but right now the Internet and its many
many cat pictures is probably the
greatest threat to your concentration
but there are many other things that can
derail you as well so before you settle
into your study spot and starting your
first task make a mental note of all the
potential things that could derail you
in the future if you're gonna get hungry
or thirsty during the study session make
sure you bring a snack or water bottle
with you or if you need your laptop for
your task it has a really bad battery
make sure you've packed your charging
cord I've had several times in my life
where I go to a coffee shop I have every
intention of working hard for several
hours and then of course I forgot the
charger so I derail also when you finish
studying for the day make sure to clear
your space to neutral bring it back to
its clean a pristine state because the
next time you come to it you don't want
to have to clean it up because it's
likely to make you procrastinate you
want to be able to just smoothly roll
into the work immediately and lastly
this is a bit of a weird one but try to
view your study space as a work
progress I know we kind of talked about
making the perfect quote unquote study
space here but if you're always seeking
out perfection you're never actually
going to use your study space to get
work done so just view it as a work in
progress that is constantly improving
but that will never be perfect and
that's okay and one idea that might help
curb that perfectionism and make you
more productive is to switch locations
in between tasks this is something that
I really enjoy doing myself and I am not
alone the author Cal Newport does it as
well and he calls it the concentration
circuit here's what he has to say about
it something about arriving at a new and
novel location some are different than
what you normally work provides a boost
to your motivation and aids
concentration over time this effect will
wane but if you keep switching locations
you can keep Reece Tim you lating this
reaction again and again maintaining an
average level of concentration that's
potentially much higher than if you had
slog through the deep tasks in one
literal sitting all right so because we
covered a lot of ground in this video I
want to do a quick recap just like we
did last week first make sure that your
study spot is exclusively for studying
context is king second keep your
lighting in mind and offer natural
lighting if you can try studying near
window and if you can't at least
experiment with your lights color
temperature and intensity until you find
something that works for you
third if you have to control over it try
adjusting the temperature of your study
space as well ideally somewhere around
77 degrees Fahrenheit but it might vary
for you fourth before you start studying
make sure you have access to all the
materials that you're going to need and
make sure that access is easy and quick
but number five also make sure you don't
have access to things that you don't
need because they are likely to destroy
your concentration and make you
procrastinate number six make plans in
advance to deal with possible
derailments to your productivity and
number seven try switching up locations
in between tasks now taking by
themselves these tips should hopefully
help you make some meaningful
improvements to the place where you work
but it is also sometimes helpful to be
able to see how other people work and to
get inspiration from them so to the end
I've set up a fun little website called
study spaces where you can see other
people's study spaces and even submit
your own now the idea for this site
popped into my head I was writing the
script for this video and once I
realized I could use the dot es
extension to get that cool looking
domain name I was able to get it
registered in just about 30 seconds over
at hover which is exactly where you
should register your domain names as
well however makes it incredibly easy to
find and secure basically any domain
name that's
there and available for the taking with
extensions including the classics like
calm and net and cooler ones like da TS
like I've used here and Dot me when you
want to actually build a website for
that domain name hovers Connect feature
will easily let you hook it up to tons
of different web services including
Squarespace and Shopify and if you want
to create a professional-looking
email address attached to that domain
then you can do that easily with hover
as well so if you have an idea for a fun
side project that needs a domain name
like I did or if you haven't yet secured
a professional domain name for yourself
and your job search give hover a try and
if you're among the first 100 people to
grab your domain with link below you're
gonna get 10% off of your first order I
want to give a big thanks to hover for
sponsoring this video and guys as always
thank you so much for watching as well I
really hope you found this video useful
if you did you can give this video a
like to help support this channel and if
you haven't already maybe consider
sharing it with a friend as well you can
also subscribe right there if you want
to get notified when new videos come out
and you can also click right there if
you want to get a free copy of my book
on how to earn better grades
alternatively you might want to check
out our latest podcast episode right
there or if you want to watch another
video on this channel click right there
or slam your face into your phone that
works as well anyway thanks so much for
watching and I will see you in the next
video