this video is sponsored by Skillshare
and the entirety of my sponsorship fee
for this video is being donated to the
black lives matter organization more on
that at the end for now enjoy the video
it's no secret that notion is an
incredibly powerful app that can do a
lot of things but can it work as a
note-taking app well you might think the
answer to that question is obvious since
it is an app where you can input text
and create hierarchies of pages and
pseudo folders but personally I have had
a tough time answering this question for
myself even though I've been using
notion for about two years at this point
and that is because before I discovered
notion I used a little tool called
Evernote for about 10 years and when you
use a tool for that long you tend to get
very used to the way that it's set up
and changes to that set up can be hard
to deal with so over the past couple of
weeks I've given myself the challenge of
building a system within notion that
gives me a lot of what I love from
Evernote but also takes advantage of
many of notions unique features so this
is my note-taking system here in notion
it looks pretty simple and that is
actually on purpose because not only
does it need to be very usable here but
to properly replace Evernote and to be
something I can use at all times it
needs to be usable on my iPhone as well
where I have a lot less horizontal space
to work with and this setup works
perfectly there so the system consists
of notebooks which are here on the left
we also have an inbox which works really
well for quick capture just quickly
getting ideas out of my head when I
don't have time to sort them correctly
and then something called the status
dashboard which is probably the coolest
part of the system but we're gonna get
to that a little bit later first let me
just show you what a notebook looks like
so these notebooks are actually
databases each of which contain many
different notes and if we look here
these notes have a status and also a
category the status is going to be
useful for the status dashboard and we
can set them to open we can set them
archived or urgent and this basically
lets you sort notes by the things that
are relevant to your life right now
things that are even urgent and things
that you want to keep for safekeeping
but you don't really need anymore and
those be archived we also have
categories and what we can actually do
is sort into one of these different
custom views which just kind of filters
based
it's category so this is just production
notes this is just song notes and what
this essentially gets you is something
just like whatever note had with the
notebook stacks and the notebooks that
afforded you two levels of hierarchy for
organization and this in turn gives you
two levels of hierarchy the first one
being music which contains our second
level which is our songs our gear our
learning singing etc and to create a new
note we have a couple of different
options number one we can just hit new
write within this notebook and it's
gonna give us a new note and I'll just
call it test note and this instance so
that now exists within this database I
can give it a category which works
really well let's just call it songs I'm
gonna have a great song called test note
someday and we can set a reminder for it
if we want to we can attach files to it
if we want to I'm just gonna leave it
like this so that's one way to add notes
to the database or we can go and use
that quick capture method we're adding
things to the inbox now the inbox is
pretty much identical to these notebooks
in terms of features it's also filtered
like this it's also sorted by default by
date updated which is my preference but
of course you could change this however
you want and if we create a new note
which others call test Note 2 then it's
gonna be again defaulted to open status
and sitting here in the Inbox what I can
do then is if I have like a review day
on the weekend I can go into my inbox
and I can drag all of these notes to the
notebook in which they belong so test
Note will say that's another song we
want to write creating the ultimate
note-taking system and notion that would
probably go in content and finally we
have the status dashboard so the status
dashboard is a place that shows you all
the open and urgent notes across all of
your notebooks and this is using the
notions linked database feature which
essentially lets you see a database even
if you are not on the page that contains
that database it's kind of like linking
out to a database that exists somewhere
else and showing you the contents the
interesting thing about linked databases
is that if you edit the content so if I
edit one of these rows here I will
actually be editing the row in that
database if I delete one of these
columns here I will
actually deleting the column in that
database but linked databases have their
own views they have their own filters in
their own sorts so you can create custom
views custom sorts do whatever you want
with LinkedIn databases and you're not
going to affect the parent database the
real database and we can use that to our
advantage
so this status dashboard uses that to
show me all the notes across my entire
system that are either open or urgent we
are first sorting by urgent and then we
sort by date updated so if I'm on a
review day once again I can go through
my system and I can look through and see
you know what's relevant to my life do I
need to set something to archived do I
need to set it to urgent and I've also
sorted it so that it shows any note that
doesn't have a category that way I can
go through in the dashboard and
categorize things so site speed upgrades
right here I'm going to put that on
projects all right so that being said
here is how you would add a new notebook
to your system first off there's an add
new notebook block here and this is just
a template block that contains a
template database so I can click it to
generate it and why don't we just call
this notebook DIY I think that's a good
parent notebook that could contain lots
of different sub notebooks and because
this is built off of a template a lot of
the work is already done for me I've
already got my filters I've already got
my sort criteria and I've already got a
few different views here most of these
don't really need any kind of editing
before I start working but I am gonna
want to edit this category view right
here and I want to make more based on my
categories
so first let's assign a category to this
test note here and we've got a test one
here I'm just gonna go ahead and rename
it to woodworking so this will be my
woodworking notebook and I'm gonna come
into category one I'm going to rename
that to woodworking as well so this will
be my woodworking notebook and I'm just
going to add a filter based on the
category and it will be good working so
any note tag with what working is now
going to be in this woodworking notebook
and once you've done that all you need
to do to create additional category
based notebooks is to duplicate this
view and then rename it to whatever you
want so maybe this one is going to be
metalworking yeah I would love to get
into welding in my spare time and all we
got to do is well first add a category
for metalworking and change our filter
criteria so as your notebooks expand and
you add additional sub notebooks within
the parents you can go through this
process of adding the category and then
adding the filter I know this is a
little bit of work to set up and I
thought really hard about how to make it
easier and I couldn't really figure out
a way that didn't compromise some of the
other features including the ability to
have quick capture the ability to easily
sort the ability to show the status
dashboard so it's a little bit of work
to set up each notebook but once you
have those notebooks set up you don't
have any additional maintenance work and
at least personally after I've got my
first maybe you know 15 notebooks that
kind of encompass my whole life built
then there aren't really any new
notebooks being created on a regular
basis so personally I'm okay with a
little bit of initial setup work and
speaking of initial setup one last thing
we do need to do for this other than
setting a cool emoji let's let's give it
a hammer is to add this to status
dashboard so here is one thing where I
would love notion to add a feature I
would love the ability to duplicate a
linked database and then change the
database it's looking at change the
original database that's not a feature
right now which kind of stinks because
it means I can't duplicate this preset
up link to database that has all the
filters in the sorts that'd be awesome
but that doesn't exist so we're gonna
hit the slash command and go to create
linked database and then all we need to
do is search for the particular database
we just created and here we are so again
the views we create here the filters the
sorts and any shuffling around of
columns is going to be unique to the
linked database it's not gonna affect
your notebook but if we change anything
about the content that is actually going
to affect what's in the real notebook so
what we need to do here first is number
one get rid of some properties that we
don't care about such as date created
and files I really don't care about
those things I just want these for next
we need to create a view so we're just
going to call this table view
I'm gonna give it a capital V because
it's going to default to creating two of
them now basically we need to do this so
we can easily duplicate the filters and
sorts we're gonna be creating here if we
don't make another view first it's gonna
be a kind of a pain to do it go in here
we're gonna create filters and this is
where notions new filter groups option
comes really in handy so I'm gonna go
here and I'm gonna make a filter where
I'm filtering for status and I'm gonna
filter for either open or urgent and
lastly I want one more filtering for
anything where the category is empty
this shouldn't happen with the way that
I've set this system up but just in case
it does I want to have this filter
criteria in here so I can use this as an
easy place to set categories for
anything that doesn't get it initially
finally the last thing we gotta do is
set up a sort first based on status and
I want it to be first so we're gonna go
descending order and then I want it to
be sorted by date updated also
descending and lastly with this table
view I'm gonna go ahead and duplicate it
and I'm gonna call this duplicate
ListView so this is gonna be that nice
little list style database that is
easily viewable on mobile hit that up
and then I'm gonna delete this original
table view with lowercase B that's what
notion defaults to call init and I don't
need it because it doesn't have any of
those cool filters and sorts on it
boom never done again a little bit of
setup work once you've got it set up for
each parent notebook you don't have to
do anything except for go through here
and sort your notes and look I have
Creighton yellow spent note-taking
system an ocean with nothing on there
we're gonna call that YouTube because
this here is on YouTube so this notes
database as you might have expected is a
template and it is in the notion
template gallery now so I will have that
linked in the description below and one
additional tip that I want to give you
here for using this is to drag both the
notes area itself and also the inbox
specifically up to your favorites bar
that's going to give you really quick
access to basically every part of your
notebook if you open the toggle here you
have access to all of your parent
notebooks and because we built custom
views for the subcategories you can even
drill into those subcategories from the
sidebar this was really important to me
which is another reason why I built it
this way and then last but not least you
have your inbox
at the top which means that when you're
on your phone when you're on the go and
you don't have a whole lot of time you
can easily open up notion get to the
Inbox
in just a couple of quick taps and add
something to it and then have it in a
place where you know you're gonna easily
be able to sort it and organize it later
on so again use this favourites area to
your advantage and use it for things
that you access beyond just your notes
database I've got my inbox here I've got
my notes sitting right here but I have a
lot of other things that I need really
quick access to on a really frequent
basis including my youtube video tracker
which basically helps me run my channel
and helps me make videos a lot more
efficiently and speaking of making
videos if you are a content creator
yourself if you make videos here or even
if you're aspiring to get into it in the
future then I want to take a second to
recommend Christopher Rhodes budget
filmmaking class over on Skillshare
Christopher Rhodes is somebody I've been
following for a long time he's a channel
here called YC imaging and his work is
absolutely fantastic in fact if you've
been following my channel for a few
months and you've noticed the production
quality increasing over time that is due
in part to a lot of the tips that I have
picked up from Christopher and his skill
short class really gets in the details
of how to make the most modest gear or a
small budget when you're making a video
and in particular I really enjoy his
lesson about location scouting which is
about taking one location and using it
really creatively to get lots of
different shot angles or even different
sets out of that one small space and
because Christopher's class is on
Skillshare you're also gonna have access
to thousands of other classes across
topics ranging from digital illustration
to animation to personal finance to even
productivity and within that
productivity category you'll even find
two classes taught by me which cover the
basics of setting up a productivity
system and then how to build strong
habits and actually stick to them in the
long term membership on Skillshare is
also really affordable with plans
starting at less than 10 bucks a month
and if you're one of the first 1,000
people to use the link in the
description down below to sign up you're
also going to get a two month free trial
with unlimited use of the platform so
you can try it out before you buy like I
said in the beginning of this video I am
donating the entirety of my sponsorship
fee for this video to the black lives
matter organization honestly with
everything that's been going on over the
past few weeks I don't know what the
perfect thing to say that would be
helpful would be but I do know that
saying and doing nothing
would be the wrong thing to do this
channel is about self-improvement for
the most part but I think that we should
be using the gains we make through
self-improvement to be improving the
lives of other people as well and to be
calling out and fighting against
injustice when we see it and it's clear
to me that black people in my country
and around the world deal with systemic
racism and injustice on a daily basis in
addition to many voices that are trying
to say that injustice doesn't exist it
absolutely does and I want to make some
small effort to use my platform to both
amplify black voices and to help which
is why I'm making this donation and
which is why instead of calling out all
the SUBSCRIBE stuff that I usually have
on the screen here I just want to point
you to a video by a Manuel show that I
watched last week called uncomfortable
conversations with a black man this was
an eye-opening look for me at some of
the different types of racism that
people have to deal with on a daily
basis and I highly recommend you go
watch it and also subscribe to his
channel he's turned this into a series
and the other videos are just as good
beyond that hopefully you enjoyed this
video hopefully you found it helpful in
some way again I'm gonna have the
template link for this note-taking
system in the description down below
which should hopefully save you a lot of
effort if you want to implement it for
yourself and as always I will see you in
my next video which is coming out in
just a few days