water is a necessary ingredient for
human survival to say nothing of optimal
physical and mental performance now if
you're watching this it means that you
are alive which means that you are at
least getting the bare minimal but are
you drinking enough water for years
we've been told from many many sources
that we are constantly dehydrated that
if we want our bodies to work optimally
we need to get our eight glasses a day
and some people think that eight glasses
actually isn't enough they go further
saying you need three or four liters and
others say that the timing is crucial
you need to spread out your water
drinking over each hour of the day which
come to think of it Oh No
No okay I'm not gonna die now but all
jokes aside do you really need to be
drinking eight glasses of water a day or
two ask the more general question that
you probably have in the back your mind
how do you really know if you're
hydrated and how do you make sure that
you stay hydrated on a daily basis well
after far more time than I initially
expected spent researching for this
video I hope to answer those questions
for you today here is everything that
you need to know about hydration let's
start with that common assertion that
you need to be drinking eight glasses of
water per day this idea has been out in
the wild for decades with many believing
the original source to be a 1945 notice
put out by the food nutrition board
which recommended that people get about
two and a half liters of water per day
from there the idea spread and entered
the general consciousness becoming the
mantra of many and nutritional food
bloggers and gym teacher
unfortunately what seems to have been
left out is the very next sentence in
that recommendation most of this
quantity is contained in prepared foods
this is what's quite the damper on the
idea they need to be gulping down two
and a half liters of water every single
day and more importantly no scientific
evidences come out and defense that idea
in the intervening decades in 2002 an
extensive research review published in
the American Journal of physiology
concluded as much and interestingly it
also noted that this conclusion is
supported by published studies showing
that caffeinated drinks and to a lesser
extent alcoholic beverages like beer in
moderation may indeed be counted toward
the daily total as the notice from 1945
points out solid food counts toward the
total as well though the Mayo Clinic
states that it's around 20 percent of
the total rather than being most of it
and of course that amounts gonna vary
based on your diet if he lots of fresh
vegetables and fruits which at the end
of the day are mostly water then that
totals gonna be a little bit higher but
if you're like me and your breakfast
consists of a bowl of nails and six
thousand push-ups then you're probably
gonna be leaning a little bit heavier on
the beverages so if you don't need eight
glasses of water a day how much do you
need well as you might expect the answer
is it depends
your body's individual hydration needs
vary based on different factors like age
weight gender environmental factors like
altitude temperature your proximity to
certain Dragon Ball Z villains and of
course your level of physical activity
luckily your conscious brain doesn't
have to worry about meticulously
tracking any of these factors because as
it turns out your body already has
ten mechanisms for maintaining an
optimal fluid balance automatically for
instance when your body detects it's a
little bit low on fluids it releases an
antidiuretic hormone called vasopressin
which increases water absorption in the
kidneys and returns it back to the
bloodstream to restore that balance when
that is it enough your body brings the
issue to your attention by making you
thirsty to which you're almost certainly
going to respond by drinking something
if you can
there's no meticulous timing or
spreadsheets or measurements or rolling
20-sided I needed and this makes sense
until very recently the human body and
almost all land dwelling animals for
that matter have had to evolve and adapt
an environment where there was no
guaranteed regular access to water so
systems for maintaining a good fluid
balance even the dry times were a
necessity so to put things simply yes
you need water survive and you need even
more to perform at your peak but your
body will tell you how much and when to
drink it so follow the thirst rule when
your body tells you're thirsty go and
drink something to quench that thirst
pretty simple now if you really want to
double check your hydration one easy way
to do it is by checking the color of
your urine if it's light yellow then
that means you're hydrated you're good
to go solid yellow or dark yellow means
you're dehydrated you should probably
drink some water and blue means your
escape to government experiment now at
least in terms of hydration the one
other thing you need to survive is a
healthy balance of electrolytes
what are electrolytes it's what they
used to make bran dough in general terms
an electrolyte is any substance that
conducts electricity when mixed with
water but within the human body
electrolytes are essentially rocks or
minerals that do everything from
regulating the function of your nerves
and muscles to balancing your blood
pressure
they're also essential for hydrating the
body without them water would have no
way to get into your bloodstream and
cells it would just pass through you
like you were a tube slide a really dead
tube slide some of the most important
electrolytes in your body includes
sodium potassium calcium adamantium
magnesium and guess what
that's right you don't have to
meticulously track these either as long
as you're eating enough you follow a
relatively balanced diet that consists
in more than just chicken tenders and
tender ejections then you get all the
electrolytes you need from your normal
meals and this means that even if you
exercise regularly even if you're
hitting the gym even if you're going
from runs or fighting bears you have no
need for the supposed electrolyte
benefits of sports drinks sure maybe
checking to quarterb Rondo before a
workout will make you feel more
JEDEC but that's mostly due to the
buttload of sugar that's in it and I
will remind you that buttload is a
technical term okay so now it's time to
talk about the exceptions because there
are always exceptions so here's the
thing for 99% of the people watching
this video the vast majority of my
audience the thirst rule is all you need
to follow and honestly I probably don't
even need to talk about the point one
percent probably gonna kill my YouTube
watch time but I want to be thorough so
who falls into that point one percent
hmm
first and most importantly people with
certain types of illnesses are
susceptible dehydration for a
particularly disgusting example if you
have diarrhea you can start losing a lot
of fluid really really fast and other
illnesses can cause rapid dehydration as
well which is why hospitals carry oral
rehydration solutions that are
specifically formulated to rehydrate you
as quickly as possible so if you're sick
and you are for lack of a better term
expelling a lot of fluids then listen to
your doctor when it comes to hydration
don't listen to me because while I am
from the internet and I have heard that
means I cannot tell any lies I'm not a
doctor the other exception is very
specific group of athletes now as the
author mark Sisson points out in his
book the primal blueprint many athletes
who trained intensely on a regular basis
can often come in to training sessions
slightly dehydrated and because they're
working so hard their thirst response
can't really keep up and that can lead
to decreased performance that being said
most athletes tend to drink a lot of
water while they're training it's just
something that's been kind of drilled
into our heads so that isn't really the
risk here for a specific group of
athletes for marathoners for Durance
athletes triathletes cyclists people who
are out training for a really long
period of time the risk is actually
hyponatremia or water intoxication which
is a dangerous dilution of the sodium
concentration in your bloodstream this
is a potentially deadly condition that's
caused by over hydration by drinking too
much water which is something that a lot
of endurance athletes if they're out
running for a long time or on the bike
for a long time can do unconsciously in
fact an observation the participants in
the 2002 Boston Marathon found that 13
percent of the runners tested after the
race had hyponatremia
now I'm not gonna go too far into this
because like I said 99% of you are not
gonna be at risk for this and it's
really only a factor if you're out
training for a really long period of
time but if you do want to learn more
about this problem Tim Noakes this book
waterlogged has lots more info
Meishan about it and I'm assured many
charts and graphs and data to sink your
teeth into all right so we have all of
our science bases covered and with that
I want to move on to one little
anecdotal problem that I have observed
in my own life which I'm gonna call flow
state dehydration so we talked about the
thirst rule but here's the thing I'm the
kind of guy who gets really into the
work that I'm doing like laser-focused
in the zone in the flow state and when
I'm researching for a video or I'm
editing something I can work for hours
and hours without eating or drinking
sometimes now on occasion I have noticed
that this has resulted in mild
dehydration I try to fix that but more
often when I actually come out of that
flow state and I realized that I'm
thirsty I'll typically want to reach for
something a little more novel and
interesting than plain old water like
coffee or orange juice now as I
mentioned in my previous video about
coffee and dehydration I don't think
there's a problem with having a single
daily cup of coffee or having a morning
glass of orange juice but it becomes a
problem when I get ultra focused on my
work I let my discipline slip and then I
go and drink three lattes instead of
switching to water after the first one
as a result I've got a single simple
goal for myself every single day I've
got this 27 inch stainless steel water
bottle and once per day I need to drink
this thing in its entirety that plus all
the coffee and tea and orange juice I
drink keeps me well hydrated and ensures
that a lot of that hydration is coming
from water and on a related note I
always make sure the backpacks I buy
have a water bottle holder on the side
otherwise I don't really have a good way
of bringing my water bottle with me when
I go work somewhere and that again leads
to more lattes purchased than necessary
so those couple of little hacks work
perfectly for me but if you do happen to
want to track your water and take for
some reason yes there are water tracking
apps out there but a lot of them adhere
to that eight glasses per day standard
which we've kind of reviewed in this
video so I don't really feel the need to
link to those and what I think would be
more useful anyway is to use a more
general-purpose habit tracker like
habiddig a-- which is my favorite or
maybe momentum each of which would allow
you to also track other goals in your
life but to wrap this up optimal good
hydration can be had by following three
simple rules number one the thirst rule
on your thirsty
drink something hydrating number two
make sure eating a balanced diet with
plenty of vegetables and fruits and
high-quality protein sources to ensure
your body gets all the electrolytes it
needs and you don't turn into that
really dead tube slide and finally
number three be vigilant about noticing
when you're starting to replace your
water consumption
with a lot of less healthy drinks and
when that happens take action to change
your habits that's it seriously now I
will let you be the judge about how
smooth this final product came out but I
will tell you the research that went to
this video is far more complicated than
I had initially anticipated and there
are a lot of sources to this so if
you're curious to learn more you want to
check out the sources that I use to make
this video I highly recommend checking
out the companion article that I've
written which I'll link in the
description down below or you can find
the card on screen right now otherwise
as always thank you guys so much for
watching you can subscribe right there
if you want to get notifications of when
I publish new videos and click right
there if you want to get a free copy of
my book on how to earn better grades
lastly you can smash your face into your
phone screen right there to get one
additional video on this channel that is
probably the most productive way that
you can smash your face into something
so definitely do that and I will see you
guys in the next video