recently I've been playing a lot of this
game called overcooked it's this game
where you play as a chef and you go
through this increasingly difficult and
crazy series of kitchens basically
trying to fill orders for customers and
of course in the beginning it's easy to
do the orders are pretty simple and
there aren't too many of them coming
your way but as time goes on more and
more orders start showing up there's
lots of little things thrown into the
kitchens to make your work harder and
the orders get more complicated and if
you get behind on just one order then
everything starts to pile up and you
have basically no hope of clawing your
way back from the brink and if you are a
student this is probably sounding pretty
familiar right now because it is a good
representation of what basically every
semester has looked like up until this
point and that leads to the obvious
question how do you not fall behind how
do you become one of those people who
can stay on top of things consistently
over the long term even as the semester
weight is a war of attrition against
both your organizational systems and
your motivation well in the case of
overcooked the answer is pretty simple
yet good but in terms of your school
performance it really breaks down to
doing three things consistently first
you need a well-organized task
management system and calendar and you
need to keep them well organized over
the entire semester secondly you need to
take your assignments and projects even
the things you need to study for exams
and break them down into mini tasks that
can be given milestone deadlines which
are easy to achieve and finally you need
to put in work frequently so you don't
get rusty basically work every single
day at least some small amount so in
this video I want to help you guys put
these three things into action in your
own lives I'm going to dig into each of
these give you some specific tips and
show you how I've implemented them into
my own life so you have some context
[Music]
the first step to staying on top of
things throughout the entire semester is
to make sure that your task management
system which is your to-do list and your
calendar is a perfect representation of
everything you need to do that way your
brain doesn't have to worry about those
things it knows that it's an external
system that it can trust and building
that system really starts at the
beginning of the semester when you go to
each your classes and you get the
syllabus for that class take some time
to transfer what's on the syllabus into
your task management system for example
here's the syllabus for one of my
marketing classes from my sophomore year
and honor there's a couple of written
assignments listed with due dates and
there's also some quiz dates so over in
todoist which is my recommendation for a
to do list app for most students I have
written all these assignments down so
that way they are in the system that I'm
going to be looking at every single day
now that takes care of the initial setup
at the beginning of the semester but
that's just the start as the semester
goes on you need to be adding anything
that your professor assigns you or
anything that comes up into that to-do
list and there are really two different
ways to do this the first method is the
most straightforward one and it's the
one that I like to use it's to simply
add new tasks into that to-do list or
under your calendar app the moment you
hear about them so if you're sitting in
class and your professor assigns you a
math assignment you open todoist you put
in the details you put in the due date
and you're good to go there is a
perfectly valid alternative to doing
this though because sometimes you have
to rush out of class and you just don't
have time to enter all the details and
push that due date button and do all
that little fiddling around while you're
in class so the alternative is to use
what I like to call a daily note this is
just a scrap of paper in your pocket or
maybe one of those tiny little moleskin
notebooks like my friend Martin has or
maybe just a note in your favorite
note-taking app where you write all of
the assignments and everything that
comes up during the day in plain English
you're not messing with due dates or
priority levels or whatever your task
management system as you do using a
daily note is an easy and simple way of
writing down all the things you need to
do for an assignment without having to
fiddle with an app but it is not a task
management system it's not organized
you can't prioritize it you can't look
at what's coming up in the next seven
days so if you're going to do this you
need to establish a daily habit where
you go through your daily note and you
transfer whatever is on it into your
more trusted robust system finally you
need a way to keep your calendar and
especially your to-do list from getting
disorganized and
chaotic and you're probably familiar
with this happening every semester all
these tasks pile up and some of them
just slip through the cracks or you
forget to check them off or the details
change and then you look your to-do list
one day and it is a mess but if you
establish a review day like Sunday
afternoons to go through your task
management system and clean these things
up this isn't going to happen and I'm
actually gonna do this right now so need
to do this app that I use these days is
called asana and it is great for working
with teams which I do so that's why I
use it over to duyst but as you can see
my personal task list here has some red
due dates on it now some of these tasks
are things that I actually did do we
just forgot to check off so I'm gonna go
ahead and check those off and some of
them I didn't do so I need to figure out
what to do with those particular tasks
the second main thing you want to be
doing on a consistent basis is breaking
your work down into manageable chunks
and then setting deadlines for those
chunks so that way you're working
consistently over the long term rather
than pushing everything off until the
last second and you should do this for
your assignments and your projects but
also for the topics you need to study if
you have a test coming up and you know
what you want to study you should break
down that studying into several
different chunks so that way you're
doing it over the long term doing this
is gonna help you deal with Parkinsons
law which states that work expands so as
to fill the time available for its
completion and I'm sure you're just as
familiar with this as I am you get
assigned a project you have three weeks
to do it but in your head it exists as
one task and of course you wait until
two days before the deadline to even
start it however when you break that
project down into many tasks each with
their own individual deadlines now you
have a well-defined plan and you know
you're going to be doing things
consistently across that whole three
weeks so here's an example of this in
action when I was a sophomore I had an
assignment in one of my English classes
to create a personal website which is a
pretty big project so I broke it down
into individual little milestones create
a list of pages make a wireframe mock up
on notebook paper start coding things
and each of those have their own
individual a deadline which helped me
make consistent progress in the project
without a whole ton of stress one
another huge benefit to setting these
milestones is that it decreases the
initial resistance to starting a task
because this is what makes us
procrastinate it's the resistance to
starting something that seems really big
and scary but when you broken your
project down that little mini milestone
doesn't
like it's gonna take that long and so
you can jump into the work right away
and speaking of right away for most
projects you should make that first
milestone do they be the exact same day
as when you get the assignment doing
this will push you to put just a little
bit of work into the project while
everything is still fresh in your mind
and it doesn't have to be big be a very
tiny amount of work for example if
you've just been assigned an essay you
could just spend five minutes brain
dumping what you know or writing down
questions on the other hand if you wait
a few days to start the project now you
have to spend a bunch of time reef
familiarizing yourself with the
requirements and getting everything
reloaded into your brain and that is
valuable time that you could be using to
play zelda instead lastly do some amount
of work every single day or at least
almost every single day because
frequency is your friend
the novelist Anthony Trollope once said
a small daily task if it'd be really
daily will beat the labors of a
spasmodic Hercules this is something
that I learned really well in the
process of writing a book
ever since 2012 I had wanted to write
one but I had failed every single time
I'd try because I would try to write
entire chapters all at once or one time
actually flew down to Texas to go to a
conference where I tried to write the
entire thing in one weekend and I
completely failed so a couple of years
later I tried a different tactic I set a
goal in my habit occur to write just 500
words a day and it didn't matter what
those 500 words were they could have
been I hate writing over and over and
over again it could be horrible horrible
words but I had to put them in no matter
what and after just a few months of
putting in this daily effort I ended up
writing an entire book in fact this book
that I wrote is about twice as long as
what I originally intended because every
single day I was getting myself into the
mode of writing and that would end up
having more ideas and coming up with
more anecdotes than I initially expected
the other huge benefit that frequency
brings is that it prevents you from
going into slumps where you get rusty
and you're not used to doing the work
anymore I have a lot of experience with
this as well if at times where I do a
lot of different podcasts and like a big
batch and it'll take weeks before I do
it again and I feel really rusty here's
how Cal Newport puts it in his book how
to win at college student slumps occur
when you take a long break from work and
then find yourself unable to easily pull
yourself back into a working rhythm in
order to deny the opportunity for this
to occur you should do some out of
school work every single day now if
you're having trouble establishing this
daily
cabott one thing you can do that will
help is start removing choices from the
equation and by that I mean pre-planning
elements of your study sessions both in
terms of location and time it can be
very helpful to establish a specific
study spot that you go to every single
day and to have a specific block of time
when you know you're going to be
studying now if you have a specific
block of time every single day that's
very good to have but if your calendar
is such that you've got like you know
student organizations or night classes
that make every day different at least
at the beginning of every week
pre-planned when you're gonna have
blocks of study time so that way you
know on a given day when you're gonna be
putting in that daily amount of work now
I know we have covered a lot in this
video but remember it all boils down to
building three consistent habits that
you keep throughout the entire semester
number one making sure your task
management system both your calendar and
your to-do list are well maintained on a
weekly basis number two breaking your
assignments and projects down into
manageable chunks and then setting
deadline dates so you're working
consistently and number three building
the habit of working every single day so
you don't get rusty
of course even if these habits do help
you stay on top of your score at the
semester there are gonna be things that
you just always seem to be falling
behind upon and for me one of those
things is my reading list and that's why
I'm really excited to tell you guys
about blinka switch is this week's video
sponsor Linkous is a digital learning
app that basically distills all the key
lessons and most important insights from
tons of different nonfiction books into
these little tiny packs that you could
read or listen to in just about 15
minutes and personally I'm a huge fan of
blankest because as somebody who's
interested in a ton of different topics
my to be read list over on Goodreads is
about a mile long now with some books I
know right from the start that I want to
read the entire thing cover to cover
Michael Lewis is the big short is a
great example here since I watched the
movie absolutely fell in love with it
and then knew I had to read the entire
book but with some other books I don't
always know if I want to read the whole
thing or maybe I just want to get the
key insights from it without digging
into all the padding and that's we're
using blinkers can be really helpful
because you have a limited amount of
time and blinkers can actually help you
vet books before you decide to buy them
and invest a ton of time to them plus
once you've read the summary of all the
key points now you've primed your brain
to be more receptive to those points if
you decide to read the entire book and
hence they're going to be more embedded
in
and of course if you've already read a
book and you just want to reefa millyar
eyes yourself with those concepts going
through the blink is a very time
effective way to do it normally a
subscription the blankets cost about 50
bucks for an entire year but if you use
that link down in the description below
or on screen right now you can test
drive the service yourself for free and
if you do decide to subscribe afterwards
that link will also get you at 20% off
now once you start using the app it's
gonna start giving you personalized
recommendations but if you don't know
where to start right now you might like
to check out a couple of links that I've
gone through myself recently a really
good one is Dan Ariely is predictably
irrational which explains why our brains
think irrationally you can actually help
you make better decisions and another
one would be Benny Lewis is fluent in
three months which is all about how to
learn new languages quickly three months
which is all about how to lose for
sponsoring this video and help it to
support this channel and thank you so
much for watching if you like this video
and you found it useful definitely give
it a like and go down in the comments
below if you have any tips that I didn't
mention here if you're not subscribed
already you can do so right there to get
new videos every single week you can
also click right there you get a free
copy of my book on how to earn better
grades or you can click right there
listen to our latest podcast episode
which answers five questions from you
guys including the question how do I
start networking and building
relationships when I don't have any
experience and you click right there to
get one more video on this channel
thanks for watching I'll see you next
week