hey what's up guys so it is roundup time
today I'm gonna be sharing 21 different
apps and tools that more or less force
you to get your work done now to be
honest right up front
none of these apps work quite like that
creepy piano in the movie core lime none
of them are gonna make your computer
sprout robotic arms that grab your hands
and literally make them start typing but
what they do provide or what I like to
call training wheels for the brain
because as I'm sure you're well aware
left to its own devices your brain is
liable to get distracted by cat videos
instead of actually doing the work that
you have set up to do now over time and
with practice you can build your self
discipline and your ability to focus but
while you're going through the early
stages of that process it's useful to
use systems that provide training wheels
be they in the form of helpful
imitations commitment devices feedback
and reports or literal drill instructors
with very little regard for the
integrity of your eardrums so each of
the apps I'm going to share with you
today fits into one of those categories
except the last one and in fairness I
did go and do a search on Fiverr for
affordable drill instructors but that
turned up no results so you're on your
own if you want to find your own
personal major pain but before you go
looking for one let's go through these
apps starting with those that fall into
the category of commitment devices what
exactly is a commitment device well to
put things simply it's anything that
creates a consequence for failing to do
the thing that you've set up to do all
the tools in this category aim to make
it painful not to do your work and there
are quite a few of these let's start
with my favorite one which is beeminder
it is no exaggeration to say that
beeminder is one of the primary reasons
why I have a successful YouTube channel
today because back when I started on
YouTube I used it to commit to
publishing a new video every single week
essentially beeminder allows you to
commit to a goal either doing more of
something or less of something and it
allows you to put money on the line
moreover it's very nerdy and it's all
about tracking data so you can hook it
up to tons of different tools including
apple health Strava todoist
and IFTTT which stands for if this then
that which basically allows you to hook
it up to pretty much any service on the
planet and due to the presence of all
those integrations the only real
limitation here is your imagination
there are tons of different goals that
you could start putting money on in
order to make sure that you are more
commit to them in the future but to give
you one idea again for three entire
years I tracked my blogs RSS feed and
made sure that I published a new blog
post a new podcast episode and a new
YouTube video every single week and I
had money on the line so I made sure
that I did it now in the same vein is
another website called stick who
dispelled stic KK and it's very similar
to be minder though it's a little less
nerdy as would be a minor you commit to
a goal and then you create Stakes or
Consequences in case you fail and you
can actually put money on the line so it
has fewer charts and graphs and it's
generally a little bit less statistics
heavy than beeminder is but on the other
hand you can set supporters who can
watch your progress and a referee will
get an email every single time you log
progress and make sure that you were
telling the truth moving on from there
we have an app with a much more specific
purpose called the most dangerous
writing app if you like me sometimes
have trouble getting started writing or
while you're writing you have trouble
with your inner critic silencing you or
trying to edit things when you should
just be getting thoughts out of your
head then this is an app that you might
want to use because once you start a
session with either a time goal or a
word count goal you have to keep typing
and if you stop typing for long enough
it completely deletes your work not only
that but it also has a hardcore mode if
you check this box and start a session
you aren't going to be able to see
anything on the screen except for the
last letter that you typed because when
you type letters they flash on-screen
but everything else is blurred and this
once again silences that inner critic it
makes you just get things out of your
head and edit later all right so now
let's talk about these strides app and
the reason I put this on the list isn't
because it forces you to work by putting
money on the line or anything like that
but it does take advantage of what's
been called the Seinfeld strategy the
comedian Jerry Seinfeld is famous for
having honed his joke writing talent by
making sure he wrote a new joke every
single day and to track his progress he
would mark it off on a calendar on his
wall and because he could see that
calendar he didn't want to break the
streak he had this visual reminder of
his progress that he didn't want to
tarnish so this don't break the streak
strategy can be very powerful because we
humans like to be consistent in our
behavior and we don't want to see those
chains broken now what you could
definitely use a calendar on your wall
do this that's not an app so it doesn't
belong on this list and well you could
use any habit tracking app in the world
to do it as well because almost all of
them show your streak I do want to give
a specific shout out to the strides app
because in that particular app when
you're creating a goal you have the
option to create a goal for your streaks
so instead of just watching a count up
to infinity you can actually set like a
30 or 60 or 90 days streak goal which
means your 30-day challenges can become
that much more official next up we've
got coach dot me which used to be call
it lift back when I started using it as
a college student but now it's called
coach me because it has a big focus on
you guessed it coaching now coach taught
me does have a habit tracking app it's
very similar to a lot of others out
there but what I want to highlight in
this video is their coaching services
because if you were one of the people
who listened to the intro this video and
did want your own personal major pain
one of your own personal drill
instructor this is probably the closest
that you're going to get for not a whole
lot of money because they've got
personal coaching services for building
new habits and staying productive for
about 15 bucks a week a lot more
expensive than everything else on this
list but if you do want personalized
coaching and you don't have a friend who
could be an accountability partner this
could be an option of course another
option could be to use the entire
internet as your accountability partner
which is what I've done by essentially
rolling my own commitment device using
Google sheets so a couple of years ago I
set a goal for myself to read 25 pages
of nonfiction every single day for three
months without fail and well I did have
an accountability partner in real life I
also wanted to make my goal public and I
wanted people to be able to track my
progress over time so I created a public
facing Google spreadsheet which
attracted the book I was reading and how
many pages I read every single day and
then I made a public on my website so
people could call me out if I failed to
read and the last tool that I'm gonna
mention here in the commitment devices
section is something that you might not
have expected I'm gonna mention discord
and or Skype as a commitment device now
for those of you who don't know discord
is an app that is primarily used by
gamers to chat with each other either by
voice or by text and it's a very cool
app in fact we have a college info geek
official discord which you can find in
the description down below
but I'm going to suggest using the voice
chat feature here to set up what I like
to call a workgroup back when I was in
college I set up one of these with a
couple of blah
her friends who each lived in different
states and every once in a while we will
get on skype we'd be on a call but we
wouldn't talk to each other we would
simply be on the call and be working and
this was in order to simulate the
experience of sitting in a room with
study buddies or accountability partners
getting work done and just getting the
motivation from knowing the other people
were also getting their work done so
even though I wasn't physically in the
room with my blogger friends I knew that
on the other line of that Skype call
even if it was silent was somebody who
was getting work done and that made me
more motivated to do my work as well
category number two on my list or the
apps that provide what I like to call
helpful limitations or to put it another
way apps that block you from doing
specific things and a lot of the apps in
this list are going to be website and
application blockers and I did talk a
lot about those in my internet
distractions video so I do recommend
going and watching that for some more
in-depth tips regarding those but here
I'm just going to recommend them if you
haven't heard about them and the first
one I have to talk about is my absolute
favorite website blocker in the world
which is freedom now there are lots of
other apps out there but freedom is the
only one that works on all the platforms
that I use and reliably blocks
everything that is potential distraction
for me on a daily basis now while
freedom is by far the most convenient of
the website blocking apps because it
allows you to find all of your blocks
and schedules from a universal dashboard
that goes out to all of your different
devices it does have a monthly cost so
if you want to pay less money and maybe
have a little bit more inconvenience
than the following apps could be good
substitutes first up if you're on a Mac
you're gonna want to get the app
self-control which is free and for Mac
only and if you're on Windows you're
gonna want to go for focal filter which
is again free and it is Windows
exclusive
I mean iPhone there's an app called
blocked distracting websites for about
three bucks though near the end of this
video I'm gonna talk about a new feature
in iOS that may supersede this app and
make it obsolete so stick around for
that and for those of you on Android
there's a free app called black site
that does the same thing there is also
an app for Android iOS and chrome called
forest which is not really a website
blocker but can kind of function in the
same manner forest helps you avoid using
your phone or distracting ways by
allowing you to grow a tree as long as
you don't exit the app if you do though
you kill the tree same with a Chrome
extension if you go to any of the sites
on your blacklist you're gonna kill that
tree that you could
groan had you just stayed away from them
during that time and of course over time
you get to see your progress in the form
of a virtual forest growing up on your
phone or in your browser and if you want
to keep that forest nice and healthy
then you are not going to be distracting
yourself and in a similar vein to forest
I'm going to mention literally any
Pomodoro app now I debated whether or
not to put Pomodoro apps on this list
because they really don't explicitly do
anything to force you to do your work
but I just had to add them because
they're so effective for me once I
started Pomodoro session and I have
committed to doing one single thing I am
so much less likely to go do anything
else but that one task and if you want a
recommendation my absolute favorite from
a door app is one called tide which is
on the iPhone Android and I like to
actually put it on my phone screen put
the phone screen on the desk and leave
the screen on during those Promotora
sessions that way I can actually see the
timer at the whole time rounding out our
section on helpful limitations are a
couple of apps that help you write more
effectively starting with cold turkey
writer which essentially locks your
computer down completely until you've
hit a writing goal of either word count
or minutes written it's very much like
the most dangerous writing app but
instead of deleting your work it just
doesn't let you do anything until you've
actually done that work alongside that
is another writing app called blurt
which isn't so sadistic as the most
dangerous writing app recalled turkey
writer it won't lock down your computer
it won't delete your writing but it does
have that feature which blurs every line
except for the one you're currently
working on which can again help to
silence that inner critic and help you
actually keep writing that brings us to
our final category in this video which I
like to call a feedback and reports none
of the apps here forced you to do
anything actively they don't make you
put money on the line that'll block
sites but they do show you in naked
embarrassing detail what you've been
doing with your time and the first one
that I'm going to list here is one
called a toggle which is an active time
tracker where you actually have to start
a clock and tell it what you're going to
be doing during that time now as with
Pomodoro apps I find that using manual
time tracking apps makes me more likely
to do the thing I set up to do because
I've set a timer and I've intentionally
started that process but this also lets
you take advantage what's been called
the Hawthorne effect which describes how
people tend to change their behavior
for the better when they know that
they're being observed or tracked and in
my experience with manual time tracking
I found that this tends to happen even
if you're the one doing the observations
of your own behavior now if you happen
to find that toggle is not the time
tracking app for you don't worry because
there are dozens of other ones out there
and I do want to give an honorable
mention to one called clock off' I which
is completely free
now toggles personal features are also
free so they're pretty comparable for
anybody wanting to use them on a
strictly personal basis but any of you
guys out there managing teams you might
want to give clock Rifai a look now both
of those apps are built around manual
time tracking and we are now going to
move over to automatic time tracking
with apps like rescuetime as you may
have gathered from the previous sentence
rescue time and other apps like it
automatically tracks the time you spend
on different websites and applications
categorizes that time as productive or
non productive and then gives you
reports on how you've been spending your
time and these reports can be very
eye-opening because you may think you
know how you spend your time but how you
think you spend your time is probably
very different than how you actually
spend your time and it can be pretty
surprising to see just how much time you
waste watching cat videos and not
actually getting your work done now
alongside rescue time and apps like
timing and hours and other things that
are very similar there is another app I
want to mention called why productive
and the madding visted list because it
does what RescueTime does but it also
allows you to create daily project and
task lists so it kind of combines
multiple productivity features into one
and finally before I tell you the apps
in this list that I use personally the
last item that we have to talk about is
something called screen time which is a
built-in feature in iOS 12 so if you're
using an iPhone you might not need an
automatic time tracker or a website
blocker because this thing can do both
of those things it'll tell you where
you're spending your time on your phone
how many hours and you can also set up
number one apps that are going to be
blocked and also something called
downtime hours which are specific hours
where you can't access any apps
whatsoever except for ones that you put
on a specific whitelist so that brings
us to a question that I'm sure that many
of you are likely to have which is out
of all the apps on this list which are
the ones that I use on a daily basis
myself well for those of you who are
wondering those apps include beeminder
which I mentioned at the beginning of
this video as one of my fav
apps and one of the things that let me
build this YouTube channel in the first
place
additionally I also use strides which is
the habit tracker that I'm currently
using and very much enjoying the tide
app which is my Pomodoro tracker of
choice freedom to block distracting
websites I'm a computer and my phone and
rescue time so I can get those reports
and see just how much time I'm wasting
on a daily basis and hopefully to reduce
that in the future of course there are
many other apps that I use to get things
done many productivity apps that don't
quite fall into the category of things
that force me to get my work done but
that do build systems or allow me to do
things much more efficiently and one of
the apps that you guys been asking me a
lot about in the recent past is one
called notion which I use for many
different things including managing
these video projects now notion is
incredibly flexible and powerful and a
lot to improve my workflows and it could
potentially be a very useful tool for
you possibly even a note-taking system
of choice but a lot of you guys have
told me that notion is also very
complicated and you don't quite know
where to start so if you find yourself
in that camp or you want to learn how to
set up a very efficient workflow really
really quickly I'm gonna recommend you
take my friend Francesco's notion course
over on Skillshare
francesco is an absolute expert when it
comes to productivity apps and this
course is a great resource for figuring
out how to get the most out of notion of
course while you're on Skillshare you
might also want to take my friend Mike
Vardy scores on time theming if you want
to become even more productive and
that's a skill that will help you no
matter what apps you're using on a daily
basis and in case you don't know
Skillshare is also an amazing resource
for learning new skills across a ton of
different disciplines because they've
got over 22,000 courses in topics
ranging from business to marketing to
storytelling to digital animation to
even music production what's more
Skillshare is incredibly affordable with
a premium subscription costing less than
ten bucks a month and even better if you
click the link in the description down
below you can get a two month free trial
with unlimited learning on the platform
you can learn a lot in two months so if
you wanna start learning some new skills
or increasing your productivity or dig
me into notion or any of the other app
tutorials on the platform and you want
to support this channel then click link
in description down below and sign up
big thanks to scale share for sponsoring
this video and being a huge supporter of
this channel and as always thank you so
much for watching hopefully you found
this video helpful hopefully appointed
you to something new that can
become more productive on a daily basis
and if it did or if you just enjoy me
talking at your computer screen then hit
that like button and subscribe so you
don't miss new videos coming out every
single week you can also get a free copy
of my book and how to earn better grades
right over here follow me on instagram
at tom frankly or check out one more
video on this channel or right around
here thanks for watching and I'll see
you in the next one