good morning guys thought we do just a
tad different video
today
what's up guys wanted to do a little bit
different of a video this week because
well I don't have a script in mind I
don't have a full outline of what I want
to talk about in mind but I do have a
couple of ideas that I got from a weekly
call that I do every single week I guess
that's why we call it weekly with a few
friends of mine I talk with Zach from
Asian efficiency my friend Stefano from
college Topia and my friend Steven who
used to run a podcast called unstable
and every morning we get on Skype and
have what you could I guess call a
mastermind group of sorts um I don't
really like that term very much but
basically it's a more structured meeting
every week instead of just hanging out
and chatting we want to help each other
we want to tell each other what's uh
going right in our lives what's going
wrong analyze the struggles and figure
out how we can each get uh more progress
towards our goals and this week I was
sort of in the hot seat of sorts and
they kind of pointed out some of the
things that I'm struggling with it's
nothing serious it's nothing like
life-threatening or anything but uh what
I've realized is there's a few problems
that I have not been taking the uh time
and putting the effort into solving and
this week I'm taking that time just to
list them off the main ones that have
been bugging me recently I haven't been
reading books like I want to especially
non-fiction I haven't been going about
my morning routine as diligently there's
also some bigger projects that don't
really have the weekly deadlines that I
put on my video production such as
getting a print version of my book
available on Amazon I really want to do
that because people have requested it
and I need to a lot time for that so
this week I'm taking the time to do that
that's why this video is a little bit
less polished I suppose um a little bit
less uh like the other ones and the
reason for that is that I want to take
some time to point out the
inefficiencies in my production process
and then develop some systems for making
that work better and uh there's a truck
driving behind me that's
cool but yeah there's some
inefficiencies and I want to take the
time to straighten them out so one of
those things is creating a more
effective default template for my videos
that has all the sound effects and
Graphics that I use on a regular basis
already in them so I don't have to
recreate that project from scratch every
time and uh I guess if you want to pull
anything from this video I mean this is
kind of just me like trying to figure
out what the heck is wrong with my life
and how I can fix it but if you have
processes that you go through on a
regular basis and you realize that there
are some inefficient parts of that that
are that are taking too much time then
taking some time off to fix those is
investment like you do have to stop or
slow down the regular work for a while
to take the time to do this but it's an
investment that pays dividends later on
down the road it's it's much like
college right like when you go to
college you're kind of taking four years
off from the time that you could be
working and making money to do some
concentrated study that will pay
dividends down the line and this is the
same exact thing if I take the time now
to figure out what's wrong in my
processes and fix it then I'm going to
be able to do more work and better work
down the line and also be able to fit in
bigger projects that aren't weekly one
other thing I've been noticing is that
with video every single week I go
through the same exact process where I
sort of trick my brain into uh into
thinking that it's going to get the
video done like on Monday like I'll say
o it's Monday I'm going to get the video
done today so that way the Tuesday
Wednesday Thursday that I usually spend
editing I can work on bigger projects
and what always happens inevitably is I
end up spending Monday through Thursday
on video inefficiently and this reminds
me of something called Parkinson's law
which essentially boils down to work
fills the time that you a lot to it if I
all lot four days to work if it's Monday
and I start doing a video and I tell
myself it's going to go up on Thursday
then more often than not I kind of
inefficiently work on it for 4 days
whereas if I work on big projects on
Monday and Tuesday and say all right Tom
you've only got Wednesday and Thursday
to do the video it's getting done much
more quickly I find that inspiration
really hits me when there's a little bit
of a deadline a little bit of time
pressure so think about that in your
work as well so that's all I got for
this video except for the fact that
there's going to be a little bonus
resource at the end of the video after
the end card and I'm not going to tell
you what it is so just stay to the end
and check it out but if you want any
ideas from this video video essentially
what I'm trying to do is point out those
efficiencies take the time to fix them
also knowing that Parkinson's law is a
thing and structuring my work time so
that I do have a little bit of time
pressure and also if you don't have a
structured group uh or a call every
single week or Mastermind I guess you
can call it with people who have the
same motivations or similar levels of
drive that you have I think that's a
really valuable thing I found a lot of
uh value in in getting with those guys
every single week and talking through
our goals and struggles and if you
haven't done that yet then and I would
suggest maybe trying it so as always
guys thanks so much for watching this
video I'll see you next week with a more
regular College info geek type video and
until then stay
cute hey guys thanks for watching this
video If you want to get new videos
every single week on being a more
effective student you can click that big
red subscribe button right there I also
wrote a book on how to get better grades
and if you click the picture of it you
can get a free copy over my website also
at my website you'll find the companion
blog post with a summary of this video
and you can click the orange logo right
there to get to it in last week's video
we went over five ways you can increase
your reading speed so check it out if
you haven't seen it and if you'd like to
connect or ask questions I'm on Twitter
@tomfrankly or you can leave a comment
down
[Music]
below all right bonus Resource as
promised I was browsing Reddit the other
day and I found something that I think
you'll like so if you go over to ambient
mixer uh ambient-mixer.com there's a
Ravenclaw common room soundscape and I
mean over here there's like there's some
other ones right there's like there like
Slytherin and there's like grindor but
but who cares about that there's
Ravenclaw is the best and yeah I have
the link in the description also in the
blog post so check it out if you like
ambient soundscapes for studying in lie
of music or I suppose you could even
combine it with music