thanks to hover for sponsoring this
video and supporting my channel
hey there my name is thomas frank and
for the past about eight years i have
made my full-time living on
the internet that's been done primarily
through my blog college info geek a
podcast that i run
and this youtube channel with income
sources ranging from
speaking engagements to youtube ads to
sponsorships
affiliate marketing sales of my own book
and
a secret only fans account one of those
is a lie
can we leave that in the video so as
somebody who makes their living
primarily from creating things for the
internet
i naturally get a lot of questions from
people who want to do the exact same
thing
and i remember being one of the people
asking those questions
back when i started my blog about 10
years ago i was primarily doing it just
to boost my resume and to have fun
but i quickly started reading blogs
written by people who were making their
full-time incomes
sometimes over six figures just running
their blogs
at first i thought this lifestyle would
be impossible for me to achieve the
freedom seemed alluring but i felt that
that was for other people who got lucky
and i would just have to work a job and
just blog on the side
but i was curious so i started learning
and started devouring as much as i could
possibly get my hands on from the
tiniest details on website speed to the
marketing psychology behind the colors
of buttons on landing pages
and about two and a half years after i
first started my blog i hit
full time income for the first time
about three years ago i hit
six figures in income for the first time
and last year we did over half a million
dollars
in gross revenue i'm throwing these
numbers out here not to brag
but to provide a little bit of context
on a what's possible
be what's happened in my experience and
to hopefully give myself a little bit of
credibility for making a video
like this so today what i want to do is
kind of explain
some of the ways that you can use to
make money on the internet if that's
something
that you want to do so first we're going
to cover some pretty important
groundwork here and then i'm going to be
covering
five different ways that you can use to
make money on the internet
and for each of these methods i'm going
to give you some tips for both getting
started in it
and being more successful with it to lay
down that groundwork i talked about the
main idea i want to communicate here
is this making money on the internet is
just like making money out in the
physical world in at least one
key dimension which is that you have to
have some way of providing
scarce value so what do i mean by that
well
value is obvious if you remember your
economics class you probably remember
that money is
number one a store of value number two a
medium of exchange and number three
a unit of account so essentially money
is a way of giving a numeric value
to well value i value not mowing my lawn
so i pay a lawn mowing company to do it
instead of course there are different
levels of value as well
something that i value more than that is
having a person to edit my videos which
is also something that takes
more skill so as a result i pay my
editor tony
quite a bit more than i pay lawn mowing
company by scarce
i mean not abundant the more choice that
a customer has when it comes to a given
service the more
you as the service provider are going to
have to start competing on price
and the more you have to compete on
price the more you have to start eating
into your margins which is the
difference between your income
and what you had to spend to make that
income on things like
buying inventory running ads paying for
web hosting whatever it might be
a great example here is drop shipping
and i will not be surprised if you get
an ad for a drop shipping course on this
video
if you're watching it on youtube
essentially drop shipping is a business
model
where you identify a product set up an
online store for it
and then when a customer orders that
product you actually send that order to
a supplier
who sends it to the customer you don't
keep anything on hand
this is a very attractive business model
because number one you don't have to
spend any money upfront on inventory
which is usually risky and requires
warehouse space
and number two you don't even have to
deal with the hassle of shipping orders
to customers instead as the ads for so
many drop shipping courses will tell you
all you got to do is find a cool product
build an online site where people can
order that product and then just
drive traffic to the website using slick
instagram ads or search engine
optimization or whatever
and you can do all of that while sipping
a margarita from a beach in bali
as long as it has wi-fi but you're going
to be doing it alongside about a billion
other dude bros trying to do the exact
same thing so remember this easy
low cost of entry equals huge
competition
equals razor thin or sometimes
non-existent margins which can put you
in the hole a better option is finding a
way to increase the value of what you're
offering or make it
more unique somehow for example while
most editors can provide basic cuts
tony can do color grading he can do
intricate sound design
and he knows how to use b-roll to make
the video that you're watching
a little bit more pleasing to the eye
but of course
those skills take time and practice to
develop
and in some cases there may even be some
form of monetary investment
like i don't know buying a two 000 sound
effects library
so keep this in mind before you can make
significant money on the internet you
have to find a way of providing
scarce value anybody who is telling you
anything different
is almost certainly trying to sell you
something and it's probably a course
that helps them make money
not doing the thing that they're
teaching you how to do you have to
provide value
luckily there is more than one way to do
that so freelancing is probably the best
place to start here because it is in my
opinion one of the easiest ways to start
making a decent amount of money on the
internet
fairly quickly especially if you have a
skill to start with it's also the place
where i started
back in high school i started a
freelance web design business and i put
up a website trying to get clients and i
actually landed a few that helped pay my
bills throughout college
now i will admit that a lot of the
clients i got didn't actually come from
the internet some of them came from word
of mouth referrals in my local area
and for other ones i was actually making
cold sales calls trying to get clients
but eventually i did get two clients who
found me through google searches and
they hired me for ongoing web work that
actually again paid some of the bills
that i had during college and provided
some decent money if you want to talk
about numbers
i think the first website i ever built i
charged about 350 bucks for
and the last one i built before i moved
into blogging i charged around 2 000
so you can make some pretty good money
doing web development whatever you want
to do
if you want to get into freelancing you
first have to learn a skill that is in
demand and that ideally you can do over
the internet so i'm talking about things
like
web development video editing podcast
editing is a big one
professional writing and sometimes even
bookkeeping
another option is actually doing
in-person services but
marketing them over the internet using
geo-targeted ads
or by just targeting people in your area
in other ways so this could be things
like photography and videography
maybe being a wedding photographer doing
interior decorating
or and i'm surprised this is a thing but
i researched it and it is
you could become a decluttering and
minimalism
consultant did you say minimalism in
fact you can even go get your konmari
certification to help people channel
their inner marie condo and declutter
their lives we live in a weird world
but hey that's the thing you can do
anyway with freelancing the great thing
about it is that the investment you have
to make up front to provide that value
usually is gonna come in the form of
time and sweat you're often not gonna
have to spend a whole lot of money for
instance as a web developer i learned
pretty much
everything i know for free just looking
at blogs online resources
and that was over 10 years ago today the
resources for web development education
that are free
are vastly better than they were when i
was learning codecademy is a great
example okay three tips for getting
started as a freelancer number one
and this is super important you have to
build an online portfolio
have a place where people can look at
the work you've done for clients in the
past
and judge whether or not your services
are going to be right for them if you
don't have any clients right now
do some work on your own or possibly do
some spec work for
a non-profit or something just to get
some experience under your belt
and a project that you can show off
number two put what you do
and where you are in your social media
bios i'm talking twitter i'm talking
instagram i'm talking linkedin
people like me often go to twitter and
type in things like
freelance graphic designer freelance
motion graphics artist and then i will
just start clicking on profiles
looking at the pin tweets looking at the
url in the profile hopefully it's a
portfolio
and i've made hiring decisions based on
that kind of a search process so do it
and finally number three build
relationships with other freelancers who
offer complementary services so
if you're a freelance video editor like
tony you might want to build some
relationships with freelance motion
graphics artists that way if a client
comes along who needs both services
if they find the other person they might
be able to refer you and vice versa
our second method for making money on
the internet is affiliate marketing
so getting into affiliate marketing
means essentially becoming an
unofficial salesperson for another
company you sign up for their affiliate
program you put links to their products
on your website or in your youtube video
descriptions
and then when people click those links
or use your discount code and buy that
product
you get a commission of that sale
affiliate marketing actually drives a
significant portion of the revenue that
comes into my business
particularly over on my website college
info geek for example
skillshare's affiliate program pays ten
dollars whenever anybody signs up
through my link
so on my website i have all these little
ads up for my own courses
over on skillshare whenever anybody
clicks those and signs up i get ten
dollars
the internet's biggest affiliate program
is amazon's now the commission they pay
on most product sales is pretty small
but the upside of participating in that
program is that
well you can link to pretty much any
product on amazon and there's
millions of products so sites like the
wirecutter make pretty much all of their
income by creating
buyer's guides guides on the best
headphones or the best bluetooth speaker
when somebody comes in and clicks the
buy button on their recommendation
they get a cut of that sale so how much
money can you make with affiliate
marketing
well it varies really really wildly for
one example
convertkit which is an email marketing
service pays their affiliates a
recurring 30 commission on any sale they
bring in
recurring so as somebody who uses
convertkit i have about a hundred
thousand people on my email list
which means i have to reluctantly fork
over about 700
a month to convertkit and that means
that the person who referred me because
there was somebody who referred me
is making a nice 210 dollars a month
just off of me recurring on the other
end of the spectrum we have programs
like amazon's which again don't pay a
whole lot per sale
at present moment for example they are
currently paying three percent for
headphone sales
so if you want to go back to our wire
cutter example if wirecutter is
recommending a 200
pair of headphones that means that if
somebody clicks their link they're
making
six dollars on that sale and that means
that wirecutter has to bring a
crap ton of traffic into their headphone
buying guide
let's be super generous and say that one
percent of the people who read that
guide
actually go on to buy those headphones
through their link that means they're
essentially making
six cents per page view so to make that
same
210 dollars that the convertkit
affiliate made just off of me
they need to bring in 3 500 page views
so to be successful as an affiliate
marketer you have to do three things
first you have to find programs that pay
a good amount per sale
second you need to figure out how to
drive more traffic to the web pages that
contain your links or the youtube videos
that contain them
and finally you want to find a way to
increase your conversion percentage
which is the portion of people who
actually click your links
and then the portion of those people who
actually go on to buy how do you do
those things
well for the first problem you just need
to do your research and platforms like
impact actually contain a marketplace
where companies can post their affiliate
programs and their conversion
percentages
and then you can apply to join those
programs if you like for traffic
you want to build an audience there's a
couple of different strategies for doing
this
personally i built a blog and then a
podcast and then a youtube channel
around a
general topic that i was interested in
and then over time as affiliate
opportunities arose for that topic
i added them in organically but some
people take
the opposite strategy some people will
first find a product they want to
promote
and then they will use keyword research
to try to match that to a problem or an
interest that people have
if you want to go this route you can use
tools like ahrefs.com to do
keyword research you're looking for
keywords that have a decent amount of
search interest
but not a lot of competition and if you
find one
you can start writing articles on it or
making youtube videos on it in the hopes
you're going to rank well in either
google searches or
in youtube search if you bring in
traffic you're hopefully going to bring
in affiliate commissions
finally you want to find a way to
increase those conversion percentages
and this could be an entire video all on
its own i don't know if it would fit on
this general channel
but essentially you want to start
learning marketing strategies
and get data driven so track how much
traffic you get and how many clicks you
get
then make a change and then track the
data again and compare and see what you
can do
income source number three european
three
is the programmatic ad so programmatic
ads are ads that run
alongside content that you create these
are different from brand deals which
we're going to talk about next
because programmatic ads are not sold by
you
and you don't deliver the talking points
yourself either so the example that
you're probably most familiar with
is youtube adsense which runs the ads
that you see
and let's be honest probably try to skip
every single time before you watch a
video
unless you're watching this on nebula
which has no ads anyway when it comes to
programmatic ads the acronym
actually no it's not an acronym it's an
initialism and the initialism that you
want to keep in mind is
cpm which stands for cost per
meal and meal is just the latin french
and italian word for a thousand so we're
talking about cost per
thousand views here this is how these
ads are often priced
so if the cpm is on average two dollars
which it could be here on youtube quite
often
then that means if you want to make the
same 210 dollars that we had back in our
affiliate marketing example
you got to bring in 105 000
views so as you can see if you want to
make money on programmatic ads
you got to have a huge audience which is
why you probably see
most of your favorite youtubers
diversifying their income streams doing
brand deals doing merch
adsense can be a decent revenue stream i
make about seven or eight thousand
dollars a month on it but it is one of
my smaller income streams and i don't
rely on it again because the cpms are so
small you have to have a huge
audience to rely on it that being said
if you are hell bent on being the next
jacksepticeye or mr beast and you know
you're going to be bringing in millions
of views
there is something really important i
need to talk to you about
when it comes to programmatic
advertising and that is the relationship
between
views and income a lot of people think
this relationship is very strong
and they'll often ask me questions like
hey dude how much money could i make
off of a million views to which i always
have to answer
it really really depends views
and income are not strongly correlated
these are only one variable
in a very complex equation and this is
going to be obvious to you
if you think about it for more than a
few seconds so
let's do an example here let's say that
i run a company that sells expensive
pool cleaning robots
if i'm considering running ads on my
friend matt's channel that's all about
pool maintenance
i can be reasonably sure about a couple
of different things
number one the people watching matt's
videos probably own pools
otherwise why would they be watching
videos about how to clean a pool
and number two because those people most
likely own pools
i can also be reasonably sure that those
people probably make a decent amount of
money
as well because they own pools so that
means i have a
relatively affluent potential customer
base
and because of that i might be willing
to pay a 10
cpm to advertise on one of matt's videos
which means that even if he's only
bringing in
10 000 views on a video those views are
gonna be worth
a lot and to give you a counter example
let's talk about
philip defranco i love philip defranco's
channel
but let's be honest a lot of what
phillyd talks about is
essentially celebrity gossip and
controversy and something that we know
about celebrity gossip and controversy
as
humans who love us a little bit of shot
and fraud in the morning
is that all kinds of people are gonna
click on that which means that if i'm
running that pool robot company
i can't really be reasonably sure about
who is in philly d's audience it could
be a pool owner
it could be somebody living in an
apartment who has no interest in owning
a pool whatsoever
and because of that i can't afford to
spend as much
per view on phillips channel maybe i'm
going to pay a 50 cent cpm
so to make the same amount of money that
map makes on 10 000 views
d is going to have to bring in well
what's 20 times
10 000. it's gonna be 200 000 views
so again the correlation between views
and income is
extremely weak and if you want to be
successful with programmatic advertising
you either need to bring in millions and
millions of views on you know video
games or celebrity gossip or whatever
you want
or maybe a little more strategic here
you pick a topic that's a little more
niched
down and that has a viewer base who
might be a little more primed to buy
slightly more expensive products now i
was picking on billy dee a little bit
earlier but
he has something that is actually a huge
feather in his cap
which is a loyal audience and that makes
his channel a great fit for
way far at brand deals so brand deals
these are the sponsored segments that
you're going to see
on most high view youtube videos these
days these are the sponsor segments that
are read by
the creators themselves and if you're
watching this video on youtube you're
going to see one at the end
of this video and if you're somebody who
usually skips those ads i would say
maybe stick around and watch this one
just to see how i
structure it because with brand deals
and sponsor segments
there is a huge amount of price
variability and that is because there
are a ton of different factors that go
in
to the quality and the effectiveness of
an ad
with a programmatic ad you don't have a
whole lot you can control
you can control the topic of your video
which may control the segment of people
who watch it and
influence your cpm somewhat you can
control the quality of the video to try
to bring in more views
but that's about it i guess you can also
control ad placement so pre-roll post
roll
but with a sponsored segment you have so
much more control because you as the
creator are doing the read
yourself the good news is that sponsored
segments and brand deals typically pay
a lot more than programmatic ads
sometimes 10 times more sometimes even
20 times more
and that's because ads that are voiced
by the creator by the person that the
viewer came to watch
are simply a lot more effective the main
downside is that brand deals are
typically a little bit less accessible
when you're getting started and that's
because you're gonna need to build up a
sizeable audience on your platform
of choice first once you bring in a
significant amount of views on youtube
or on instagram or wherever it is that's
when you're going to start seeing raid
shadow legends and various pubic hair
removal products sliding
into your dms now there are a lot of
factors that are going to go into the
effectiveness of your spots but
the most important one especially for
your long-term success
is trust you have to put your audience
first which means
only promoting products that you know
are going to be valuable and helpful
for the people who watch and trust you
another important concept that can
increase the effectiveness of your
sponsor reads is
the ada framework which stands for
attention interest
desire and action i think i first
learned about this concept in the movie
glenn gary glenn ross where alec baldwin
explains it with a lot more swear words
than you're gonna hear in this video
but essentially a good ad follows these
steps
in this order first working to get the
viewers attention
then getting them interested by talking
about something that the viewer
hopefully cares about
only at that point is it useful to start
introducing the products
talking points and tying them to that
interest i see a lot of ads here on
youtube that do that whole smooth
segway thing but then immediately launch
into the talking points for the product
which makes the ads
less effective than they could be lastly
i have to say this
if you're a creator who gets approached
about brand deals remember what i talked
about earlier with regards to views
and pricing they are not strongly linked
so it may be worth pricing your first
couple of deals with a brand or an
agency based on price
since you really don't have a whole lot
of extra data to give them at that point
but after that you shouldn't be pricing
solely based on views
and never let an agency talk you into a
view
guarantee because you know the views are
not strongly linked
to pricing so if they are trying to make
you believe that they are
they're probably not treating you fairly
finally we have method number five which
is selling
your own products like this cool pixel
llama sticker that i have on this mug
which is not mine but the sticker is so
if you want to sell your own products
i don't blame you because whether we're
talking about sponsor segments
or cpa ads or affiliate commissions in
any
case you're advertising somebody else's
product which means that
you don't get the entirety of that sale
you just get a small slice of the pie
and what if you want the entire pie for
yourself well selling your own products
can get you that
minus your expenses of course so the
main thing i want to talk about when it
comes to sales of your own products
is that doing this almost always
involves some kind
of upfront investment that could be
monetary investment in the case
you have to buy inventory though there
are ways to mitigate that using
crowdfunding sites like kickstarter is
one of them
but there is almost always going to be a
huge
upfront investment of your effort and
time and since this is your own product
you haven't sold before there is a big
risk factor because you don't know how
well
it's going to sell so my main tip here
is to do some market research
and the one example that always comes to
mind when i think about this
is involving my friend grant baldwin who
was a professional speaker who spoke at
colleges and schools for most of his
career and at some point he wanted to
create
a course for people like yours truly who
wanted to do the same
thing so instead of investing a ton of
effort up front and creating this big
long course and then trying to sell it
he first pre-sold access to a rough
outline of the course
to a small portion of his email list of
which i was one of those people
and i bought access to that pre-sale
which was about half of the price of the
regular course
and what i got at first was literally
just an evernote outline
with a bunch of bullet points of the
things he thought needed to be in the
course
and personally i found this really
really helpful because
i'm a quick learner and i really liked
just being able to go down this bullet
list and get a lot of my initial
questions answered
so this was in my opinion a really great
way
to do some market research gauge that
interest and
kind of mitigate the risk involved in
selling your own products
now personally i use all five of these
methods to create multiple sources of
income for my business
and if you're just starting out that
should be your eventual goal
but at the beginning it'd be a good idea
to just pick one of these
and make that your focus at first but no
matter which one you choose there is one
common factor which is that you need to
create an
online presence for yourself if you're a
freelancer that's going to include your
portfolio where you can show potential
clients your work
and if you're selling your own products
you need a place where people can go
to buy them but even if you just want to
make money on youtube it's still a
smart idea to create your own online
space you don't want your entire
business to be at the mercy
of a platform that you don't control for
me that space is my personal website
thomasjfrank.com where i have links to
my book
to my courses that people can buy and to
other work that i've done
and if you want to create a space that's
like mine then the first thing you're
gonna need
is a domain name which you should get
over at hover
hover is the best place on the internet
to get your hands on domain names not
least of which because they have a
pain-free quick checkout process without
any annoying pop-ups or friction they
also have
hundreds of domain extensions you can
choose from so you can get your
classic.com or dot me
or you can get something kind of funky
and interesting like i've gotten with
thomas.lol and one thing that i'm going
to note here is that even if you're not
ready to start your business if you do
have a name in mind it's a very smart
idea to secure the domain name
now so nobody else can take it from you
once you are ready
to get started once you do have your
domain name you can also create a
professional looking email address for
it like thomas collegeinfogeek.com or
thomas thomasjfrank.com
plus there's a feature called connect
where you can easily connect your domain
up to
online website builders and even online
store builders so if you are ready to
get your domain name head over to
hover.com
thomasfrank where you can get 10 off
your first order and support this
channel
thanks so much for watching if you
enjoyed this video hitting that like
button gently with your middle knuckle
is definitely helpful that helps the
youtube algorithm know that people like
these videos and maybe it'll send it out
to more people so definitely helpful for
me
and i just checked my stats the other
day and realized that only 40
of the people who watch my videos are
actually subscribed so
if you aren't subscribed yet and you
enjoyed this video definitely hit that
subscribe button so you don't miss out
on future videos beyond that i'll have a
couple other videos on the screen here
you can click on or you can follow me
over on instagram where i'm doing q a
videos every single week if you've got
questions
send them over and that's it so thanks
for watching and uh
if you don't want to do anything i just
said well don't because i'm not your dad