here's an interesting question given all
the books out there how do you know what
to read or to rephrase that how do you
avoid the bad or mediocre books that
just waste your time well that is what
we are going to try to answer in this
video though I think we need a more
fitting set first give me a second all
[Music]
right that's better so I've gotten a lot
of questions on this particular subject
in the past but I'm just gonna go ahead
and read the most recent one for you I
desperately need a video about how to
efficiently develop a reading list that
saves you from stumbling upon bad books
which may put you off a whole genre I'd
also like to know how to read more books
in more diverse categories and how to
avoid abandoning the older items on my
list for a random book that I just heard
of now I do want to be a bit careful
with this topic because when I think
back to some of the best books I've ever
read they've been things that I just
randomly picked off the library shelf or
was given to by a friend and I don't
want you to avoid those serendipitous
occasions but given the absolute tirade
of content that comes out of the
publishing houses of the world and the
Internet in the interest of helping you
triage all the options out there I want
to give you some recommendations for how
to find the best books in a particular
genre and avoid wasting your times on
the bad ones or the mediocre ones or the
ones that are just kind of padded out
for sales value or if nothing else and
the first thing we're going to talk
about is one of my favorite websites in
the world which is goodreads.com I've
been on Goodreads for quite a long time
and I found many of my favorite books
and Goodreads recommendation lists which
I would highly recommend checking out
for instance one of my favorite
non-fiction books of all time Bill
Bryson's a short history of nearly
everything was right near the top of one
of Goodreads best nonfiction of all time
lists and that's actually where I found
it and Goodreads is useful for other
things besides just its list feature if
you do see a book on a shelf at Barnes &
Noble or some book store or a library
and you're not sure whether or not to
read it the reviews on Goodreads can be
highly detailed it can be very good ways
to triage the books that you have on
your list to figure out what you should
prioritize and a lot of authors actually
have very active Goodreads profiles in
fact Pat Rothfuss who wrote the name of
the wind which is one of my top 5
fiction novels of all time has an
incredibly long review history which I
perused many times in the past and on
one day when I was just casually
scrolling through it I saw that he had
written a five-star review for a fiction
book called the girl who circumnavigated
fairyland in a ship of her own making so
I picked this up read it and even though
it's kind of a why a novel I found it to
be a really good read
so in short Goodreads gives you an
extensive database of lists of all
different types of genres I mean I found
cyberpunk novels on their lists I found
hacker history and crime history stuff
in their lists so whatever it is you can
probably find a list about it it also
has a huge user base so there's lots of
reviews for most books out there and you
can use the review histories of lots of
your favorite authors who are active on
the platform to find new books that they
liked and which you may like as well now
another great way to figure out whether
or not a book is worth your time is to
read a summary of it and there are
actually several resources on the
internet that you can go to to find lots
and lots of book summaries and I'm gonna
give you a few recommendations here
starting with the free ones and then
moving on to some that do cost money so
in the free category I want to point you
towards two different websites which are
each run by people that I have a lot of
respect for and who have been following
for a long time first and foremost there
is a website of Derek Siver's who
founded the company's CD Baby which if
you have any music on Spotify or you
know anybody who is an independent
artists and has their music on Spotify
or Apple or iTunes they probably went
through CD Baby they're kind of the og
in this industry and since then derek
has sold the company and spent a lot of
his intervening time between now and
then reading and reviewing and taking
notes really detailed notes actually on
a lot of books so if you go over to his
website which is I believe
sever's org slash books you're gonna
find a huge list of book reviews with
lots of notes and summaries which can be
a very good way to figure out whether or
not a book is actually worth picking up
and along the same lines my friend Nat
Ellison has another very long and very
detailed book notes page on his website
which I'll have linked in description
below because I can't think of the URL
right now and that brings us over to the
paid options one of which is new books
in brief calm which I believe is just
run by one guy who reads books and then
writes very detailed summaries of them
now on that site you can actually get
access to the first part of each summary
for free and then afterwards I think
it's about three bucks per summary if
you want to just buy them and get access
to them and another resource that I'd
used in the past is called a blink it's
now in contrast to new books and brief
which operates on a pay-as-you-go basis
you basically by each summary as you
want it Linkous operates on a
subscription model so if you're the kind
of person that wants to devour lots and
lots of summaries it could be a very
good option for you now I do want to
give you one word of warning when it
comes to book summaries because reading
them is much like getting the notes from
your friend instead of actually going to
class you're getting a secondhand
account of the source material and that
could be good for getting through that
material quickly and seeing what at
least somebody else believes is the most
important points from the material but
you're not taking it in yourself so
there may be things that would have
resonated better with you that are just
omitted from their account and that
example of getting notes from a friend
actually brings to mind one additional
tip which is to make friends who like to
read lots and lots of books from which
you can get lots of recommendations
earlier in the video I mentioned the
book the name of the wind by Patrick
Rothfuss and the only reason I ever read
that book is because a friend of mine
basically shoved the book into my hands
and told me that I had to read it now
usually when people recommend books to
me I think well my Goodreads list is
already so long I've already got so many
books that I want to read before this so
I'm never gonna get to it but in that
case I read the book I put everything
else on the back burner and I do not
regret doing that at all that book was
amazing and that brings me to something
that this person mentioned in their
question they wanted to know how to
avoid abandoning the older items on
there to be read list or the TBR if
you're in the booktube circles in favor
of taking up random books that people
just recommend to you in the moment or
that catch your eye on the bookshelf and
quite honestly I don't think this is a
problem yeah you probably want to get to
the books on your TBR at some point
they're interesting but just because
they made it onto your list before a new
book doesn't mean that they're gonna
have a greater impact on your life than
a new book will as I talked about on
this channel a lot of times in the past
the greatest ingredient to learning is
interest so if something catches your
eye and you're interested in it don't
shove that away because you think you
need to get through something that was
further down your list first follow your
interest and let it guide you in fact
well I'm thinking about it Martin you've
actually deleted your entire two to be
read list right yes yeah so there you go
now to round this video out I do want to
offer a few more pieces of advice for my
own experience regarding reading books
and having a lot of choices and all that
kind of stuff
number one don't finish a bad book
remember the goal if there is a goal to
reading a book is not
you turn the final page and be able to
say that you did it or be able to check
it off on your Goodreads profile it's to
get something useful out of the book or
to enjoy reading it you've probably seen
all these people on the internet talking
about how they read a book a day or a
book a week and how it changed their
life but to be honest the number of
books you read is not a metric that's
worth tracking I mean it can be fun but
it's what you get out of those books
that really matters at the end of the
day so if you pick up a book and you
start reading it and then halfway
through you think this is a waste of my
time then put it down don't finish bad
books remember your time is more
valuable than what you paid for the book
if indeed you pay for it at all but as a
caveat to that tip don't be overly
concerned with reading the best quote
unquote books out there because the best
books are just the books that other
people say are the best and like we said
before you may gain something out of a
book that nobody else is going to see
because you have your own unique life
experience in your own unique goals and
furthermore even if a particular book
doesn't make it on to your favorites
list or doesn't change your life
immediately it may send you down a path
that leads you to other resources which
do for example one of the books that I'm
gonna talk about in next week's video
about books that changed my life is one
called Harry Potter and the methods of
rationality which is at the end of the
day kind of a silly fanfiction that
basically writes the first Harry Potter
book if Harry Potter was a boy genius
and I really enjoyed that book but I
wouldn't say that book in particular
changed my life but what it did do is
get me interested in rationality in
heuristics and biases and that book led
me to reading a book called The Thinking
Fast and Slow which did change my life
and last but not least don't forget to
enjoy the process of reading one of the
top lessons I've learned in life is that
you never really get there whenever you
get to a milestone there's just another
milestone waiting at the top of the next
hill that you can see so enjoy what you
read don't worry about having read all
the best books out there because you're
gonna want to enjoy the actual process
and on that note of enjoying what you
read one of the things that I am greatly
enjoying right now is the complete
collection of Sherlock Holmes stories
though it is slightly inaccurate for me
to say that I am enjoying reading them
because I'm actually listening to them
on audible now you know the deal with
these audible spots I recommend a book
that I'm enjoying to you every single
time I do one but with the Sherlock
Holmes stories I do have to get
a little bit specific because since
Sherlock Holmes is so famous many
narrators have tackled the task of
reading his stories you can find many
different collections on audible for
example there's a collection by Simon
Vance which is very good there are
collections by a narrator named David
Timpson which is very good but for my
money the one that you want to get is
the one that is read by none other than
that great
Stephen Fry not only is his voice
absolutely fantastic but this collection
of stories is over 60 hours long and
it's only one credit so for my money it
is one of the best deals that exists on
audible and I am really enjoying it and
what's better if you're not already an
audible customer you can go over to
audible.com slash Thomas or text at
Thomas - 500 500 on your phone to get a
free trial of their service and a free
audiobook download whether it's Sherlock
Holmes like I'm recommending for you
right now
or anything else of your choosing and
when it comes to choosing you're gonna
have a ton of selection because audible
has an unmatched library of titles
across a ton of different genres ranging
from all the bestsellers to lots of
really obscure stuff so whatever is on
your to be read list if you have not
deleted it like Martin has you're
probably gonna be able to find it so
once again if you want to get started
with audible and start listening to
audiobooks which can be a great way to
make your downtime more efficient the
time on the bus time spent driving time
spent folding the laundry all that kind
of stuff then head on over to
audible.com slash Thomas or once again
text at Thomas - 500 500 on your phone
big thanks to audible for sponsoring
this video of being a huge supporter of
this channel and as always guys thank
you so much for watching if you enjoyed
this video give it a like to support
this channel and you might also want to
click right there to subscribe so you
don't miss out on new videos when they
come out you know it's like right over
there to get a free copy of my book on
how to earn better grades or go right
over here to listen to our latest
podcast episode last but not least click
right here to watch one more video on
this channel and I will see you in next
week's video on five books that changed
my life