Hey, what's up guys? So, I think it's
high time for a bonus video. So, let's
step away from the study tips and
tactics for a minute and talk about how
I actually make these videos.
Specifically, in this video, I want to
show you my gear and also walk you
through my actual filming process. So,
let's dive right in. So, believe it or
not, I'm actually rocking a relatively
inexpensive setup to make these videos.
Uh, for the camera, I'm using a Sony
NEX5N mirrorless camera, which ran me
about 750 bucks when I bought it, and
takes really high quality videos for the
price. Now, that's hooked up via HDMI to
a small TV which I used to set my scene
up and make sure I'm in focus and all
that good stuff since my camera doesn't
have a flip out screen. For lighting,
I've got a couple of DIY lights
constructed from supplies I found at
Lowe's and clamped onto cheap light
stands from Amazon. They cost me about
100 bucks to make for both of them and
they're much easier to store and work
with than the pre-made options I found.
So, I'm more than happy with them for
now. I've also got some accent lighting
on my backdrop to warm up the scene a
bit. And speaking of the backdrop, what
do you guys think of the new one? I
actually just moved. And this time
around, I actually made measurements and
used a level instead of just slapping
things up over time. The other important
part of the backdrop is my computer,
which is also what I use for recording
the audio. And on a side note, this is
actually a new build that I've been
saving up for for quite some time. And
let me know in the comments if you'd
like to see a bonus video on it, and
maybe I'll do it. Now, I actually think
audio quality is more important than
video quality. So, I recently invested
in a Mackie Pro FX8 mixing board, which
feeds the audio via USB into my
computer. There, I record using Adobe
Audition. And then on the other end of
that chain is a Sure SM7B dynamic mic
which I use for both recording the
College Info Geek podcast and my videos.
Before buying this mic though, I was
actually using a $99 Blue Yeti, which
just connected via USB, and it wasn't
actually too bad. To start the filming
process, I put my camera up on top of my
bookshelf and then connected to the TV
via HDMI. Then I set up the lights, put
my mic in the mic stand, and plug it
into the Mackie with an XLR cable. Next,
I'll start recording with Audition and
the camera. And then before I go through
my script, I'll make some dumb faces so
it's easy to find a shot for the video's
thumbnail. And finally, I'll start
recording. I typically don't memorize my
scripts before filming. Actually, most
of the time they're just lists of bullet
points. And this means that I just keep
saying lines until I'm done with plenty
of mistakes along the way. So, that's
just a quick overview of my shooting
process. And this video was supposed to
be a thank you for when we hit 10,000
subscribers. And we are a little bit
past that. Oops. Still, thank you so
much for the support and the feedback
you've given me so far. This has been a
ton of fun, and I can't wait to keep
making better and better videos every
single week. Now, for the next bonus
video, let's set the milestone at and
how about 50,000 subscribers. But I
actually want to hear from you down in
the comments. What kind of a bonus video
aside from college tips and studying
advice do you want to see? And also, if
you're still curious or have more
questions about my shooting process or
other parts of the video creation
process, I'm actually doing a little
minieries on my podcast both this week
and next week over that entire process.
And you can click the card or link down
in the description if you want to listen
to that episode. The first one's out
right now. And if you subscribe to the
podcast, you'll get the second one when
it comes out next Monday. So, that's all
I've got for you today. Thanks so much
for watching this bonus video and I will
see you in my video over test anxiety
coming out on Thursday.
[Music]
[Applause]