this is the notebook that I carry with
me every single day in my backpack and
in this video we are going to answer the
question is this the best notebook in
the world or is it something that's just
kind of a gimmick and I guess to answer
that question we first have to ask an
answer a preliminary question which is
what exactly is this well this is
something called the rocket book ever
last and ever since I kind of previewed
it back in my iPad pro versus notebook
paper video I've been getting a lot of
questions about it and as you can see
from the many many scuffs on the cover I
have had this thing for a while and I've
been able to put it through its paces so
what I want to do today is go over the
features of this notebook kind of give
me the specs and also tell you why I
think it's really cool and we're gonna
end the video with my verdict on whether
or not it's something that you should
maybe try out in your own workflow and
to start things off we got to talk about
what is probably the main feature of
this notebook which is the fact that you
can erase it there are only 32 pages in
the notebook which means it doesn't take
up a whole lot of space in your bag or
out a whole lot of weight to it but you
can very easily erase the pages that you
write on with pen by using a damp cloth
and just wiping it away it's really
really easy now I do want to note that
this is not a feature that is unique to
this one notebook and the way that they
achieve it is by requiring you to use a
specific type of pen called a friction
pen or a friction pen I'm not exactly
sure how to pronounce that brand name
but essentially these are pens that
allow you to erase their ink even on a
normal paper I'm gonna talk a little bit
more about that later in the video
but first let's talk a little bit about
the specs of the rocket book starting
with the fact that there are three sizes
there's the executive size there's a
mini size which actually flips upwards
instead of to the side and then there's
the letter size which is what I have
it's your standard 8 by 11 notebook and
I think that it's the one that's gonna
work best for students or people that
need a lot of writing area when they're
taking notes or drawing out diagrams or
doing whatever you do with a notebook
now there is one other rocket book that
you can get your hands on which is
called the wave and it's different from
all the other models because instead of
wiping away the pages with a damp cloth
you actually put the entire notebook in
a microwave and that erases the entire
notebook all at once but I wasn't super
interested in getting that notebook
because you can only do that about five
times before it no longer will fully
erase the pages whereas the Everlast
should theoretically last you as long as
you want it to lap
in any case one of my favorite features
of all the rocket book models is the way
they've laid out their paper because
it's grid paper but instead of being a
grid of lines it's a grid of really
subtle faint dots so I don't really get
in your way and because it's grid paper
it makes it really good for writing but
also for sketching drawing out things
like UI elements or website elements in
fact when I was doing the initial
designs for our latest version of
college info geek
I used that paper to sketch things out
before then diving into figma and
getting into the details
however the coolest feature of the
rocket book and by far the biggest
reason that I wanted to get it far
beyond the ability to erase the pages is
the system they've set up for letting
you digitize your notes because they
have a system of letting you do it a lot
faster than you can with normal notebook
paper and that's what I was really
excited about so at the bottom of every
single page in your rocket book you're
gonna see two things first you're gonna
see a QR code and then you're gonna see
a row of seven different icons and when
you download their companion app to your
iPhone your Android you can actually set
up different destinations for each one
of those icons be it box via Dropbox
Google Drive Evernote or tons of
different other options and for each
destination service you can also pick
where exactly you want it to go within
that service so for example with
Evernote you can choose which notebook
you want your scans to go to based on
the icon you choose now here is the cool
part after you've finished writing a
page of notes you can mark off one of
the icons at the bottom of the page then
using their app you can scan that page
and depending on which icon you marked
it will automatically send your scan to
the destination that you've set up in
advance and as you might imagine this
massively cuts down on both the friction
and the time that takes to digitize your
notes if you're taking your notes on
regular paper and you want to digitize
them with an app like Evernote then you
have to open the app you have to first
select the notebook that you want the
scan to go into you have to hit the Add
button and then you have to take your
scan but with the rocket book system
this entire process is automated and
there were some of the cool features as
well you can choose whether you want to
do a PDF or JPEG and if you have
multiple scans so you're sitting in
class and you've taken multiple pages of
notes you can actually bundle all the
scans for each page into a combined PDF
and this can be really useful if you
want to make sure all the pages from one
note-taking session go into one single
document in Evernote or your note-taking
system choice so overall these
digitization features this notebook
offers combined with the ability to
erase pages may justify the
and a hefty price tag and let's talk
about price now because unless you're
getting the mini which is usually around
fifteen or sixteen dollars the rocket
book both the executive and the letter
versions are right around thirty to
thirty four dollars depending on where
you get them and that's pretty steep for
a notebook it might not be a huge step
up if you used to high quality notebooks
like the moleskin but if you're like me
and you're coming from like $2 Walmart
notebooks the sticker shock can be kind
of extreme and especially with a price
tag like that we do have to be pretty
discerning when it comes to the writing
experience since writing is we're gonna
be spending most of your time doing with
this notebook so what's it like well in
my experience to put things in a
nutshell it's pretty good it's much much
better than writing on the iPad screen
with my Apple pencil which I not a big
fan of doing but it's not quite as good
as writing on normal notebook paper I
would say it's about 90% is good there
are three main nitpicks to kind of drag
the writing experience down for me again
not a ton just a little bit it's not
quite as good as normal paper first and
foremost when you're writing with these
Frick's young pens or friction pens I
don't know how to pronounce it you don't
always get this perfect black streak of
ink that you're gonna get with a normal
high quality pen though I did find that
after I spent a little time practicing
getting used to using it you kind of
realized that there is a specific amount
of pressure you have to use and once you
get used to it that happens far less
often secondly there is the texture of
the paper which is a double-edged sword
it's glossy so it makes it a lot easier
to erase with a damp cloth and this is
important because when writing on a
normal paper with a friction pen you
have to use this little eraser nub on
the end and it's kind of a laborious
process to erase your paper and honestly
it isn't worth it so that glossy paper
does have a big benefit because you can
erase a paper very very quickly but
again it's a double-edged sword because
since it's so glossy your pen doesn't
really have the same amount of grip and
it just doesn't feel quite as precise I
find it harder to write really neatly or
really legibly than I do with normal
paper finally the ink does take about 10
seconds to dry and I think this is again
due to the glossy nature of the pages
and this isn't a huge problem but if you
do write something down and then you
move your hand up quickly to make an
annotation or draw an arrow or something
you can smudge your writing and it won't
make it illegible because there would be
kind of like a ghost of it there but it
will make your page look messy
personally I don't like that all that
being said these are still minor
nitpicks and they haven't stopped me
from using the notebook on a daily basis
I just love that ability to scan things
so quickly and so automatically now the
only other concern that I have about the
rocket book and something that you
should probably keep in mind is I'm not
sure how long the Pens last again you
have to use friction pens with this book
and through some googling I found they
probably won't last as long as a normal
pen but at least in my case mine has not
run out yet and once it does a three
pack of these pens is about five or six
bucks at Target so it's not too big of a
deal at least for me so if you want my
verdict on the rocket book Everlast
I really like this notebook it is my
daily driver though I do have to admit
that it costs quite a bit more than most
other notebooks out there so it's really
up to you whether those digitisation
features and the erase ability of the
pages makes up for that big gap in price
now regardless of whether or not you
choose to go with the rocket book
Everlast or even if you decide to
handwrite your notes at all you should
make sure that you are using a well
organized well-thought-out note-taking
system as we go into the year and
honestly I would extend that to your
entire productivity system in general
make sure you are using a good task
manager make sure your file organization
system makes sense and if you are in the
mood to scrutinize these things well you
are in luck because I have just released
my very first online course which is all
about how to build a productivity system
and if you want to take it it is on
Skillshare and it is live today over the
course of the class is 10 different
videos you're gonna learn how to set up
your task management system how to
manage your calendar how to set up and
organize your folders and files how to
process your email more effectively and
in general create a productivity system
that ensures that you're always on top
of everything you have to do in your
life and of course because my class is
on Skillshare the membership that gets
you access to it also gets you access to
over 25,000 other courses in business
and web development and graphic design
and video editing and a ton of different
topic areas that can boost your skills
and your career prospects as well so if
you want to start the year out right if
you want to make sure you're pushing
yourself and building new skills every
single day and make sure you're staying
organized over the long run then sign up
for skill share using the link in
description down below there Premium
Membership is really affordable cost in
just about as much as a Netflix
subscription and what's best if you're
one of the first 500 people to click
that link and
sign up below you're gonna get a two
month free trial with unlimited learning
on the platform which means that yes you
can essentially go and take my course
for free which I highly recommend that
you do so click that link sign up and
start learning today a huge thanks goes
out to Skillshare for sponsoring this
video and being a big supporter of my
channel in general and as always guys
thank you so much for watching if you
like this video definitely give it a
like to support my channel and if you
want to get notifications of new videos
when they come out to get subscribed
right there you can also click right
there to get a free copy of my book on
how to earn better grades in school
click it right over here to watch one
more video on this channel or go and
follow me on instagram at Tom frankly
thanks again for watching and I will see
you in the next one