what is the best system for taking notes
in class well luckily for you I get the
research and it turns out that there are
five different note taking systems that
are generally accepted to be pretty darn
good and of course I will be
representing these note-taking systems
with Street Fighter characters because
why not so the five note taking systems
I'm going to go over in this video
include the outline method the Cornell
method the mindmap method the flow
method and the write on the slides
method the first note-taking system on
my list is the outline method I've
chosen Rio to represent it because the
outline method is straightforward based
on hierarchy disciplined and overall
very simple in fact you couldn't get
more simple than the outline method
unless you were just straight up writing
paragraph notes down and if you think
that's gonna be a good note-taking
method well things are not gonna work
out for you so the outline method is a
note-taking system that's based on
bullet points and hierarchy basically to
take outline style notes you simply
create top-level bullet points of all
the main points in the lecture then you
make lower-level bullet points to fill
out all the details if you're taking
outline notes on paper it's a good idea
to either space out your main bullet
points or summarize them at the top if
your professor goes through them and
then make new bullet points that are
more detailed down the line however if
you're taking these notes on a computer
like I always did in a program like
Evernote or by word or another word
processor you can easily go back add new
bullet points and format things without
having to mess up the structure of your
document too much so honestly for the
outline method I think using a computer
is a perfect approach the second
note-taking method on my list is the
Cornell method and I've chosen Chumley
to represent it because she's got
multiple kicks and it's got multiple
sections the Cornell method was
developed by Walter puck back in the
1950s and it still holds up pretty well
today when you take your notes in the
Cornell style you divide your paper into
three distinct sections on the top of
your paper you'll have two different
columns developed one being the Q column
and the right one being the note-taking
call and underneath those two columns
you add another box for with a summary
during class you use the note-taking
column on the right to write notes in a
normal style however this is where the
Cornell method deviates from other note
taking systems
as soon as you can after class you write
down questions or cues in the Q column
these are meant to help you review later
you also write down a summary at the
lecture in the summary column these two
sections of the Cornell method the
summary and the Q column they're both
designed to help you build reviewable
notes the first time you write them that
way you don't have to go back and rework
your notes so much note-taking system
number three is the mind map method you
know it's been said that your mind is a
map of the territory that is reality so
maybe by that logic the mind map system
is the perfect note-taking system
actually that doesn't make any sense at
all either way I chose dhalsim to
represent the mind mapping system
because he's a meditator and he's always
focused on improving his mind to beget a
mind map you simply take a blank piece
of paper draw a circle in the middle of
it and add the main topic of lecture
there then you'll start branching off
little trees and adding subtopics
eventually you'll have lots of little
branches and you'll create a mind map I
never actually used mind maps for my
class notes but I have used them for
blog post topics before when I wanted to
write a blog post on all the ways you
could save money in college I wanted to
make sure I could cover all my bases
so I created a my map I put saving money
in college in the middle and then tried
to figure out all the different facets
of a student's life where they have to
spend money building a mind map helped
me organize all these topics and as a
result I was able to create a more
comprehensive list in the end the fourth
note-taking system is the flow method
this system was invented by the writer
Scott Young who's probably best known
for going through the entire MIT
computer science curriculum in a single
year Scott uses what he calls holistic
learning and his approach is
diametrically opposed to the rigid
transcribing style of the outline method
as a result I chose Blancas to represent
this note-taking system his fighting
style is that of basically a wild animal
and it's the complete opposite of more
disciplined fighters like ryu or guile
and that is a perfect way to describe
the flow system of note-taking you're
not trying to get every single detail
from the lecture down to your paper and
in fact the point is not to transcribe
the lecture at all rather it's to learn
while you are sitting in class as you
take your notes your goal is to create
an original document that represents
your mental image of the subject it's
not to record verbatim what your
professor said as you take notes you can
go back to earlier points at details
draw on arrows and little offshoots and
basically create something that is your
own
the entire point of the flow system of
notetaking is to learn at once
this lets you accelerate your learning
and that's the real strength of the
system final system of taking notes is
the lazy man's way of taking notes and I
call it the write on the slides method
to represent this note-taking method I
chose Zangief because Zangief seriously
do you really think I'll put a whole lot
of thought into these things if your
professor actually lets you download the
lecture slides before class then it can
be pretty convenient to just go print
them off to computer lab and write
directly on them one of the cool things
about this method is that the slides
more or less mirror the flow of lectures
so you almost get a sort of Timeline
view when you take notes on slides it's
kind of like SoundCloud where people can
actually leave comments I had specific
times during an audio file taking notes
on slides isn't that accurate but it's
pretty close and when you do it you can
look back and say okay at this slide he
was talking about return on the cost of
buzzwords energy management so those are
the real strengths of the method you
don't have to write as much because the
slides sort of do it for you and you get
a sort of timeline view for your notes
so those are in my humble opinion the
best five note taking systems out there
which one is right for you hey there
thanks for watching my video on the
different note taking systems you can
use if you like this video I would
absolutely appreciate it if you could
give it a like and share with a friend
who's maybe not as good at taking notes
as you want charity's a good thing right
if you want to get more videos every
single week on being awesome in college
booting more videos on how to take
better notes once y'all have coming out
in the next couple of weeks that hit the
subscribe button up in the corner yeah
that one you missed last week's video
well you can click the button right into
that it's not actually a button it's
more like a little movie clip but it'll
get you there all the same so whatever
you want to get links to other websites
with additional information on any of
these note-taking systems then click the
orange logo on the left corner where
you'll find the companion blog post for
this video if you'd like to get a free
chapter in my book hacking productivity
when it comes out well like that thing
also if you would like to suggest any
other video ideas for the future or
leave a comment then leave a comment or
you connect with me on Twitter
[Music]