thanks to notion for sponsoring this
video and supporting my channel
when you think about the idea of being
rich what's the first thing that comes
to mind
well if you're like most people the
answer is probably money that's what we
think of when we think of a rich person
somebody who has a lot of money
or if you're somebody who spends a lot
of time watching online content creators
maybe something that also comes to mind
is audience somebody who has a lot of
followers a lot of subscribers
a lot of people commenting on their
videos but i think this idea of richness
can be a lot
more broad than we typically think it's
not just money we can be rich in
in fact the other day i saw somebody
tweeting about the idea of time
billionaires
if you're 20 years old you have more
than a billion seconds
left to live on average whereas somebody
who is a little bit older
even if they have a big bank account
they're not a time billionaire
so i got to thinking the other day while
i was out on a bike ride like what does
richness mean to me and indeed that
definition comes out a lot more broad
than just money
or followers for me i want to be rich in
not
just time as in like being a time
billionaire but also
in having free time time to explore
specifically time to build new skills
to pursue ideas that interest me i want
to be rich in
relationships and not just casual
relationships not just
audience members who follow me online
but deep relationships people with whom
i can have deep conversations people who
i love and who love me back and i think
if you really asked yourself this
question you would come up with the same
answers or some very similar answers or
at the very least
money wouldn't be the only thing on that
list and yet
in my own life i continually find myself
with priorities that align with the
money side of richness
or with the audience size side of
richness and i often find myself
de-prioritizing these other more
ethereal parts of richness even though
when i really think about it when i
really think about what i
want these are the things i want more
and i wonder
why is that so here's the theory that i
have right now at least for me
but i think this might apply to other
people as well these sides of richness
the money the audience the business
growth
they're easily tallied it's very easy to
keep track and keep score
of these things you can easily see how
much money is in your bank account or
how much money you make every year
it's very easy to say i make six figures
i made five beggars last year i made six
figures now
you can put a growth number on that you
can make spreadsheets and
see different percentages but reds and
greens and with audience growth it's the
exact same you can easily see how many
followers you have
be it on youtube or facebook or
instagram or any social network and by
contrast these other areas of richness
are a bit more ethereal
having free time is a little harder to
really keep score of it's harder to
really focus on what that
means relationships it's hard to focus
on what that means and i think
as a result we tend to take these areas
for granted and to de-prioritize them or
at least we're very incentivized to do
so
not least of which because of the
society we live in the economy we live
in
and when the companies that we interact
with when it comes to these platforms
like with social networks these
companies are highly incentivized to
keep you on the platform and to keep you
focused with growing your audience
if you are a creator and with the
economy all businesses
want to have more sales they want to
have more economic activity
so they're very incentivized keeping you
focused on how much money you can make
so you can therefore spend that money
they are not incentivized to make you
think about
how much free time you have how deeply
you are invested
in your close relationships so as an
individual
you have to find a way to prioritize
these other areas of richness if you do
care about them
i've been thinking about that lately how
can i prioritize these areas
when the money and the followers and the
business success are so easy
to get addicted to so easy to keep score
of and this is a tough
problem and i'm probably not going to
solve it for myself overnight but i
think there are a couple things that i
can do to start
moving in the right direction and the
first one has to do with intent
what actions can i take that will
solidify my intent to prioritize
these other areas of richness more
effectively one of them is just simply
writing down and then periodically
reminding myself of what i truly care
about so i've written down my priorities
and i've put the money and i've put the
audience growth
at lower on the list than these other
things i think we need to
kind of periodically look at what our
priorities are because it's very easy to
get
lost in the minutia of our day-to-day
lives
and with all the different opportunities
that come at us and we need to remind
ourselves again and again and again i
think
of these priorities so we can make more
informed decisions
instead of just chasing the shiny thing
when it presents itself
beyond that though i think it's very
important to think about our proximity
to the sources of information
the tools and the relationships that
cause us to focus on the things that
long term we don't want to be constantly
focused on
and in terms of focusing on the money
focusing on the audience and business
growth
i am constantly exposed to and am very
close to
a lot of those things my social networks
my youtube channel
stats page uh slack where i have a lot
of my business conversations
they're all right behind me on this
computer which is in my home it's not at
some far-flung office somewhere where i
can commute and do my work and then come
home at the end of the day and be
physically separated from it it's all
right here in many cases
it's all on this distraction rectangle
that's in my pocket most of the time
and that presents a problem i've been
thinking a lot about bad
habits lately and one of the things that
causes us to continue to engage in a bad
habit
is when we're in very close proximity to
it i think this is why cold
turkey is the best way to break a bad
habit rather than trying to
self-regulate because
you know if you have a bad habit in the
first place and you've called it a bad
habit
then you've already stated to yourself
that i have a problem
self-regulating and if you remove
yourself from the source of temptation
that's the strongest way to not engage
in that lack of self-regulation so if i
want to increase the time that i spend
focused on these more important aspects
of richness then i have to figure out
how to
increase my distance or decrease my
proximity
to everything that incentivizes me to
keep focusing on the money to keep
focusing on the audience
and that might mean turning off this
computer at the end of the workday that
might mean
you know signing up for social
obligations making plans
with friends more often that might mean
leaving my phone
up in a room for most the day so i don't
have quick access to it and these are
just a few ideas this is less of a
tactical video and more of a video
designed to get you
and me thinking about the overall
concept here
how can we decrease the amount of time
we spend
focused on these easily tallied aspects
of richness and
increase the amount of time we spend
focused on the other things that we
might care about
a bit more so i know this wasn't as much
of a scripted video as i usually do but
i've been thinking a lot about this idea
over the past couple of weeks
especially since i just moved into a new
house and this is actually the first
house that i've ever bought which has
got me thinking about you know wanting
to learn how to make it my own
in fact you're probably hearing the echo
down here that's because this basement
well at some point be an amazing studio
but right now has a lot of work
i just started tearing up the
floorboards so i can have people come in
here and lay carpet
and i've been thinking about like you
know i could hire people to come do
everything here but there's a lot of it
that i just want to learn how to do
i want to learn how to make this place
my own in fact i've gone as far as
setting up an entire project in my
notion task manager for
home improvement projects things i need
to buy things i need to learn
and that brings me to notion i guess if
you haven't heard me talk about notion
well number one i'll be very surprised
because i kind of talk about it all the
time on this channel but number two
notion is my absolute favorite
productivity app in the world and it's
something that you should check out if
you haven't already because
it really gives you a tool set that you
can use to build an all-in-one
productivity system i use notion to run
my entire business we manage all of our
video projects in it all of our podcasts
we have a company wiki in there we have
all kinds of stuff and i also use it for
my personal life i have a note-taking
system i have my task management in
notion i've built all these templates
that allowed me to do things
i couldn't do before when i was using a
bunch of disparate productivity
apps to you know try to manage my life
students use notion to take notes in
class companies use notion to build
things like company wikis run their
processes on board new employees
it's really kind of just a tool set that
you can use and bend
to your will so if you haven't tried
notion now is a great time to try it not
least of which because their personal
plan used to be five bucks a month
to get unlimited blocks but now is
completely free so there's
no real downside to giving it a try and
there'll be a link in the description
down below so you can sign up and start
building something that works
for you also once you're signed up once
you've played with it a little bit
you'll also find a ton of tutorials over
my brand new channel thomas frank
explains and free notion templates for
things like task management
note-taking project management and lots
more so check those out after you use
that link in the description down below
to sign up
and give notion a try big thanks as
always to notion for sponsoring this
video and being a big supporter of my
channel
and if you like this video hit the
subscribe button which will probably be
covering my face right now
uh check out that new channel thomas
frank explains and check out the other
videos that i'm gonna have
on screen right here and right here or
don't do any of that
go buy your own house demo your own
basement do it better than i did because
as always i'm not your dad