if I asked you to think of a really
tough problem what is the first thing
that comes to mind oh if you're anything
like me you probably thought of some big
complex math equation right for most
people math seems like one of the most
difficult subjects out there it's
abstract it's complex and unfortunately
for those reasons a lot of people adopt
the belief that they're just not math
people which is patently untrue because
math is a skill that can be learned just
like any other but since you clicked on
this video hopefully you are not one of
those people hopefully we have at least
some degree of belief that you can
become better at math and you have the
motivation to do so and if you do the
obvious question is how do you get
better at math well fortunately this is
one of those questions that has a pretty
simple answer you want to get better at
math you have to do lots and lots of
math and the tougher the problems are
the better because tough problems will
stretch your understanding and lead you
to new breakthroughs but in the course
of studying math and working through
these tough problems you are eventually
going to come to problems that just
stumped you that you could completely
stuck on and when you get to these
points it's important to know how to
eventually solve these problems because
these are the ones that are really going
to stretch and build your skill set so
that is what I want to focus on in this
video I want to give you some practical
techniques for working through and
eventually solving those problems that
seem insurmountable at first to start I
want to focus on a piece of advice that
the Hungarian mathematician George Poe a
shared is a 1945 book how to solved it
goes if you can't solve a problem then
there is an easier problem that you can
solve find it this is in my opinion the
most important technique to understand
and put into practice when you're trying
to solve tough math problems because
math builds upon itself more complex
concepts are built upon simpler concepts
and if you don't have a strong grasp on
the fundamental principles then a more
complex problem is going to likely
stumped you so if you come across a
problem that you can't solve first
identify the components or the
operations that it wants you to carry
out a lot of times complex problems will
have multiple now what you can do in
this case is split the problem into
multiple problems that isolate just one
of those components or operations I want
to show you this concept in action so
let's work through a quick example now I
did have one example picked out that
would be pretty easy but it ended up
being a little bit too easy so let's do
something a little bit more complicated
so this is a sum
problem which uses the Greek symbol
Sigma and it essentially says that we're
going to add up a series of expressions
that use a variable starting at 1 and
ending at 4 but if you notice this
summation problem also has a fractional
exponent in it now maybe some of you
math was out there I could do this kind
of a problem in your sleep but it's also
possibly the case that you don't have a
really firm grasp on either summation or
fractional exponents so when you're
working a problem that combines the two
of them you might get stuck so assuming
that's the case let's break this problem
into two simpler problems that each
focus on just one of the underlying
concepts first let's create a simpler
summation problem that just gets rid of
that fractional exponent all together
now all we have to do is evaluate that
expression for x and then add up the
answers which gets us to a final answer
of 66 and now let's move on to the
fractional exponent now I'm gonna go
pretty quick here because this is not a
lesson on fractional exponents but
essentially you can rewrite this as 4 to
the power of 3 times the power of 1/2
and then you can rewrite that again to
the square root of 4 to the power of 3
and once you evaluate that you get an
answer of 8 now the whole point of
working these simpler single concept
problems is to master the underlying
concept or operation that you're working
on here so if you solve a few and you
still don't feel really confident on
that concept keep working it until you
do remember mastery means not being able
to get it wrong not just getting it
right once anyway once you've mastered
those underlying components in an
isolated setting now you can come back
to the more complicated problem that
combines them at this point you should
be able to work those isolated concepts
in your sleep which means that all of
your mental processing power can go
towards the new and novel problem of how
they work in tandem now there is one
additional way of simplifying tough
problems that I want to talk about and
you might have already guessed it if you
paid really close attention to the
examples I didn't use really complex
numbers I didn't use long numbers I
didn't use decimal points I didn't use
big fractions and I stuck to a low limit
on my summation problem really complex
big numbers with lots of decimal points
can distract your attention away from
the concepts and the operations that
you're supposed to be practicing so if
you're stuck on a tough problem that has
these kinds of numbers go work a similar
problem with really small whole numbers
that are easy to add or operate in your
head that way you can really zero in on
the actual concepts of course sometimes
you have to shake even understanding of
the concepts and operations themselves
food actually
work with them and solve that problem
and in that case it's time to go do some
learning go dig into your book look
through your notes or find example
problems online you can follow along
with step by step so you can see how
people are getting to the solutions
using these concepts and if you need to
you can actually get a step-by-step
solution to the exact problem you're
working on as well there are several
tools out there that you can use to do
this but the two that I want to focus on
in this video which are the best ones
I've been able to find our Wolfram Alpha
and Simba lab both of these websites
will allow you to type in an equation
and get an answer and also give up and
symbolize that you can follow along with
the difference between the two is that
Wolfram Alpha while being much more
powerful and capable does require you to
be part of their paid plan if you want
to get those step-by-step solutions by
contrast well I found that typing in
equations into simple AB was a little
bit slower and less intuitive than it is
with Wolfram Alpha they're step-by-step
solutions are free regardless of the
tool that you choose to use here the
underlying point is that sometimes it
can be useful to see a step-by-step
solution for a problem you're stuck on
but there are two very important caveats
here first and foremost before you go
running off to find a solution ask
yourself honestly have I pushed my brain
to limit trying to solve this problem
first expending the mental effort
required to solve the problem yourself
is going to stretch your capabilities
it's gonna make you a better
mathematician in a way that just looking
through solutions won't now if you do
need to look up a solution that's fine
look it up follow the steps and make
sure you understand how the answer was
arrived at but once you've done that
challenge yourself to go back and rework
the problem without looking at that
reference it is really important to say
vigilant about this because if you want
to get better at math the whole point is
to master the concepts that you're
working with the danger that comes with
looking up solutions is that with math
it's really easy to follow along with a
step-by-step solution and comprehend
what's going on but that is very
different than being able to do it on
your own and that brings me to my final
tip for you and this is especially
important for anybody in a math class
working through assigned homework
don't rush when you work through math
problems I know it's really tempting to
try to work through homework as fast as
you can and heck I even made a video
about it pretty recently but with math
and science and any sort of really
complex subject especially rushing is
only going to hurt you down the road
because when you rush you don't matter
for the concepts you just brute force
your way to answers or you look things
up or you otherwise kind of Chiti face
your way to a completed homework
assignment and later on when you're
sitting in a testing room or you have to
apply what you've learned in the real
world you are gonna get a harsh lesson
about exactly what it is you don't know
so let's recap here if you want to get
better at math and you want to improve
your ability to solve those really tough
problems first identify the combination
of concepts or operations being used in
a problem and then isolate them work
simpler problems that use just one and
then master each concept you can also
simplify the problem by leaving the
combination of concepts intact but
swapping in smaller easier to handle
numbers if you need help with the
concepts themselves go to your book or
an explainer article online look up
sample problems or use a tool like
Wolfram Alpha or symbol AB to get
step-by-step solutions to the problem
you're working on and finally don't rush
through your homework assignments make
sure you're focusing intently on
mastering the concepts not just
finishing hopefully these tips will give
you the confidence to tackle some really
tough math problems and to expand your
math skill set and on that note I want
to leave you with a quote from the great
physicist Richard Feynman who said I
don't believe in the idea that there are
a few peculiar people capable of
understanding math and the rest of the
world is normal math is a human
discovery and it's no more complicated
than humans can understand the bottom
line is this ultimately your ability to
get good at math and anything else for
that matter starts with having the
confidence to approach it and as you
solve problems and make mental
breakthroughs your confidence is going
to naturally increase it becomes a
self-sustaining cycle if you're
interested in starting the cycle
learning now a great place to begin your
journey is at brilliant a learning
platform uses hands-on problem-solving
as a basis to help you learn math
science and computer science really
effectively I'm actually taking their
computer science fundamentals course
right now and as I was going to the
first section of algorithms the quiz
questions they gave me forced me to
learn new math I had never learned
before I had to dig into wiki's and
example problems and eventually I had to
get out a sheet a notebook paper and
literally draw out algorithms step by
step so I can understand what was going
on this process provided me with a much
more intense and effective learning
experience than I got sitting through
most of my college lectures and these
types of challenges that really force
you to dig in form the foundation for
all of their courses which include
probability logic calculus astronomy
computer memory and more
in addition to the structured courses
brilliant also has weekly challenges
that you can use to improve your skills
as a community where you can talk with
other learners and it has a
fantastically detailed and helpful wiki
with lots of explanations and examples
so if you want to get really on a try
click the link in the description down
below and sign up for free to start
learning and as a bonus if you're among
the first 200 people to sign up you'll
also get 20% off of your annual premium
subscription I want to give a huge
thanks to brilliant for sponsoring this
video and helping to support this
channel and as always guys thank you so
much for watching if you found this
video helpful you can give it a like to
support this channel and maybe consider
sharing it with a friend who could
benefit from it as well otherwise you
can subscribe right there and maybe hit
that Bell icon if you want to be the
first to know when new videos drop or
click right there to get a free copy of
my book on how to earn better grades
alternatively you can click right there
listen to our latest podcast episode on
how to crush job interviews or if
nothing else you can click right there
to get one more video on this channel
right now thanks for watching and I will
see you in the next video