hey what is going on guys so on this
channel we have covered lots of
not-so-subtle and pretty obvious
productivity flaws that a lot of us are
guilty of having things like constantly
getting distracted multitasking all that
kind of stuff but today I want to talk
about five things that you may be doing
that are subtly and secretly killing
your productivity just as surely as all
those obvious things and an alternate
title for this video to be quite honest
could be five things that I am doing
that are killing my productivity because
this is sort of a video we sat down and
wrote to me and a couple of good friends
and I just kind of asked them like what
do I do
that makes me a less productive person
and the first thing we're going to talk
about here is probably my number one
flaw when it comes to my professional
life which is perfectionism I constantly
overthink things and I have this
tendency to want tweak things again and
again and again and if this went
unchecked and I was allowed to do this I
would probably never actually publish
anything and actually for a really long
time about five years ago my business
stagnated for about a year and a half
and part of the reason for this was that
I didn't have myself on a strict
publishing schedule so I would allow
myself to just kind of tinker for months
on one project without actually getting
it out and then around August of 2014
right around the time I actually started
doing YouTube I put myself on a strict
publishing schedule I told myself I am
going to put out one podcast episode one
video and one blog post every single
week regardless of whether or not they
are perfect and as a result my business
actually started to grow and another
huge benefit to doing this was that
after I published ten or twenty videos
none of which were perfect but all of
which were actually published in a
timely manner I started to realize that
my view of perfection was something that
I could have never attained at the start
and this whole idea of doing a lot of
work to gain skills over time through
learning and through mistakes is
reminiscent of a story in the book art
and fear about a ceramics teacher who
divided his class into one-half of the
class was told that they would be graded
on the quality of a single pot while the
other half of the class was told they
would be graded on the quantity of pots
they created by weight and something
interesting happened at the end of that
class all of the objectively
pots that came out of the class were
created by the quantity group not the
quality group see well the people in the
quality group spent so much time
theorizing about what would make the
perfect pot all the people in the
quantity group spent time actually
making pots and through making mistakes
over time they got better than the
quality group could have ever hoped to
get through pure Theory alone
so if you're like me if you struggle
with perfectionism in your work then put
yourself on a schedule
give your projects deadlines where you
have to put them out into the world or
put them away and move on to the next
one alright so the next bit dirty
laundry that I'm going to air out here
is what I like to call organizational
sludge these are the tasks in your task
management system that haven't gotten
done have been overdue for two weeks
they're the stuff that's been laying on
your desk or in your inbox for weeks
that you haven't processed yet basically
over time any organizational system or
area in which you do your work is gonna
get a little bit messy just bit by bit
until it starts to SAP your efficiency
it's kind of like that story of the frog
sitting and slowly boiling water which
actually is that true okay it's
definitely not true but the metaphor
still holds in the story the Frog is
basically a okay with the water as it
gets hotter and hotter and hotter until
it dies and it's the same with your
organizational systems you don't realize
that things are getting kind of crusty
over time until you start really losing
efficiency so what I like to do is have
an organizational day every single week
where I look at my systems I look at my
task management system I look at my
calendar I look at my room my inbox my
backpack and I ask myself how can I
reset this back to a usable state all
right item number three on my list is
taking inspiration from too many sources
either online or authors or whatever it
may be and this is something I really
struggle with so for example one of the
people I love following on Instagram and
YouTube and many other places actually
is Gary Vaynerchuk I take a lot of
inspiration from him and I really look
up to him as a creator but at the same
time I also really like people like
Peter McKinnon and Liza Koshi in Cal
Newport people who put a lot of time and
artistic energy into singular pieces of
work that take a really long time to
produce so I'm admiring these people
over here and I'm striving to be like
them but
on the other hand I got Gary telling me
I need to put out more content content
every single day put stuff on Instagram
and snapchat and musically in YouTube
and I can't do both and that's the
problem I'm following all these people
online and I feel like I can be like all
of them but when I step back and I
really think about it
Gary Vaynerchuk is very successful liza
Koshi very successful Cal Newport very
successful but Gary Vaynerchuk does not
have the life of Cal Newport he's not
doing new and original research into
computer science and by the same token
Cal Newport is not spending his time
making incredibly polished comedy videos
he's teaching students he's writing
books and he's doing research and he's
definitely not building a snapchat
Empire so at the end of the day I need
to realize that I could really only be
great that one or at most a very small
group of things I can't be just as good
at everything as all the people I'm
following online are because they've
kind of chosen their lanes and they're
staying in them and I kind of have to do
the same if I want to keep doing really
good work and before we move on to the
next item I do really want to mention
that another very related point here is
that it's very easy to try to please
everyone and when you're trying to
please too many people people who have
lots of different desires
you're gonna spread yourself too thin
just as you would if you're trying to
follow too many influences so whatever
the kind of work you're doing is
remember that at the end of the day you
are the ultimate authority as to the
direction that it should go in alright
item number 4 on our list is believing
that you are the exception to the rule
what is the role well the rule might be
you need to sleep seven hours a night or
you need to close all of your tabs and
slack and your Instant Messenger when
you're writing a paper on your computer
or like we just talked about in the
previous tip that you can't be just as
great as all the diverse online
influences that you follow and again
this is a huge problem for me
I run a self development channel and I
constantly tell people that you have to
focus that you can only be great if you
have a few objects that you're pursuing
and yet I constantly tell myself or at
least like there's this little part of
my brain that constantly tells me yeah
but you're the exception you can do all
those things as long as you figure out
the most efficient learning techniques
out there you can do them because you're
good enough and that's not true that's
just self delusion that's just me
fantasizing and trying to turn into
reality and that's a fruitless pursuit
so
it's my particular problem with
spreading myself too thin or it's
believing that you can pull an
all-nighter realize that no you are most
likely not the exception then you should
probably follow the established best
practices for whatever you're trying to
do and that brings us to our final
subtle productivity killer which is the
refusal to acknowledge and adapt to
delays in your work this is actually
something that my friend Martin said was
an issue for him but when he said it in
the car when we were talking about it I
realized that this is also an issue for
me essentially when I plan to do
something and I had a delay or something
comes up and interrupts my work or takes
longer than expected the next day I
often wake up and sort of trick myself
into believing that I can do everything
that didn't get done from the day before
while still doing everything that was
planned for today and Martin put it
really well he said you have to realize
that if you have a delay in your work
then where you are right now is your new
starting point regardless of what you
may tell yourself you can't do
everything from the day before and all
of today's stuff if you didn't get it
done yesterday why do you think today is
going to be any different now that
doesn't mean you shouldn't work hard and
try to catch up if you can but the
problem is a lot of us beat ourselves up
when we can't catch up like this and
then we end up just getting further and
further behind
so instead try to be flexible adapt to
your new starting point to rework your
plan and move forward additionally if
the delay was caused by your own
procrastination or some productivity
failing on your part don't beat yourself
up about that either
consider that the first mistake and as
James Clare would say what you want to
avoid is the second mistake the one that
starts a trend as long as you can hop
back up in the proverbial horse and keep
writing then that one mistake isn't
really gonna hurt you in the long run
after all making mistakes is an
essential part of growth as long as we
can pinpoint what caused the mistake and
learn from it
and speaking mistakes nowhere is that
point more true than in the realms of
math and science these are two
disciplines where mastery is nearly
impossible without tons of failure and
its associated learning and if you're
somebody who wants to get better in
these fields then you should absolutely
check out brilliant brilliant is a
learning platform that takes an
incredibly active approach to teaching
math science and computer science and
throughout their courses on topics like
logic and probability and calculus
gravitational physics and solar energy
and computer science topics like
algorithms and machine learning you'll
find yourself thrown immediately into
challenging problems that not only boost
your interest in the
subject but immediately give you
something to sink your teeth into
something to which you can actually
apply all the concepts you're learning
really really quickly
this approach to teaching this material
means that you're not spending a ton of
time and lectures or waiting through
introductory material you get right to
the heart of the subject and as a result
you learn more effectively so if you are
interested in learning more about math
or science or computer science and you
want to start learning for free and
support this channel then head on over
to brilliant org slash Thomas Frank
which will find in the description down
below and if you're among the first 83
people to sign up with that link you're
also going to get 20% off of your annual
subscription we need a huge thanks to
brilliant for sponsoring this episode
and helping to support this channel and
as always guys thank you so much for
watching if you enjoyed this video then
like is appreciated you should also
click right there to subscribe so you
don't miss out on new videos when they
come out and you might also want to grab
a free copy of my book on how to earn
better grades right there additionally
you might want to check out our latest
podcast episode on how to give a killer
speech right over here or you can watch
one other video on this channel by
smashing your face and your phone screen
as always right here thanks for watching
guys and I will see you in next one