Hey guys, it's Thomas Frank and as you
can see from the video title, this is a
little bit of a room tour. And the
reason for that is that I've been
getting a few requests for it. And I
just wanted to do it as a thank you
because we just passed 5,000 subscribers
over the weekend. And I just really want
to say thank you because I never
expected the channel to grow this fast.
And it really validates a lot of the
work I'm doing to see people watching
and commenting and subscribing and all
that cool stuff. So seriously, thank you
so much. Again, I'm going to keep
putting more effort into making these
videos better and better and covering
all the topics you guys are requesting.
So, definitely keep asking questions.
But yeah, for this 5,000 subscriber
milestone, I just wanted to show you the
room that I work in, some of the gear
that I use to make videos and uh
podcasts and all other kind of stuff in
this room. Uh when I hit 10,000, I think
I'm going to do a video about how I make
videos, maybe the shooting process and
how I set up. But you'll have to wait
until 10,000 for that. So, until then,
enjoy this room tour. Heat. Heat.
[Music]
[Applause]
Heat. Heat.
[Music]