the American journalist Jean fer once
said that writing is easy all you do is
stare at a blank sheet of paper until
drops of blood form on your forehead
make no mistake though writing is hard
and Fowler was lying coffee can help
especially when it's in a cool mug like
this one but it only goes so far so
today let's enlist the help of our robot
overlords and look at some writing apps
that can help us write more efficiently
and faster cogle is a free mind mapping
tool you can use to organize your
thoughts and get down everything you
want to write about and if you want
something a little bit more time based
maybe you're writing fiction then
storyline Creator is another tool that
will work for you also I have to mention
Evernote that is where all my scripts
and video ideas start out I basically
just dump info and it's my favorite
organizational tool for writing speaking
of huge multi-purpose applications
scrier is an app that many many
novelists use to write their books in
fact I used it to write my book it's got
a planning tool it's got a cartboard
where you can put scenes and ideas it's
got sophisticated writing tools a
distraction free mode all sorts of
features and if you want something a
little bit more simple I've heard that
novel is an alternative to that well
it's got a paired down feature set
compared to scrier it's got a nicer
design and it's meant to be a little bit
more simple and I've seen some writers
enjoy using it to get really simple one
of my absolute favorite writing apps is
byw which is a minimalist markdown
editor for the Mac if you often have
trouble finding the right word to
describe something then twin Road writer
might be for you it's got an engine that
detects when you paused your writing and
then suggests alternate words to the
word that you just wrote if you have
trouble writing all together then you
should check out WR or die which is an
app that lets you set consequences for
not writing including kamakazi mode
which starts deleting your writing if
you pause for too long on the positive
side written kitten is an app that shows
you a cute picture of a kitten every 100
words you write you can also check out
750 words which is a web app that helps
you build a consistent habit of writing
every day and gives you your stats and
in that vein there's also a new website
called daily page which gives you a
daily writing prompt to help you build
your writing skills now if you're a grad
student or somebody who has to manage a
lot of research in your writing then you
should definitely give mentally a look
and if you want to edit your papers more
effectively edit minion is a little tool
made by the guy who created writ or die
which point out weak words in your
writing lastly I've got those little
accessory apps to help you get in the
mood for writing and one of them is
cativity which is a website that
generates coffee shop noise in case you
really like that and it gets you in the
mood but you don't happen to have a
coffee shop nearby and the last one is
brain.fm which is a website that uses
artificial intelligence to generate
music that supposedly helps you increase
your focus and concentration so that is
all I've got for this video obviously
this is not a comprehensive list of all
the writing apps out there so definitely
suggest other ones down in the comments
that we would find helpful also if you
watched any of my other videos to the
end you probably know that I wrote a
book about a year ago and if you would
like to know how I wrote that 27,000
word book within a period of 3 months I
have a podcast episode where I go over
some of what I learned and some of the
practices I used to get it done so click
the card right now if you'd like to tune
in that's all I've got for you guys
today so if you're using this video to
procrastinate on a big writing
assignment stop it and otherwise I will
see you guys in next week's video thanks
for
watching hey guys thanks so much for
watching this video on writing apps now
if you want to get new tips on being a
more respective student every single
week you can click that big red
subscribe button right there I also
wrote an entire book on how to earn
better grades and if you would like to
get a free copy of it you can cck a
picture of the book and I'll send you
one and if you would like to see the
list of all these apps with links to
each one go to the companion blog post
by clicking the orange logo right there
last week's video we talked about how to
overcome perfectionism so check it out
if you haven't seen it yet and if you
would like to connect with me I'm Tom
frankley on Instagram and Twitter or you
can leave a comment down below