this video is sponsored by skillshare
among his many other accomplishments
benjamin franklin was one of the most
well-respected writers of his time
but that wasn't always the case earlier
on his career at one point benjamin
franklin found himself in the midst of
an epistolary duel which basically just
means he was arguing with somebody
through letter writing and at one point
during this argument benjamin franklin's
father
found these letters and in typical dad
fashion took the opportunity to tell old
ben
just how bad his writing was now most of
us probably wouldn't want our dads
critiquing our writing we get a little
defensive
but benjamin franklin took this
criticism to heart and in response
he started seeking out the best writing
he could get his hands on so he could
deliberately study it
and start honing his writing craft and
through this process he became that
well-respected writer
and thinker now you might not have
become the most well-respected writer of
my generation
at the top of your to-do list but even
if that's not the case improving your
writing skills is one of the best things
you can do for moving forward in your
career and becoming a better
communicator
so today i want to share five huge tips
for improving
your writing whether it's a cover letter
or a novel we're going to talk about
ways to improve
how often you write building a writing
habit but we'll also talk about some
ways to improve the clarity of your
writing and also
how interesting it is let's actually
start there this interestingness
angle how do you make your own writing
more interesting and more fun to read
well this reminds me of a quote i once
heard somewhere or maybe i made it up
i'm not sure but it goes like this
an interesting person is an interested
person in other words if you want your
writing to have some flair to it
go out and apply your interest both to
cool experiences
but also to learning from a wide variety
of sources
and that's the first main tip here read
widely as the author of cormac mccarthy
once put it books
are made out of books and the best
authors are the ones who have a wide
repertoire of experiences
and knowledge and different authors
they've read to pull from so they can
take things
and creatively mash them up into
something you've never read before
if you only read one author or one genre
then your writing is gonna feel
kinda samey it's like trying to cook a
chicken with nothing but black pepper on
your spice rack
if you wanna make something truly
delicious and truly interesting to eat
then you may want to have some more
spices on that spice rack so
expand your reading palette and if you
want to do this in a way similar to how
ben franklin did it and also try to
actively engage with what you read
as well one good way to do this is when
you come across a phrase or passage that
you really like
pause ask yourself well how would i
write this
or how would another author that i
really like write this and then
asking yourself this question going
through this mental remixing exercise
you're engaging with the material in a
way that's much more
intense than if you just read it and
then passed on i'm also in the habit of
highlighting these passages and saving
them to my read-wise so i can come back
to them and ponder them sometimes
this is one that has been stuck in my
head particularly as of late
night city was like a deranged
experiment in social darwinism
designed by a board researcher who kept
one thumb permanently on the fast
forward button
so actively engaging with a wide array
of material is a great way to sort of
build an armory of different weapons you
can use for different challenges
different situations
but if you want to be able to use them
to wield them well then you need to
write often
build the skill of writing and as you
probably know
writing often is kind of hard to do i
see writing as kind of like riding a
bicycle it's all about building momentum
and that first
initial challenge of getting on the bike
is usually the hardest one
after that a lot of times you can coast
put a little bit of effort in and you
keep moving forward
so how do you build that initial bit of
momentum so one way you can do this is
to build for yourself a writing
ritual which is basically a set of
habits that make getting into the
writing process a little bit easier at
least get you over that resistance
and this can involve writing in a
specific place or having a list of
things that you do before you start
writing
personally when i was writing my book 10
steps to earning awesome grades which
i think i published about uh six years
ago now there was this
little office in the leasing office my
apartment building where you could go to
study it had wi-fi
it had totally blank walls and it had
this wooden desk going around the border
of the room
that was basically it so it wasn't a
very fun place to be
but it was a place where my video games
weren't there my friends weren't there
it was total solitude so i would go
there and i would put in my 500 words
per day which i
kind of used that goal to get this book
done and there was this sort of
motivation i would go in there and i
kind of wanted to leave so i would get
my 500 words done as quickly as possible
or at least i thought that because
interestingly enough
once you build the writing momentum in
the beginning of the session
you often now have those creative juices
flowing you're in a state of flow
and you will write more in many cases
than you thought you would so i went in
with the intention of doing 500 words
and came out having written 1500 or
sometimes 2
000. so having a specific writing place
even a place that's kind of
not all that pleasant can be helpful you
can also have certain habits in your
writing ritual as well
maybe having some noise cancelling
headphones that let you have some more
control over
the environment where you're writing
maybe having a specific playlist that
you'd like to write to i've got one
called sunday study that i almost always
use when i write and i'll have that
linked in description below if you want
to check it out
or maybe having a specific scent or a
specific drink like having a candle that
you write with
or making a cup of coffee or a cup of
tea whatever it is
find your writing ritual and use it to
get over that writing resistance
and we use the bike metaphor before and
i stand by the belief that starting is
the hardest part
but just like bike writing writing
writing
writing writing writing is about keeping
momentum going
when you're in a session you want to
keep the flow going so you can keep
creative things coming out of your brain
and onto the page and one of the biggest
killers of that momentum
is editing while you write so the next
big tip is to
separate your writing process from your
editing process
when you edit your writing when you see
a sentence that you just wrote and
you're like i gotta go back and change
that
i saw a spelling error i gotta go back
and fix that you're actually getting
into a different state of mind you're
doing a context switch
and you're now in a mind state that is
less creative you've arrested that
momentum
and if you're constantly editing what
you've just written then you really
never
get any good momentum going in the first
place another metaphor that i like to
use for writing is of
mining for gold if you never get down to
i don't know
20 feet deep under the ground you're
never gonna get the gold in the first
place
so you have to build enough momentum to
excavate a bunch of dirt a bunch of
not very useful stuff to get to the
point in a writing session where the
real
good gems come out you can come back and
edit them later
the other point of this is that you
often don't know what the end product is
going to look like
after you've gone through several
different iterations so it's kind of
pointless to try to do a first
draft that's perfect because it's always
going to change a great example this may
be my favorite comes from the
cinematic masterpiece that is emperor's
new groove if you don't know about the
troubled history of this movie when it
started out in development it was
supposed to be a much more serious story
kind of in the vein of the lion king
that kind of a feel
and what we ended up with was this buddy
comedy movie one of disney's best movies
ever
but very different than it initially had
been conceptualized
so just realize that what you start
writing right now is
probably not going to look anything like
your final product so just let yourself
get ideas onto the paper like i say
get a mess on the paper you can come
back later and clean that mess up
it's a lot easier than trying to craft
something perfect from a blank page
okay so let's talk about the edit
process now you've got your first draft
on the paper
or on the computer screen and now you
want to hone it and make it as good as
it can be
what's the first step to doing that well
i think a good first candidate
is reading your writing out loud like
i'm gonna do right now with the script
we tend to think of writing as a silent
art form but it has a lot more in common
with music than you might think
because we don't often think about this
fact we often overlook another very
important piece of good writing
rhythm for example you might use too
many sentences of similar lengths in a
row
for example you might keep using similar
phrases or you might elongate your
sentences
leaving the length a little too long
stringing too many clauses together
running on and
on and on you might also just use
phrases that have a lot of similarity
or you might have simply a word
simply simply forgotten a word see now
reading out loud can feel a bit awkward
especially if there's another person in
the room ask me i go through scripts all
the time with my editor in the room and
yes it is a little bit awkward but
if you don't do it you're liable to
gloss over things that could help make
the reading experience less awkward for
your reader
and that's really the most important
thing right reading out loud
not only exposes you to the rhythm of
your writing but it also slows you down
necessarily when we read silently when
we're reading for comprehension we read
between
200 to 400 words per minute on average
when we're scanning through our own
writing trying to find little things to
fix
we go even faster than that and the
faster you go
the easier it is to skip over things but
when we read out loud
most people can't read comfortably out
loud at more than 150 words per minute
and at that pace it's very easy to pick
out spelling errors
grammar issues or opportunities to
simplify
that's our last tip here there is this
great quote in the book on writing well
from the author william zinser that goes
the secret of good writing is to strip
every sentence to its cleanest
components i want to give you a great
example of this back in world war
ii president franklin d roosevelt's
aides put out this statement
and this is a mouthful so bear with me
here such preparations shall be made as
will completely obscure all federal
buildings and non-federal buildings
occupied by the federal government
during an air raid for any period of
time from visibility by reason of
internal or external illumination
president roosevelt took that and
changed it to this
town and buildings where they have to
keep the work going to put something
across the windows
he removed 20 words from the original
sentence and the ones that were
remaining got
way way simpler and in doing so he
communicated so much more
because the original blurb of text
actually communicated nothing to most
people
if you felt your brain kind of sliding
out of your ear when i read that first
blurb you're not alone it was a bunch of
jargon it was almost impossible to
understand
and sometimes your own writing takes on
a similar quality sometimes we're trying
to sound smart use big vocabulary
sometimes we don't even really consider
the simplicity and it gets a little bit
too complex
the simplicity doesn't necessarily mean
stripping things down to as few words as
possible because sometimes
words add color words add description
they make things more vivid and
interesting but a lot of times words are
there just because we want them to be
there we have a lot of i think trauma
from our teachers telling us word limits
that we had to hit for essays in high
school in elementary school right
and a lot of times we're trying to use
big words that make us sound a little
bit intelligent but from a reader's
perspective
they would almost always rather have you
use the word use
then utilize words then
lexicon because it's easier to parse
easier understand these big words don't
really add
anything to the reading experience if
you want to take your writing even
further there's a great class
on skillshare all about writing personal
essays from roxane gay who has written
for the new york times and has written
several published books of her own
fantastic class that'll help you hone
your writing skills and help you apply
them
to personal essays personal statements
for
job applications all kinds of stuff that
comes up in the daily life of even
non-writers and because her class is on
skillshare when you get access to it you
get access to thousands of other classes
and
writing is a hugely well represented
area on skillshare there are classes on
writing with humor there are classes on
writing fiction
there are a ton of classes that can hone
your skill set in this area so it's a
great way to
just as ben franklin once did start
deliberately practicing deliberately
studying also on skillshare you're going
to find a few classes from yours truly
i've got one on productivity for
creatives which has a whole section on
building that creative writing habit
which can also be applied to any other
creative work i've got classes on
building your productivity system
on building strong habits so it's also a
great place for becoming more
productive and skillshare is a very
affordable learning platform too with
your annual plans starting at less than
10 bucks a month and that's just their
normal pricing
actually right now if you're one of the
first 1 000 people to click the link in
the description down below and sign up
you can get 30 off that normal annual
price and this is even available to you
if you've already gone through a free
trial
so you can use that special pricing to
get back into skillshare and take any of
the classes you want from marketing
classes
to public speaking classes to classes on
digital illustration
and video editing so once again be one
of the first 1000 people to use that
link in the description down below and
sign up to get a full
30 off your annual premium subscription
doing that is also a great way to
support this channel so if you choose to
support my sponsors
seriously thank you so much and thank
you for watching this video all the way
to the end
seriously you are awesome got one last
thing here and that is to ask you a
simple question
what is your best writing tip that i
didn't mention in this video leave your
answer in the comments down below we can
all learn together become better writers
together
and i've got a playlist of videos here
with some more writing tips writing apps
i've recommended in the past
so check them out if you're curious
beyond that you can get subscribed if
you haven't done so already or
go and do literally whatever you want
because as always i'm not your dad