to use the technical term this video is
about how to get a buttload of work done
now the definition of a standard
buttload it has been in dispute for
years but regardless if you're watching
this video you probably feel like you
have that resting on your shoulders so
as somebody who went from being an
overly involved college student straight
into being an overly idea Laden content
creator entrepreneur whatever you want
to call me I feel like I always have a
lot of work resting on my shoulders and
I tend to get a lot of it done which
leads to the question I get emailed
often how do you get so much work done
well let's move back a little bit first
into this perception of how much work we
have to do when people ask us how we're
doing what's the answer we usually give
them that's right it's usually I'm just
so busy the word busy is just so
commonly uttered from our mouths and I
want to challenge you on this assumption
what is busy really mean now for all the
crap he gets Thomas Edison actually said
something pretty smart on this subject
and I'm going to read it off my phone
real quick because I didn't memorize it
being busy does not mean real work the
object of all work is production or
accomplishment and to either of these
ends there must be forethought system
planning intelligence honest purpose as
well as perspiration seeming to do is
not doing now that's something you
should really take to heart how much of
your time is seeming to do and how much
of it is actually spent doing and
getting real things accomplished
producing real work of real value for
the past few months it seems like I've
actually been able to produce a lot more
work than I used to in the past and if I
look through the archives on my blog it
seems like for a couple years I was only
putting out maybe five things a month at
most now I'm creating videos almost
every week I'm doing my podcast every
week blog posts episodes of listen money
matters another podcast I'm a part of
and I wrote a book in a few months which
just came out a couple of weeks ago so
how was I able to increase this output
and go from just being busy all the time
and feeling sorry for myself about how
much work I had on my shoulders to
actually getting things done well to be
honest I could attribute this to a lot
of factors motivation habits planning
time management task management
efficiency delegation hiring people
there's all sorts of things that go into
getting work done on top of the just the
simple discipline of sitting down
working and
I could devote videos to every single
one of these topics and many of them
will get videos in the future but the
topic I want to focus on in this video
is the act of planning specifically
daily planning what we want to get away
from here is this feeling of being busy
and not actually getting a whole lot
done not really focusing on any specific
tasks you have to do and you're probably
familiar with some of the common cases
where this happens you're in the library
you've got all your material out in
front of you but you don't really know
which thing you should study so now
you're on Facebook daily planning
alleviates this problem because if you
do it right you know exactly what you
should be doing at any given time for
instance my morning routine is a form of
a daily plan the moment I wake up in the
morning I know exactly what I need to do
I need to come to my apartment I need to
turn off my wake-up alarm that I talked
about in another video and then I need
to immediately meditate go into my
seven-minute workout go for a walk make
breakfast read books etc I know exactly
what I need to do and as a result I do
it so morning routines are incredibly
important but I want to talk about the
actual daily plan that encompasses your
specific tasks that you need to get done
whenever I get a new task that needs to
be done at some point in time it goes
straight into todoist
and to do is is the to-do app of choice
that I use there are a lot others out
there but it's the first point of
contact for any task I have it is not
the only place where tasks end up living
in my system on Sundays I create a
weekly plan in a paper notebook really
simple and write down exactly what I
want to accomplish that week then when I
wake up in the morning and go through my
morning routine I have a habit which is
to simply create a daily plan so on that
whiteboard right over there I write my
daily plan every single morning and I
put the day of the week at the top and
then I write down the six to seven maybe
eight if I'm feeling really productive
that day things that I need to get done
and I don't stop there though I try to
estimate when each task should be done
by so I'll put a dash and then I'll put
the time when I'm estimating these times
I try to take into account a fudge ratio
and this is a concept I wrote about in
my book and basically it's taking the
time I estimate to get things done and
applying a little bit of a buffer to it
because we are very bad at planning for
things that go wrong we're very bad at
planning for inefficiencies and we tend
to take the best best case scenario as a
guess for
me SME times so now that I have this
daily plan I have a list of tasks in the
order that I need to do them I have an
estimate for the time that each one
should be done and now I know at any
given time what I should be doing once
I'm done with my morning routine I jump
right into the first one and try as best
as I can
to get it done by the time I estimated
seeing it right on the board next to me
reminds me that that's what I should be
working on I don't let myself get
distracted by other things now that's
not to say that I'm absolutely perfect
about getting the list done every day
but combined with other productivity
techniques that I applied in my life
like habit tracking and commitment
devices and the Pomodoro Technique and
things like that it's actually really
effective and my output has gone from
here to here I'm not exactly sure what
those are but there's a gap so the
lesson is clear here if you want to get
a lot of things done you need to plan
your day out in advance and then stick
to that plan doing so will let you know
what to focus on on any given moment and
you'll spend a lot less time feeling
busy but not getting much work done so
thanks for watching this video and I
will see you in the next one
well hello there and thanks for watching
my video on getting massive loads of
work done with daily plans now if you
want to learn more about effective
planning I wrote an entire chapter about
it in my free book on earning awesome
grades and you can get your own copy by
clicking the picture of the book right
there you want to get more videos every
single week on being an awesome college
student studying better building habits
and what not then click that big red
subscribe button and you can also find a
summary and links to anything I talked
about in this video by going to the
companion blog post which you can find
by clicking the orange button right
there if you missed my last video
there's a clip of it playing right there
and lastly if you want to suggest topics
for new videos or connect with me you
can either follow me on twitter
@tomfrankly or just leave a comment on
this video see you in the next one