thanks to trade coffee for sponsoring
this video and supporting my channel
in a couple of my recent videos i've
mentioned that i spend time every single
morning reading
and recently i've gotten back into the
habit of taking detailed notes when what
i'm reading
is non-fictional now i found that this
is a habit that is tough to stay in
and easy to fall out of because taking
detailed notes on what you read requires
effort and self-discipline especially
given the fact that i no longer have any
exams or professors forcing me
to do so it's just something that i want
to do but that being said
taking notes on what i read is an
incredibly useful habit
to be in so today i want to share how i
take notes from nonfiction books i'm
going to give you the details of my
system
talk a little bit about how i decide
what to record versus what not to record
and hopefully give you some ideas about
how you can take notes on the books
that you read whether they're assigned
in class or just books
that interest you and my system breaks
down into a four-step
process read highlight record
and synthesize so we're going to start
off with the reading part
now since this is a video on note-taking
you might think we could just skip past
this part and go straight to
highlighting
but you know what they say garbage in
garbage out
and in this case i'm not talking about
garbage books per se
but rather about garbage comprehension
because if i'm reading in a way that
doesn't promote good comprehension i'm
not going to be able to take good notes
so this part of the process
is just as important as the note-taking
process
when i read i'm trying to promote the
best possible comprehension so
i read in the morning which is what i
found to be the best time of the day for
me to engage with the material and stay
focused
and if i need to i will move around my
office if i'm sitting in my chair and
it's
a little bit too relaxing i'm getting a
little bit too daydreamy
i will sometimes pace around the office
while holding the book and still reading
it or sometimes i'll sit on the floor
just to get into a different
position all right step two in the
process is to highlight which i actually
do simultaneously while
i read i keep a pen with me which i use
to star areas in the margins that i want
to draw my eye to later on
when i'm actually taking my notes and
yes i actually do
write in the margins of my book and i
will also underline key terms
so i can further draw my eye to exactly
what the idea
was now if you don't want to write in
the margins number one you could just
get ebooks because the kindle app and
the ibooks app and basically every
uh electronic app out there will let you
create little highlights
personally i like to write in physical
books better and then there are also
these little
book flags so these things can
non-destructively allow you to mark
places in a book and there are many
different colors so you can use one
for say quotes one for just interesting
things
and on that note i actually have a
system of symbols that i use so i use
stars for general highlights that i want
to draw my eye to later on
and then i use ex for examples so in a
book if there's an example that is
backing up a main point
that i want to remember i'll mark that
with an ex i use the letter
f for further reading so if a book is
mentioning
say another author or a book that they
draw inspiration from or maybe just a
paper
i'll put an f there so i can remember to
follow up and maybe check that out later
on
q is for quotes now when i go and i
write my notes i generally try to put
the notes in my own words as much as i
possibly can
but sometimes there's a great quote and
i want to remember it exactly as it was
stated so i'll use a q for that i'll use
question marks if there's a passage in a
book that i disagree with or that
confuses me
that will allow me to dig in and maybe
try to verify a claim see if i was wrong
or if the author was wrong
and finally sometimes i will write
actual notes in the margin of the book
these will not be lengthy but
occasionally i really want to get
something out of my head that relates to
a specific area
on a page so i'll just write a little
margin note that kind of primes me to
elaborate on that point a bit more when
i'm doing the actual recording
and that happens in the recording stage
which is the third step
of the process so once i'm done reading
and highlighting a chapter i will sit
down on my desk i'll go back through the
chapter and i'll
use my highlights and my margin symbols
to guide my eye to what i want to take
notes on and i take notes in an app
called rome research
putting them in an outline style now
what i like about rome and i made a
video about this tool very recently
is that i can very easily make links to
any other page i have
just by putting brackets around a term
or by using a hashtag to use
a tag they're kind of the exact same in
rome so if i have say a queue somewhere
i know that's a quote i will put that
quote in my notes and i'll give it the
quotes tag so i can easily look up
quotes
later on or if there is something that
refers back to a page that i've already
taken notes on
say caffeine i can easily put brackets
around the word caffeine
and link to my caffeine page and over
time this creates this interconnected
web of knowledge that
kind of represents the way that
knowledge is organized in the brain i do
have to note that right now
rome research is enclosed beta with a
wait list and there are details about
that that i can put in the description
down below
not going to fill up too much time with
them but the gist here is that
other than that linking system you can
recreate these outline style notes in
basically any other
note-taking app the main idea is i'm
writing down
what i highlighted so i'm interacting
with the material one more time
and step four here i'm synthesizing it
so this is the last step in the process
where i'm trying to find a way
to connect the information i've just
learned and recorded to what i already
know
or otherwise finding a way to utilize it
to wrangle with it
to kind of retrieve it have to work with
it so one thing that i will do
is i'll write my own thoughts in my
notes in italics
if there's a point that i have a little
bit of my own input on
i will put that right in the notes right
under my recording of the point and this
helps me to
connect my own ideas and things i
already know from other sources
to what i've just read i'm building more
pathways to it
and i'm more likely to remember it long
term and if you want to see an example
of how i take these notes and how i go
about this process of synthesizing what
i've learned and connecting it to my own
thoughts and opinions
i just recently finished reading the
book hyperfocus by my friend chris
bailey
very good book and i took very detailed
notes on this book which i have posted
on my website and i'll have that linked
in the description down
below one last thing that i would like
to note here is that this entire
note-taking process
especially the part where i'm adding in
my own thoughts and opinions
and using the little question mark
symbol to mark spots where i have a
disagreement
is kind of an embodiment of my absolute
favorite quote
by bruce lee which goes like this adapt
what is useful
reject what is useless and add what is
specifically
your own that is exactly how i try to go
about the learning process and how i
think you should
as well now if you'll excuse me i've got
some more reading to go do
which also means that it's time to brew
a fresh cup of coffee
and luckily i've got some brand new
beans to try thanks to trade coffee
with trade coffee you get to discover
new roasts from some of the nation's
best roasters instead of just buying the
same old beans from the store every time
or just randomly guessing whenever you
want to try something new and for me
making coffee is one of my favorite
parts of the day but when it comes to my
knowledge of coffee i would say that i
know enough to be dangerous
i know a little bit about the different
roast types and i at least grind my own
beans at home
but it still seems that whenever i want
to try something new and i grab
something random off the shelf
half the time it ends up being something
that i don't really like
that's why trade's coffee quiz is great
when you sign up it asks you a few
simple questions about your tastes and
then it builds a taste profile for you
so that the rotation of coffee roasts
they conveniently deliver to your door
is always something you're going to like
you can even rate each bag to improve
what you'll get in the future
this b-roll setup was a lot of work all
right time for a taste test
okay yeah that's good so if you want to
try some great new coffee and support my
channel then give trade a try using the
link in the description
down below and if you're one of the
first 100 people to use that link you're
even gonna get 30
off your first back just take the quiz
and that promotion will be automatically
applied
plus you're even gonna get free shipping
all right guys that is it so hopefully
you enjoyed the video and thank you so
much for watching if you did enjoy this
video hit that like button to show the
youtube algorithm what's up you can also
get subscribed
right there it's kind of hard to talk
when i'm bending over and basically
breaking my spine right now
but look how much effort i'm putting in
for you uh there's also more videos on
this channel so check them out
right here or here as always smashing
your face through the phone screen is
more effective
than using your fingers or thumbs so do
that or don't because as always
i'm not your dad