one of my favorite parts of my morning
routine is the time I spend reading
every single morning I sit down in this
office chair I grab a book and I read
accompanied by a few essential tools a
cup of freshly brewed coffee a pen for
marking at my book so I can take notes
on what I read later and perhaps most
importantly this little green notebook
that sits near my feet this is my
distraction journal whenever something
pops into my head and pulls my attention
away from what I'm reading
I simply jot down a note about it in
this journal so my brain can safely
dismiss it without being worried about
forgetting it
but there's something odd about my
distraction journal in between the pages
of little notes about distractions you
know buying a deck umbrella or checking
with my team about something there are
pages upon pages of notes about my most
creative and most significant work in
fact my most recent entry in this
distraction journal has nearly 6 pages
about a video that I'm working on nearly
outlining the entire thing so this is a
distraction journal this is meant for
jotting down quipped little notes and
then getting back to what I was doing
and yet I find myself using it to do
real serious significant work even when
I don't intend to meanwhile half the
time I sit down at a computer with the
intent to do some quote/unquote serious
work I find myself staring at a blinking
cursor I'm kind of like if you've seen
the movie limitless I'm kind of like
Bradley Cooper's character Eddie Mora
you know I put in the time I stay in the
room and yet nothing now unlike Eddie my
solution to this problem is not taking a
small translucent drug though what we're
talking about limitless I do have to
just take a second to admire the way
that filmmakers use the change in color
rating to illustrate the change in his
mental state after taking NZT that from
a filmmaking perspective is just it is
it's great but I digress my solution
here is not a drug it's an idea creative
work or difficult challenging work is
kind of like a non-newtonian fluid now
if you've never heard this term before
you've probably at least seen one of
these substances in the past a
non-newtonian fluid acts just like a
normal fluid most the time but when it's
struck really quickly its structure its
molecules become very rigid and the
entire substance acts
like a solid so imagine if you had an
entire bucket of the stuff and you
wanted to submerge your hand into it
well you could do it very easily if you
did it slowly if you eased your hand in
maybe started with the fingertips first
but if you punched it if you just slam
your hand into it very quickly the
substance is going to tense up and it's
gonna be basically like punching a wall
it's not going to work and this is
exactly how I think of creative work as
well when you make these giant sweeping
statements like Eddie Morra and
limitless today's the day I'm gonna
write the entire book today you slam
into the brick wall the task you've set
for yourself is so big so intimidating
that you just can't get into it but he's
into it and you sometimes find yourself
immersed in what psychologists call the
flow state a place where you're
completely focused on your work in the
state the act of creation is
all-encompassing it's fun and you
sometimes find yourself losing track of
time until you come out of it now
getting into the flow state is not
always easy but it does seem like you
can do it more consistently when you
ease into your work it's almost like
you're tricking your brain into doing it
so for the rest of this video I want to
share three ideas you can use to trick
your brain into getting into the flow
state and the first one is very simple
start incredibly small don't make these
grand sweeping gestures that just make
your work very intimidating and the
example I want to give here is actually
about the book that I wrote a few years
ago so if you know anything about my
work you know that I've written a book
called 10 steps to earning awesome
grades this book was actually not my
first attempt to write a book it was my
second my first attempt was a complete
and utter failure again because I just
intimidated myself and I never got
started and I made what I thought was a
very big grand gesture that would force
me to write the book I literally bought
a ticket to a conference down in Texas
and flew down there the conference is
called finish up weekend and the entire
point of that event was to get a bunch
of creatives a bunch of entrepreneurs
into a room and have everyone pick one
task and work as hard as possible for
like 54 straight hours to get it done
so I showed up with the intent to write
an entire book thinking that being
surrounded by all these people and
having a grand intention would make me
get the book done but instead I came out
of that event with
thing to show for it I remember staring
at my word processor on my laptop just
unable to write anything that I was
happy with so for this book I took a
completely different approach number one
this was not even intended to be a book
when I started this was gonna be like a
five thousand word max PDF like a bonus
download for people who join my email
list over my website and my approach to
writing that PDF was to first create a
big outline in Evernote that had ten
different sections at a bunch of little
sub bullets beneath them and then with
my habit tracking app I set a goal of
writing 500 words per day so every
single day I would pick one of those sub
bullets from that outline and sit down
to write 500 words and because that goal
was so small on a daily basis just write
500 words about one tiny little topic
from my outline I wrote consistently so
consistently in fact that my five
thousand word PDF eventually ballooned
into a twenty seven thousand word book
which is now in print and an audio book
so again if you can start small that
will help you to put an effort
consistently and over time those small
little efforts will add up and you'll
get something that is just as grand as
you intended in the first place
alright tactic number two is to assume
that you are creating garbage or at
least allow yourself to create garbage
and this is another thing that really
helped the process of writing this book
when I sat down to write my 500 words
per day that was my only goal just write
500 words they didn't have to be 500
beautifully edited words they didn't
have to all make it into the book I just
had to hit 500 words and on some days I
really did not feel like writing so I
would spend you know the first two or
three hundred words of that writing
session writing about how I really
didn't want to be there and I really
didn't want to be doing that but
eventually I would build some momentum
and I would usually get you know at
least one or two usable paragraphs out
of that writing session
finally tactic number three jot things
down in non-ideal places do work in
places that don't feel like they're made
for work and this brings us back to the
distraction journal this thing is not
meant for intense writing I don't you
this or at least I don't intend to use
this to outline fold videos and I
definitely don't intend to outline fold
videos while I'm sitting in my reading
chair trying to get some reading done in
the morning I also don't intend to
outline full videos as I'm coming out of
the shower or when I'm taking a voice
note in the car
but nonetheless full videos get outlined
in all those places sometimes and again
it's because I'm in a non-ideal place
I'm in the least intimidating place in
the world and I think that the
environment the setup can be just as
intimidating as the tasks you set for
yourself and can be just as paralyzing
so do things like keeping sticky note
pads around the house or keep a
note-taking app on your phone you don't
consider to be the final place where
your writing is going to live or if
you're not a writer for whatever task
you often find yourself paralyzed on
find a non-ideal way to do it in just
little tiny bursts and you're sometimes
gonna find yourself working more than
you intended because you've slipped into
the flow State so in summary number one
start incredibly small number two allow
yourself to create work that might be
garbage because some of it is not going
to be and finally number three do work
and non-ideal places keep sticky notes
around keep voice recorders around
whatever you have to do don't always
force yourself to do work in the place
you have designated for work because
sometimes that place is a bit
intimidating and if you want an example
that isn't writing another thing that I
find quite intimidating is music
production especially as somebody who
spent a long time working with audio for
my videos for my podcasts I know
probably too much about music production
for my own good so when I think about
the process of writing and producing a
song I'm already thinking about
automating reverb parameters and adding
in tons of different additional tracks
and it can get intimidating and caused
me to never start so the music I've
actually produced has almost universally
started as me just messing around on my
guitar or messing around on my piano
getting something that I liked and then
gradually adding layer upon layer just
sort of playing around until I get
something that actually sounds pretty
good and if you would like an example of
that I recently put on a track called
icicle swords over on my music youtube
channel so I'll link that down
scription below and you can take a
listen if you are curious and maybe
subscribe to that channel if you want to
see new tracks in the future also if you
want to see additional music stuff and
some more bonus videos related to the
kind of content I do in this channel you
may also want to follow me on Instagram
over at Tom frankly beyond that if you
enjoyed this video hit that like button
to show the YouTube algorithm what's up
get subscribed right there or check out
one more video on this channel right
over here
or of course don't do any of that and go
do whatever it is that you want to do
because as always I'm not your dad