good habits are foundational to
achieving your goals however what they
aren't is easy to build and getting them
to stick around is even harder which is
why so many people eagerly start trying
to read more books eat better go to the
gym only to inevitably find themselves
going back to the warm familiarity of
Netflix Cheetos and the 68 calories per
hour they burn while sitting just days
later of course most of these people
make things even harder on themselves
because they don't go about building
their habits in a smart way so what
we're going to do today is go over four
common habit building mistakes that
people often make and what you can do to
avoid them and we're going to start with
what is possibly the most common habit
building mistake which is jumping into
the deep end right away this could
involve taking on too many habits at
once or attempting to build a really
difficult habit instead of starting
small a lot of people think that to be
successful they have to jump immediately
into very difficult habit if they want
to read more books they have to start
reading 50 pages a day or if they want
to get good at piano they have to start
practicing for 2 hours every single day
but all progress is made in small steps
even Neil Armstrong's first step onto
the moon was a small one the giant step
for mankind that he referenced was a nod
to the years of incremental progress in
small refinements made not only by the
astronauts themselves but by the
thousands of Engineers scientists and
technicians that supported them as well
they knew that to do something great it
would take years of incremental progress
and that progress is only possible if
the objective at each stage is something
that is slightly Out Of Reach but that's
still doable another group of people who
know this very well are game designers
they can can throw all sorts of
interesting elements into their games
but most people will get overwhelmed and
stop playing if everything is thrown to
them all at once and that's why smart
designers build in steady progressions
take a game like holl night for example
eventually hours into the campaign
you'll be dashing and double jumping and
using all sorts of powers to take on
multiple enemies at once but in the
beginning all you can really do is jump
and swing your sword at a beetle so take
a queue from the astronauts and game
designers start small and then build
what the author Nick winter would call a
success spiral make your initial habits
it's easy practice piano for just 15
minutes read 10 pages of a book get up a
half an hour earlier than you normally
do and as you prove to yourself over
time that you can handle your habits
then slowly spiral up move that 15minute
practice goal to 30 minutes or start
getting up a little bit earlier than you
were before or maybe even add new habits
to your plate but in the beginning start
small don't jump into the deep end right
away that brings us to mistake number
two which is assuming that there is no
chimp a few years ago I ran across this
really cool band called chimps banner
and if you're into really technical
instrumental metal I would definitely
recommend checking them out because I
really like their music their name
though always confused me I had
absolutely no idea what chimp spanner
meant that is until a couple of years
ago when my friend Simon who is from the
UK used the word spanner to refer to a
wrench and that's what it hit me chimp
spanner equals monkey wrench and that
also helped me to understand the old
saying throw a spanner in the works now
this is just an interesting tidbit about
the differences between UK and us slang
and phrases but here's the point there
is always a proverbial chimp waiting to
throw a spanner into your habit building
work and the big mistake that people
make when building new habits is
assuming the chimp doesn't exist they
assume that everything will go well all
the time and that nothing unexpected
will pop up to derail them which of
course means that they're not ready when
something inevitably does so realize
that the chimp is always there ready to
throw a spanner into the works or to put
it the way Charles doig would in his
book The Power of Habit anticipate in
reflection points points at which you're
likely to run into pain or discomfort or
some inconvenience that's likely to
derail you and then plan for those
points in advance now for some of these
points the only real plan you can make
is to simply be ready for the discomfort
before it comes for example in the book
doig reports on a study that focused on
people who had gotten knee and hip
replacement surgeries now to fully
recover from a surgery like this
patients have to start exercising and
moving almost immediately afterwards and
a lot of people never do fully recover
because they can't bring themselves to
accept the pain involved so what the
researchers in the study had people do
was very simple they gave them a piece
of paper and they had them write down
goals and action steps for what they
were going to do to get that exercise in
these were often very simple like one
man's plan to simply walk to the bus and
meet his wife after work but in writing
them down these people were anticipating
moments of pain and planning on how to
deal with them and the results of the
study speak for themselves the people
who did this started walking twice as
fast as the average patient now it is
worth noting that not all inflection
points have to be faced head-on like
this because many of them can be avoided
through good planning and I'll give you
one simple example every single morning
when I wake up I make myself a smoothie
and I could easily be derailed from this
habit if I ran out of crucial
ingredients like the milk that I use so
I make sure that that never happens by
following the rule that I learned from
cgp Gray's podcast cortex two is one and
one is none I always have a backup that
way running out of the first one will
not derail me mistake number three is
choosing not to sit Beneath The Sword in
ancient Greek history there is the story
of The Sword of Damocles in which a
cordier Damocles is given all the power
and luxury of a king for one day but in
addition to all of this there was also a
giant sword placed above his throne
hanging from a single horse's hair and
for Damocles the threat of this sword
dropping was enough for him to give up
all those luxuries all the riches all
the power back to the real King in the
story The Sword is a metaphor for the
precariousness of having power one false
move could set tragic events into action
and because of this I always think the
sword when I'm building new habits
because I like to set up my own sword
when doing so in other words I set up
consequences for failure and most people
choose not to do this they choose not to
sit beneath that metaphorical sword and
with no consequences looming above them
they often lack the self-discipline
required to stick with their chosen
habits for the long term so how do you
sit under the sword well for me the best
way of doing this is to use what are
called commitment devices external
systems that are set up to track my
progress but also to ensure that there
will be some kind of consequences if I
fail to stick to my habits the simplest
example of this which doesn't require
any kind of app or special tool is to
make a bet with a friend who cares about
you for example a few years ago I made a
bet with my friend Martin that I would
read 25 pages of non-fiction every
single day for 3 months if I skipped
even one day I would pay him $100 and to
keep myself accountable I gave him a
link to a spreadsheet where I tracked my
progress which showed that I indeed
never skipped a day if you do want to
use a special tool for this though there
are sites like be- minder and stick both
of which essentially act like that
friend and will charge you money if you
fail to stick to your goals and there
are also habit trackers like strides
habit Hub and habitica all these let you
track your habit building progress and
build streaks over time and the main
consequence that they bring to the table
is the threat that those streaks will be
broken though habitica in particular
uses game Design Elements as well so
you've got experience and health and
multiplayer quests and your character
can lose health or even die if you slack
off whatever you choose to use I highly
recommend that you find at least some
way to hang that metaphorical Sword of
Damocles over your head head at least
until you know the Habit you're trying
to build is fully ingrained that brings
us to mistake number four which is
trying to build a habit without a strong
personally meaningful reason for doing
so as the author Simon synic would put
it you need to start with why don't try
to adopt a habit just because someone
you follow does it or because you saw it
on your favorite YouTuber's morning
routine video now that doesn't mean the
Smoothie from that video isn't something
you should put into your own morning
routine but before doing so you should
ask yourself if it's actually going to
move you towards things that matter to
you as the author James Clear rightly
points out in his excellent book Atomic
habits good habits can make rational
sense but if they conflict with your
identity you'll fail to put them into
action and you have to keep this in mind
because it could be so easy to get
caught up in emulation for the wrong
reasons take reading for example you see
all these successful people on the
internet reading tons of books every
single week so you think that you have
to as well but what other thing that you
want to learn right now would be better
learned in another way reading a book
isn't the only way to learn something
sometimes you learn better by just
messing around the tinkering or by going
to a class or taking a course or by
going down a Long messy Google Rabbit
Hole now you can't really track your
messy Google rabbit holes on good reads
you can't really put them up on your
shelf in your garage next to your
Lamborghini you know what I like more
than
Lamborghinis anime it's hard to brag
about them but that doesn't make them
useless and depending on what you're
trying to do that method of learning
might be more useful than reading a book
and if that's the case you should
probably dial back your reading goal to
make room for it for example one of my
biggest interests right now is learning
to produce music now there are a ton of
music production books out there but
right now I'm just trying to figure out
how to use logic on my computer and I
found that the most effective way to do
that is to simply try to do things in
logic and then to go find a tutorial or
a video or a forum post when I get stuck
at the moment doing that is far more
useful than simply going through a book
so to Briefly summarize first start
small and build success spirals don't
try to take on too much at once two
acknowledge the existence of the chimp
and anticipate those inflection points
figure out if if you can avoid them if
possible and if not mentally prepare for
the discomfort that they will bring
three sit beneath the sword integrate
accountability and consequences into
your habit building efforts and finally
number four start with why make sure
that you have a strong personally
meaningful reason for each habit that
you choose to build one thing that is
incredibly meaningful to me is music
which is why earlier in the video I
talked about how I'm learning music
production and in fact the background
music you're hearing right now is
actually something that I produced and
played myself and to touch on that
playing as aspect for a second one thing
that has become abundantly clear to me
in the past couple of years is that your
ability to play an instrument is
determined less by how many years you've
been playing then on how consistent you
are with putting in hours of deliberate
practice I mean I got my first guitar at
13 years old but it's only in the last
couple of years that I've gotten really
serious about practicing it on a regular
basis so if you want to learn how to
play an instrument as well then use the
Habit building techniques from this
video to make practicing into a strong
habit and while you're at it you should
also seek out the best learning
resources that you can find one of which
is f play if you want to learn how to
play the guitar Fender play is a great
place to start not only can you use it
to learn tons of songs for guitar bass
and even ukulele but the app also
includes thousands of video lessons tabs
and something that I really appreciate
myself a comprehensive chord database
complete with videos on how to play them
properly additionally there's a section
called my path that you can use to go
through a logical progression of skills
and songs which means that you'll never
sit down and not know what to play and
that playing can happen anywhere as
you'll find Fender play in your browser
as well as on the iPhone iPad and
Android devices so if you want to start
learning and playing then head to the
link in the description down below to
get started with a 14-day free trial and
if you decide to go with your annual
plan you're also going to get 10% off of
Fender guitars amps and gear I want to
give a huge thanks to fender for
sponsoring this video and working with
me seriously I have been playing Fender
guitar since my dad let me borrow his
40-year-old acoustic back when I was a
teenager so to say I'm excited about
this sponsorship is a bit of an
understatement so seriously thanks
Defender for that and as always thank
you guys for watching as well if you got
something useful out of this video
definitely consider hitting that like
button you can also subscribe right
there to get new videos when they come
out and also click right there to get a
free copy of my book on how to earn
better grades lastly you can check out
one more video on this channel right
around here or you can click it right
over here to hear some of my other
guitar work thanks again for watching
and I will see you guys as always in the
next video