this video is sponsored by ocean which
is now completely free for personal use
check it out at the link in the
description down below
in 1997 history was made in the world
chess when IBM's deep blue supercomputer
finally beat world champion chess player
Garry Kasparov for the first time this
moment has often been cited as the death
knell or the superiority of human
intelligence and the rise machines but
if you look at the highest levels of
play in the world of chess now they
aren't dominated solely by computers
instead as it's detailed and David
Epstein's book range which I highly
recommend by the way there's a form of
chess called advanced chess or sometimes
freestyle chests where teams of humans
and computers pool their collective
resources to play at a higher level than
the computers can achieve on their own
these teams are called centaur teams and
in a tournament that was described in
the book a team consisting of two people
who were both not grandmasters and three
normal chess computers beat Hydra which
at the time was the top chess playing
supercomputer these sent our teams are
essentially the result of the admission
that both our human minds and the
computers that we use have their
weaknesses and that when you develop a
symbiotic relationship where both bring
their strengths to the table and play
off each other you get the best possible
combination on one hand the computers
are able to memorize and store millions
of possible board states and analyze
nearly every move that a player can make
given one of those board states but on
the other hand humans have a unique
ability to think creatively to think
outside of the box and to make
unorthodox strategies using the tactics
provided by these computers and this
combination this realization that man
and machine or rather we and our tools
work best in tandem is key to learning
how to think strategically which itself
is one part of being overall a
productive
effective person in the past I talked
about the idea that you have a planning
mode and a robot mode where the robot
mode executes on the plans laid by the
planning mode and if you want to be
productive with your robot mode you have
to learn how to work faster how to stay
focused for longer how to be more
efficient with your moves but just as
important is the effectiveness of the
planning mode the plans you make the
strategies you set into motion need to
be effective at moving you towards your
goals and I want to talk about one
specific aspect of strategic thinking in
this video which is the act of looking
ahead of being a forward thinker if you
can anticipate what's going to happen in
the future and either position yourself
to take advantage of that or position
yourself to sidestep as many of the
consequences that say a negative event
will bring then you overall become more
effective and one specific technique
that is often used in strategic planning
in forward thinking is called the
what-if analysis and this is what I'm
hoping you'll be able to use in your own
life after you watch this video
essentially a what-if analysis is a
mechanism for asking the question what
if what if I did this what if I did that
but if I took one certain specific type
of action what would happen a what-if
analysis asks this question and then
uses the available data to get the most
accurate potential answer possible now
these what-if analyses can be incredibly
complex going all the way up to the
Monte Carlo simulations that are run and
data science companies and a huge
businesses where they will run hundreds
of thousands even millions of different
simulated scenarios to get an answer
that is as close to the truth as they
and there can also be a lot simpler and
a lot more applicable to your own life I
want to give you a couple examples so my
favorite example here comes from back
when I was in college I had a roommate
who was in Computer Engineering for two
years and after a couple years it got to
the point where he was realizing he
really didn't want to be in that major
he wanted a switch but he was scared to
do it because he was afraid that
switching majors
would put him far behind where he was he
was kind of giving in to that sunk cost
fallacy feeling like all this effort he
already put in was going to be worthless
if he switched his major well as it
turns out our university has this tool
called a degree audit report where you
can essentially see how far you are
along in your chosen major in your
chosen degree with all the classes
you've taken so far but our university
had what was called a what-if degree
audit tool as well where you can choose
any major they offered and see where you
would be if you were to switch to that
major and the funny thing is when he ran
a what-if degree audit for the major he
wanted to switch to turns out he was
actually further into that major than
into his own major so by switching he
put himself ahead a little bit but he
was only able to do that because he was
able to use data to ask a question and
get an accurate answer but running a
what-if analysis for another example
let's ask some questions about your
money such as how much house could you
afford right now what price of house
would you be able to buy right now or
what could you do with your money if you
got a raise what would you do with your
money if you lost your job or had to
take a pay cut right now these questions
can bring a lot of anxiety especially
when you don't feel like you have the
ability to get the answer so what if you
had a tool where you could input your
income input your expenses and then see
exactly how much money was left over at
the end of the month after it goes
through some calculations well this is
what I actually do every single month I
have built this kind of a tool for
myself so I can input those numbers and
then I can run these what-if scenarios
what if I made more money what if I
maybe wanted to hire somebody else could
I afford to hire that person or what
I be in the red at the end of the month
when I looked at my left over column for
housing I've actually built myself a
housing calculator where I can put in a
purchase price and I can see what my
estimated monthly cost of ownership
would be I can then compare that against
my rent I can put that into the expenses
column and I can see is there money left
over at the end of the month given that
purchase price or do I need to save up a
bit more do I need to make more money
asking these questions and then in
putting numbers into this budget model
or spreadsheet that I have built
represents that combination between the
strengths of our tools and the strengths
of our own minds I'm able to run this
what-if scenario and get a fairly
accurate picture because the spreadsheet
has the ability to be insanely
detail-oriented it can hold all these
numbers at once it can perform all these
calculations but I am able to make the
strategic plans to think big picture and
combining this tool and this tool I'm
able to make better decisions
so hopefully this overview has given you
at least one tool for making more
strategic decisions in your future and
with regards to the specific budget
modeler this seriously does help me make
really really good decisions with my
money it helps me sidestep potential
problems I can get myself into in the
future so I'm gonna have a template in
version linked in the description down
below you can make a copy of it you can
input your own numbers make whatever
changes you want to it and hopefully you
find it as helpful as I do of course
running a business requires a lot more
than just simple budget planning which
is why I use a lot of other tools as
well ranging from analytics platforms to
specialized research tools but the place
where I do the majority of my planning
is notion for just one example I have
this database where I plan all the
videos podcasts and other content that
we produce and this lets us know when
things are going live what stage they're
at and lots of other really useful
information and because it's built on
notions really powerful templating
system every time I generate a new video
project it automatically gives me a
place to write my script which lets me
easily add formatting and comments from
an editor along with automatic
checklists for every stage of the video
production process and the view
cool things so if you're looking for a
way to manage your work more effectively
you should give notion to try to
especially if you're working on a team
and that's because notion has powerful
collaboration features that let you work
on documents together in real-time share
files and even create wiki's that keep
everyone on the same page and let you
document complex processes in fact
that's one of my main use cases
I am methodically building this wiki for
my company the documents processes and
shows everyone how to do things step by
step but the best part is that notions
personal plan is now completely free no
trial no block limits if you're using it
on your own it is now 100% free and if
you want to bring in a team you could
always upgrade to their team plan at any
time so click the link in the
description down below and give notion a
try and as always thank you so much for
watching if you enjoyed this video hit
that like button to shoot the YouTube
algorithm what's up and if you haven't
subscribed to this channel yet you may
want to do so by clicking right there
or smashing your face into your phone
screen if you are watching this on your
phone another good place to smash your
face would be over here where you can
find a couple of other videos that you
can check out if you still have some
time watching videos and you're not on
YouTube distracting yourself
procrastinating but of course if you
want to do that go ahead and do that
because as always I'm not your dad