hey what is up guys and welcome to the
final video in our procrastination mini
series over the course the past couple
of videos we have dug into the science
behind procrastination talked about what
you can do step by step to stop
procrastinating when you find yourself
doing it in the moment and that leaves
us with one final question which is if
you are a chronic procrastinator if you
find yourself putting things off again
and again how do you stop that process
how do you stop that cycle and this was
really the question that led me to do
this series in the first place because
as I alluded to in the previous video I
have been a chronic procrastinator for
quite some time in fact every video I
have put out on this YouTube channel
over the past three or four years has
always been done kind of last minute
and this honestly goes back even further
than my YouTube career goes back into
high school and middle school I was the
kid who would come to school at 6 a.m.
the day homework was due and I would do
it in the cafeteria before school
started and I was always proud of this
and I think that sort of built the
foundation for my chronic
procrastination later in life so I went
I dug into the reasons for my own
procrastination and I ended up finding
some common themes that I think a lot of
you are going to identify with which is
gonna form kind of the meat of most of
this video and then we gonna get into
one final tip that I think everyone
needs to implement no matter what the
specific causes are that they're dealing
with but the first thing that I want to
mention here is that I think
self-awareness is a hugely important
aspect in becoming less of a
procrastinator because everyone has
particular reasons for why they tend to
put things off yes in the science video
we talked about some of the most common
causes and I think those are going to be
kind of universal across the board but
everyone has their own specific demons
everyone has something that causes them
to put things off and that's gonna
affect them more than it might affect
someone else so before I dig into my
reasons for procrastination which I do
think a lot of you are going to identify
with I just want to put this out there
observe your own behavior
observe the decisions you make and why
you make them both emotional short term
decisions but also long term decisions
as well once you get into the habit of
doing this you can start to identify
some of the underlying causes for why
you do things that you don't want to do
such as procrastinating on your work so
as I mentioned I'm going to go over four
big causes for my own procrastination in
this video
starting with the first one which is
that I am often overwhelmed with
everything that I have to do and this
causes me to basically become paralyzed
I have this analysis paralysis because
I'm aware of the huge amount of things
on my plate all the projects that are
currently going on and it makes it very
difficult to focus in on the one task I
need to do but of course to get over
procrastination that is exactly what I
need to do I need to basically put
everything out of my mind except for the
one thing that needs to be focused on at
this moment and to drive that point home
I want to share one of my favorite
quotes from the book of meditations by
Marcus Aurelius do not let the panorama
of your life oppress you do not dwell on
all the various troubles which may have
occurred in the past or may occur in the
future
just ask yourself in each instance of
the present what is there in this work
which I cannot endure or support you
will be ashamed to make any such
confession then remind yourself that it
is neither the future nor the past which
weighs on you but always the present and
the present burden reduces if only you
can isolate it and accuse your mind of
weakness if it cannot hold against
something
thus stripped bare when we let the sum
total of everything we need to do occupy
our attention then the weight of it all
can become unbearable and that's how we
get paralyzed that's how we put things
off so by sitting down and getting clear
on exactly what needs to be done in the
present moment maybe by writing it down
on a piece of paper and putting
everything out of our attention except
that one thing we can easily move
forward because in almost all instances
if you get clear enough if you make it
actionable enough it's easy to do or at
least the path is clear secondly I need
to let go of the belief that
procrastination is actually a good thing
and I think this is something that is
not unique to me in fact in the book of
mine for numbers by Barbara Oakley she
talks about how this is something that
can become a pattern of behavior you can
start to almost brag about how you were
able to get things done even though you
procrastinate it and in my case I start
to attribute positive aspects to the act
of procrastination itself such as that I
work better under pressure the time
pressure of a deadline actually makes me
more creative but what I believe is
actually happening is that I have set
lower standards for myself then I
actually have the potential to achieve I
have been procrastinating for so long
that what I set out to achieve every
single time is something that is
achievable by a procrastinator
by somebody doing things at the absolute
last moment and if I could get over that
belief I would be able to achieve so
much more so if you're like me if you
tend to make these justifications and
you tend to brag about how your
procrastination is actually a good thing
quote-unquote then every time you have
to put something off a little bit every
time you have to compromise on your
vision because of a deadline realize
that that is a product of you
procrastinating and far from
procrastination being an asset in this
case it was actually a hindrance it
caused you to compromise on your
original vision or what you wanted to
achieve alright big issue number three
for me which is the fact that some
aspects of my work just aren't
fulfilling and they aren't fun and that
also causes procrastination and I think
this may be one of the biggest problems
for a lot of you guys out there as well
some of your work just is not fun you
don't want to do it now as I mentioned
in the first video in the series a lot
of people are gonna say well if that's
the case you need to drop your work and
go follow your passion man find work
that you want to do that gets you out of
bed in the morning and the fact of the
matter is that no matter what you're
doing there's always going to be aspects
of your work that aren't fun there's
always gonna be little tasks that you
don't really want to do so instead of
focusing on those tasks in the fact that
they aren't that fulfilling I think that
you need to focus on your identity this
is something that I think about a lot
instead of telling myself that I really
don't want to do this task and fixating
on that I fixate instead on the fact
that I want to be known as a hardworking
person and like the author James clear
talks about in his excellent book atomic
habits every action you take is
essentially a vote for your identity so
when you fixate on your identity it
actually influences the actions you're
going to take it's kind of a two-way
street that leaves us with our fourth
and final problem which for me I think
is the biggest one and it's the problem
of perfectionism one of the biggest
reasons that I find it difficult to
start my work is that I have this
overarching belief that it has to be
absolutely perfect from the start and
even though in past videos I have
recommended getting in making a mess
you know going with that terrible first
draft idea I have trouble actually doing
this now there are a lot of different
reasons for perfectionism and in fact
I've even done an entire video on
perfectionism which you may want to
watch after this one but for me I think
the biggest influence is the fact that
my previous body of work has set certain
expectations or at least I
believe that it has the fact that for
the past four years I've been putting up
videos that have done well that people
have found useful makes me feel like
everything I put out in the future
essentially has to be the be-all end-all
resource on that topic it has to be
supremely helpful and this is honestly a
pretty egocentric view right I'm just
one person among billions on a speck
floating through space so every piece of
work I put out can't be the most perfect
thing ever but there's this internal
belief that it has to be and you might
have this problem as well if you've
gotten good grades in the past or you've
gotten a lot of great feedback from your
boss maybe you feel like everything you
do going forward has to be absolutely
perfect and I want to stress that this
perspective isn't completely useless but
it's an Editors perspective and it's a
terrible perspective to have when you go
into the creation process at the start
when you're thinking like an editor you
can't create very well when you're
fixated on what other people are going
to think and how your work is going to
be judged you can't be creative you
can't make that mess that's important
for just getting things started and at
least for me this relates very heavily
back to my second problem which was sort
of bragging about procrastination
feeling like it was almost a superpower
of mine because it would cause me to
delay the start of my work until right
before the deadline at which point of
course there is no time to first make
that mess and then go back and refine it
later so for me at least the solution
here is twofold number one let go of
that perfectionist mindset at least in
the beginning of the process so I can
actually make that mess and get those
thoughts out of that piece of paper and
number two start work well in advance
maybe even use mini deadlines to
facilitate this that way there actually
is time for refinements all right so
those are the four big issues that at
least for me cause chronic
procrastination and hopefully you
identified with at least one of those
along with my suggestions for how to
start improving upon it but in addition
to those I do want to give you one final
suggestion which i think is going to be
universally helpful for anybody watching
this video and struggling with
procrastination and it's to set up your
environment in accordance with the
twenty second rule this is a concept
from Sean Akers book the happiness
advantage and just this concept is that
you want to take anything that you want
to do less often and increase the
friction required to start doing it so
it takes more than 20 seconds to start
doing and of course this 20 second
figure
is more illustrative than anything it's
not based on some scientific principles
so if something takes less than 20
seconds or more than 20 seconds that's
fine but the basic idea here if you want
to set up your environment so that it's
more inconvenient to go play video games
or to go check stats like I have a
problem with doing and so it's less
inconvenient to start doing your work
and I think this is very important for
anyone to keep in mind but it's
especially important for chronic
procrastinators because you can aspire
to embody the identity of a hardworking
person you can aspire to be less of a
perfectionist but that doesn't happen
overnight no big change does and when
you're in the process of making a big
change in your life you need to set up
systems that keep you on track almost
like training wheels
so install a website blocker on your
computer or disconnect the Internet when
you need to do your work or make an
entirely separate user account that has
nothing but your work programs and
websites available on it put your video
games in inconvenient places basically
do whatever it takes to make
procrastination as inconvenient as
possible so you can start working on
becoming less of a chronic
procrastinator do that and then start
working in earnest on at least one of
the issues we talked about in this video
and you will be well on your way to
becoming the kind of person who does not
put things off now one thing that a lot
of people tend to procrastinate on to
their detriment is securing their online
lives too many people I know use the
same passwords across multiple accounts
they don't use two-factor authentication
and they do all kinds of other things
that could open them up to potentially
getting hacked or having their online
accounts compromised and as more and
more of our lab LaHood's become
dependent on online systems you can't
afford to be one of those
procrastinators fortunately one of the
most important steps to becoming secure
which is having a strong unique password
on every site that you log into is also
one of the easiest if you use a tool
like - link - Lane is an incredibly well
designed password manager that gives you
a streamlined way to secure your online
life and make sure it's hardened against
hackers corporate data breaches and
online phishing scams their app which
akyüz across all major platforms
including Windows Mac OS Android and iOS
automatically generates strong and
unique passwords for all of your online
accounts all this data is then stored in
a secure user account that is protected
by a patented security architecture
which encrypts all of your data and make
sure that you are the only person that
can access it and aside from offering
you better security - lien can also save
you a ton of time as well because once
you have your user data in their account
it can automatically fill in login forms
and even log you into most sites on the
Internet automatically so if you want to
start improving your online security
today and start saving time as well then
head over to - Layne comm slash college
info geek which will find in the
description down below and sign up and
if you'd like to save a bit money on
their premium subscription which gets
extra features like a VPN and secure
file storage then use the code college
info geek at checkout to get 10% off of
that subscription as always want to give
a big thanks to dashlane for sponsoring
this video and being a big supporter of
my channel and thank you as well for
watching if you enjoyed this video
definitely give it a thumbs up and get
subscribed right there so you don't miss
out on new videos when they come out
every single week you can also click
right there to get a free copy of my
book and how to earn better grades which
may be useful to you since finals are
definitely right around the corner you
can also follow me on instagram @ Tom
frankly or get one more video on this
channel by clicking right there thanks
for watching and I will see you in the
next one good bye