let me tell you about how i recently
ruined my morning routine there's this
fun little game that everyone's playing
right now called wordle if you haven't
heard about it you have to guess a five
letter word you get six tries to guess
it and with each guess the game tells
you if you got the letters correct and
if you got their positions correct it's
a great game and every morning since i
discovered it i have been grabbing my
phone off my nightstand playing the
wordle solve the word and then i get up
and start my day perfect little routine
but then something slowly started to
change i'd finish the wordle then i'd
open up twitter and i would check my
notifications and then i slowly started
checking instagram as well and then tick
tock and before i knew it my morning
ritual had completely changed i wasn't
just taking five minutes to play the
wordle and then getting up and actually
starting my day i was waking up and
losing half an hour just scrolling
before i'd finally snap out of my social
media induced stupor it was a huge waste
of my time and i'm not alone in wasting
that time in fact there was a study that
was recently done that found that people
are currently using social media around
two hours a day meaning conversely we
are spending a lot less time doing the
things that if we're very honest with
ourselves we want to do a lot more of
like reading books or practicing our
hobbies or even just finding simpler
ways to cure our boredom one little
interesting tidbit along these lines i
found is that since the original iphone
was introduced
chewing gum sales have absolutely
plummeted because in checkout lines
people are now just staring at their
phones instead of impulse purchasing
packs of big red simply put social media
has become a huge time sink and for a
lot of us that time we spend scrolling
the feeds is largely unconscious it's
non-deliberate and it creates this
fundamental disconnect in our minds
because we know there are other things
we would rather be doing which better
align with our goals and our aspirations
so what can we do about this problem
well the funny thing is that technology
is the thing that created this problem
and yet it is technology that seems to
come riding to the rescue claiming that
it is also the solution now we've got
apps and browser extensions that will
block social media and for the iphone at
least there's even this focus mode that
will limit how much time you spend on
certain apps per day but there's also a
much simpler solution in fact it is so
stupidly simple that when i thought of
it i thought it would be way too simple
to make an entire video about it
that is until i tried it for myself and
i had some surprising results so
here it is if you want to stop
mindlessly scrolling social media if you
want to break your addiction to your
phone and use it more deliberately then
you don't need some app you don't need
some david goggins video all you need
is to log out
[Music]
seriously that's it
use social media when you intend to use
it and then log out if you need to use
it again log back in want to check your
dms log in that's totally cool wanna
scroll tick tock during your lunch break
and watch weird videos of people biting
emojis out of thin air cool that's your
prerogative i won't even judge you
honestly hank green's take on that trend
is pretty creative but let the default
state of your phone be
logged out
now you might be thinking there are
actually even better solutions to this
problem like yeeting your phone across
the room or deleting social media apps
off your phone altogether or quitting
social media cal newport style yes these
methods are more effective but if you've
already used them or that's how you
think then this video isn't for you this
video is for the much larger group of
people who either don't want to or can't
get themselves to get these apps off
their phone who can't get themselves to
stop mindlessly scrolling and if that is
you and sometimes that's me to be honest
then logging out is a much easier
solution it's just as effective because
it throws up a roadblock but you're not
really losing out on anything because
you're still 30 seconds for being able
to log in and do anything you would
normally do on a social media app and
your phone's still with you so if you
get an important call or a message or a
notification you can still look at it
but it's that introduction of a little
bit of inconvenience a little bit of
friction that makes all the difference
you're going from three seconds and no
effort to just open twitter to 30
seconds and a little bit of effort to
grab your password grab your two factor
off code which i hope you are using and
actually log in and that is what makes
all the difference because that
unconscious impulse we have to
mindlessly scroll it only survives an
environment of zero friction and this is
an environment that smartphone
manufacturers and social media companies
have successfully built for us and a lot
of us live in this world but you can
also destroy that environment simply by
logging out simply by adding a little
bit of friction into the process this is
a very similar idea to one that michael
pollan actually shared in his netflix
documentary cooked when he talked about
weight loss and dieting he said eat all
the junk food that you want as long as
you cook it yourself there's a longer
explanation of this idea from one of the
people he interviewed for that
documentary specifically in the second
episode if you are curious but it's
getting at the same idea that we're
getting at here with this idea of
logging out so many of the bad habits
that we just can't seem to shake are
only a problem because they don't
involve any work they're bad habits born
out of convenience and if we can add in
just a little bit of inconvenience then
we can break them naturally without the
need for any fancy apps or the
aforementioned david goggins videos in
the book atomic habits author james
clare generalizes this idea with his
inversion to the third law of behavior
change where he says sometimes success
is less about making good habits easy
and more about making bad habits hard so
as i mentioned earlier i originally
thought that this idea was too stupidly
simple for its own video maybe it's good
for a tweet but a whole video come on
but i changed my tune when i actually
observed my own results and my own
behavior with this because after i had
the idea ironically i didn't log out i
had the idea while i was reading a book
and i immediately realized it would be a
good idea but then my brain started
throwing up these little objections like
what if i get an important dm or isn't
it gonna be a waste of time to be
constantly logging in and logging out or
what am i gonna do when i'm in line at
the grocery store buy chewing gum no no
the funny thing is that none of these
objections really stand up to scrutiny
they wouldn't actually hold any water
and i don't really think they were
supposed to instead it was the dopamine
craving side of my brain just trying to
delay just trying to kick the can down
the road and this is the ultimate
argumentative tactic of anything that is
representing the status quo whether it
be another person or an organization or
that side of your brain that just really
wants to check twitter whenever it feels
like it and that side of me won out for
about a full week before i finally sat
down opened up all my social media apps
and actually logged out but once i did
that the change was kind of drastic i
remember about a day after i did this i
was standing in line at the coffee shop
i pulled out my phone and i felt my hand
go through that very familiar routine of
swiping over and opening twitter only to
see a logged out screen immediately i
just didn't care anymore because i
wasn't deliberately trying to check
twitter i was just looking for that
quick dope mean hit and there was a
roadblock there and quickly after that
those little cravings to pull up my
phone in the first place also started to
fade quite quickly as well so i think
that this is an incredibly helpful
method and i think that a lot of you are
going to agree with me this is a very
good idea but you're also going to have
those same objections popping up back in
your head the same little delaying
tactics from that dopamine craving side
of your brain so
here's my challenge to you ignore those
little objections open up twitter open
up tech talk open up any app that you
find yourself mindlessly scrolling
through in a non-deliberate way and log
out give it a try because again you're
not really giving anything up now
earlier i mentioned james claire's third
law of behavior change which you can
find in his book atomic habits and a
great way to get the rest of the
insights from that frankly fantastic
book even if you are short on time is
with audible who have kindly sponsored
this video on audible you're going to
find atomic habits alongside an
unmatched library of titles that
includes audiobooks across pretty much
any genre as well as podcasts workout
programs and original programs and all
these give you a great way to learn new
things while you're out walking or
you're driving to work or you're just
taking care of stuff around the house
and you can't sit down to actually read
a book each month your membership gets
you credit for one title across their
entire catalog that is yours to keep
forever and along with that you get
access to an on-demand and growing
library of included audiobooks workout
programs and lots more and the best part
is that you can actually try it out for
free because if you go over to
audible.com thomas or text thomas to 500
500 on your phone you can sign up and
get a 30 day free trial that comes with
a free credit for any title that you
want now if you haven't already listened
to atomic habits i'm going to highly
recommend you start with that book it is
absolutely fantastic and if you have i
will recommend kevin mitnick's ghost in
the wires because that is one of my
personal favorite audio books i actually
fall asleep to it every single night so
check that one out as well once again
head over to audible.com thomas text
thomas to 500 500 on your phone or
simply click right there to get started
with that free 30-day trial thanks as
always for watching hopefully you
enjoyed this video and if you did hit
that like button for the algorithm and
if you're looking for something else to
watch i've been doing a lot of personal
finance content recently and i've got
more in the works so right there i've
got a video on three habits i think
everyone should use for managing their
money check that out and i'll see you in
the next video