the surrealist painter of Salvador Dali
had a pretty interesting hack for
generating new creative ideas during the
afternoons he would sit in his chair
with one arm draped over the side of
that chair holding a key and beneath
that key there was an upside down plate
from there he would let himself drift
off until just before the moment he was
about to fall asleep at which point the
key would fall from his hand to clatter
onto the plate and wake him up
often with a new artistic idea in his
mind Dali called this technique sleeping
without sleeping but you might recognize
it as a pre alarm clock version of the
modern power nap and he wasn't the only
one who used this Thomas Edison was
rumored to do the exact same thing with
a ball bearing instead of a key and
Beethoven while he didn't use this key
and plate method was fond of taking naps
in his carriage in order to get new
musical ideas all of these people knew
well the benefits of an afternoon nap
which is if you think about it probably
the best productivity technique ever I
mean if you think about all the other
ones we've talked about on this channel
whether it be the Fineman technique or
the Pomodoro Technique or even just
cleaning up your study space they all
kind of sort of involve work which makes
them a hassle right who needs that
by contrast taking a nap in the
afternoon involves basically no effort
whatsoever and yet has a ton of
productivity benefits it can help deal
with feelings of fatigue and maybe more
energetic for the rest of the day and it
can also help with creativity and memory
consolidation but if you do it wrong it
could also just leave you feeling groggy
and waste a ton of your time and because
that I put on my research and hat this
week and I wanted to figure out what
actually makes a good productive
afternoon nap so that is what you're
going to learn in this video and I've
got five big things to share with you
ranging from basic nap techniques to
some more advanced stuff and some tools
and even app that can help you out but
first we do need to answer the question
why do people like to nap in the first
place there are a couple really
important reasons for this number one
being that a lot of people are actually
pretty sleep deprived in fact a couple
of years ago the CDC put out some
statistics showing that over 40 million
people in the US alone get less than six
hours of sleep per night that being said
there is one other big reason why people
like to take naps and it has to do with
your circadian rhythm that built in
biological mechanism that governs the
ebbs and flows of your energy levels
throughout the day most people
experience their biggest dip of energy
levels and
middle of the night around 2:00 to 4:00
a.m. when they are conveniently fast
asleep but there is another pretty big
dip in energy levels in the afternoon
around the hours of 1:00 to 3:00 p.m.
now the degree to which your energy
actually drops in the afternoon is
definitely gonna vary both from person
to person and based on a ton of
different factors including the quality
and amount of sleep you've actually got
at night but the fact still remains that
an afternoon nap is a great way to deal
with that dip in energy when it happens
so that brings us to our big question
how do you take a proper afternoon nap
one that leaves you feeling revitalized
and productive afterwards instead of
like a truck hit you basically which is
what I've always experienced the first
tip I have for you has to do with the
duration and timing of your nap and
we'll start with duration for most
people the best nap duration out there
is going to be a 10 to 20-minute nap the
prototypical power nap and the reasoning
for this has to do with the sleep cycle
which I've detailed in other videos
we're not gonna get too deep into here
but basically sleep happens in a cycle
of about 90 minutes and it goes through
several different stages and the later
stages of the sleep cycle involve slower
brainwave activity if you're woken up
during one of these stages you're gonna
experience what's called sleep inertia
that feeling of grogginess and that
desire to go right back to sleep which
is not what you want from an afternoon
nap now if you happen to have 90 minutes
free in the afternoon then by all means
get yourself a 90-minute nap get a full
revolution through that sleep cycle and
that's actually gonna get you some
additional benefits that a power nap
won't get you such as memory
consolidation but I'm guessing that you
like me and most of the people do not
have an entire hour and a half in the
afternoons to spend conked out on a
couch so 10 to 20 minutes is going to be
the best bang for your buck you're gonna
want to take that 10 to 20 minutes
between the hours of 1:00 to 4:00 p.m.
this is because before 1 p.m. you're
probably not gonna be all that tired
that afternoon energy dip hasn't hit yet
but more importantly after 4 p.m. if you
take a nap you risk messing with your
night's sleep so try to stick it within
that window
now at this point some of you probably
have a little nagging question in the
back your mind it has to do with that 10
to 20-minute recommendation and that's
that it takes people quite a while to
fall asleep right and you're correct the
average person takes around 14 minutes
to fall asleep at night and some people
definitely take longer so given that
wouldn't attend to 20 minute power nap
be basically useless if you're not gonna
fall asleep until 15 minutes into it
that was my suspicion as well but then I
came across an article on life hacker
called how I mastered the power nap
written by a guy named Daniel tenner and
through his experience he realized that
he could gain a lot of benefits from
napping even if he didn't fall asleep
the act of simply laying down and
closing your eyes for a while and just
relaxing can help with those feelings of
fatigue and make you more productive and
what's more he notes that getting rid of
that expectation to fall asleep can
actually help you eventually learn to
fall asleep more easily and he notes
that napping is a skill so when you
start out you may not be able to fall
asleep or get into that relaxed state
but after a while you're gonna find it
easier and easier to do all right my
third tip for you here has to do with
your environment and it's gonna come as
a surprise to basically nobody watching
this that the best environment for
taking a nap is pretty much the best
environment for going to sleep as well
someplace that's dark and quiet but the
problem is unless you work from home you
probably don't have access to a
perpetually dark and quiet place and
that's why keeping a couple of simple
tools in your bag can help you out a lot
for starters you can pick up a $5 eye
mask at Target or Walmart and that can
help make basically any place dark and
as a bonus it will definitely come in
handy if you ever find yourself on a
red-eye flight which I did a couple of
weeks ago and on the noise front
earplugs are extremely cheap and really
easy to use or if you can afford it and
you are able to sleep on your back
instead of your side noise canceling
headphones can definitely be a good
investment
[Music]
speaking of headphones my fourth tip for
you here is to try out an app called
pieces or possess or possess I don't
know how to pronounce it but it's a
pretty cool app for helping you take an
app and its core this is an app that
generates ambient soundscapes that are
great for falling asleep too and you
also have the option of having a voice
guide you to sleep kind of like a guided
meditation and there's a lot of
granularity in your options with that
voice you can turn it off completely or
you can actually have it fade out after
a few minutes and just transition to
that music additionally there's a sleep
timer function so you can tell it the
only one on that for 20 minutes and
it'll wake you up which will help
prevent you falling into those deeper
stages of the sleep schedule and hitting
that sleep inertia and that brings us to
our last and most advanced tip which is
to try taking a coffee nap which
involves drinking a cup of coffee or
something else caffeinated and then
immediately taking a 20-minute power nap
now you're probably thinking to yourself
that this sounds stupid right because
caffeine is going to interfere with the
quality of your sleep but actually
caffeine takes about 20 minutes to
really kick in in your system so by
immediately taking a power nap right
after you drink that cup of coffee you
actually gain the benefits of both a nap
and a cup of coffee I've seen several
prominent internet people praising the
benefits of this practice and yes I'm
going to go with Internet people because
I can't think of a better term for it
but CGP Grey uses it Tim Ferriss uses it
and studies done in both the UK and
Japan have found that it is more
beneficial than a nap alone or coffee
alone and to give you a little insight
into how this works essentially as you
go through the day your brain generates
a chemical called adenosine which builds
up the desire to sleep now obviously
once you take a nap your brain is going
to clear out some of that adenosine by
sleeping which is gonna help you feel
more energized and get rid of those
feelings of fatigue and as you may have
heard me talk about in other videos
caffeine molecules are actually very
similar in structure to adenosine
molecules which means that they actually
block those adenosine receptors
preventing the actual adenosine
molecules from plugging into them and
making you feel tired so you kind of get
the best of both worlds the nap clears
out the adenosine that's already there
and the caffeine prevents more from
plugging into those receptors making you
feel more alert now one word of warning
here if you are going to try this
technique out you still do need to be
very careful about building up a
dependence to caffeine so if you are
going to try taking a coffee nap maybe
take it easy on the coffee in the
earlier part of the day and I do want to
know one other thing while I'm talking
about warnings here and basically being
your dad which is that naps should not
be used as a band-aid they should not be
used to cover up other bad health habits
that are constantly making you tired
aside from getting enough sleep at night
you should be making sure that you get
enough exercise you should make sure
that you go outside and get sunlight
exposure often enough make sure you're
drinking enough water make sure that
your nutrition is good basically
everything I talked about in my why
you're always tired video you should be
making sure that you have taken care of
in your life provided that you do have
those things taken care of though naps
can be one more tool in your arsenal for
helping boost your productivity in the
middle of the day and as Edison and Dali
and many others throughout history knew
well a nap can also help to boost your
creativity and might actually help you
solve a tough problem that you've been
stuck on and on that note if you're
looking for tough problems to solve
problems that will improve your critical
thinking skills and your analytical
abilities and improve your mastery in
both math and science then you should
check out brilliant brilliant is a
learning platform that takes an active
challenge based approach to teaching
math science and computer science and
throughout their courses on astronomy on
gravitational physics calculus computer
algorithms computer memory and many many
more you're gonna find yourself
immediately thrown into challenging
problems that number one build your
interest in the subject immediately
which often doesn't happen in courses
that start more passively and which
build your expertise much more
efficiently additionally when you find
yourself stuck on a challenging problem
in one of their courses you're also
gonna find it extremely detailed wiki
with tons of example problems and detail
that can help to flesh out your
understanding and an active community of
thousands of other learners so if you
want to start improving your
problem-solving abilities I highly
recommend giving brilliant a try you can
go over to brilliant org slash Thomas
Frank to start learning for free today
and the first eighty three people who
click on that link in the description
down below will also get 20% off of
their annual subscription huge thanks to
brilliant for sponsoring this video and
being a continued supporter of this
channel and as always guys thank you so
much for watching also it has come to my
attention that a lot of you do not know
that I have a podcast and I do I do it
with my friend Martin every single week
so if you want more content like this
but in a longer format definitely check
out our latest episode right here lastly
you can find one more video on this
channel right over here smash your face
on your phone or do whatever you want
I'm not you
do whatever you want I don't care man
yeah video is over I'm gonna go take a
nap