At some point in your life, you're
probably going to be asked to give a
presentation. And this can be a great
opportunity for you, but only if you
prepare correctly. Otherwise, it's an
opportunity for failure. Even if you are
a great speaker, even if you're
charismatic and confident and you're
able to walk up on a stage without, as
one Cards Against Humanity card put it,
peeing a little bit, your presentation
can still fall flat on its face and bore
your audience to tears if it's founded
on a poor idea or structured in a bad
way. Fortunately, communicating your
ideas to an audience in a way that's
persuasive and exciting is a skill that
you can learn and get better at. So,
today I want to share four big ideas
that you can use to start crafting and
delivering better presentations. And
speaking of skills that you can learn,
this video is sponsored by Skillshare.
Skillshare is an online learning
community with over 15,000 courses you
can take in a ton of different topics,
including graphic design, web
development, business skills, and of
course, presentation skills. And I'm
going to talk about them a little bit
more near the end of the video. and also
recommend a couple of courses that you
might want to take if you want to
improve your presentation skills. But
first, let's get into the tips. Starting
with the absolute most important element
of any presentation that you're ever
going to give, which is the idea. The
underlying idea or concept that you're
trying to communicate with your audience
is the beating heart of your
presentation. As Chris Anderson, the
creator of TED puts it, "Your number one
mission as a speaker is to take
something that matters deeply to you and
to rebuild it inside the minds of your
listeners." And that's what
communication is all about. taking your
ideas and sharing them with people who
are willing to listen. And when it comes
to presentations, it's especially
important to highlight this because a
lot of people are concerned with how
they're going to look or how they're
going to sound on stage. And they don't
give as much thought to the substance
and the meaning of the idea that they're
communicating. But in truth, the
substance of that idea matters so much
more than how you look while you're
delivering it. So before you ever step
on a stage, understand all the details
of your idea. Understand why your
audience should learn about this idea.
and make sure that each part of your
presentation relates to that idea and
supports it. So once you've nailed down
the idea behind your presentation, it's
time to start looking at some tactics
that you can use to make that
presentation more compelling. And the
first one I want to talk about is
storytelling. The human brain is
fundamentally wired to be drawn in by a
good story. And storytelling is probably
the mode of communication that we are
most receptive to. Also, telling a story
is a great way to add emotion to your
talk. And that's especially useful when
your idea isn't all that emotional
fundamentally. For instance, back when
the movie Prometheus was about to come
out, the marketing team put out this
fake 2023 TED talk where the CEO of Whan
Industries, Peter Whan, comes out and he
gives this talk about human progression.
And it's a pretty self argrandizing talk
that's basically meant to build up him
and his company in the eyes of the
audience. But he starts out this talk
with a story about the Titan Prometheus
stealing fire from the gods and giving
it to humanity as their first piece of
true technology. and he gets into these
ugly and kind of disgusting details
about the punishment that the gods used
on Prometheus after he did this. And
while this isn't all that related to the
progress of technology, it's a great way
to add some visceral emotion and imagery
to the talk that's otherwise kind of
sterile. Now, if you're going to add a
story to your talk, you need to know the
elements of great storytelling. And
there are three main elements I want to
talk about here. Number one, any good
story needs to have a character that the
audience can empathize with. And here I
want to note that personal stories can
be especially effective at forging a
connection between you and your
audience, especially if that story shows
a little bit of vulnerability on your
part. You also need a conflict or some
sort of problem. Basically, the thing
that makes your audience curious and
interested in the story. And finally,
you need a satisfying conclusion that
ties back into your idea. And on a
related note, you've probably heard that
telling a story can be a great way to
open a presentation or speech. And this
is true, but there's a catch. As the
author Michael Port puts it in his book,
Steal the Show, if you're opening with a
story, it had better be a great story.
Otherwise, open with a note that's
intellectually or philosophically
important. Often, when a speaker starts
with a story, many in the audience
think, "Oh boy, here comes another one
of those dull opening stories." In other
words, we're all pretty jaded when it
comes to the typical way that people
structure their talks. After all, most
of us have sat in school from anywhere
between 18 to 30 years. So, we've sat
through a lot of presentations and we've
seen it all. So, if you're using an
opening story as a crutch, people are
going to catch on right away and it's
going to hurt you. Now, in addition to
storytelling, another tactic you can use
to connect with your audience is to use
analogies and metaphors to essentially
meet your audience where they are. Using
an analogy is a great way to explain
something in terms that your audience is
going to easily understand. And a really
good example of this comes from the
movie The Big Short, which is one of my
favorite recent films. Now, in case
you're unfamiliar with this movie, it's
basically a story of how the great
financial crash of 2008 happened. And in
telling that story, the movie tries to
explain the inner workings of some of
the outright fraudulent financial
inventions that helped to cause it. One
of those inventions is called a
collateralized debt obligation or a CDO.
But instead of just trying to straight
up explain this purposely complicated
financial instrument, they create an
analogy that's much easier to
understand. After Ryan Gosling's
character introduces the concept, the
camera pans over to Anthony Bourdain,
the famous chef. And then he creates a
story about how he bought fish on
Friday, but then three days later, it's
getting kind of rotten. but instead of
throwing away, he just throws it into a
stew and calls it something new. And
that creates a much easier to understand
picture of how CDIO works. And it's much
more emotionally visceral as well, since
most people have smelled rotten fish,
but don't even know what a CDIO is.
Also, analogies and metaphors give you
access to yet another tool for
connecting with your audience, and that
is humor. And one of the masters at
using this type of humor that I think
you should study is John Oliver. Even
though his show covers topics that are
objectively boring, like the federal
budget and gerrymandering and the IRS,
millions of people still tune in to
watch it because Jon is an expert at
using analogies to tie those boring
topics to things that are funnier. For
example, in one episode, he takes the
IRS's practice of literally hanging up
on its own customers, which they call a
courtesy disconnect, and ties it to
other things whose names hide their true
meaning, like the Care Bears, who are
still vicious bears. And if you can
learn to do this as well, especially in
a way that connects with your specific
audience, you're going to gain their
trust and keep them much more engaged
throughout the entirety of your
presentation. The last tactic I want to
talk about today is audience
interaction. Because if you can take
your audience and get them actively
involved in the presentation, then you
can improve that presentation by a huge
margin. And to explain how to do this, I
want to tell you a story from my own
life. So back in 2012, when I was still
a college senior, I flew to New York
City for a conference called Blog World.
I was a blogger at the time. was pretty
small and I had a lot of heroes that
were going to be there who we really
wanted to see. So on the second day of
the conference, my friend Alex and I
went to go see one of our favorite
bloggers give a talk, but we couldn't
get into the room because it was
standing room only and there was so many
people packed in that there were
literally people in the hallway trying
to hear what he had to say. So instead
of getting into the mosh pit ourselves,
my friend Alex says, "Hey, let's go see
this guy Marcus Sheridan speak instead."
And we go into his room. It's much less
packed and it turns out that Marcus is a
pool salesman. So, I'm thinking this guy
probably doesn't have a whole lot for
me. But by the end of his speech, I was
convinced that Marcus was hands down the
best presenter at the entire conference.
And the reason for this was that Marcus
was an expert at audience interaction.
And more importantly, he made his
audience feel special. My most intense
memory from the presentation is when he
put up a slide on the projector that
just said October 10th, 2008. And
underneath there was the number 7,882.
And then he asked the audience, "Does
anybody know what this number means and
why it relates to this date?" And
because I had been taking an economics
class, I raised my hand and I said, "I
think that's the number the Dow Jones
fell to on October 2008 during the stock
market crash," which was the right
answer. And Marcus came over and said,
"My man, this guy knows what's up." And
he made me feel so special that I had
like absolute wrapped attention for the
rest of the entire presentation. And I
loved it. Now, Marcus is a great speaker
across the board. He's got a lot of
energy. He's really engaging and he has
a lot of practice doing this type of
audience interaction. But still, if you
can learn to do this, you're going to
have a lot more success in your own
presentations. But I do want to give you
a couple of warnings. Number one, don't
start your presentation off with
audience interaction because it can
backfire. Remember, when you get up on
that stage, you haven't made your first
impression yet. So, your audience is
still naturally a bit skeptical. You
have to build their trust first.
Secondly, you need to have a plan for
what you're going to do if your audience
doesn't answer your question in the way
you expect or if they don't answer at
all. Now, these are certainly not the
only tactics you can use to craft a
great presentation. And I think if you
want to get better, you should go out
and learn from as many sources as you
possibly can and make them diverse.
Don't just watch other speakers. Watch
TV shows, watch movies, watch
advertisements because these are all
forms of communication. They all have
information that you can glean and adapt
into your own style. Additionally, there
is a lot to be learned from taking
actual planned out courses from an
expert instructor. And one great place
to find those courses is over on
Skillshare. Skillshare has a ton of
courses you can take in many, many
different topics, but the ones that I
want to focus on here are their courses
in presentation skills and design. For
instance, one of my favorites on the
platform is a course called Presentation
Essentials by Simon SK. And if you're
not familiar with Simon SK, he gave my
favorite TED talk of all time on a
concept called Start with Why. And his
course over on Skillshare is an
excellent supplement to this video. And
if you want to improve your presentation
skills, it would be a great idea to go
take it. You'll also find courses on how
to nail your delivery, on visual
storytelling, and on crafting slides
that rock in addition to many, many
other topics. Plans on Skillshare can be
had for as low as 10 bucks a month. But
if you'd like to start learning today at
absolutely no cost. You can get a
two-month free trial by using the link
in the description down below and using
the code ovation when you sign up. I
want to once again thank Skillshare for
sponsoring this video. It really helps
to support this channel. And thank you
for watching. If you like this video,
give it a like to support this channel.
And if you have questions, leave them
down in the comments below and I will do
my best to get them answered. If you
haven't subscribed yet, you can click
right there to subscribe to this channel
and get new videos on being a more
effective student. And you can click
right there to get a free copy of my
book on earning better grades. Also, if
you want to get another video, you can
click right there to watch one. And you
can listen to our latest podcast episode
right there. Thanks for watching.