be honest with me here when you study
your get work done how good are you at
focusing on that work and by that I mean
how susceptible are you to distractions
that pop up or the temptation to
multitask this is a really important
question to ask yourself because a lack
of focus
a lack of the ability to concentrate is
one of the best ways to waste a lot of
the time you dedicate to studying that's
because when you get pulled away from
your main task into a distraction or
some other task you're not just wasting
the time that it takes to get that
distraction done with there's also
something called a cognitive switching
penalty and as Josh Kaufman points out
in his book the personal MBA which I
highly recommend by the way in order to
take action your brain has to load the
context of what you're doing into
working memory if you constantly switch
the focus of your attention you're
forcing your brain to spend time and
effort thrashing loading and reloading
contexts over and over again that's why
it's possible to spend an entire day
multitasking getting nothing done and
feel exhausted at the end you've burned
all of your energy context switching
instead of making progress this is why
it's so important to build the ability
to focus if you can do that you're going
to eliminate a lot of these potential
cognitive switching penalties you could
have incurred from your day and that
means you're gonna be able to pack your
work into a more concentrated shorter
amount of time and get more done so in
this video I want to give you five quick
ways that you can start building the
ability to focus and concentrate on the
task at hand and the first one is called
pre commitment pre committing to a task
is simply building some sort of device
that binds you to finishing it before
you actually get started and to do this
you can use what are called commitment
devices it's why I use beeminder to
ensure that I create two things every
week on my website if you have some way
of making sure there's a consequence for
not getting your work done you're gonna
be more motivated to stay focused on
that work this can be as simple as
writing down that you're going to get X
done in 30 minutes and if you don't
finish within 30 minutes you know that
you've failed
you've externalized that goal by writing
it down and now that you failed it
you're gonna feel bad you can even do
something crazy like hiring a lady off
Craigslist to slap you in the face like
Minnie Safety did or you could stay
within the realm of sanity that's cool
too you can also pre commit to one task
by eliminating your ability to do
anything else during that time this is
often called the burnt ships technique
and it's in reference to an inaccurate
but still compelling story about Hernan
Cortes telling his men to burn their
ships before they attack the Aztecs the
motivation for doing this would have
been to keep his men focused on the task
because they had no
option they couldn't go back now you
probably don't have an actual boat to
burn of your own and even if you did it
probably wouldn't help you get your
homework done but you can take
inspiration from this idea by removing
the ability to do other things while
you're focused on a task and one way you
can do this is by blocking distracting
websites on your computer using an
extension like stay focused or a program
like focal filter you could even
entirely disconnect the internet if you
didn't need it
tip number two is to have a distraction
sheet next to you while you work now
talked about this before as in addition
to the Pomodoro Technique but whether or
not you're pre committing using that
technique or just studying in a
different way having a piece of paper
next to you where you write down what's
distracting you helps you get back into
your work because you know you've made a
reminder of that distraction you can get
back to it later if it's important but
you're externalizing it you're pulling
it out of your brain and you're allowing
your brain to get back to the task at
hand tip number three is to try out an
app called forest which is available for
both iPhones and Android devices forest
is an app that tries to help make your
smartphone less of a distraction and it
does this by letting you plant a seed
and then if you don't touch your phone
for 30 minutes it grows into a tree you
do touch your phone it kills the tree
and you failed that session now I can
see it already people in the comments
saying that you could just turn off the
phone or leave it in a different room
and that does work but the thing that
forest does is it provides an instant
reward the minute you finish a 30-minute
session getting immediate tangible and
quantifiable results for something is a
great way to build a good habits and if
you're just turning off your phone and
putting it in the other room you may not
see those immediate tangible benefits
but if you get a nice cool tree on your
phone if you don't touch it for 30
minutes then that's a nice thing you can
look at so if turning your phone off
works for you that's cool but if it
doesn't try the app Oh tip number four
is to meditate once a day and I've been
doing this for a few months now and
honestly I just do it for three minutes
in the morning and I try to focus on my
breath now the idea behind this is that
your attention is like any other muscle
in your body
as you train it it gets stronger and
your ability to focus increases I found
that just trying to focus on my breath
for three minutes a day has increased my
ability to stay focused on other tasks
like reading or writing now an important
thing to note with meditation is that
your attention will wander and that's
okay the act of noticing that your
attention is wandered and they you've
started daydreaming and then bringing
that attention back to your initial
point of focus is what helps build that
attention muscle my fifth and final tip
is to eliminate potential
distractions while you're studying now
when I talked about pre committing
earlier I talked about the burnt ships
technique and that's focused on
eliminating your ability to distract
yourself but there are also a lot of
distractions that can happen to you
environmental distractions people coming
in and asking you to do things and if
you can eliminate the potential for
these to happen you're going to have an
easier time focusing so pay attention to
any potential source of distractions
before you study this could be something
that can pop a notification up like your
phone or something on your computer or
just being in a specific location where
your friends are likely to find you I
actually have a whole section on
eliminating distractions in my book on
earning better grades which is free so
if you want to get some more tips in
this area then you can click the card
there or the link in the description and
grab the book so those are my five tips
this week for helping you build
concentration in your ability to focus
hopefully you found this helpful and I
want to leave you with a quote from the
Roman poet Horace who said rule your
mind or it will rule you now if your
internal ability to rule your mind and
stay focused right now isn't as strong
as you'd like it to be that's okay
work on building it but also take
advantage of the external systems and
tools we have to help you out that could
be using apps and extensions like
forests and stay focused hiring some
lady off Craigslist to slap you in the
face or just asking a friend to keep
tabs on you while you're studying anyway
I hope you found this video useful
thanks for watching and I will see you
next week
hey guys thanks so much for watching my
video on how to build more focus and
concentration if you want to get new
videos every single week on being a more
effective student than the best possible
decision you can make right now is to
click that big red subscribe button
right there
I also wrote a book on how to get better
grades if you want to get a free copy of
that click the picture and I will send
you one if you want to get links to
anything I mentioned in this video then
go to the companion blog post by
clicking the orange logo right there if
you missed last week's video is a clip
of it playing right there so definitely
check it out and if you want to suggest
topics for new videos or just connect
with me I'm Tom frankly on Twitter or
you can leave a comment thanks
[Music]