about a week ago I came across a video
on my friend Kevin's channel med school
insiders called seven regrets of my 20s
and watching his video got me thinking
about some of my own regrets and
mistakes specifically from my college
career because by no means did I have a
perfect college career by and large I'm
happy with how things turned out and I
didn't make any huge mistakes but there
are definitely some things that I would
have done differently if I were
magically time-warped back to my
freshman eighth year now all that is
unlikely to happen as I haven't angered
any wizards lately I still think that
detailing these mistakes and going
through what I would have done
differently will be useful for other
people who might be finding themselves
in a similar situation in the near
future including possibly you that's
because one of my most important beliefs
is that you can learn just as much from
the failures of others as you can from
your own as long as you can call that
little voice in your head that says yeah
but that won't happen to me right then
you can start to use the experiences of
others to prepare yourself potential
situations in your own life so today I'm
gonna be sharing eight stupid mistakes
that I made in college and the lessons
that each one of them taught me first up
in my list was a mistake I made in both
my freshman and my sophomore year which
was starting up the semester way too
gung-ho thinking I could do literally
every single reading assignment every
single piece of homework everything and
then fizzling out after just a few weeks
I'm not gonna lie I came into college as
a very ambitious student as is befitting
somebody who would make an entire
website on academic success and I wanted
to do really well in my classes I wanted
to every single test and do all the
reading so when I started my semesters I
told myself I'm going to read every
single reading assignment and I'm gonna
take notes on every single thing that I
read but as you can probably guess that
didn't last for very long and there's a
big difference between say my first week
Mis class notes which I'll show right
here and well the market lack of any
notes beyond that now I have to say that
I did get lucky because a lot of the
classes that I went to had a lot of
overlap between what was presented in
class and what was in the actual reading
assignments in homework but if I had
been in classes where a lot of crucial
information was locked the textbook then
that burnout that I experienced a few
weeks into the semester could have
really hurt
mistake number two which is a bubbly
fizzy and caffeinated mistake all
throughout college until probably my
senior year I was absolutely addicted to
energy drinks and I'd like to tell
myself that this wasn't because of the
caffeine content it probably was
caffeine is a surprisingly addictive
substance but I was also addicted to
energy drinks because they provided what
the author Taylor Clarke calls in his
book Starbucks beverage entertainment
they were something that made a study
session just a little bit less boring
because I knew I got that colorful can
of fizzy sugary liquid next to me while
I went through my math assignments the
lesson here for those of you who haven't
already gotten addicted to energy drinks
is don't let it happen because it can
very well happen both for those beverage
entertainment reasons and for the
caffeine reasons you don't need nearly
as much caffeine as you think you might
as long as you are maintaining a good
sleep schedule and if you do want to use
caffeine or you enjoy drinks that have
it maybe stick to coffee or tea instead
and there are a lot healthier and if you
aren't going to Starbucks and buying $4
lattes they are a lot cheaper as well so
the next mistake on my list here is
jumping the gun when it came to
selecting an internship so this goes
back to my sophomore year of college I
spent the summer before that year and
the very beginning of that year going as
hard as I could to try to get an
internship I went to every single
networking session that I can learn
about I went to all the career fairs I
went to all the pre career fairs and the
pre pre Career Fair breakfasts I met
recruiters from dozens of different
companies I handed out tons of different
resumes and all of this work definitely
paid off after the career fair season
after all that kind of died down I was
presented with no less than seven
interview offers at seven different
companies and I was pretty stoked about
these but I didn't end up going to any
of them because before even my first
interview was scheduled I got a call
from one company that said hey Thomas we
really liked your resume we really liked
talking with you at the career fair we
think that we don't even need to
interview you we would like to offer you
an internship sight unseen because we
think you're a great candidate and I was
ecstatic when I got this call and
because I was ecstatic and because I was
so stoked that they had offered me an
internship I had never been offered an
internship before
I took it right away now I don't want to
say that this decision led me down the
wrong path because I'm very grateful for
the experiences I got at that internship
but as a result of taking it right away
I cancelled all seven of those other
interview requests I didn't even give
them the chance to see if they were
gonna be a better opportunity than that
first one and I remember later during
that summer talking with other people
who are my classmates and friends and
asking them what their internship
experiences were like and some of them
actually ended up getting internships
that paid a lot more than mine did so I
think the lesson here is don't jump the
gun if you get a job offer you're going
to think that this is the only one
that's gonna come to you you're gonna
think that if you let this opportunity
slip through your fingers you're making
a horrible decision but it is totally
okay to say thank you so much for the
opportunity
can I take a few days to think about it
from there you start to analyze your
options and since I did this internship
and then I went and started my own
business and haven't worked a full-time
job since then I don't have the personal
experience to tell you about how to do
this correctly but I did come across an
excellent answer on reddit about this
exact same question so I'm going to link
to that in the description down below
and I highly recommend you give it a
read in case you find yourself in this
situation in the future all right
mistake number four on my list is
dropping my very first programming class
so this goes back to my very first
semester of college my freshman year I
ended up taking the engineering level
Java programming class and this was
because even though I was a business
student weirdly the business Java
programming class even though it was
easier than the engineering level one
had a prerequisite that I wasn't going
to be able to take until my second
semester whereas that engineering one
had no prerequisites and I was like I
want to start learning Java I want to
start programming this is what I came to
college for so I started that class and
immediately I found it really really
difficult the labs are difficult the
homework was difficult and I even found
it difficult to follow the lecture
material while I was sitting in class so
and it pains me to admit this after
about a couple of weeks I actually
dropped that class and just resigned
myself to taking the business level Java
class instead and this mistake is really
an echo of a mistake I made back in high
school where I didn't get a very good
grade in my calculus class because I
shied away from the tough problems the
moment
problem presented itself to me and I
thought I can't do that I don't even
know where to begin I would disengage I
would basically give up and as I've
learned in the interviewing years this
is not how you become a better
problem-solver
you can't just disengage the moment a
problem seems like it's too tough to
solve if you focus on it you're
eventually going to find the answer and
if you can't do it on your own you can
ask for help I didn't do this which
meant that I wasted a bunch of time
during my freshman year because I
dropped that class and wasted all the
hours I put into it prior to the day I
dropped it but it also meant that I
ended up going into a Java class that
was frankly too easy for me I could have
done the engineering level Java class if
I had really buckled down and focused on
the problems but I didn't so if you find
yourself in a class you feel is just too
hard make sure you were actually working
to solve those problems ask yourself
have I really put in the time have I
really focused or that I just disengage
and tell myself that's too hard all
right
failure number five here kind of related
to number four I failed to take
advantage of professor office hours for
a lot of my college career when I got
into my junior and senior year I started
to get smart and I started to use them a
lot more often but freshman and
sophomore year I hardly ever went to
professor office hours and what's worse
I remember professors actually offering
completely free review sessions you know
after class when people could just come
and ask whatever questions they wanted
in review for tests and I skipped these
two these are gold mines I remember
going to a couple of these during my
again junior and senior year and using
them to get really good grades on tests
because teachers would essentially
answer questions straight from the study
guides
I skipped these in my first couple of
years of college and I skipped professor
office hours which meant that again when
I got stuck on tough problems
I wasn't utilizing the resources that I
had available to me I was just
disengaging and telling myself I can't
do that so if you're in college or even
if you're in high school use the help
you have available to you professors are
there to help you not just by lecturing
to you at the front of the classroom but
by working one-on-one with you as well
all right stake number six and this is I
think the most emotional one on the list
here I titled it in my list seeking
companionship in the wrong places so to
put a long story very short the February
of my junior year I ended up breaking up
with the girl I was dating at the time
and for a while I was totally fine being
single but as many people end up finding
they start to get lonely after a while
and I remember that my senior year fall
started and I found myself in what I
would say is the closest to a depression
that I have ever been in I don't think
that is it it was a true depression and
I haven't really experienced what other
people have experienced in that realm of
things but it was a very sad and kind of
down period of my life and what I tried
to do to fix that I thought that I
needed to go out and find someone else
to date but I went about it in the wrong
way I started going to bars like almost
every single night and I'm not a huge
drinker but I would go out there because
the only solution to finding someone to
date in my mind was that I had to go out
to bars like where else do you meet
people who actually want to get in a
relationship right and this was the
complete wrong approach because I would
go number one put myself in an
environment where I was very unlikely to
find people who had similar interests
and passions and values to what I had
but also I psyched myself out every
single time I went into a bar or
nightclub because I went there with the
express purpose of finding somebody and
that meant I put a ton of pressure and
anxiety on myself and this went on for a
few months until one night on a whim I
decided to go to the anime club party at
my school because my roommate was the
president at the time so this was just a
completely fun thing to do I had
absolutely no expectations from it and
wouldn't you know it
that's where I met Anna my girlfriend
who have been with for six years and I
met her there because I put no
expectations on myself I didn't have any
anxiety which allowed me to be myself
and that's why she was attracted to me
so if there is a lesson here at all I
would say don't put so much pressure on
yourself to find a companion go out do
things with the intention of finding
friends and having fun and while you're
doing those things in the process you're
likely to meet people who again share
passion so you might be attracted to and
they might be attracted to you and
you're not putting
turn yourself so you're gonna be
yourself in those situations all right
mistake number seven is not doing my due
diligence when it came to the costs of
college and this specifically is
referring to the costs of living on
campus but when I was researching what
it would take to live on campus because
I wanted to live in the dorms so I could
meet as many people as possible and be
as close to the opportunities as
possible
the first bit of information I found on
my colleges website is that I had to pay
for the dorm up front for an entire
semester which I believe was about
$3,500
each and every semester and I didn't
look past that I said okay I don't have
$3,500 so I went out and took out
student loans to pay for it only later
in my college career when I started to
really get to know the college's website
for a part-time job that I had been
hired for did I learn that there was
actually a month-to-month
payment option for that dorm so to give
you some context my original plan going
into college was to get an apartment off
campus so I could pay for at month to
month with my part-time job earnings I
didn't have parents that could pay for
my college so I knew I would have to
basically cover everything myself and I
wanted to minimize debt but eventually I
decided against the apartment idea
because again I wanted to be in the
thick of things I wanted to be on campus
and meet as many people as possible all
that good stuff but I didn't do my due
diligence I didn't learn about this
month-to-month option and had I done
that I probably could have paid for my
dorm months a month with my part-time
job earnings or at least taken out far
fewer dollars in student loans so the
lesson here is do your due diligence
don't take the first bit of information
you have at face value especially if
it's going to involve you taking out a
large student loan dig in ask questions
challenge your base assumptions and you
might find something that could save you
a lot of money
[Music]
and that brings us to our final mistake
on my list which was failing to take
advantage of what I call the fun
opportunities and I call them the fun
opportunities because I have to separate
them from the professional opportunities
in college I really did take advantage
of professional opportunities I was in
Business Council I started a blog I was
in all these like academic standards
committees and computer advisory
committees all these things that I had
done just basically that boost my resume
and that may actually be another mistake
that I think about when writing this
list but what I put off where all the
things that seemed really fun so to give
you some context here my college has
over 800 student organizations and clubs
including things like downhill
dirt-boarding Club skydiving Club all
these outdoor adventure clubs and when I
was a freshman I went to this thing
called Club fest where everyone except
these booths and it was basically this
entire event designed to show the
freshmen just what was available and
what they could join and I remember
seeing all these clubs and thinking
these seem awesome I want to do all of
these but I'm here for four years I can
do them whenever I want I have all the
time in the world so of course I let
other things get in the way I let
homework get in the way I let video
games with friends get in the way I let
all these events that I thought would
build my professional presence in my
resume get in the way and four years
went by without me ever doing any of
those things I never did the skydiving
Club I never did the downhill
dirt-boarding Club I didn't none of it
so if you find yourself in a similar
situation where there's something you
want to do but you feel like you owe all
the time in the world to do it you have
to commit to it to find a way to set a
date or commit to it with a friend so
it's actually going to happen even if
something seems really fun if there's a
little bit of friction required to get
into it or if it's gonna take some time
you're always going to find something
that quote-unquote comes up and makes
you put it off a week and then another
week and then another week until one day
you find yourself on your deathbed and
you really regret never going downhill
dirt boarding now one potential regret
that I thankfully didn't have to put on
this list was failing to use my free
time to work on independent learning
projects because this was definitely
something that I did in college while a
lot of the guys in my dorm used most
their free time to play video games I
used the vast majority of my free time
that wasn't taken up by classes or
projects or part-time jobs to work
independent learning projects that
really interested me and that really
paid off in fact all the hours that I
spent in my dorm learning PHP in
Photoshop video editing gave me the
skills that I needed to build and refine
college info geek which eventually
turned into a full-time business for me
so while I'm not suggesting that you
never hang out with friends or never
play video games because I definitely
think you should do these things I do
want to leave you with one parting
thought whether you're in college or
high school or even in the professional
world make sure that you're using at
least some of your free time to pursue
independent learning projects that
interest you don't just come home and
spend all your free time on Netflix or
video games or hobbies the only result
in consumption learn something build
something and remember that since you
get to pick the project your higher
level of interest in it will almost
always lead to faster learning and you
never know how it's gonna pay off in the
future now if you want to accelerate
your learning in that project even
further you should also check out skill
share skill shares library of over
20,000 courses taught by expert teachers
and practitioners in a ton of different
areas including graphic design web
development story crafting and even
marketing all their classes are hands-on
with projects that you can immediately
sink your teeth into so you're learning
actively right away and there's also a
chat area where you can ask questions
and get feedback now one class that I
want to highlight for you this week is
Thomas Laurie's class I'm creating a UX
design portfolio and this is partly
because creating a portfolio is an
essential skill for anyone doing
creative work but also because the class
uses a free tool called Sigma which to
spoil things a little bit is a tool that
I've been using to craft a brand new
version of the college info geek website
and this tool is amazing anybody who
wants to get into the field of web
design
I think should start learning it so if
you wanna start going through that class
or check out any of the other classes in
skill shares library then click link and
the description down below and sign up
and when you do you're also going to get
a free two month unlimited trial of your
service you can learn as much as you
want in two months and after that a
premium subscription to their service is
less than ten bucks a month and you can
cancel at any time so it's risk-free and
honestly I think it is an awesome
service I wanna give a big thanks to
Skillshare for sponsoring this video of
being a big supporter of this channel
and as always guys thank you so much for
watching if you enjoyed this video and
got something out of it maybe consider
leaving a like you can also subscribe
right there if you don't want to miss
new videos when they come out every
single week you can also get a free copy
of my book on how to earn better grades
right over there watch one more video on
this channel right around here or follow
me on Instagram
@tomfrankly thanks for watching guys and
I will see you in the next one