this video is sponsored by skillshare
where i just launched a brand new class
more on that at the end of the video
the single greatest opening line ever
written in a novel can be found on page
one
of william gibson's neuromancer the sky
above the port
was the color of television tuned to a
dead channel
there are certainly novels that i've
enjoyed reading more than neuromancer
but
no opening line has stuck with me like
that one in
a single sentence gibson conjures this
lonely
melancholy feeling it's familiar but
it's also strange and it has stuck with
me
ever since i read it when i was 15 years
old and from a cultural standpoint the
rest of this book is no less impressive
this was published back in 1984 back
when the internet was
barely a thing back when almost nobody
had a computer and it is
the book that put the cyberpunk genre on
the map if you've watched the matrix if
you've watched ghostness shell
if you've played games like deus ex or
cyberpunk 2077
you have seen and experienced the impact
that this book
has had and countless other movies tv
shows
books fashion trends they all trace
their roots back
to neuromancer and reading through this
book there is obviously a ton of raw
talent on display
but beyond that there is a practice that
allowed gibson to create the imaginative
world in this book
to create the memorable turns of phrase
that are on almost every page
and it's the same practice that helps
people like you and people like me
when we're feeling creatively uninspired
we're feeling drained
it's a simple habit but it may be the
single biggest differentiator between
people who make
innovative memorable work and those who
don't
gibson himself described it as creating
a personal microculture
but personally i like to use just one
word
steve jobs once said that creativity is
just connecting things when you ask
creative people how they did
something they feel a little guilty
because they didn't really do it they
just
saw something it seemed obvious to them
after a while that's because they were
able to connect experiences they've had
and synthesize new things and the reason
they were able to do that
was that they've had more experiences or
that they have thought more about their
experiences
than other people i pulled this quote
from an interview that jobs did with
wired magazine back in 1996
and in the interview he also expressed
this frustration
that most people in tech don't have
diverse experiences
and hence they don't have enough dots to
connect to
create things that are better than
average and as creative people if we
want to make things that are better than
average
and if we want to be inspired with our
work we have to be collecting
dots i've gone through enough periods in
my life now feeling listless
feeling uninspired with my work to know
that one of the main reasons for that
feeling
is that i haven't been doing enough dot
collecting i haven't been reading widely
enough i haven't been
trying new things in short i haven't
been exploring
and if you're in a period right now
where you're feeling uninspired a lack
of exploration
is probably one of the main culprits for
you as well so today we're going to
discuss
three ways you can make exploration a
more consistent part of your life
the first one is to broaden the scope of
what you intake
the books you read the movies you watch
the people you talk to
all of it like job said creativity is
just combining things and when you're
learning from a wide variety of sources
you're building this
vast treasure trove of pieces in your
head with which to combine
consider for a second the term
cyberspace which was essentially coined
in neuromancer if you want to get
technical about it gibson actually
coined the term in a short story called
burning chrome from a couple of years
earlier but either way what fascinates
me about this
is that gibson coined this term and all
the connotations we have around it
and he didn't have access to the
internet in fact he wrote neuromancer
on a typewriter because he didn't own a
computer and the first web browser
wouldn't even come until 1990
so gibson's conception of cyberspace as
this
near ubiquitous daily destination for
billions of people
while it seems like an obvious thing
today back then was a complete invention
of fiction it was something that he
completely made up or rather
cobbled together from many different
sources the main one being as he says
seeing kids in an arcade playing video
games especially the way they were
transfixed on the screen in a sort of
trance and that
mental image was combined with other
mental images other experiences
including a flyer for an apple ii
computer
that he saw at a bus stop and this is
how all creative people work
we bring new things into existence not
by conjuring from some void
like the one behind me but by combining
the things that we learn
and experience and the more you get out
and learn the more you experience the
wider that variety of things
the better your creative output is going
to be but
you might ask how do i know where to
start how do i know the things i'm in
taking are actually worthwhile and are
actually going to lead to better
creative output
well the main thing i'll say about this
is don't think too hard about it
don't try to force exploration because
you never know what is going to
contribute to your next
piece of creative work so follow your
interests
we could talk a little bit about the
whole garbage in garbage out principle
it's probably a good idea to be
you know at least spending some of your
time in taking things that are
challenging
things that make you sort of work not
just like you know glossy popcorn stuff
but i will provide you with this one
concrete suggestion
study the people you admire in doing the
research for this video i went through
all these
magazine interviews some some really
really lengthy magazine interviews
with gibson with steve jobs with uh the
design legend george lois and in
addition to pulling lots of quotes and
insights that contributed to the script
for this video i also now have a list of
a ton of stuff that i want to check out
and it makes sense if you like something
then
there's a good chance that you're going
to be interested in the things that
influence
that thing's creator so whatever you
like seek out the creators of it
and look for either recommendations or
maybe even just off-the-cuff mentions
of the stuff that influenced them you're
likely to like it as well
but don't just stop at media consumption
your ability to
put out creative work to combine things
isn't solely influenced by the media you
consume in the conversations you have
it's also maybe even more influenced by
the experiences you have
diverse experiences and i think one of
the main reasons that so many people
feel so
listless so uninspired is that they are
in sore need
of some new experiences a lot of us get
set on a path by our parents or by a
teacher or
we stumble across something that works
and then we just keep exploiting that
thing again and again and again
partly because there are material
rewards for doing so but partly because
we're afraid to try something new
this is often called the exploration
exploitation dilemma do we continue
exploiting the thing that we know is
working
or do we divert some resources towards
trying to seek out something that might
pay out even greater rewards
in the future well as creatives we need
to be constantly exploring even if
something is
currently paying out right now if we
keep sticking to just that one thing
eventually the well is going to run dry
and far before it does
it's going to become uninspiring if
that's all we're doing as creative
people we need to be constantly taking
on new opportunities seeking out new
experiences
and i realized that it's this mindset
that actually led me to doing the work
that i do today to being fortunate
enough to make videos for a living
a few years ago the folks at luther
college asked me to write a talk for
their sophomores about my career path
and in preparation for that talk i sat
down and i tried to draw
this map of my career path and what i
ended up with was this critical path
with my college major and the internship
i did
but also all these little branching
offshoots experiments different things
that i had tried
and the most interesting offshoot from
that entire exercise was a small summer
gig that i took
during the summer after my junior year
the aerospace
engineering department on campus needed
somebody to shoot a bunch of videos for
a project
and then edit them together and i really
didn't have a whole lot of experience
with doing that but they said they would
teach me if i was willing to learn
so i took on the job and in doing that i
learned how to do complex editing i
learned how to set up
lighting for interviews i learned how to
shoot b-roll and my original motivation
for taking on that gig was because i
wanted to make some extra money during
the summer
and it seemed like an interesting enough
gig but now i realize
that experience among all others is the
number one thing that
basically enabled me to become a
youtuber so the next time you're
presented with an opportunity and you're
tempted to say no
at least pause and ask yourself what are
my reasons for passing up this
opportunity
because while it's true that you can't
take on every opportunity that comes
your way without stretching yourself too
thin
most interesting opportunities have
something to teach you something that
you're going to be able to combine with
other things you learn later on
something that can help you become a
more creative person
and you don't want to let fear or this
feeling like you need to stay in one
place and exploit what you have now
be the only thing that causes you to
pass that opportunity up
finally we need to talk about labels i
feel like there's this metaphorical
burmese tiger pit that i'm always
tiptoeing around
as i've built my personal brand online
as i've grown my audience over the past
10 years
i have acquired a label of sorts i'm
the productivity guy or at least one of
them
and with that label comes a certain
pressure i feel
this pressure to act in alignment with
that label in my personal life
i feel like i need to have read all the
latest productivity books i feel like i
need to have experience with all the
latest productivity apps
and because time is limited that creates
pressure for me to reject
certain experiences certain learning
opportunities that come my way
even if there are things that interest
me and you might feel this kind of
pressure as well
maybe from several labels your
profession your gender
your age in one way or another each one
of these labels whispers
stay in your lane well we might feel
safe if we stay in our lane we sure as
heck are not going to feel inspired so
as you explore and as you pursue things
that interest you
don't allow labels to give you tunnel
vision don't let a label push you away
from
something that interests you a label can
be useful as
a communication device it can help guide
your audience
potential clients potential employers to
you that can help you define your niche
but it can also put your mind in a box
if you let it
so if you can avoid doing that if you
can keep pursuing the things that
interest you if you can keep broadening
your array of experiences
and learning sources you're going to
find the quality of your creative output
going up
but moreover you're going to find
yourself more inspired and more often
getting lost
in the work that you do before you go
i've got a brand new class on skillshare
called productivity for creatives and if
you enjoyed this video and you're
looking for additional ways to boost
your creative output to boost your
inspiration
i think you're going to get a lot out of
this class exploration is a huge topic
in creativity which is why i put so much
time into the script for this video
but there's a lot more that we can do to
boost our abilities as creatives
especially pulling from the realm of
productivity and that is what this class
is all about
so if you want to learn how to build
your inspiration muscle if you want to
learn how to more consistently do
creative work on a daily basis
and get inspired by the creative work we
talk about that in the class
if you want to learn how to reduce the
friction in your work how to automate
certain things how to build templates
that help you speed up your process
we talk about that as well and because
it's on skillshare the cost for the
class is very low just an
hour of your time and your attention
because if you're one of the first 1000
people to sign up with the link in
description down below
you're going to get a free trial which
means that monetarily speaking you get
to take my class
for free and you'll also have unlimited
access to every other class on the
platform which there are thousands
during that trial and afterwards
skillshare is still a very affordable
platform with their plans at less than
10 bucks a month on the annual basis
so it is a hugely valuable service to
have access to they've got classes on
graphic design they've got classes on
video editing they've even got more
classes on productivity in fact my good
friend nathaniel drew just launched a
new class of his own so definitely check
that one out after you watch my class
once again use the link in description
down below and if you're one of the
first 1 000 people you're gonna get that
free trial
and as always big thanks to skillshare
for sponsoring this video and supporting
my channel
if you like this video i put a ton of
time into the writing and i would hugely
appreciate hitting
that like button to show the youtube
algorithm what's up if you didn't like
it well obviously don't hit it that's
totally cool
maybe tell me that i have a weird face
in the comments i'll also have a
subscribe button right here so you can
click that if you want to get
notifications of new videos when they
come out
and a couple of additional videos that
have already come out are going to be
floating around the screen
here and here well they're probably not
going to float but they might look like
they're floating if i do this with my
hands
anyway smash your face into your phone
screen to watch one of those for extra
style points and i will see you
in the next one