here's a question that I think about a
lot given a limited amount of time how
much of a huge gigantic body of
knowledge can you cram inside of your
brain now if you're still studying for
finals this is probably on your mind
right now but I'm interested in this
question in the context of self-directed
learning so this is a bit of an
announcement video for a challenge that
I'm going to be giving myself on May
12th which is about 2 weeks from now
I'll actually be going out to Japan for
3 weeks with my girlfriend Anna now this
is her first time going out there but
this will actually be my third time and
I'm just going to throw up some pictures
for my first couple of trips to make
this video a bit more interesting but
actually my first time going out there
inspired me to start learning Japanese
and uh I studied really hard for quite a
while and made some pretty good progress
but after the last time I went which was
two years ago I completely stopped
studying so I've had my Japanese skills
atrophying for about 2 years now and now
that I'm going back I'm remembering how
amazing it is to be able to converse
with people in their native language and
how rewarding it is to be able to speak
something that you've had to study
really hard to learn so I don't want to
go this time for my third time and not
be able to speak at the level I was able
to speak at 2 years ago so here's the
challenge uh I want to see how much I
can learn in 10 days how much Japanese
can I cram inside my brain through lots
of intense studying for uh from tomorrow
Wednesday and then uh 10 days from now
so next Friday and what I'm going to do
is create three different videos a
little minseries documenting my progress
in this little Learning Adventure and
the reason I want to do this is because
since I'll be going out to Japan it's
actually pretty hard for me to make
videos and I didn't want to leave you
guys high and dry for 3 weeks so instead
of just having nothing come out on the
channel I'm going to do this Challenge
and I'm going to show you exactly how
I'm learning I'm going to show you the
plan that I set out for myself the goals
that I'm setting and then show you the
actual progress now right now um if as
I'm thinking about it I remember a few
kanji I remember some different phrases
I can say things like suen or k Ichigo
Jen or something like that but really my
skills have atrophied quite a bit and I
want to see how far I can get so in the
first video it'll the intro day one
video I'll show you what level I'm at
I'm going to quiz myself today and see
exactly where I am day five will be the
second video and I'll show you the
midpoint progress and then the last
video will be day 10 I'll be showing you
the level that I'm at going into the
trip so yeah this Thursday and next
Thursday we'll have normal regular
videos but then on May 14th look forward
to the start of that series and the day
one assessment to my own skills and also
my plan for learning Japanese now if
learning a language is something that
you want to do yourself well maybe this
series will give you a bit of
inspiration or some direction on how you
can do it in a self-guided way and then
later on in the year I actually want to
get more into self-guided learning and
do some exploratory videos on that so
consider this series a little bit of a
first foray into that topic if you want
to follow along see my progress or hear
my terrible pronunciation you can either
subscribe to this channel right here on
YouTube or you can subscribe to the
newsletter over at College infogeek
where you'll also get a free copy of my
book on earning better grades so that's
it for this video I really hope you
enjoyed the miniseries and I hope you
also enjoy the video coming out next
Thursday on how to stop making stupid
mistakes on your exams see you then