when I was a kid one of my favorite
shows on Nickelodeon was Jimmy Neutron
and when I watched that show one of the
inventions that stuck out to me the most
was book gum these were little sticks of
gum that each contained the entire text
of a specific book and as Jimmy put it
when you chew it you know it and ever
since I saw that episode I've always
wished that invention actually existed
how cool would it be to be able to just
chew a stick of gum and know the text of
Moby Dick or your math textbook but of
course book gum does not exist
sadly so what I want to do today is talk
about what you can do to remember what
you read better because you can read
more books you can read them faster but
if you are not in taking the information
and you're not able to recall it and
apply it later on then what are you
really reading for in the first place
and as I see it there are two different
categories of books that we need to
cover first there are books full of
facts and concepts that you need to
simply know things like the
mere-exposure effect from Daniel
Kahneman's Thinking Fast and Slow or the
definition of a caravel which you can
learn in Daniel Boorstin z-- history
text the discoverers the information
contained in books like these is of a
more academic nature it's less
applicable to your life you can't use it
so easily but you still may need to know
it be it for a test down the road or
simply because you want to so first we
are going to quickly cover five specific
techniques that you can use to more
effectively remember the information
from basically any book that you're
reading but these are gonna be
especially useful for these more
academic types of books after that
though we are going to talk about these
second category of books these are the
more actionable practical books things
like music theory or the science of
cooking these kind of books are actually
trying to teach you something that you
will use and as you may imagine the most
effective way to remember the
information in these types of books is a
little bit different but first let's
talk about those five general reading
techniques and the first one is called
pre reading so to effectively pre read
before you dig into the actual chapter
first go over the books table of
contents skim the chapter look at the
chapters subheadings may be some bold
lists and then go to the back of the
chapter there's a summary or review
questions review those as well
doing this before reading has the effect
of priming your brain to more readily
pick out the most important information
when you're actually going through the
text and if you want a really great
example of how priming can affect your
brain just briefly close your eyes and
think about a specific color and do that
for
a couple of seconds then once you open
your eyes again you're gonna start
noticing that color everywhere in your
environment
you've primed your brain and pre-reading
does the exact same thing for words on a
printed page secondly highlighting can
be very effective but only if you do it
right see a lot of people have the
tendency of highlighting way too much
when they read or going through the text
and highlighting immediately instead of
trying to read and understand the text
first
so as Walter puck points out in this
book had a study in college read the
text before you start marking it this
has the dual effect of making sure that
you're focusing all of your attention on
actually understanding what you're
reading instead of looking for sections
to highlight but it also prevents you
from highlighting too much and this is
important because the more that you
highlight the less useful those
highlights are I mean imagine if you
highlighted every single piece of text
in a book you would have essentially
just changed the background color of the
paper and gained nothing anyway other
than that one little word of warning
about highlighting I do have one
additional tip which is that it's good
to know if you were doing your
highlighting on a Kindle or on a digital
platform of some sort usually your
highlights go to a specific area of the
app for example in the Kindle app you
can bring up all of your highlights for
a specific book in one convenient place
tip number three take notes after you
read and notice that I said after you
read now you don't have to wait
specifically until you end an entire
chapter but I think it's good to at
least read a section try to get into it
and then go over it again and take notes
on the most important details now you
might be asking what par the most
important details how do I know what I'm
supposed to take notes on and hopefully
you're pre reading will give you a
little bit of illumination in this area
because you're gonna start picking out
what's most important but in general
some good things to look out for include
key terms which are often bolded or
italicized main points and also examples
and stories that highlight those main
points and these can often be summarized
you don't have to take notes on them in
too much detail now again the length and
the specific format of your notes is
gonna be completely up to you you're
gonna get better at it over time but if
you want some examples I can provide a
few including my own notes on Charles
Duhigg the power of habits which I
published on my personal website I'll
have linked in description down below
that brings us to a very related tip
which is to summarize what you read
after you're done reading it and with
summaries in particular I think it's
good to finish an entire chapter and
then go back try to pick up the main
points maybe look at your notes and then
write a summary again you don't want
this thing to be too long you just want
to be a very
distilled version of what you read that
contains the most important and salient
points
finally seek out secondary sources of
information that can complement what
you're reading this has the dual benefit
of building additional neural
connections to the material that you're
forging through the book but it also
keeps your level of interest high or
could potentially boost it for topics
that you're not super interested in
because a lot of times staring at a
piece of dead tree on your desk isn't
the most interesting way to learn about
a topic right and make no mistake about
it interest is the most important
ingredient to effective learning and
long-term recall as the author Frances
Lockwood put it over a hundred years ago
in the long run the secret of study
resides in our ability to bathe our
thought our task our lesson in the
stream of interest so if you can and you
have time to do it to find other sources
of information that can boost the level
of interest you have in the topic now
this could be other books but it could
also be a podcast episode or a museum
tour or maybe even a video game the
reason that I still remember what a
caravel is is because I was actually
using them in Civilization five as I
read about them in the discoverers this
is what a pause for a second to point
out that I played over a hundred turns
of survived last night to get b-roll for
the stupid care of all section and it
turns out the Portuguese civilization
doesn't even get caravels because they
get a better unit automatically you get
the point all right with my future selfs
editing complaints out of the way it is
now time to move on to that more
practical category of books books that
are actually trying to teach you
something that you will use in the
future so as you probably could have
guessed the most effective way to recall
the information in these kinds of books
is to mix reading with doing mix the
academic study with practical
application I mean that's kind of the
point of these kinds of books anyway
right now what I want to do with this
section of the video is just give you a
few practical examples of how I'm
putting this concept into action and
let's start with Brian Boone's book on
music theory one thing you learn about
early on in this book is the interval
patterns that define different types of
scales for example there's a specific
interval pattern for minor scales and
that differs from the one for major
scales now I could have just read about
this after all it is a music theory
after all and the interval patterns
aren't too difficult to grasp and
understand but to understand them better
after I read about them I went and wrote
an interval pattern down at
of paper at my piano and then I spent
some time picking random notes in
building scales from those notes using
the interval pattern doing this helped
me to build a more concrete
understanding of how these patterns
worked it was more solid than if I had
just read and tried to memorize them and
to further solidify that mindset I also
spent some time improving within the
scales that I have built now regardless
of what you think of this piece it's
obviously more fun to play than just
going up and down scales and again this
goes back to that quote about interest
if you can bind what you're learning to
something that you're more interested in
like playing fun music you're gonna
understand it and remember and recall it
a lot more effectively for another
example let's talk about the code book
by Simon Singh this book traces the
entire history of cryptography starting
from very simple Caesar ciphers and
skittle EES going all the way up to
theoretical quantum cryptography now
while remembering the historical details
in this book would mostly entail using
the techniques we've already talked
about the actual methods of crypt
analysis like frequency analysis are
much better understood through practice
and wouldn't you know it in the back of
the codebook there is an entire code
breaking challenge so while I was
reading the codebook I also spent some
time trying to work through those
problems and interestingly as I worked
through them and gained more practical
experience in crypt analysis my interest
level rose and I was able to remember
the details more like that's the only
reason I can remember what asked Italy
is fun little side note that knowledge
of what asked Italy was actually helped
me to beat an escape route recently so
if you want to get better at beating
escape rooms you may want to read the
codebook alright so we have covered a
lot of information in this video but I
do want to leave you with one final tip
after you're finished reading a chapter
or a section go for a walk take a break
hit the gym take a little bit of time to
refrain from in taking more information
because in this modern world we have
access to so much of it there are so
many different sources and if we're not
careful we can find ourselves spending
literally all of our waking hours in
taking information but if you want to be
able to use that information you
be able to recall it you can't
constantly be in taking new things you
have to give what you've already read
we've already taken in time to kind of
marinate time to set itself up and
actually integrate itself into your
existing banks of knowledge so use these
techniques to start learning more
effectively but at the same time always
keep in mind the words of the great Gabe
Newell now earlier in the video we
talked about how exploring topics in
different mediums can help you to more
effectively remember what you've read
and a very easy way to do that just to
go out and find a documentary on the
same topic you're reading about
curiosity stream has over 2,400
documentaries from some of the world's
best filmmakers covering science
technology history and more so whether
you're reading about the history of the
Apollo space program or the reign of
Louie the fourteenth you'll be able to
find something there that can further
expand your knowledge and interest and
if you're looking for a place to start
I'm gonna recommend these deep ocean
series which is narrated by the always
excellent David Attenborough or you can
dig into original series we drink
Stephen Hawking Sigourney Weaver and
Derek Muller
and you can do it from anywhere I still
find curiosity stream on roku smart tvs
iOS android chromecast and of course on
the web you can get unlimited access to
everything on curiosity stream for just
$2.99 per month and if you'd like to try
it out for free first you can go over to
curiosity stream comm slash thomas and
use the promo code thomas at checkout to
get a completely free 31 day trial huge
thanks goes out to curiosity stream as
always for sponsoring this video and
also supporting my channel and thank you
guys so much for watching as well
hopefully you found something useful in
this video and if you did definitely hit
that like button and also subscribe
right there to get new videos every
single week you can also click right
over here to get a free copy of my book
on how to earn better grades watch one
more video on this channel right here or
check out our latest podcast episode
right over here thanks so much for
watching and I will see you in the next
one