I get inspiration from a lot of people
but one of those people is Elliot Hol a
strong man and YouTuber whose simple No
Frill style of teaching and very
minimalistic editing this videos gave me
the confidence that I actually needed to
start making videos without thinking
that I needed insane editing and huge
budgets and all the crazy stuff that a
lot of other channels use now if you
watch the trailer over at his channel
strength camp you'll hear him say
something that has become the
Cornerstone of my own exercise
philosophy and it's the most important
part of the game is your game piece and
it makes sense doesn't it cuz if your
life is a game then the hardware that
you play with is your body and your mind
and if they're not in good working order
you're not going to be able to play the
game very well now I make this point for
an important reason it's this as
students who are busy and who are young
we make a couple of really uh fish
excuses in our lives when it comes to
exercising one we say that we're young
our bodies are going to take care of
themselves uh we don't need to take care
of them as much it's not as much of a
priority and two we feel that we're too
busy to make time for exercise that it
can come later after we've put in in all
this grunt work to become successful if
you've made those excuses before or
you're making other excuses that cause
you to work out less than you want to
then I'm here to help you squash those
excuses and in this video I want to help
you do two things one make more time to
work out and two Gain the motivation to
do so so let's start with time and the
first thing that I'm going to say is the
same thing I said in my video on high
density fund you need to schedule time
to exercise and I'm not talking about
just saying oh I'm going to work out
three times this week at some point use
the time management skills you're
building and actually look at your week
schedule actual times that you're going
to work out and make sure you're in the
gym or wherever you work out at those
times just like scheduling fun
scheduling your exercise time will
necessitate that you work more
efficiently when you're actually
studying or getting homework done now if
you're finding that becoming a more
efficient person and scheduling your
workouts isn't enough and you're really
really busy then do what I do every
morning I wake up and as part of my
morning routine I do something called
the seven-minute workout it's actually
just seven minutes and I use an app on
my iPhone to guide me right through it
which I'll link to in the blog post for
this video and uh it's part of my little
10-minute block with my meditation that
I do for 3 minutes the other nice thing
about the 7-minute workout is that it's
all body weight exercises I actually do
it right here in this office and I don't
need anything except for my body weight
and a wall to do wall sits and a chair
to do chair standup exercise things I'm
not really sure what those are called
chair step-ups so let's move on to the
topic that most people probably have
more trouble with which is motivation
and I've got four ways that you can
increase your motivation to exercise get
a buddy externalize your motivation
tackle the ignition costs first and make
exercise fun so getting a workout buddy
is seemingly simple you just find a
friend who also wants to exercise and go
to the gym with them but one thing I
want to caution you on this is you need
to find somebody who's not going to
bring your own motivation levels down if
you find that the person who wants to go
to the gym with you is actually making
it harder for you to get to the gym than
if it would be on your own then don't go
to the gym with that person unless you
want to make a conscious effort to help
them get fit but if you're trying to
bolster your own motivation you need to
find somebody who is going to provide a
positive influence one thing you can try
is actually getting a buddy who isn't
really a good friend I found my workout
buddy when I was on the Iowa State
subreddit one year and we ended up going
to the gym together for 6 months since I
didn't know him really well I couldn't
just walk into his room and say hey I'm
not feeling it today I had to show up if
I didn't want to embarrass myself and
actually having a workout buddy is one
way you can externalize the motivation
to work out but let's talk about a
couple of others basically externalizing
your motivation is going to come through
commitment devices committing prior to
the actual workout so you have to go do
it one way I did this as a sophomore was
signing up for an Roc physical fitness
class so as a civilian I actually worked
out with the Army k and did the exact
same workouts they did at 6:00 a.m. and
yes it was hell but I was really fit
that semester in later semesters I
signed up for a lifting class which met
3 days a week and while it wasn't at
6:00 a.m. it was a really good way to
stay in shape and I got an extra credit
to boot now if you don't have access to
a workout partner or classes you can
sign up for you can also use apps as
commitment devices and I'll talk about
some other apps I really like at the end
of this video but the ones I want to
talk about right now are beinder and
packed be minder I've talked about
before and it's a general commitment
device app where you can pledge money
towards a certain goal and gimpa is an
exercise specific goal where you pledge
money to go to the gym a certain amount
of times a week third on our motivation
list is dealing with ignition costs so
tell me if you feel the same way that I
do I think that the actual Act of
getting ready to work out putting on my
gym clothes taking off my regular
clothes and walking to the gym is
actually more difficult than the actual
Act of lifting the weights this is a
common problem for a lot of things we
want to do the act of preparation of
getting ourselves into the task and
getting ready for it is often harder to
summon the motivation for than doing the
actual task to account for this there
are couple things you can do and the
first thing I would do is split it into
two different tasks respect the ignition
cost as a task of its own and then the
actual workout as a second task if you
keep something like an accomplishment
journal or you track your tasks and
habit RPG and give yourself rewards then
give yourself a reward for finishing the
ignition and then give yourself a second
reward for doing the actual workout you
can also put that secondary task the
actual workout out of your mind
altogether and simply commit to
finishing the ignition I know a lot of
people who say to themselves I'm just
going to walk into the gym with gym
clothes on and count that as as a win if
I can do it but once they're actually in
the gym they're already there so their
mind goes what the heck I'm going to
work out I won't go into it too much
here but this is an example of BJ fog's
tiny habits model and if you want to
learn more about it I'll probably do a
video in the future but I'll also link
to some resources in the blog post for
this video so the last thing I want to
mention about motivation before I talk
about apps is the act of finding ways of
exercising that are actually fun a lot
of people think exercising and working
out is strictly limited to jogging in
the treadmill or going to the gym and
lifting weights but if that's not
something you enjoy you're probably not
going to do it no matter how much
motivation you try to summon or at least
you're not going to do it as often as
you want so regardless of the schedule
you set up for actual traditional
working out find something you enjoy and
augment your exercise schedule with that
if you're in college there are probably
a bazillion intral sports leagues you
can join you can go hiking or you can do
what I do and play lots and lots of DDR
so before we finish this video and I
tell you to get off your butt and hit
the gym let's talk about a couple of
apps that can help you keep motivated to
exercise now I talk a lot about habit
RPG on this channel because I really
like it for General habit building but
I've actually sort of modifyed it and
turned it into a workout tracker as well
for my own uses if you take a look at my
habits column I have a couple of
standard habits there that I track but
for the most part I list individual
exercises and give myself credit when I
get them down to the gym if you want to
take this concept A step further then
check out fitocracy I used to use
fitocracy all the time and it's
basically the best way to turn exercise
into a video game that I've ever seen by
tracking the sets and Reps you do you
can get experience you level up and you
can also get achievements and go on
quests it's actually pretty similar to
Habit RPG but it's focused on exercise
the last one I'll mention is an app
called Fitness buddy which my friend
Youngtown told me about and if you're
looking for an app that will give you
specific workout routines and also show
you how to do specific exercises it's an
amazing resource all right so hopefully
this video will help you create more
time and motivation to exercise more in
college because seriously having your
body and mind and good working order is
the foundation to being able to use all
the other techniques I talk about on
this channel if you have other tips and
things that have worked for you that I
didn't mention in this video then feel
free to share them down in the comments
and I will see you next
week hey there thanks for watching my
video on exercising more in college now
I know this video is a bit of a
departure from the specific study
strategies I usually talk about on this
channel but if you liked it and you want
to get more tips on being an awesome
college student then hit that big red
subscribe button right there I also
wrote a free 100 plus page book on
getting better grades so if you would
like to get a copy click the picture of
the book and I'll send you one you can
also find links to any resources I
mentioned in the video by going to the
companion blog post right there and if
you missed last week's video there's a
clip of it playing so definitely check
it out lastly if you want to suggest
topics for new videos or just connect
with me then I'm @ Tom frankley on
Twitter or you can leave a comment
thanks