as you can probably tell from my
backdrop in my entire room I am a fan of
playing video games but I have a pretty
complicated relationship with video
games and I can illustrate that on
something I like to call the Workplay
compulsion scale so as you can see here
it looks like a teeter totter and if I
had my priorities in order and acted in
the way that I wanted to act on a daily
basis then I would work for a certain
amount of hours and then play video
games for a certain amount of hours and
I would be nicely placed in the middle
but unfortunately I find myself slanted
over onto the work side and my work
tends to BL lead into the time that I
would want to be gaming however this
video isn't about my particular problem
with video gaming it's about the
problems for the people on the other
side of that teeter totter the people
who find that video games start seeping
into their work time the time they
should be studying or getting homework
done if you find yourself in that area
and video games are a major distraction
to getting your work done then this
video is for you and I've got five tips
to help you start pulling yourself more
into that middle area so tip number one
and I think this is probably the most
important tip in the entire video which
is why it's going first and it's to
Simply set up an environment for for
studying that is only for studying now
if you saw my video that summarized
Marty lobell's study less study smart
lecture you'll know that I talked about
how environmental cues and the context
of the situation we're in actually
largely defines our Behavior one detail
from the lecture that I didn't talk
about in that video was a study done at
the University of Hawaii which actually
looks like this where researchers wanted
to figure out if they could improve
students grades by changing their
environment so they did one simple thing
they told students to turn their desks
around in their dorms towards one wall
and put a sticky note labeled St study
area on the lamp next to their desk the
students were instructed to only use
this desk for studying and everything
else all of the activities had to take
place somewhere else and what do you
think happened well in comparison to the
control group of students who didn't do
this the students that did do it had an
average of a 1.0 GPA increase so the
action item here for you should be
pretty clear find an area that is
different from your gaming area and do
your studying there for instance the
temptation to game out here not that big
likewise the temptation to play games in
the library or a coffee shop is probably
going to be a lot less than the
temptation to play G games in your
living room or at your computer that has
steam installed tip number two is to
increase the friction involved in
getting into a video game so the idea
here is to increase the difficulty and
the amount of steps involved into
getting into a distracting activity and
uh basically make doing your work the
more attractive option in that case so
one way you can do this is by actually
creating a different account on your
computer for work and only installing
the programs you need for work on that
computer and you can also set up
extensions like stay focused or programs
like focal filter to to reduce the
amount of distracting Webb browsing you
do as well my third tip is to Simply
game after you're done working for the
day use gaming as a reward and this kind
of goes back to the concept of
highdensity fund that I talked about in
last week's video use the anticipation
of a long gaming session later on in the
day as a motivator to get your work done
more efficiently now tip number four is
to play games that work well with your
schedule so if you're really busy and
you have a lot of studying to do then it
might not be the best idea to get
invested in a like 120 hour jrpg or a
super long wow raid on the other hand
playing a few sessions of Smash Brothers
with your friends is probably not going
to suck up a whole ton of your time so
just be mindful of the real world
commitments you have and select your
games accordingly and tip number five is
my favorite tip because it's actually
fun and it's to Simply turn your life
into a game you can actually reduce the
compulsion to play lots of video games
if your life feels like a game itself
and the best way to do this is to Simply
set goals that are specific and that
you're actually stoked to achieve now I
do this on a page on my website called
My impossible list which you can find
linked down in the description actually
and basically I break my entire life
down into different SE and set goals for
each one every time I achieve a goal I
cross it off but I also iterate on that
goal and make something a little bit
harder so I'm essentially leveling up in
every category you can also use tools
like fitocracy or habit RPG to actually
track your habits and Gain real stats
and actually kind of play a real game
while improving your life at the same
time so hopefully you'll find these five
tips useful enough to take gaming from
an unproductive distraction to a healthy
habit if you find that your own gaming
habits are still really hard to break
though there's actually some online
communities that I suggest you check out
and over on Reddit there's one called
stop gaming as well as no wow there's
also a site called quit law.com which is
specifically for people who play League
of Legends but I think it has some
useful information I'd also like to give
a quick shout out to both some of the
members in the college infogeek habit
RPG Guild and some people over at the
r/g getstudying Reddit they both helped
me flesh out the ideas for this video
and I'll link to both of them in the
companion blog post so that's it for
this video if you've got any additional
suggestions or experiences of your own
for making gaming less of a distracting
habit then let me know down in the
comments otherwise I will see you in the
next
one hey there and thanks for watching my
video on balancing gaming in your
studies now if you want to get more
videos every single week on being an
awesome college student then click that
big red subscribe button right there and
also if you want to get a free 100 plus
page book on getting awesome grades
click the picture of the book right
there and I'll send you a copy you can
also get a summary and links to any
resources I mentioned in the video will
be going to the companion blog post
right there and if you missed last
week's video there's a clip of it
playing so definitely check it out
lastly if you have any ideas for new
videos or just want to connect I'm on
Twitter at tomf Frankle or you can leave
a comment on this video thanks