a couple of weeks ago we talked about
the relationship between music and
studying and whether music is an eff of
study Aid or if it's just a distraction
and if you're like me music is probably
pretty effective for you but some days
music just doesn't help and nothing
helps and you find yourself just
completely unable to focus and maybe
during those moments you've wished there
was something you could plug into your
brain that would force you to do work
like mind control music well if books
and movies and comic books are any
indication it's probably a good thing
this stuff doesn't exist uh for example
if you remember in the fifth Harry
Potter book there is a music box that
opens up and basically hypnotizes
everyone and makes them all sluggish and
drowsy or in isue 46 of the Teen Titans
there's a villain called the Fiddler
that can play music which makes the
Titans try to kill each other so yeah
I'm pretty happy this stuff doesn't
exist mind control music aside though
what about music that can simply cause a
cognitive change and be intentionally
designed to do so we know that music
does affect your brain in certain ways
so could you design music for a specific
intended effect well if you ask certain
people the answer is going to be yes and
if you put brain music as a search term
here into YouTube You're Going to get
tons of videos promising all sorts of
benefits like increased Focus or better
sleep meditation music all kinds of
stuff now there are a lot of techniques
that people use to create this kind of
music and if you know anything about
this topic you've probably heard of one
of them which is binaural beats which
I'm going to use as the example here to
explain this stuff so a binaural beat is
an illusion actually it's just two
different tones at two different pitches
played in each ear and if you're to put
one earphone up while one was playing
you would just perceive a steady Tone If
you put the other earphone to your other
ear you would hear a tone at a different
pitch but when you listen to them both
at the same time your brain creates an
illusion of a beat oscillating back and
forth between each side of your head and
usually this oscillation is really
really fast so what does this have to do
with creating music that can help your
brain focus better or achieve some other
desired benefit well this has to do with
the fact that a lot of neural activity
is rhythmic and this activity is called
neural oscillation or in more popular
terms brain waves back in 1924 a German
psychiatrist named Hans berer invented a
device called an electroencephalogram or
EEG device which enabled the measurement
of human brain waves and it was
discovered that certain frequency ranges
of these waves are associated with
different types of cognitive activity
for instance super slow delta waves are
measured during the deepest phases of
sleep whereas higher frequency beta and
gamma waves are associated with
wakefulness and mental attentiveness
once that was known it wasn't too long
before the idea of influencing these
brain waves using external stimuli came
up and in 1934 an English researcher
named Edgar Adrien demonstrated how
using ftic simulation basically flashing
a bunch of Lights in front of somebody
at a very specific frequency could be
used to drive the brain's Alpha Waves
below or above its natural frequency
band what was happening was that the
frequency of the external stimulus was
causing the brain waves to move toward a
similar frequency they're sinking up
basically building off of that in 1949 a
researcher named William grey Walter
published a study showing that this ftic
stimulation could also cause mental and
emotional changes now in addition to fic
stimulation or is it photo stimulation I
didn't really check uh audio has also
been studied as a form of external
stimuli that can cause changes in brain
activity with regard to those binal
beats I was talking about earlier these
are only one form of auditory
stimulation that's been studied but they
seem to be the most commonly known and
the idea is about the same as with
adrianne's experiments design the beat
to oscillate at a certain frequency and
hopefully gain a desired cognitive
effect this is often known as auditory
driving so the million dollar question
is does this auditory driving actually
work can you put your earphones in turn
on a binal beach track or something
similar and then focus more effectively
well from the research I've been doing
for the past couple of weeks I had to
say that scientifically it seems like we
don't really know at this point I found
several studies using binal beats or
other techniques that did seem to have
positive results but then I found a lot
of other studies that seem to have no
results at all and in the blog post for
this video I'm going to dump a lot of
that research in case you're really
curious and you want to dig in now one
thing that we do know from those EEG
measurements EEG it's hard to say fast
uh is that audio and other external
stimuli can cause changes in the brain
the question is is can you design that
audio to cause specific beneficial
changes and right now that's unclear so
from there we get into anecdotal
territory and a lot of people do report
that this brain-enhancing music does
help them study better and then some
don't and for the people who do we
always have to consider that at least
part of the effect may be due to the
placebo effect basically people being
told that this is going to help you and
then they see a change because they're
expecting it so with that in mind here
is my personal experience with brain
music back in college I discovered binal
beats because I was basically looking
for anything that would help me study
better and they didn't work at all and
the main reason for that is they just
don't sound good to me I can hear that
pulsing back and forth and it's honestly
annoying and I think any benefit I would
have derived from that has been
overrided by the fact that I was
listening to something I would rather
not listen to so I ditched it went back
to my normal study music and that was
the rest of college near the end of last
year though my interest was renewed in
this topic when I was scrolling through
some website I can't remember which one
it was but I found a new tool called
brain.fm which creates algorithmically
generated music that's designed to help
you focus and being curious I tried it
out and I actually found myself focusing
better but moreover I didn't find myself
annoyed with the music it generated
after I tried it out I talked with a
couple of the co-founders because I was
really curious about the technology
behind what they were building and it
turns out that it does build off of some
of those older techniques I talked about
earlier in the video but they're also
doing a lot of new things one of the
main differences is that the
oscillations they build into their music
use more natural sounding instruments so
it's blended into the music a little bit
better and because they're doing so many
new things there hasn't been time to do
a whole lot of research around what
they're building though there have been
a couple of preliminary studies at
Northwestern University doing like go no
go test visual Reaction Time tests that
do have some pretty good early results
so with all that being said at this
point I can't say whether or not it's
going to be effective on a large scale
and I'm not sure if I ever will be able
to because this is weird Neuroscience
territory we're stepping into but I have
been using it myself for about two
months and uh it's still effective and
it's actually generally more effective
than normal study music for helping me
Focus so I usually use it when I'm
writing and in a few months I'm probably
going to do a full review on the channel
after I've tested it really long term
ter and know for sure that the placebo
effect has been kind of pushed off the
table in the meantime if you want to try
it out for yourself they sent me a link
that you can use to get a longer than
normal trial and I'll have that linked
up in the blog post for this video and
to be clear I don't have an affiliation
with them other than having talked with
the founders but I am cautiously
optimistic about what they're building
and after long-term testing if it works
out I would be happy to recommend it to
people in the future I'm also going to
link to a lot of those other binaural
beats and isochronic tones and brain
enhancing music that I found here on
YouTube in the blog post so if you want
to try those things out I'd be curious
to hear from you guys does this stuff
work better for you than your favorite
study music if you tend to study with
silence does it work better than that or
does it not work for you at all I'll
have a discussion thread in the College
infogate Community where you can put
your thoughts and other than that thank
you so much for watching I will see you
guys next
week hey there guys and thanks so much
for watching this video now if you want
to get new tips on being a more
effective student every single week you
can click that big red subscribe button
right there and I also wrote a free book
on earning better grades if you want to
get a copy you can click the picture of
the book and I will send you if you want
to get those music links and also links
to a lot of the research I did for this
episode which is a lot then you click
the orange logo right there to go to the
blog post and if you missed last week's
video we talked about what to do when
you have a group project and you have a
lazy member who's not pulling their
weight so check it out if you missed it
if you want to connect I'm Tom frankley
on both Instagram and Twitter or you can
leave a comment down
[Music]
below