your turn to hold the camera this time
fine what's up guys so I know a lot of
you have been asking me to do an updated
room tour and I thought it is high time
to do it because I actually just moved
to Denver which is probably one of the
biggest life changes I have ever gone
through but luckily my good friend
Martin who was holding the camera right
now is here with me so that's pretty
cool and as a result of moving here I
have a brand new room/ studio workspace
so I want to give you guys a tour and
show you some of the gear that's in it
let's go
welcome to the brand new studio so the
biggest thing about this room is that
it's no longer a room for me to really
hang out in or sleep in it is entirely a
work room at this point it's my studio
it's my editing space it's where I do a
lot of my b-roll and animations I've
been able to actually turn this space
into something that I can dedicate 100%
to creating videos and podcasts and I'm
going to show you some of the gear that
I use to make all that happen so let's
start with the desk here I think the the
most stand out part of the desk here is
these monitors which are on these arms
here so these are the Dell u2412m
monitors I got these a few years ago and
if you're looking to get monitors like
this these are excellent but there's
actually a new model called the U 1524 I
think it is and it's basically the same
price but it's better and every single
way has more ports so definitely get
that if you're looking for Dell monitors
they are each on a freedom arm from
erotech I decided on two singular arms
rather than one dual arm because the
desk goes up against the wall and I
wanted to have a little bit more
flexibility with how the arms were
structured and then let's see here what
else we got here the desk itself is the
uh Jarvis bamboo standing desk so I can
actually move it up to a standing height
I can move it down to a sitting height
and that lets me vary up my workday I
can spend some time standing I can spend
some time sitting and that is much
better for my back and my overall health
uh on the desk we have a Logitech gaming
mouse we've got a steel series mouse pad
which is my absolute favorite mouse pad
I think it's the best mouse pad that
exists on the face of the planet so
definitely get that one if you're
looking for a new mouse pad and the
razor black widow keyboard which I've
had for a few years and is still going
strong these are Mackie I think they're
called C4s and they are studio monitor
speakers so these have a very flat sound
profile and they allow me to mix audio
in a very accurate way that's good for a
lot of different types of audio systems
podcasting set up we've got a boom arm
this is I think it's a h boom arm and on
the end this boom arm there is a sh sm7b
microphone this is actually the
microphone that Michael Jackson recorded
Thriller on and is what I record all of
my podcasts and voiceovers for videos on
and that goes into a macki pro fx8 mixer
and this basically gives me fine-tuned
control over all the audio levels and
I've also got little task cam recorder
hooked up to it and this thing just lets
me take a backup recording every time
I'm making a podcast or doing an
interview so if the power goes out or
something I'm good and I've got a backup
recording one other cool little feature
this desk is that it's got this
swiveling drawer built in so I've got
quick access to the stuff I use most
often scissors pair of headphones that I
use for phone calls uh Sharpies pens
pencils got some sticky not pads in here
a pencil sharpener and I do stash some
SD cards down there for when I need them
as well and then over here we have a
flip out box cutter which is useful for
and packages come
in and then there is the chair this is
the office master om5 and it's an urg
omally designed chair I figured that if
I'm going to be spending 40 or 50 hours
a week sitting on my butt editing videos
I better be doing it in something that
is designed for keeping my back healthy
so I got this a few months ago and it is
excellent it was an excellent investment
so over here we have a curtain that
basically never moves in fact it is
attached to the wall over here I've got
my whiteboard where every single night I
write what I'm going to do the next day
so Thursday this is what I wrote last
night also got a cube organizer here
this is from Target you can get it at
pretty much any Target that you want and
this is where I store pretty much
everything that I need to access on a
regular basis so down here I've got a
lot of filming gear there's mic cables
XLR cables my DJI osmo cameras in here
uh gorilla pods in here all sorts of
cords and an iPhone mount for filming on
the iPhone top drawer you got more pens
and pencils all the like office stuff
you get from Staples pretty much a whole
lot of other kind of stuff in here extra
batteries lots of really boring stuff
but this thing is probably my favorite
thing here this is the Perplexus
ultimate and it's not really for work
but it's like my favorite toy ever and
it's just really good for taking a break
and doing something kind of tactile when
you don't want to work another thing
I'll mention about the cube organizer
here is I have this plug strip that's
actually velcro down to the surface and
this just gives me easy and instant
access to outlets for charging my camera
batteries my iPad and keeping the
shredder plugged in when I want to shred
stuff also got some Command hooks on the
wall to keep these headphones nice and
organized this is the one I use for
podcasting and this is just a pair of
headphones that I love and that Sony
doesn't make anymore so I try to keep
them in as perfect a condition as
possible and then we have the YouTube
subscriber button so let's move on to
the part that I am most excited about so
for the past 2 and 1 half years I have
had to set up and tear down some part of
my filming setup every single time I've
wanted to make a video and now I don't
have to do that because I have room for
the tripod for the boom arm for the
shotgun mic this stuff can stay set up I
can walk in here and I can film a video
just like in 20 seconds pretty much and
actually to that end one other little
piece of automation I've built into the
room is over there you can see there's
this little remote on the wall and this
actually controls some remote controlled
Outlet plugins and that controls the
video lights so if I hit one of those
buttons the video lights over there are
going to turn on and if I hit another
one these back lights behind the desk
turn on also this is another part of the
setup I'm really excited about this is
my overhead shooting setup and basically
Al what this allows me to do is slot my
camera right into this overhead hanging
uh tripod mount and that lets me do my
whiteboard animations and all sorts of
other overhead demonstrations really
easily this thing is something I built
out of stuff from Home Depot but I used
to have to fold it up and put it away
every single time I got done using it
because there was no room but now I've
got this space this is just simple
tabletop and some A-frame legs from Ikea
and that helps me keep it up at all
times over here I've also got my lenses
so I can easily swap out I probably use
two lenses or three lenses per video at
least two sometimes three and then over
here we've got the different surfaces I
use for the overhead setup so if I want
to do a wood background I can just slot
the wood right there and go to town or
maybe I want to do this nice green
pattern bam there you go or I can do
cork so I guess the last thing is the
closet here and this isn't really all
that exciting but I know some people are
going to want to see it so I'll just
show it off here this is B basically we
keeping all of the stuff that doesn't go
anywhere else in the apartment but I do
have easy access to some other things
like my toolkit so anytime something
needs fixed or upgraded all the tools I
would ever need are in here I've been
building a collection for quite a while
and now it's pretty useful now the one
thing that you don't see in here that
you've probably seen in every other
iteration in my room is my bookshelf and
because I wanted to have the tripod and
the boom arm set up all the time I
couldn't fit the bookshelf in here but
that's okay because I actually found a
better spot for it the last part out
here welcome to my brand new reading
corner I thought this was much better
use of this piece of furniture than just
sitting behind my tripod all the time
and now I've got a great spot to read
during my morning routine which I do
every single morning got a glorious
picture of Nick Offerman right there
picture of Professor Leighton back there
nice lamp and all these books that I
haven't read yet so this is where I'm
going to be spending a lot of time in
the future so guys that wraps up the
room tour hopefully you enjoyed it and
if you're you're curious about any of
the specific model numbers or you want
links to any of the gear that was on my
desk or around the room I'll link to as
much of it as I can down in the
description below now before I wrap this
video up I do want to let you know about
one other thing and that is that my
podcast the college infogeek podcast has
a YouTube channel now so if you haven't
gotten into the podcast yet there are
over 50 episodes over on the YouTube
channel I'll have that Linked In the
description down below as well and if
you like the stuff on this channel I
think you're really going to like the
podcast as well it's got a mix of fun
banter and ation but also a lot of
in-depth content sometimes I interview
other experts sometimes I just talk with
my friend Martin and we take questions
from uh you guys and sometimes we each
go and do research on a particular topic
and then come and share the lessons
we've learned and I think you're going
to get a lot out of it in any case so
definitely go check it out subscribe to
the channel if you enjoy it and if you
have questions or topics you want us to
cover on the podcast or on this channel
let me know about them down in the
comments below thanks for watching and I
will see you in the next video