Hey, what's up everybody? It's Thomas
from College Infogeeek. And you ever
just wonder like how are you going to
get all the information of these crazy
huge reading assignments in a freaking
weekend? I want to share a quote with
you that I learned over the weekend
while doing research for this video. And
it goes like this. The mark of a
successful college student is the
mastery of knowing not only what to
study, but also how to study it. And
this applies to your readings as much as
it applies to anything else in college.
So, in last week's video, I went over
some strategies that you can use to
figure out whether or not you actually
need to do a reading assignment at all.
Now, in this video, I want to start
focusing on how you should actually
tackle the reading assignments that you
do need to do. And I have three main
goals that I want you to keep in mind
here. Number one, you want to learn the
right information from your readings.
Obviously, you can't learn every single
thing in the book. So, you want to
figure out what is important and get
that into your brain. Number two, you
want to retain that information for as
long as you can and be able to use it
later. And number three, you want to
reduce your study time and the amount of
time you have your nose stuck in the
book. So to start improving in all of
these areas, the first thing that I want
you to think about is the why. Why are
you doing this reading? Now, a lot of
people would say you're reading to
learn. And obviously, yes, that's the
point of the education. But I think
there's another more immediately
practical reason that you're doing a
reading, and that is how you're going to
be assessed on that reading. Being a
strategic reader means using different
strategies for different reading
purposes. And those purposes are defined
by the assessments you're going to face
in class, which lead back to your
immediate goal of earning awesome
grades. Now, most students tackle their
reading assignments like zombies. They
look at the reading assignment and they
go, "Must run my eyes over x number of
pages by tomorrow night. That's it.
Don't be a reading zombie. Otherwise,
your exams are going to turn into a
chainsaw." Know what it is that your
brain needs to pull out of the reading
and focus on that. So, here are four
common reasons that you might do a
textbook reading. Number one, you're
going to be facing down a multiplechoice
test. Number two, you're going to have
to do an essay, actually creating
something from scratch in your own
words. Number three is the evaluation of
data in labs, which applies to more
technical and scientific majors. And
number four is the summarization of
research for class presentations and
reports. The type of assessment that you
have to do will dictate what kind of
information you need to pull out of your
readings. For instance, if you're going
to have to do a multiple choice test,
then you're going to want to focus on
the details of the reading assignments,
taking smart, concise notes about all
the little things in a class and then
turning those into questions that you
can study rapid fire later on. But if
you're in a class where you have to
write essays, then thorough knowledge of
the main ideas is more important, and
you're going to want to focus more on
summarization and making sure that you
can communicate what you learned in your
own words. So, there's a tip from the
video I did last week on figuring out
whether or not you even need to do a
reading assignment that applies
perfectly here as well. and that is to
gauge your classes. As the semester goes
on, be mindful of what's in the syllabus
and what your professor generally uses
to assess you and then apply that
knowledge to your readings. Now, this
will take practice, but as time goes on,
you're going to find that this
mindfulness really pays off in the time
it saves you and the clarity it gives
you when you're looking at your book.
So, once you've gauged those classes and
figured out the type of information you
want to pull from your reading, how do
you actually go about doing that
reading? Well, to start out, let me give
you a universal tip that applies to any
reading you do, and it's this. Don't
read your textbooks like you read a
newspaper. People who read the newspaper
aren't reading to apply what they're
learning. They're just reading to get
the gist of the day's events. You're not
reading for gists. You're reading for
application. Also, don't expect that
you're going to learn efficiently by
just reading and rereading passages over
and over again. The writer Virginia
Folks said that how often you read
something is immaterial. How you read it
is crucial. Think of a book like an art
museum. You can walk through the Met in
New York 10 times, look at all the
paintings each time you go through, and
still know next to nothing about any of
the art there. You might know the
general layout where certain pieces are,
but if I ask you for details, which
artist created this painting, where was
this dog thing sculpted? You won't have
a clue. Books are really the same.
Passively running your eyes over the
pages is like casually strolling through
an art museum and not actually studying
any of the pieces. It's actually worse
because the brain is better at
remembering emotionally evocative
pictures and imagery than it is at
remembering squiggly, arbitrary lines on
paper. So instead, try to read in the
same way that you talk with a friend who
challenges you intellectually. You
listen eagerly. You contribute your own
words to the conversation and eventually
both of you create information that
comes together to make something new.
This is called active reading and it's
crucial for being able to retain what
you learn from your textbooks and be
able to apply it later on. In my next
video, I'm going to go over a framework
of specific techniques that you can try
out to start using active reading. But
to round this video out, I want to leave
you with a technique that you can use to
create a small win in your studies. And
here it is. Create two different habits
for your textbook readings. The first
one is going to focus on just getting
you to read consistently. And the second
one is going to focus on getting you to
start using active reading instead of
passive reading. So the first habit I
think you should try out is reading
daily. And this might mean planning
ahead in advance what you're going to
read for a certain week and maybe even
reading some outside material if you
finish everything. But it's all about
getting into the habit of reading every
single day, making it a consistent
effort. And for the second habit, try to
write down a small amount of notes for
each reading you do or create a small
summary for each reading. It doesn't
have to be anything large. You just want
to get into the habit of doing it and
being more actively involved in your
reading. Now, with both these habits,
you can experiment with making them
either input-based or outputbased.
Input-based habits have a fixed amount
of effort that you have to put into
them. So, read for 15 minutes. It's only
15 minutes of effort and then you're
done. On the flip side, output-based
habits are based on making something
concrete. So, write one page of notes
could be an output-based habit. And the
amount of time and effort you need to
put into it isn't fixed. Personally, I
use both of these types of habits in my
own reading. So, for my actual reading
habit, I use an input-based goal. Read
for 15 minutes every single day. And
then once I've gotten into that, I
usually read for longer and I start
getting more engaged. And then I use an
output-based call, which is to write
half a page of notes on what I'm reading
to make sure that I'm actively learning.
Whichever type you choose, it's also
important to build a small reward into
your habit. And getting good grades is a
good reward, but it's something that's a
little too far off to really count. So,
I would say find something else that
rewards you for getting the reading done
every single day. For me, that's ticking
off a daily inhabit RPG, which I've made
a little bit more valuable by creating a
challenge in the College Infogeeek
Guild. And if you want to join that, you
can go to the companion blog post for
this video, which you'll find linked
down in the description. Otherwise, you
could do something else like watching an
episode of your favorite show on
Netflix, playing a video game, or
something else fun. Just make sure that
you're building this loop of here's a
cue to do my reading. I'm going to do
the reading and take the notes and then
give myself a small reward to reinforce
the positive uh feeling I get from doing
that reading. So, that's it for this
video. If you want to get my tips on
active reading, which will come in the
next video, then make sure you subscribe
to this channel and you'll get those
right when they come out. Otherwise, I
will see you in that next
video. Hey, thanks for watching my
video. If you enjoyed it, then you can
support me by giving it a like on
YouTube or sharing it with a friend. If
you want to get more videos just like
this every single week on being a better
college student, then click the
subscribe button right there. If you
missed the last video, a clip of it is
playing right below there, and you can
click that to watch it. Also, you can
get a summary and links to anything I
mentioned in the video by going to the
companion blog post, which you can find
by clicking on the orange logo right
there. Lastly, if you want to get a free
chapter of my book when it comes out,
then you can click that book and
subscribe to the College of Bookkeep
newsletter. You'll also get notified
when new podcast episodes and blog posts
come out every week. Lastly, if you have
ideas for new videos or you just want to
connect with me, you can do so on
Twitter or leave a comment on this
video. Thanks.