okay i'm gonna do the entire video
balancing these on one finger
never mind hey what is going on guys so
today i thought i would do another book
recommendation video but i do want to
tell you up front that this is a little
bit different than my previous book
recommendation video which was all about
books i think that
every student should read by contrast
this is a list of the best books that i
personally read this year so while every
book on this list is educational and i
found to be very useful i'm not
necessarily going to say that you
have to read this book if you're a
student but i do think that you'll find
a lot of the books on this list
interesting no matter who you are case
in point
the first book on my list is the code
book by simon singh now this is a book
that teaches you all about the history
and the ins and outs of cryptography the
science of
encoding and decoding messages the book
basically gives you a comprehensive
overview of this topic and it starts all
the way back in roman times and goes
over caesar ciphers and mono alphabetic
substitution ciphers
moves on to poly alphabetic substitution
ciphers and then goes into the modern
day and covers things like
diffie-hellman key exchange and public
private key cryptography
and even quantum cryptography now the
book is lacking a little bit in
practical details about how to secure
your online life though we did do a
podcast episode all about that
you can check out in the description
down below but it is an absolutely
fascinating read and i could not put it
down once i started reading it
second on my list is essentialism the
discipline pursuit of less by greg
mccune
and we did have to look up how to
pronounce that on fourvo before making
this video so i'm pretty sure i have
that right but if you're irish then you
can correct me that is an irish name
right
no idea boy now i have to look at that
so one of them said
this book talks all about how to
prioritize the most important things
that you're doing in your life and focus
on those things how to work without
distraction
and this book was really important for
me because as an entrepreneur and a
creative person
i get a ton of ideas and if i don't keep
my mind restrained a little bit
i'm easily able to just go off and get
distracted on a new idea before
finishing something that i'm already
working on
so reading this book really shifted my
mindset and made me take single-minded
focus on an important task a lot more
seriously than i had in the past
and this was one book that we did talk
about on the podcast so if you want an
overview or summary of it i'll have that
linked in description down below
the third book on my list is a big one
debt the first five thousand years by
david graber was a
fascinating read and admittedly i'm
actually not done with this book yet but
i am about halfway through
and it is really really interesting if
you have any sort of inclination towards
reading about
economics i actually heard about this
book back when i watched the money
episode of the crash course world
history series with john green and the
idea that explorers
is really fascinating basically in
classical economics they teach this idea
that before money
there was barter basically before you
had coins to trade with you took your
cow to the market and you lopped off
part of its leg and you traded that for
some rice but the thing is while this
theory is taught in most
intro economics textbooks
anthropologists have found almost
no record of any society that ever used
pure barter before the development of
money instead they used informal debt
bonds which eventually became formalized
by the development of money and
ious and banking and so forth anyway
again this is not the kind of book
that's gonna help you balance your own
checkbook or save more money efficiently
but it is a fascinating introduction
into how economics
really works next up on my list is the
elon musk biography by ashley vance
and you may have seen this one coming
since i did make an elon musk video
pretty recently i've been getting more
and more into reading biographies in the
past couple of years i've read
biographies on jeff bezos on steve jobs
and on elon musk and i have to say the
one on elon musk inspired me the most
and i came away with more respect for
him than i did for the other two
obviously all three of these men are or
were wildly successful and they all
definitely had glaring flaws that i
don't want to emulate but out of the
three i came away with the feeling that
elon musk has this just
driving motivation to improve humanity
as a whole
that's the reason i made my video on
musk in the first place and listening to
his biography because this is one that i
did listen to as an audiobook
was really motivating for me it made me
want to put more effort into my own work
book number five on my list is the big
short by michael lewis now if you've
seen any of my conversations with my
friend taha on twitter you will know
that the big short is
my favorite movie of all time and
earlier this year after watching the
movie for probably the third time
i decided it was high time that i
actually read the book that it was based
on
and this book is an excellent overview
of exactly
why the financial crisis of 2008
happened so if you have any interest
in recent history and economics and why
the markets all crashed the way they did
and how corrupt the system really was
this book is a fascinating read and it's
honestly a lot of fun to read as well
though it will probably also make you
mad
all right book number six on my list is
how to not be wrong the power of
mathematical thinking by jordan
ellenberg like the title implies this is
a book about math
but before you go clicking out of this
video if you don't like math it is not a
math book you're not going to have to
work on problems
it is a simple introduction to certain
math concepts in fact he has one page
that teaches you calculus
in one page at least the fundamental
concepts of it and moreover this book
spends a lot of time talking about
statistics and how statistics are
misinterpreted or misused by the media
or by people who have an agenda to
further so by reading this book even if
you don't go pick up a math minor
university or study the concepts further
it is going to give you a more intuitive
understanding of statistics and you're
going to be able to
more accurately interpret the ones you
see in your everyday life
book number seven on my list is the war
of art by stephen pressfield and this is
another book that we covered on the
podcast this year and it is
probably the best book i have ever read
for when you are struggling with
procrastination
this book is basically a meditation on
the work of an artist
the daily consistent work put in over
years and years
it deals a lot with the concept of
resistance and how to defeat it and
honestly if you have a lot of trouble
putting in consistent daily work into
things that you're striving to do
this is a really good read book number
eight on my list is kitchen confidential
by anthony bourdain and i picked this
book up because as you might have heard
my previous video i have been really
into cooking recently now this book
while wildly entertaining is not a
how-to on the science of cooking there
actually is a book called the science of
cooking which i also picked up but i am
not done with yet
but this book is more of an expose on
the life of a professional cook and if
you've ever watched any of anthony
bourdain's tv shows before you will know
that he is an incredibly
entertaining guy and that definitely
transfers over to his writing now i will
say that this book did teach me a couple
of things which is why it's on this list
if it was just entertaining i probably
wouldn't have put it on there and
actually has a chapter that talks about
why restaurant food tastes different
than the food you make at home
and he also talks a little bit about
some of the basic tools you can add to
your kitchen to be a better cook
yourself but for the most part the book
is mainly full of stories of bourdain's
time as a cook and eventually a chef
and because it's anthony bourdain and
because he does narrate the audiobook i
highly recommend
listening to it rather than reading it
and finally the ninth book on my list is
good to great by jim collins and this
book was really useful to me as an
entrepreneur because it's all about how
companies go from
good or mediocre to great the entire
book is based on a five-year long study
that looked at data from
hundreds of different companies and
identified the ones that spent a really
long time in the mediocre zone
and then finally had a transition point
to greatness that was sustained and i
took a lot of lessons away from this
book that i tried to apply to my
own work into my own company but one of
the most important was the concept of
level 5
leadership the book explains that a
level 5 leader is somebody who embodies
two
incredibly important characteristics
first they have an indomitable will
and work ethic they're willing to put in
whatever it takes to further the goals
of the company
but at the exact same time they are
humble they live by that excellent quote
from harry truman it's amazing what you
can accomplish if you do not care who
gets the credit
and after i read that i took that to
heart i realized that i run a business
where my face is basically on
everything but there are a lot of
elements that i have been able to let go
that have actually improved because i've
done that so guys that is my list of the
best books that i read this year and i
would love to hear from you
what are the best books that you read
this year let me know down in the
comments i'll also have all these books
linked in the description below so you
can check them out if you want
and for the ones that we did happen to
analyze on the podcast i will have links
for those podcast episodes as well
beyond that if you enjoyed this video
you can give it a thumbs up and you can
also subscribe right there if you want
to get notified when i publish new
videos and you can also click right
there if you want to get a free copy of
my book on how to earn better grades you
can also find our latest podcast episode
right there where we recapped 2017 and
kind of did a little year in review
and if you want to find one more video
on this channel click right there
thanks for watching and i will see you
in the next video