this video is sponsored by brilliant be
one of the first two hundred to sign up
its link below to get 20% off your
annual premium subscription it all
sounds so simple sit down and do the
work but it isn't is it
ever since you merged your workspace
with your living space ever since the
days begin to bleed into one another an
undifferentiated cycle light dark ever
since your social interactions move to
small fake islands you haven't been able
to focus
Shia's impassioned calls to action fail
history and you're starting to wonder if
you'll ever be able to concentrate or
get anything worthwhile done ever again
this is really dramatic isn't it okay so
I've heard this a lot lately it is way
harder to stay focused when you're
working at home versus your office or a
coffee shop or wherever it is that you
normally work the lack of separation
between your work and your personal life
not to mention lots of additional
distractions floating around means that
your home is kind of like the final boss
of difficult workspaces
well now that probably be a Chucky
Cheese actually but still today I want
to talk about how you can actually stay
focused on your work not to mention get
started on it in the first place
when you're working from home and first
we need to talk about intentionality
potentially the most useful thing you
can do when you sit down to work is set
a strong intention first if you're
anything like me I'm sure you can think
back to a time when you sat down and
instead of working intentionally you
found yourself bouncing between mostly
useless busy work tasks things like
answering your email or checking your
credit score I was even possible these
tasks are easy and they give you an
immediate feeling of accomplishment so
they're tempting to work on but they
also caused you to procrastinate on the
work that you really should be doing the
work that's truly meaningful to you so
really they often end up being a net
negative and setting a strong intention
before you work helps you to avoid them
at least until the real work is done now
one useful way of setting intention
is to follow the rule of three this is a
concept for Chris Bailey's book the
productivity project and it's really
simple when you're writing out your
daily plan choose no more than three
meaningful tasks that you intend to get
done and if your write your daily lists
on a whiteboard like I do then you might
want to tweak how you use it by writing
these three intentions at the top and
then listing any smaller tasks below
them in a deep-fryer our ties way don't
worry about those until you get the main
intentions taken care of then when it's
time to sit down for a session of
focused work look at your list and
choose just one item to work on really
mentally commit to devoting this working
session only to that item and just like
that you now have a strong intention
that will help to guide you and keep you
on task or at least you would if you
happen to be sitting in an empty room
and like a monastery with no phone or
internet access or anything else to
distract you but since you're at home I
would wager that your environment is
absolutely teeming with distractions and
if your intentions are gonna be
translated into action
then these need to be dealt with there's
just no getting around it and that has
to deal with how your brain is wired the
human brain has evolved over millions of
years to be a highly sensitive
instrument ever attentive to the small
changes in a constantly shifting and
often dangerous environment and while
this has enabled the very survival of
our species it has also made a lot of
people very angry and has it been widely
regarded as a bad move and that is not
least of which because it renders us
easily distracted when we're trying to
do complex work even if we set a strong
intention beforehand because meaningful
work is hard because it requires us to
really tax our higher brain functions we
are naturally resistant to doing it and
will take any excuse to fixate on
something else additionally our brains
also have what's called a built-in
novelty bias even when we're not
resisting difficult tasks we are drawn
to new things kind of like flies to a
light bulb an analogy can be found in an
observation that I made back when I was
in middle school see when I was a
student I used to carry a pack of
chewing gum in my pocket for you know
myself and any time that I would get a
piece of gum out again for myself any
one of my classmates who saw
pack of gum come out of my pocket would
stop what they were doing and instantly
become a mooch I will literally die if
you do not give me a piece of that right
now and saying the word no to any of
these classmates was like hitting him in
the face with a brick the wounded looks
in their eyes told me that in denying
them that stick a big red eye had ripped
apart their dreams torn their hopes to
ribbons and extinguished every spark of
happiness and joy that had kept them
pushing forward in this cruel cruel
world thus far and yet seconds before
this exchange would happen not one of
those classmates was thinking about
chewing gum hadn't even crossed their
mind and this is how our brains work we
have this novelty bias but of course a
novel object has to be brought to our
attention for it to be engaged at a site
at a mind it's why marketers and
advertisers talk so much about the ADA
framework attention interest desire and
action it's the order of operations that
governs most the actions we take
including the ones that lead us to
indulging in distractions also if you
don't you big read then fortunately you
can use this knowledge of human
psychology to your advantage if you know
that being merely exposed to a potential
distraction is gonna put you aboard the
Bata Express on a one-way journey to
wasting the rest of the day and look at
more cat pictures than you probably need
to then all you need to do is ensure
that you aren't exposed in the first
place the entire house in other words
remove any potential distractions before
you start working dealing with them
ahead of time is infinitely easier than
trying to fight them in the moment I
swear I'm just getting footage to make
this point more visual seeks hours later
no you're not always going to be able to
do this Chris Bailey's book hyper focus
breaks distractions down into four
different categories based on whether or
not you have control over them and
whether you find them fun or annoying
and those are you have no control over
like loud colleagues construction noises
or calls from your mom are hard to plan
for ahead of time the best you can do is
to deal with them while keeping your
original intention in mind and then get
contract as quickly as possible but the
distractions that you can control can
also be dealt with in advance and let's
start with your phone because it's
probably the worst offender now in the
past I have been a bit soft on phones
put it on Do Not Disturb I said use
features like focus mode on Android or
screen time on iOS to simply limit the
time when you can access distracting
apps but you know what I think it's time
to get a little bit tougher if you don't
need your phone for your work and let's
face it you probably don't then keep it
out of arms reach personally I've been
setting my phone they do have a stirred
mode for most a day and also putting it
on the printer at the other side of my
office so again it's out of arms reach I
also have it set so my favorite contacts
can get through doing it disturbs my
phone does actually work as a phone but
everyone else gets silenced along with
all app notifications your computer is
also a huge potential distraction and
that is mostly due to the fact that it's
connected to the Internet and if that's
a particularly big problem for you then
you might want to actually disconnect it
when you don't need it either by
disabling your Wi-Fi or by actually
unplugging the ethernet cable burn that
there is one rule that I highly
recommend you follow don't keep email or
any instant messaging apps like slack or
telegram or whatever Microsoft teams
whatever it is don't keep any of these
open while you work these are constant
sources of novelties they are
distracting by nature but they also come
with the additional social pressure that
you feel would respond to a message when
it comes in personally I'm part of
several different slack groups and over
the past few months I've gotten into the
bad habit of keeping them open while I
was working and I realized that I would
sometimes spend entire workdays just
chatting with people so now I only check
slack an email at specific times of the
day and I respond everything in batches
to remove other computer-based
distractions you can look into getting a
distraction blocker which will block any
websites or apps that you put on to a
block list I use one called freedom
which can be set up to block sites
during pre scheduled windows of time
throughout the day or enabled for timed
work sessions now I'm not gonna spend a
ton of extra time talking about apps
here but if you're looking for other
ones that can help you focus I've
recently published a page on my website
called the focus toolkit which
recommends several more
have that linked in the description down
below lastly since you're at home ask
yourself there any other potential
sources of distraction that are
particularly that you should address
like maybe your game consoles or a
temptation well if that's the case put
the Power Core in another room until
you're done with your work make it
inconvenient to access them so you don't
do it impulsively I'd also recommend
keeping a distraction journal nearby and
whenever something pulls you away from
your work make a note of what it was and
why it pulls you away so you can figure
out how to eliminate it in advance the
next time you sit down now once you've
taken care of all those distractions the
last thing you need to figure out how to
do is to get rid of the resistance you
feel towards starting and this is
serious mental resistance towards
difficult tasks is a big issue for just
one example there was once a study done
on people who felt high levels of
anxiety towards doing math and the study
found that the mere anticipation of
having to do math caused increased brain
activity and some specific regions of
the brain namely those that deal with
threat detection and even physical pain
and what this illustrates is that
certain parts of our brain view
difficult mentally taxing tasks in the
same way they would view touching a hot
stove room fortunately this version that
you feel towards difficult tasks really
only affects you at the beginning once
you get into it you build up momentum
that overcomes that resistance so all
you need to do is to reduce your
resistance enough to get started and you
do this by making the task feel less
daunting now the first method for doing
that is to break down your tasks in
other words narrow the scope of your
intention earlier on the video we talked
about setting an intention by choosing
one of the three meaningful tasks on
your daily plan but if those tasks feel
too big then simply break one down into
smaller chunks that way you can pick one
of those chunks and set it as your
intention instead
for example when I sit down to write I
never set my intention as write a video
script instead I create multiple
subheadings based on an outline and then
I sit down with the intention of writing
a draft just a single section now if I
push forward two more sections during
that writing session great but that is
not my intention when I'm starting out
secondly commit to working only for a
specific period of time and make it low
enough that you no longer feel
so if 30 minutes feels like too much
then go for 15 now whatever time you
decide to go with set it on a timer or
at least put it on a timer app using one
of these tools creates a little bit of
external pressure so there's one less
thing you have to rely on your willpower
your internal self-control to handle so
now you have all the tools and the
concepts that you should need to sit
down and do some focused work but if
you'd like to see an example here is
exactly how I do it first I will look at
my whiteboard which now lists my top
three intentions of separately four
other smaller tasks and if each of these
is too big for a single work session I
will choose part of one and set my
intention based on that next I choose
how long I'm going to work and lately
that has been about thirty five minutes
for a session at least for starters
which means the very next thing I do is
set a 35 minute block timer on freedom
and choose a block list that supports
the task for writing a video or for
doing research as my morning block list
which blocks slack email all social
media YouTube and any busy work sites
like Google Analytics which are a pretty
big distraction for me personally
then I'll choose something to listen to
which slightly has been either the focus
sessions on brain FM or my Sunday still
a playlist on Spotify which I'll link to
down below and finally I set an actual
timer and littlemack tool bar app called
be focused this takes all of 30 seconds
and in that time I've done everything we
mentioned here I've set an intention
I've removed all distractions ahead of
time and I've eliminated my brains of
version 2 starting by choosing a
manageable time for my timer and I found
that doing these few things and nabel's
me to stay focused for much longer and
helps me to be a lot more productive and
it makes sense right once you've taken
the big problem that seems so difficult
to solve the problem of not being able
to focus and broken it down you're left
with just a few smaller easier to solve
problems and these quick actions neatly
take care of each one and it's worth
remembering that all problems are like
this once you've broken them down into
smaller parts you start to see little
angles of attack that you can take for
applying useful solutions and doing this
is a skill that you can get better at
through practice and one great resource
for getting that practice is brilliant
the math science and computer science
courses on brilliant are all built to
engage your problem-solving abilities
as they quickly throw you into
challenges that force you to really
interact with the concepts you're
learning and not only is learning with
brilliant help me to become a better
problem-solver since you're spending the
majority of your time actively solving
problems but it can also help me to get
ahead and understand the world more
thoroughly brilliants library features
more than 60 in-depth courses with a
full math suite that covers everything
from basic number theory to high-level
probability along with science and
computer science courses and that
includes a new course on neural networks
which are a fundamental part of
artificial intelligence
so to start learning and building your
problem-solving skills today head on
over - brilliant
org slash Thomas Frank and sign up link
will be in the description down below
and if you're one of the first 200
people to do that you're even gonna get
20% off your annual premium subscription
so that is it thank you so much for
watching and if you'd like this video
definitely hit that like button to show
YouTube's algorithm what's up you may
also want to go follow me over on
Instagram because today I've actually
put up a little bonus video with an
additional tip for dealing with a
particular type of distraction that I
know a few of you deal with on a regular
basis so check that out link will be in
the description down below otherwise you
can subscribe right there or check out
one more video on this channel right
over here probably I think this is where
the button is going to be yeah smash
your face into it and watch some more
videos dude otherwise go do whatever you
want because as always I'm not your dad