at some point in your life you've
probably heard about the concept of
aam's Razor which states that when you
have multiple competing hypotheses you
should take the one that makes the
fewest assumptions because generally
speaking the simplest answer is the one
that's most likely to be correct but
aam's Razer isn't the only mental razor
you should keep up in your brain toolbox
there's another one called handens Razer
and this one deals with the intentions
of other people handens Razer states
that you should never attribute to
malice that which can be adequately
explained by stupidity and while this is
kind of a tongue-and-cheek concept
except I also think there is a lot of
truth to it and I've tried really hard
to integrate it into my own mindset on a
day-to-day basis and I think doing so
makes me an overall happier person by
making sure my attitude is set correctly
a few months ago I read a book called
the happiness equation by a guy named
Neil Pasa and in this book Neil argues
that happiness is 90% attitude and only
10% circumstance and when I look back at
my own life I agree with this when I
look back six or seven years I was
definitely less successful as a freshman
College I had less money I had a lot
more uncertainty but I wasn't unhappy
and I don't think that I'm a whole lot
happier on a datto day basis now than I
was back then because my attitude was
similar both now and then and when I'm
thinking about these concepts of
happiness and attitude and looking at
them through the lens of dealing with
other people as handland Razer leads me
to do I'm reminded of a quote by the
Roman Emperor Marcus aelius which I
really want to share with you guys today
now in Roman history aelius is known as
the last of the five good emperors and
while he was definitely a great ruler he
was also a great philosopher in the
philosophy of stoicism and his writings
which have been collected in the book
meditations are where this quote comes
from so in book two of meditations
Aurelius writes when you wake up in the
morning tell yourself the people I deal
with today will be meddling ungrateful
arrogant dishonest jealous and Surly
they are like this because they can't
tell good from evil but I have seen the
beauty of good and the ugliness of you
and I've recognized that the wrongdoer
has a nature related to my own not of
the same blood or birth but of the same
mind and possessing a share of the
Divine and so none of them can hurt me
no one can implicate me in ugliness nor
can I feel angry at my relative or hate
him we were born to work together like
feet hands and eyes like the two rows of
teeth upper and lower to obstruct each
other is unnatural to feel anger at
someone to turn your back on him these
are
obstructions I think this is a really
powerful quote no want to give you my
little interpretation of it here
basically that 2016 Thomas Frank version
2,000 years later so when somebody is
being jealous or being rude or coming at
you in any sort of negative way you can
realize that you are of the same nature
you are both imperfect human beings
going through imperfect circumstances
within this world and when you realize
that you can root yourself like a tree
and bend not break because you realize
that whatever they're going through that
is most likely what's causing them to
act this way and once you do that number
one it can set your attitude and make
you a happier person overall because
you've let the negativity wash over you
instead of fuel you and make you react
in a negative way yourself but number
two it can let you get to the other part
of human nature which is to cooperate
with your fellow human beings so
hopefully you found this quote helpful
and insightful like I did and if you
want to read the entirety of meditations
which actually isn't all that long you
can find the whole thing online for free
because it is 2,000 years old and hence
in the public domain so I'm going to
have a link down in the description
below if you're curious you can find
that down there also in the description
you'll find another video I did on
Market aelius which was on
self-discipline so check it out if
you've missed it if you enjoyed this
video and you want to see more you can
click the Subscribe button right there
to get new content on being a more
effective student every single week and
you can also click right there to get a
free copy of my book on earning better
grades alternatively if you want to
watch another video you can click right
there to find one that'll probably
interest you and you'll find more
additional resource links down the
description below the like button which
you can hit if you want to support this
channel thanks for watching I appreciate
you guys and I will see you next week