hey what's going on guys so it has come
to one of those fairly infrequent points
in my life where I start to reevaluate
some of the tools that I'm using to get
my work done and this time around my
critical eye has fallen on the apps that
hold my thoughts and machinations
I like that words a good word
machinations anyway yes it is time to
talk about note-taking apps because
after about a full week of let's be
honest here far more research than I
should have done for this topic I am now
ready to present to you my top 10
note-taking apps in 2019 now before we
dive in I do want to talk a little bit
about my criteria for this list first
the apps on this list primarily use text
as their input method because I can type
a lot faster than I can write and I want
to be able to type and get data out at
the speed at which I think so what we're
gonna talk about apps like Evernote and
OneNote which can support drawing to an
extent we're not gonna focus on apps
that primarily use handwriting as their
method of input like note shelf two for
the iPad plus a lot of those apps have
integrations with Evernote anyway
secondly every applicant to talk about
here has some form of cross-platform
availability not every app and list is
available on every platform but nothing
on this list is available on only one OS
and finally a criteria number three
which I find to be the most important
criteria I don't think an app is a
note-taking app unless it combines its
note-taking or editor area with its UI
for browsing files or notes I think this
is crucial for a note-taking app because
I'm constantly referencing different
notes searching for things and I want to
have all that available in one window so
that means apps like Google Docs and
Microsoft Word and Dropbox paper all not
going to make the cut here though I do
have to admit the Dropbox paper in
particular has probably the best writing
experience in a writing app that I've
ever tried though we do have one app on
this list that does come very close to
that level of greatness so stay tuned
for that app before we get to that one
though we do have to go through the
other entries on my list and where
better to start than with Evernote ah
yes
Evernote the granddaddy of syncing and
note-taking apps I have been using
Evernote for darn near nine years at
this point and I have to admit that it's
a very powerful tool that I basically
can't get myself to break away from it's
got a pretty capable rich text editor
the ability to share notebooks with
people it's got tags the ability to save
searches and a ton of different
integrations with other apps
it also features optical character
recognition
which means you can scan in images with
text and it can make that text
searchable and you can also annotate
images in the app as well but for all
its strengths Evernote frustrates me and
that's primarily because you cannot
create nested hierarchies of notebooks
you can do notebooks and you can do
notebook stacks but that's it
now some people out there like the
writer Michael Hyatt for example
advocate using a tag based structure to
gain that hierarchy instead but that
doesn't really work because on the
Evernote mobile apps those tags are not
going to show in their hierarchy they're
all alphabetical so it kind of breaks
down still Evernote is incredibly
powerful is available on basically every
platform and because of those reasons I
am continuing to use it at least for
certain parts of my workflow even though
I have many other options in 2019
speaking of other options let's now talk
about OneNote Microsoft OneNote is
probably the closest competitor to
Evernote in terms of features as our
gonna find similar image support optical
character recognition the ability to
annotate images and honestly the editor
area is a lot more flexible and
customizable than Evernote is
additionally Microsoft OneNote is free
like actually free the only way you'd
ever pay for Microsoft OneNote is if you
decided to upgrade your onedrive storage
as that's the only way they ever charge
you money they just use onedrive for
their storage that being said I
personally just can't get into OneNote I
know a lot of people out there love it
it's incredibly powerful which is why
it's on my list but it doesn't work for
me because you cannot sort notes within
your notebooks by date modified date
created or alphabetically you can only
drag them around like their actual note
cards or pages in a notebook and that
combined with limited tagging
capabilities and the same number of
organizational levels of hierarchy as
you get in Evernote you don't get more
makes OneNote kind of a no-go for me
personally that brings us over to bear
which is an absolutely beautiful app
that I wish that I could use as a daily
driver in my workflow but bear is a Mac
and iOS exclusive and that's kind of a
bummer because I also use Windows on a
daily basis alongside my back and iPhone
that being said if you are a Mac and
iPhone only kind of person bear is
definitely worth your consideration this
is primarily because unlike Evernote and
OneNote bear has a beautiful hybrid
markdown editor and if you're not
familiar with markdown it's a markup
language so it allows you to format your
text as you type by putting different
symbols around your text so for example
you could put two stars around
word to bold that word now a lot of
markdown editors force you to write in
plain text and then you can only preview
your formatted text but bear doesn't do
that and actually format your text as
you write which I really really like
additionally bear also has a pretty
interesting organizational system that
does let you create as many levels of
hierarchy as you like and they use tags
to achieve this by typing hash tags in
your document then using slashes to
create additional tags beyond it you can
create your own organizational structure
now some people don't like having tags
right in the editor window like that but
some people might not mind that and I
also have to give a shout out to their
archive feature which lets you archive
notes and take them out of search and
your organizational hierarchy but not
delete them of course if you are an
apple exclusive kind of person then we
do have to consider Apple's own notes
program mainly because it's free and
unlike bear if you happen to not have
access to an Apple computer at some
point or you're a part-time windows guy
like me you can't at least access your
notes at icloud.com
now though Apple Notes doesn't have the
awesome hyper markdown capabilities of
bear or some other apps are going to
talk about it does have really nice
formatting tools and to my eyes the
default formatting looks better than it
does on Evernote additionally yep you
guessed it you can indeed create your
own nested list of hierarchical folders
and I love in that feature moving on to
the next item on our list we are now at
Google keep which is a pretty nice and
simple note-taking app that's available
in the browser and also on pretty much
all of your devices as well now when I
was testing Google keep the number one
word that kept coming up to my mind was
simplicity it's a very simple
note-taking app there is simple but
effective formatting options and you can
even change the background color of your
notes to visually distinguish them the
problem for me though is there's only
one level of tags that you can create
you cannot create a hierarchical level
of basically anything so there's no
hierarchical organization so I guess if
you're gonna use Google keep as a
note-taking app you're gonna want to
rely mostly on their search function and
I guess with it being Google that search
function is probably pretty good
but that being said since it lacks true
organizational hierarchy I don't see
this as a viable alternative to Evernote
or OneNote or anything more complex but
if you want a scratch pad for taking
notes and setting reminders for later
Google key could be a good bet that
brings us over to notion and I know a
lot of you guys were waiting for me to
talk about notion it's definitely the
app that I get the most questions about
these days and for good reason because
notion is
could be powerful it's definitely the
most flexible tool on this list allowing
you layout pages however you want to
create an infinite hierarchy
organization on the sidebar and even
interlink between pages easily it's also
got a great hybrid markdown editor
that's very similar the one you're gonna
find in bear though it does have some
quirks that keep me from really loving
it such as the fact that you cannot
precisely select text if it goes outside
a single block of information but my
gripes about the editor aside notion can
do things that no other app can do
that's mainly because the combination of
a couple of different features first
their table feature is actually a
database feature so every row at a table
actually links to its own page and
secondly they've got a templating
feature that allows you to make
basically anything into a template and
I've combined these two features to
build notion out into an incredibly
powerful video management platform that
has made our editing process so much
smoother so in one area of the app I've
got a database with all of our videos
who's sponsoring them there publish
dates all kinds of good information like
that but if you click into any video
you'll see there's a very well laid out
template that allows for us to create a
b-roll database a script and also has
some checklists that are automatically
populated every single time we need to
do a video so for very complicated
processes like going through the
publishing process we can just go to
that automatically generated checklist
and make sure nothing gets left behind
now like I said I get a lot of questions
about notion over on Twitter and on
Instagram so if you guys want to see a
more detailed notion video on this
channel definitely let me know in the
comments down below right now the
verdict is out on if it's a great
note-taking app but it's definitely a
great organizational app in general and
it's again very flexible all right let's
talk about standard notes now standard
notes as far as I can tell it could be
wrong but I think standard notes is the
only app on my list that is developed by
one single developer given that fact
I've got to say that I'm pretty
impressed with everything the developer
has been able to accomplish with this
app for one it is easily the most
security focused app on list as
everything you write is encrypted by
default and only you can access it now
you'll immediately notice that the free
version of standard notes is just a
plain text editor there is a note
browsing window but you can't write and
mark down there's no rich text editing
it's just plain text but upgrade to
their extended version and you get a
whole bunch of extensions that you can
optionally turn on or off there are
several different editors to choose from
including multiple markdown editors a
rich text editor and even a co
and this is really cool you can choose
which editor you want to use I note by
note basis you can create custom folders
with your tags and these are infinitely
nested ball and you can even define
custom searches based on those tags or
even other information and then save
those searches within the app standard
notes is not perfect though for one the
image support is kind of lacking right
now as you have to host your images
elsewhere to have them displayed within
the app and you also cannot drag and
drop notes between different folders or
tags still I've got to say that I am
pretty impressed with what the developer
has accomplished so far now we are on to
me taking a break and playing with this
puzzle because well there's a lot of
items on this list alright enough of
that let's talk about slight slight is
by design a very team focused
note-taking app that could also work
pretty well for a solo note-taker it's
got an absolutely fantastic hybrid
markdown editor that I found pretty
similar to the one in Dropbox paper
which allows you to format your text
on-the-fly and also embed images and
videos and even tables I'm also a big
fan of their table of contents view
which lets you quickly zoom to different
headings within your note and this is
something you'll find in Google Docs and
Dropbox paper and it's something we even
built under the articles and latest
version of college info geek but it's
very rare to find in a note-taking app
so props to sly for including it now
site also allows you to create a nested
hierarchy of notes within the app so you
can organize things though the way they
implement it is kind of weird because on
one side you've got channels and then
within the middle part of the app that's
where you can create these collections
which are infinitely nestful
the only problem is that you can only
sort by a recency on a channel level so
they're sorting options are a little
less powerful than other apps can offer
you now much like notions sleight is
built primarily for teams so you can
collaboratively edit a document with
somebody in real time there's also this
great comment section that puts comments
in a nice little window to the side of
your editor I really like that sleight
is also available on mobile apps and on
the web and I'm basically every platform
out there so at least from a design
perspective it seems to be one of the
best note-taking apps that I could
actually find when doing the research
fourth is a video my main gripe with it
right now at least right now is the
experience of using it because it can be
slow at times and I've also run to some
bugs where the text actually isn't
formatted after I've put the formatting
tags around it that being said sleight
is a pretty new company and I do have to
admit that when I tested a few months
ago it was much slower than it is now so
they're making big improvements and I'm
gonna be keeping an eye on the team's
progress going forward but that is
talked about the future and we are
living in the present and
at present in my opinion the note-taking
app with the best organizational
structure of them all is our ninth app
on the list
Ulysses now Ulysses is often billed as
an app for serious novelists and writers
but I think it can also work really well
as a note-taking app and that's because
primarily it has that amazing
organizational system that I just
alluded to not only can you create a
nested hierarchy of as many folders as
you want but when you go into a
top-level folder you're able to see the
notes within subfolders along with notes
in that top-level folder as well and I
love that additionally you can define
sorting options for every single folder
in the app you can create custom
searches you can do tags there's an
archive view there's an inbox view
there's a favorites view there's recency
views evila sees basically has it all
and I absolutely love it the biggest
bummer is just like bear it's only on
Mac and iOS platforms so I can't use it
unless I want to just totally give up my
Windows PC as a writing device so that
leads us to this question what does a
guy who uses a Windows computer and a
Mac computer on a daily basis and who
really wants a great writing experience
to do well in my case the answer is to
use the last app on our list which is
type aura type Aria is a desktop writing
app that has the best writing experience
I've ever had
next to Dropbox paper it's got that
Hybrid markdown writing system that
automatically formats your writing as
you type it's much faster than slight
and unlike bear again it's on Windows
along with Mac and even Linux it's also
full of features for serious writers
like a focus mode that dims the text
that you're not currently working on a
table of contents mode for zooming
between your outline headings just like
in sleight and themes lots and lots of
themes which you can customize with CSS
if you want however there are some
caveats
like I said type or is a desktop writing
app there is no mobile app right now
which is kind of a bummer the other
thing is that typer almost didn't make
my list because unlike everything else
that I've talked about it doesn't
actually store or sync your notes itself
it's purely a markdown editor the reason
it still fits my definition of a
note-taking app is because of its file
browser once you've opened up a folder
in the app you can easily drill down
into all the subfolders and open up as
many documents as you want but again the
biggest downside here is the lack of a
good mobile app now I don't really care
too much about this since I'm really
only using type Aurra for serious
writing for like finish
articles or video scripts but if you
really need to access your type or our
documents remember they are just
markdown files within your folder system
on your computer so if you're using
Dropbox or Google Drive then you can get
a markdown editor for your iPhone or
Android that can access those cloud
platforms such as ia writer so now it's
time to come to a verdict which app on
this list wins hmm
honestly it is pretty hard to come to a
definitive conclusion on this because
everyone has different features they
want different needs different devices
they use different budgets so instead of
just recommending one app I'm gonna name
some winners in a few different
categories and then it's up to you to
choose for the actual writing experience
again the wind goes to type aura sleight
is also pretty good but I'm waiting for
it to get a little less buggy and a
little more snappy so I'm gonna be
keeping my eye on that and using type
aura in the meantime for note
organization the wind goes to Ulysses
again with infinite Lane estable folders
and tags and custom searches really
nothing else out there beats it at least
in my eyes for overall capability and my
general recommendation I still have to
give the win to Evernote yeah it doesn't
have markdown support which I really
really want long those nestled folders
but otherwise it's got a ton of
capabilities though I do have to say
that notion in particular is really
nipping at the heels of Evernote in the
capability Department and if you care
more about those database and templating
features then you might actually think
it's more capable now I do want to make
one last note here with all these
devices and apps and capabilities we
have it can be really easy to
overcomplicate things because if you're
anything like me having all these
capabilities makes it very tempting to
try and do too much and that's why I am
once again listening to Gregg McEwan's
excellent book essentialism the
disciplined pursuit of less this was one
of my favorite books from 2017 and it's
one that at least for me is worth
returning to because it has great advice
for figuring out how to narrow down your
focuses in life and honestly this is one
of the areas where I tend to struggle
the most now if you also want to get
more focused with your priorities you
know I start digging into essentialism
then you are in luck
because you can start listening to it
for free today on audible all you to do
is go over to audible.com slash Thomas
or text Thomas to five hundred five
hundred on your phone and you can
download that audio book or any audio
book of your choosing for free and
you're also gonna get a free 30-day
trial of their service as well and once
you start the trial you are quickly
going to find out that audible is the
best place to get audiobooks on the
entire internet they have an unmatched
selection of audio book titles
tons of different genres including
biographies and psychology and sci-fi
and once you download an audiobook it is
yours to keep forever regardless of
whether or not you cancel you're always
gonna be able to listen to it across all
of your devices so if you want to gain
the ability to learn new things wherever
you are whatever you're doing whether
it's going on a long bike ride or
cooking or doing chores then once again
go over to audible.com slash Thomas or
text Thomas to five hundred five hundred
on your phone to get that free audiobook
download and a free 30-day trial of
their service but thanks as always to
audible for sponsoring this video on
being supporter of the channel and as
always guys thank you so much for
watching hopefully you got a lot of
value out of this video hopefully you've
got something that you can go try out
now and if you enjoyed this video
definitely hit that like button and
subscribe right there as well to get new
videos when they come out every single
week you can also click right there to
get a free copy of my book on how to
earn better grades follow me on
instagram at tom frankly or click right
over here or smash your face into your
phone screen to get one more video on
this channel thanks for watching and
I'll see you in the next one