this video is sponsored by curiosity
stream get access to my streaming
service nebula when you sign up for
curiosity stream at the link below
this is not a phone or at least that's
not how you should view this piece of
technology instead you should look at
this thing as a powerful computer nearly
as powerful as the other computers you
use but a more annoying one and a more
distracting one since it probably goes
with you everywhere that you go so like
I mentioned in my recent video about how
to focus when you're working from home
I've been recently trying to redefine my
relationship with my smartphone and that
includes doing things like putting it on
the other side of my office when I'm
working during the day keeping it on Do
Not Disturb for most of the work day and
once we're able to go out into the world
again I'm also gonna be experimenting
with keeping it in my backpack when I go
out instead of having it in my pocket
but this whole process of redefinition
also extends to the setup of the phone
itself the apps that are on it and some
other settings as well so this video is
gonna be kind of a what's on my iPhone
video I'm gonna show you how I organize
my phone show you some of the useful
apps on it that I think are gonna be
interesting to you but before I do that
I want to reorganize my phone and get
rid of some of the things that don't
need to be here and I thought it might
be useful to do this on a video so you
can kind of see my thought process and
maybe go and do the same thing on your
own phone if you want to follow along at
home here is the series of questions
that I asked myself for each of these
apps first and foremost do I actually
use this app I've got a whole bunch of
apps on my phone that I just have not
used for years and for some of them I
don't even remember downloading them now
there is one exception to this question
which is if you feel reasonably certain
that you're gonna use an app again in
the future even if you're not using it
currently right now so for instance this
you disk app is an app that actually
shows you location of frisbee golf parks
or disc golf parks and this is something
that I want to go do with my fiance at
some point so I'm gonna go ahead and
keep that app here second question is
this app needlessly duplicating
functionality that I have on another
device and I know of a couple of
examples already that I can get rid of
off my phone I have new score which is
like a
sheet music app I've got that on my iPad
which functions much more like a piece
of sheet music than a tiny little phone
when I'm practicing piano so I don't
need that on this phone additionally I
really know that I don't need the
YouTube studio app this is an app that
lets me look at analytics on my videos
which also just causes anxiety sometimes
so I think it's a much better idea for
me to go proactively look at analytics
when I think it is actually
strategically a good idea to do so on my
computer and this is something that you
should be keeping in mind in general you
want to make sure that you're working
proactively not reactively as much as
you possibly can so if you have apps on
your phone that are constantly pulling
at your attention and not really giving
you that much value then you may not
really need them in the first place so
the third question that I think is
useful to ask is are the benefits of any
specific app are they outweighed by the
drawbacks you know we we have such an
easy time downloading apps onto our
phone that we often will justify doing
so because it just gives us one tiny
benefit and encounter ports book deep
work he calls this the any benefit
approach where we will add a tool or
process really anything to our lives
just because it has you know any kind of
benefit and we don't stop to think what
are the drawbacks and are they worse
than the benefits that we're getting
here so in the case of Twitter I would
say this pulls up my attention more than
I would like it to and again it's just
duplicating functionality that I have on
my computer I can easily tweet I don't
need to do it in line at the grocery
store so it is going bye-bye and the
final question that I asked myself after
I've gone through all the others is is
this app a time suck and if so can I
mitigate against it so a good example
here is the YouTube app I'm keeping this
on my phone because I often actually pay
for YouTube premium for this purpose I
like to put videos on and turn the
screen off and kind of use them as
podcasts and then I will go for long
bike rides or long skating sessions and
I will listen to videos on my phone
sometimes but I don't want it to be a
time suck so there are some things that
you can do if you want to keep an app on
your phone
you want to mitigate against that
possibility first and foremost like I
mentioned earlier in the video it's
really good if you can just keep your
phone away from you as much as possible
keep it on the other side of a room or
in a different room put in your backpack
if you're going places but beyond that
on iOS specifically there is a function
called screen time and with screen time
you can do a couple of interesting
things first and foremost you can set
app limits either for specific apps or
for groupings of apps so if I turn this
on I can say you know 15 minutes of
Instagram every day is a limitation that
I want to set but I could also just say
you know all social networking has a
limit of let's just say like 30 minutes
so this would let me quickly check
things maybe post a couple of things
since that is part of my job but then
it's not going to be a problem for the
rest of the day additionally with screen
time you can add downtime so you can
just say the phone is basically not
usable from you know 10 p.m. to 7 a.m.
which is pretty useful and there's one
other really really powerful mitigation
tactic but I'm going to talk about that
later on in the video for now I'm
finally done going through my phone
getting rid of apps that I know I don't
need and this is now how my phone is
organized and if you've seen my previous
iPhone videos it doesn't look a whole
lot different I've got my most
frequently accessed apps on the home
page I think including the home row here
we've got 24 apps which I'll kind of go
over in a second and then over on this
page we have our folders I have added a
music folder so I can very easily access
a couple of music specific apps and also
because I know some of you are gonna be
annoyed by the fact that I don't have
complete rows here and there's one just
sort of hanging out in a second row
there so a couple of different apps that
I want to focus on here and highlight
number one Rome QC so in my previous
video I talked about Rome research and
how I'm using it as my main research
note-taking app right now and like I
said there is not a Rome app there's no
Rome I phone app a Rome Android app but
there is the ability to create links
from Safari to specific websites and put
them on your home screen so that is
exactly what I've done and this
basically just launches a Rome tab
and lets me easily quikcapture an idea
that I have and then sync it to my roam
database later another really frequently
used one possibly one of the most useful
apps on my phone is actually the stock
voice memos app I get random ideas for
videos or something I want to say in a
video that I'm already working out comes
to me and I just I'd like to talk it out
into my phone another quite frequently
used app is notion I basically run my
entire business out of notion and I also
write all my video scripts there so once
I'm done with a video script on my
computer I will often open it up on my
phone to do practice runs and sometimes
I actually use the phone as a little bit
of an assistance device I'll put it up
on a music stand
especially if I'm using my iPad for
something else but I've actually got my
iPad with notion doing the exact same
thing over here which I'll just show you
it's just sitting over here a little bit
out of frame now we do have a couple of
fun apps on my home screen fender toon
is the app that I use to tune my guitar
it works perfectly well I always use the
auto-tune function and I can just number
one I can tap it to hear what the string
is supposed to sound like and then it
will automatically tell me if I'm in
tune when I actually strum the strings
of my guitar I've also got an app called
real good here so I often get the idea
to watch a movie or I get the idea to
watch TV show or I'll get a
recommendation and I used to just shove
these things into todoist or Evernote
but this app actually lets you get kind
of like a dedicated place to track the
things you want to watch so I will just
track movies that I want to see and this
kind of lets me know that oh yeah I
didn't want to see that movie and then
I'll go mark it and say that I did watch
it if I did though I haven't watched my
narrative report yet don't spoil it in
the comments actually I can't watch I
can't look at the comments now oh oh
Strava I use for tracking my cycling
distance and my running distance
unfortunately it does not track inline
distance along with calories so I'm kind
of having to choose between one of the
two and I'm kind of leaning towards
calories right now since I do a lot of
like you know weird circles and don't
actually go for distance every time when
I skate but the really really big one
here is true coach so I started working
with a lift
coach recently his name's Matt Reynolds
and he runs a business called barbell
logic if you are curious and essentially
four times a week I have to work out and
not only do I have to work out I have to
film my final sets and I have to
actually send in my final sets and all
the reps that I did to my coach and then
he breaks down my form
overhead press looks great this is the
right sort of rotation that we want but
there's also a huge amount of built-in
accountability there now there's not any
like money on the line or anything but
the fact that I respect my coach and the
fact that he is expecting me to get my
videos in on the day that I have an
assigned workout means that I absolutely
get my workouts done so this app just
kind of makes that a really easy process
I filmed it with my phone I trimmed the
videos I upload them I give them a
little bit of feedback if there's
anything that I have a concern about and
just as with the Apple watch here this
helps me to stay active and also make
real progress in my lifts and my overall
strength now earlier in the video I
mentioned there was one more trick you
could use to mitigate against
distracting apps you chose to keep on
your phone such as YouTube which I do
have legitimate uses for sometimes but
it can also be a bit of a time suck well
if you go into the Settings app you can
find the app in question which is
YouTube here go to this search area and
we can actually disable it from showing
in search and disable the app from
subbing and search as well and once
you've done that now when you swipe down
you are not going to see it in that
search suggestions area and if you
search for it it's not going to be there
either so again it's just creating a
little bit of increased friction so it
doesn't become a distraction now talking
about YouTube specifically other than
its potential for being such a
distraction one other big gripe that a
lot of people including myself have with
it is well the algorithm and how it
makes it difficult for creators to
branch out and try new things which is
why I recently got together with a bunch
of other fellow creators and built
nebula if you haven't heard about it
nebula is a creator own streaming
service where you can watch all of my
videos without ads and where myself and
other creators have a place to branch
out and well try new things and
alongside all my content you'll also
find other creators there like
productions Ali Abdal Lyndsey Ellis
legal eagle and dozens more and like I
said we are trying out new things for
instance my friend Brian from real
engineering has a series on logistics of
d-day Tom Scott recently released this
awesome game show called money and I
even have an exclusive episode on a
series called working titles all about
these secrets hidden in the intro of
gravity falls which is one of my
favorite TV shows of all time but the
best part is that we've teamed up with
curiosity stream and bundled nebula with
it so when you sign up at curiosity
stream comm slash Thomas you'll not only
get access to thousands of high-quality
documentaries and other titles on
curiosity stream like the science of
sleep and David Attenborough's light on
earth which is a deep dive into
bioluminescence one of the coolest
concepts in all of nature but you also
get free access to nebula for as long as
your curiosity stream subscriber and
right now is a particularly good time to
sign up as you can get a full year of
curiosity stream for just $11.99 so
that's literally $1 per month to get
thousands of high-quality documentaries
add free videos and original content
over on nebula and to support your
favorite online creators and there's
even thirty one day free trial so you
can try before you buy so once again
however the curiosity stream comm slash
Thomas and sign up and thank you if you
do thank you for watching this video as
well by the way hopefully you found this
helpful and if you did maybe consider
hitting that like button to show the
YouTube algorithm what's up otherwise
you can subscribe right there click
right there to get one more video on
this channel potentially follow me on
Instagram if you want access to bonus
tip videos that I'm putting up over
there every now and then and I think
that's it for my ending spiel so you
know if you want don't do any of that
and go do exactly what it is that you
want to do because I'm not your dad