[Music]
when you're trying to wake up at an
early time in the morning really it is
getting to bed on time that is the
crucial Factor here so I'm not going to
talk too much about this uh this first
part of the equation here but check out
that video if you missed it so let's go
into the second part of the equation
which is having a compelling reason to
wake up in the morning so if you take a
second here to delve into the archives
of your mind I'm sure you can remember a
time in your life when you were extra
super motivated to wake up early could
have been for a positive reason maybe it
was your birthday and you really wanted
to open your presents or it could have
been for a bad reason maybe you woke up
and you realized you were late for exam
the point is that there are things that
are sufficiently motivating to get you
out of bed no matter how early it is and
you can take advantage of this fact by
establishing a compelling reason to get
out of bed in the morning that is having
something you're really excited to do
the moment you wake up and I think it's
important to talk about this because a
lot of people who want to wake up early
are doing so so they can establish
morning routines they're really
ambitious they want to have this routine
of habits and activities that drives
them towards long-term goals but the
thing about long-term goals is that the
rewards don't always come right away so
it's not always enjoyable to do
everything in your morning routine in
the moment and when your morning routine
is filled with these kind of habits it's
not exactly exciting to get up so if you
can add at least one thing to your
morning routine that you really truly
enjoy doing something that's fun it's
going to be so much easier to get a bed
to give you an example one of the parts
of my morning routine used to be to get
up and go for a half an hour walk with
my favorite daily podcasts and because
it was daily I knew I could wake up
every morning and look forward to a new
episode which made me really excited to
get out of bed so the the third part of
the equation here is to go through what
I like to call an automatic wakeup
response the moment your alarm goes off
and in particular I think your automatic
wakeup response should be to jump out of
bed immediately and the reason that
doing this works so well is because in
the few minutes when your alarm goes off
in the morning your brain is kind of at
war with itself you got like the
rational part that makes long-term
decisions and plans and it's kind of
fighting against this more instinctual
part that just wants to go back to sleep
and if you can get out of bed right away
before your brain even has time to come
up with an excuse for why you should hit
the snooze button Buton then you're
going to be a lot less susceptible to
those excuses okay so now we've come to
the fourth part of the equation which is
to get help both from apps and tools and
other people in case you're unable to
build the first three parts of the
equation into your habit on your own and
I want to give you some app
recommendations up front and these app
recommendations come in two different
categories one is an app that helps you
get up more easily and then the other
apps are kind of like annoyance apps
that just basically won't shut up until
you do a specific thing so let's talk
about that first category first I only
have one recommendation for you here but
a lot of people recommend it in the
comments and it's called Sleep Cycle
alarm and what it does is it uses your
phone's accelerometer to measure your
movements throughout the night and then
it uses that data to figure out what
your personal sleep cycle is and it
tries to wake you up at the end of one
of your sleep cycles so you feel more
rested on the other end of the spectrum
we've got the apps that basically try to
force you out of bed by not turning off
before you fulfill a specific
requirement and there are a lot of these
I'm just going to give you a few
recommendations here but there are
definitely more one of them is called
spin me and it makes you spin around in
circles before it turns off another
one's called Step at a bed and it's kind
of like a podometer app it makes you
take a certain amount of steps before it
turns off there's an app called alarmy
that makes you go take a picture of a
specific item in your house that you set
beforehand before it'll turn off and in
a similar vein there's one called
barcode alarm which makes you scan a
barcode that you pret there's also math
alarm clock and lots of other apps that
are very similar which make you solve
math problems or logic puzzles before
they all turn off and hey if none of
these apps end up working you can always
build your own version of Colin F's
ejector bed which is probably the most
effective method instead of getting out
of bed ever devised but if early morning
concussions aren't your thing there is
one more thing you can do which is to
form an accountability group if you can
find people who have the same goal as
you who also want to wake up early then
you can all team up and keep each other
accountable and while you could find
people on your campus or in your local
area to team up with there's also lots
of ways to find people online who would
be more than willing to join a group I
actually found a couple of subreddits
that are entirely dedicated to waking up
early so you could check those out or if
you wanted to you could post a thread in
the College infogeek Community which
I've got linked down in the description
and I'm sure many many people would want
to join you in this Crusade once you've
got your group established there are a
ton of different ways you can keep each
other accountable just a couple of ideas
for you here number one if you guys are
all in the same time zone or a similar
one you could actually set up an early
morning conference call you could do
something like Skype or Google hangouts
or if you want to use your phones and
there's more than two people you could
use freeconference call.com and
basically you just have a call every
single morning to ensure that everyone's
awake alternatively you could just use a
habit tracking app like habitica and you
could all party up and then create a
challenge for waking up early that way
each person has to wake up early and
check off the Box otherwise they will
hurt everyone else in the group and let
me tell you that's pretty motivating so
those are the tips I have for you in
this video and there's one thing I
wanted to talk about before I go and
it's what I alluded to in the intro
which is that you don't have to wake up
early to be successful it's not a
prerequisite for it and that's why even
though this is a video about how to wake
up early I didn't spend any time trying
to persuade you to do so and that's
because people are simply wired to have
different sleep schedules and there are
plenty of successful people who go to
bed really really late so Ben Franklin
was wrong and there was actually a 1998
study published in the British medical
journal that proved it by comparing late
risers to early risers and they found
that there was really no socioeconomic
differences no cognitive differences no
livelihood differences really it's kind
of the same and people who wake up late
actually have a few advantages over
people who rise early so my real
recommendation for you in this video is
to pay close attention to your body's
energy levels and figure out at what
time of the day you do your best work if
you do really good work like at night
then go to bed late and wake up late and
on the other hand if you do really good
work early in the morning then you can
use the tips in this video to take
advantage of those early morning hours
so hopefully you find this video useful
what I was kind of trying to do with
this video is to create a more
comprehensive resource for building the
habit of waking up early and I got to
say the article I wrote for this video
is actually even more detailed than this
video itself is and there's even more
resource links so check it out in the
card on screen right now or in the
description down below if you enjoyed
this video then you can give it a thumbs
up to support this Channel and if you
want to get more tips on being a more
effective student every single week you
can click that big red subscribe button
down below I also wrote a book on how to
earn better grades and if you would like
to get a free copy sent to your email
you can click the picture of the book
right over there and in last week's
video we talked about how to get to bed
on time and how to figure out what your
bedtime should be it's actually a pretty
good companion to this video so check it
out if you missed it once again if you
want to check out that full blog post
with lots of extra details and resource
links you can click the full article
button right there and if you'd like to
connect with me all you need to do is go
into your bathroom turn off the light
and say Bloody Mary into the mirror
three times thanks for watching and I
will see you in the next
video