the Great American writer Mark Twain
once said to never put off till tomorrow
what may be done the day after tomorrow
just as well of course when we live by
that advice sometimes we find ourselves
chugging concentrated coffee at 2 a.m.
in a valiant attempt to stay up and
finish a project that's due in 6 hours
I've been there as productive as I'd
like to think I am I have been there and
if you've been there as well or maybe if
you're there right now this video is for
you now we're going to look at some
specific concepts related to planning
and willpower in a minute namely the
impact effort Matrix and ego depletion
but first I want to talk about the
foundation here location selection I
think your location is incredibly
important when you're working under
pressure and personally I like to pick
my locations for studying based on vibe
that is what's going on around me I tend
to favor coffee shops and libraries in
fact I still go to my university library
at times even though I've graduated
because I like to be in an environment
where the people around me are also
working it motivates me also close
proximity to caffeine does help the most
important part of location selection
though is avoiding the call of the
pillow when you're working under a time
crunch it's likely going to be working
late into the night so you want to pick
a location that's as far away from your
bed as possible call up James Cameron go
study at the bottom of the Marana trench
or go to the summit of Mount Everest
don't worry about the lack of oxygen
that's not a big deal seriously though
the later it gets the more you're going
to start rationalizing how good a nap
might be and the more you're going to
start deciding that certain aspects of
your project maybe aren't all that
important so just make sure you pick a
study location where it would be more
effort to go to bed than it would be to
just finish your project now with that
piece of business taken care of it's
time to plan your efforts before you
start working it's a good idea to look
at your workload and break break it down
into individual components and then to
assess those components to figure out
which ones deserve the bulk of your
attention Dwight Eisenhower often
remarked that what is important is
seldom urgent and what is urgent is
seldom important in the book The Seven
Habits of Highly Effective People Steven
cvy popularized the isenhower decision
Matrix which is based on this principle
within that Matrix tasks are categorized
based on their importance and their
urgency and that Matrix is used in a lot
of time management systems but when
you're studying under a time crunch
everything can seem urgent because of
that the main factor you should be
focusing on is importance and to that
end we're going to use a similar but
more fitting tool which is called the
impact effort Matrix here tasks are
given scores based on their impact to
the overall success of the project and
the effort that it's going to take to
implement them to give an example of
this when I was a senior in college one
of my final projects was to build a web
app and my idea was to build something I
called am Panic it was an app where
you'd have to log in before a certain
time each morning and tell the app you
were awake otherwise it would send an
embarrassing email to someone like your
mom this app idea was actually the
precursor to the early wakeup system I
us now which I detailed in this video
but when I was working on it I found
myself in a time crunch so to help me
finish it on time I broke the project
down to the individual sections I needed
to code and then prioritize them based
on this impact effort Matrix the core
functions the code that ran the
scheduling and email delivery systems
and the code that let the user tell the
system they were awake those things took
a lot of effort to build but they were
also the most high impact parts of the
project on the other hand some parts of
the site like the about page the FAQ
page the contact page those things were
lower impact but they were also really
easy to implement they didn't take much
time and because of that I made sure to
include them to make the project seem
more complete the main element of the
site I chose not to focus on as much was
the registration and login system a good
one should have functionality to reset
passwords but I felt that I didn't have
time to do everything so I focused more
of my time on the alarm functions
because that was rather the point of the
project and I just grabbed old code from
a previous project for registration and
login and this decision did pay off the
code that ran the alarm portion of the
system was more advanced than most the
other projects in the class so I ended
up getting an a taking this back to you
to assign impact and effort scores to
each component of your project or to
each assignment if you're juggling
multiple consider the following factors
what the core deliverables are the
grading criteria for the project which
components count for the most points
what percentage of your grade each
assignment counts for overall and how
much each component will contribute to
the knowledge you need to have for tests
which usually impact your grade the most
once you've assigned a score to each
component of the project I think it's a
good idea to tackle the ones that are
the highest impact but also the highest
effort first this is due to something
called ego depletion a phenomenon
described in Daniel comet's book
Thinking Fast and Slow citing research
from the psychologist Roy bow Meister he
reveals that an effort of will or
self-control is tiring if you have to
force yourself to do something you're
less willing or less able to exert
self-control when the next challenge
comes around so use the bulk of your
willpower to deal with those high impact
High effort tasks first that way later
on you'll only have the high impact low
effort tasks to tackle when you're
feeling drained and that is where we're
going to wrap this video If you select
your location wisely plan based on
impact and effort and Tackle your tasks
in an order that utilizes your willpower
effectively you're going to get through
this time crunch in one piece if you
enjoyed this video and found it helpful
then give it a like to support this
Channel and I would love to hear any
additional tips you have down in the
comments and of course we will cover
additional strategies in the future
especially regarding how to deal with
procrastination well that's all I got
for you guys so as always thanks for
watching and I will see you next
week hey guys thanks so much for
watching this video If you want to get
new ones on being a more effective
student every single week click that big
red subscribe button right there I also
wrote a full length book on earning
better grades and if you'd like to get a
free copy of it you can click the
picture of the book to get one you can
also find a summary in additional
resources at the companion blog post
which you'll find by clicking the orange
logo right there and in last week's
video we talked about what to do if you
feel you have too many interests and
need to prioritize your time so check it
out if you didn't see it lastly if you
want to connect or ask questions I'm Tom
frankley on both Twitter and Instagram
or you can leave a comment below