hey what's up guys so you're probably
thinking this isn't Tom's normal
backdrop and you would be right so this
week I'm actually in Portland Oregon
staying with my friend Chase and this is
his much cooler office than mine um he's
let me use it for a while and this week
I wanted to do a video to follow up on
last week's video which went over that
whole passion versus experience and
skills debate and I kind of wanted to
just augment that video which was a more
General discussion with my own
experience how I got to where I am today
and how I became a YouTuber now I know a
lot of people have done like these my
YouTube Story videos and they're really
cool I like to watch them for the people
that I enjoy watching but I want to
frame mine in the context of how I got
to here from where I was as a student
early on in my college career and near
the end of high school and kind of like
show how my major selection which was
totally different than what I'm doing
now progressed into me being a full-time
YouTuber so and I'm like away from home
so I don't have access to my full
computer but if I have pictures online
I'll kind of like throw them up in here
and kind of like make the story a little
bit more visual so let's go back to like
high school um actually I'm GNA go back
a little bit further than that because
my major selection was was really really
different than being a YouTuber like I
didn't go into film I didn't go into
Communications or journalism or anything
like that I went into a major called
management information systems and this
is basically like the IT guy major so
like if you think of the guy who's
running all the networks and systems at
a big Corporation or like the dude who
runs all the computers at your school
and makes sure the computer labs are set
up like that's what I wanted to be I
grew up watching The Matrix and like my
favorite character was tank the dude who
had like 15 monitors and all the
scrolling text coming down and I wanted
to be that I wanted to run all these
systems because when I was I think 12
years old um I wanted to make a website
and I found this site called like Yahoo
geoc cities where you could drag and
drop elements onto a page and it was
basically like PowerPoint so I made a
website for like a favorite band of mine
and it was terrible it looked really
terrible and uh eventually I was like so
fed up with it that I wanted to start
changing things and the drag and drop
editor wouldn't let me do it so I had to
figure out how to start coding my own
websites and I was reading tutorials on
like these super old websites one was
called like web monkey I think and um I
just kind of learned HTML and CSS and a
lot of the other languages that like the
web is built upon and I was having fun
building my own websites and I kind of
put that aside for a while but then
during my junior year of high school I
met a friend in a math class and uh we
got talking about web design cuz he said
that he knew how to code and I was like
well hey dude I also know how to code uh
why don't we set up our own business and
charge people to build websites so that
was actually what we did and uh right
after high school ended I had like I had
so much trouble finding a summer job
because I was not yet 18 and I was also
going off to college so nobody wanted to
hire me so we just went out and found
clients and built websites for them and
that sort of Built This Love of
computers and the reason I went into
Information Systems rather than like
computer science or computer engineering
is because Information Systems is more
of a mix between business and computers
and the reason I love to business is
because when I was a junior or maybe
even a sophomore I can't remember the
year now but I joined a club called
business Professionals of America in my
high school I basically did it because I
needed stuff to put on my resume for
college applications um but it was fun
and we got to go to these like State
conferences where we'd stay in a hotel
and you'd have to do competitions and
the competitions I entered were like
HTML coding and web design and I did a
business plan competition which kind of
like got my appetite wetted for
entrepreneurship and I ended up running
for State office and got elected as the
state treasurer which let me travel to a
different state I went to Reno and
Nevada went to the National Conference
and it was super cool and I was kind of
getting these ideas in my head that
maybe someday I wanted to be an
entrepreneur or at least do something
involving business but I also wanted to
kind of meld technology into that with
computer stuff so M it was I ended up
declaring my major early in College I
think most people declare their Majors
uh two years after they start college so
after their junior year starts but I
ended up declaring my major during my
sophomore year and I started getting
into these classes and uh right away on
campus I got a job at the campus Tech
Support Center so I got to learn how to
remove viruses and basically how
computers worked like from the ground up
and it was really cool and that led into
an internship where I worked at a
Fortune 500 company and um I worked in
the network department and this is kind
of where things started started to shift
because my preconceived notion of the
networking Department was that I would
be a dude who would like be wiring up
servers and Hauling cable around this
gigantic corporate campus and I'd be
able to kind of go through all the
secret tunnels and be all over the place
all day long and I'd always wanted to
find a well-paying job that was
Technical and like intellectually
challenging but also physically
challenging I didn't want to be in a
cubicle all day so I got this internship
and it turned out to be nothing but
cubicle work was like in a box 40 hours
a week just changing like configuration
settings in servers and what I learned
actually and this is what I alluded to
in the other video you kind of have to
learn what you don't like to do as well
as what you do like to do what I learned
is I really don't like maintaining
things I like to create things and I had
almost no opportunities to create things
in that role it was all maintenance and
it was all sitting in the cubicle and it
was like almost a prison sentence to me
the co-workers were cool like they gave
me a lot of opportunities and I hate to
say it but like the work itself ended up
being almost like a PR sentence which
kind of motivated me further to keep
working on college infogeek so go back
like a year before that internship
started I got a summer job on campus and
I don't really know what to call this
job because they called us Cyclone AIDS
since uh Sai is the mascot of Iowa State
University where I went I'm just going
to call it like student orientation
assistant basically my job was to give
tours to the campus to other students
and parents and help them sign up for
classes and also answer any and all
questions people had about the college
and about the like experience of going
to college itself so I was learning all
this stuff and at the same time I was
reading blogs like life hacker and other
things like that and there was this one
like college specific blog that I was a
huge fan of and near the end of my
freshman year they actually were hiring
some new writers so I applied but I got
rejected and I had like this whole
application and i' had written this
whole post for them as part of that
application I didn't want it to go to
waste so I just figured I would put up
my own blog and it was just like another
one of these attempts to kind of bolster
my resume and have a personal project
that would look good to employers and I
just sort of did it for fun for like a
full year until right around the time I
did that internship a year later uh one
of my posts kind of blew up and got
shared all around the web and since I
was like hating that job so much I
decided to pour all of my time into
trying to make this website as big as it
possibly could be and it was just
writing at first but I actually ended up
finding out that I liked to write and
there was a lot of C activity in it I
got to create things I got to share
things with people and help people out
and I found out that was much more
conducive to my personal traits than
changing configurations and servers in a
cubicle for 40 hours a week so that's
what I ended up doing like all
throughout College whenever I had free
time I would work on articles and I
would soak up as much knowledge as I
possibly could from people like mentors
of mine and people I looked up to and
eventually I found out that I was really
liking to listen to podcasts when I was
at the gym or driving and I found that I
was like listening to podcasts more
often than I was reading blogs maybe a
couple years after I started the blog so
beginning of 2013 I was like I can start
my own podcast and that is exactly what
I did started the college infogeek
podcast uh which you can find down in
the description for this video and then
I think it was like the middle of 2014
the same thing happened again where I
noticed like I'm watching a lot of
YouTube videos I'm not reading very many
blog posts anymore I'm listening to
fewer podcasts and I'm putting a lot of
my time into YouTube for whatever reason
reason and I'd found creators like cat
Icarus and my friend Satchel Dres and my
friend Youngtown like I was watching
video game channels cuz I really like
video games but I was also really
fascinated with how they edited their
videos and kind of like put it all
together and I was really curious about
how all that worked so just like with
podcasting I figured what the heck I'll
just try doing some videos I I didn't
even want to become a YouTuber really I
just wanted to have some videos to throw
on my blog as like a way to shake things
up but the response to the videos was
way better like way way better than I
had ever gotten for podcast or for blog
post for anything else and so here we
are and what I found with videos is
every week I can kind of push myself to
learn something new and like use a new
editing technique or do some different
kind of Animation or light the set a
little bit differently like it never
gets old so I ended up kind of finding
my passion through this long progression
of just adding different types of
content to my website and that's kind of
how I got to where I am now today I
really didn't have a whole lot of
experience making videos uh before I
became a YouTuber the only real
experience I had besides like making
dumb videos with my brother as a kid was
uh I think it was the summer after my
junior year I had spoken at this event
called ignite which is a an event where
you do like five minute talks and every
slide progresses every 15 seconds so you
like have to know your slides perfectly
and they had not yet posted the videos
of the talks online and I wanted to see
mine so I just emailed the department
who had put the event on I was like hey
if you guys want uh I could help edit
those videos I don't really know how to
edit very well but I'm willing to learn
and they told me well we're already done
editing those videos but we have another
video project and pays if you want to
learn will teach you so I said heck yes
let's do it it was like a few week
project really wasn't a long thing at
all but they taught me how to use Final
Cut and they taught me kind of like how
to do lighting for uh setups like
documentary setups and that kind of like
built a little bit of a foundation that
I was able to apply to my YouTube videos
and I actually don't use Final Cut
anymore but a lot of a lot of the
concepts were the same and I was able to
sort of apply them to what I was doing
so that's kind of my YouTube story and
hopefully this gives a little bit of
context to the video from last week
about you know passions and experiences
for me my passion really came out of
like five full years of just working on
this website and adding new things and
also doing other part-time jobs and
internships and finding out what I
didn't want to do and really getting
this motivation to make this work so I
didn't have to do that kind of stuff in
the future so hopefully this has
provided some sort of context or helped
you in some way and uh I'll see you next
week hey there guys thanks so much for
watching this video If you want to get
new tips on being a more effective
student every single week you can click
that big red subscribe button right
there also I wrote a free book on how to
get better grades so if you want to get
a free copy of it click the picture of
the book and I'll send you one and if
you want to check out the article for
this video click the orange button right
there and it'll take you to that page
you missed last week's video again we
talked about that passion versus skills
and effort debate so check it out if you
missed it and I'm on Twitter or
Instagram at tomf frankley if you would
like to connect see you next week
[Music]