hey what's up guys so I just got my
hands on some new books and I am itching
it to read these things but before I do
we do need to talk about the opposite
side of the reading coin which is
writing specifically the writing of
essays now the status of the essay as a
cruel and unusual punishment was hotly
debated at the formation of the Geneva
Convention back in 1949 but if you bring
this fact up to your teacher they're
just gonna tell you not to believe
everything here on the Internet and
you're still gonna have to do your essay
which is unfortunate because among all
the types of assignments out their
essays ranked among the most
time-consuming you can take this from
somebody who basically writes essays for
a living I mean I know I'm a youtuber
but every script that I create is
essentially an essay before I
communicate it in front of this camera
and even though I've been writing these
for a really long time they're still
super time consuming so what I want to
do today is give you some practical tips
for speeding up the essay writing
process now I do have to throw a
qualifier on there because if I don't
then it really boils down to two main
tips number one that typed the same word
over and over and over again until you
hit the page requirement or number two
massive plagiarism both of which are
probably not things you want to be doing
so let's throw that qualifier on there
let's speed up the essay writing process
without sacrificing quality
while still ending up with something
that is worth reading and that
communicates a well structured idea now
typically the formation of
well-structured ideas starts in the
research stage so let's start there
[Music]
when you're writing a research paper or
the process of finding sources to back
up your arguments can actually be one of
the most time-consuming parts of the
project and that's because no matter how
many sources you have it's really easy
to convince yourself that your paper
would be truly great if you just got one
more source and then once you have that
you want another one and then another
one Cal Newport calls this research
recursion syndrome you get stuck in this
endless loop of just finding source
after source and it becomes really easy
to go down rabbit holes that you think
are gonna yield really insightful
information but end up being completely
irrelevant to your paper now luckily
Newport doesn't just stop at giving the
dragon a name but he also gives you the
tools you need to slay it his book how
to become a straight-a student outlines
a series of steps with some general
rules for avoiding this problem while
still getting the information you need
to follow this process first you venture
into the Stax library or the internet
and you find your sources once you've
found them you make personal copies of
them and annotate those copies finally
you decide if you're done and if you're
not you loop back to step number one
let's go ahead and call this the
efficient research algorithm since it's
a logical set of steps that are easy to
understand and carry out in order but
without flushing out this algorithm it's
hard to know exactly what you're
supposed to be doing on each step so
here are a few details that'll make it a
bit more useful first when you're
looking for your sources start with
general sources things like broad
histories overviews the top big popular
science books these kind of books are
easy to find and they kind of gloss over
everything within your topic now that
does make them not quite as good as
specific sources for finding arguments
that you can use in your paper but they
do have bibliographies and I do point to
other works now with specific sources
like we said they are more powerful
they're gonna contribute more but number
one they're difficult to find if you
don't know where to look and to because
they are so detailed it's really easy to
go down rabbit holes that don't end up
being fruitful so if you start with a
general source and use that to drill
down to find specific sources you're
going to be really efficient in your
research process now before I move on I
do want to say that research in itself
is a huge topic so if you do want to
learn how to do it more efficiently get
some more tips we did just publish an
article all about library research over
on college info geek and I'll have that
linked in a description down below
moving on to that second step of the
algorithm I find the easiest way to make
copies of sources that I want to
reference later on is to just take
pictures of them with my phone and I do
this all the time when I'm researching
for
Oh scripts now I'm the kind of person
who likes to own my books but I also
like to write at coffee shops and I can
only fit so many books in my backpack so
when I know I have a quote that I want a
reference or something that I want to go
back to I'll take a picture of it with
my phone that way I have a good
reference of all the different sources
that I'm going to use lastly when it
comes to that question of are you done
or should you repeat the algorithm you
can follow Newports rule of thumb first
list out all the arguments that you want
to make in your paper and then figure
out which ones are crucial and which
ones are merely helpful but the
arguments that are crucial aim to have
at least two good sources to back them
up and for the ones that are merely
helpful one will probably do the trick
[Music]
now when you're looking over your list
of crucial and helpful arguments keep
this mantra in mind quality over
quantity this applies to the number of
sources you choose to use but it also
applies to the number of arguments that
you choose to flesh out in your paper
because unless there's some arbitrary
requirement in the assignment a smaller
number of well-structured
well-thought-out arguments always beats
out a larger number of mediocre ones and
that might sound obvious on the surface
but it's important to note that the
inclusion of a mediocre argument can
actually detract from the entire paper
even if the other arguments are good now
this idea of quality over quantity
doesn't just apply to the number of
arguments and sources you're using
because you should also scrutinize the
actual words and letters that you're
using what I mean by this is that when
people know they're writing an essay
that's gonna be evaluated a lot of them
experience temptation to utilize that
cornucopia of abstruse esoteric
terminology contrapositive to the
vernacular in other words people use big
fancy words because they think it's
gonna make them as sound a smarter but
this usually has the opposite effect
in fact at Princeton University
psychology professor did a study about
10 years ago that showed that
perceptions of intelligence actually go
down when people use needlessly
complicated vocabulary but when you
think about it this is really common
sense and you don't have to go read a
bunch of charts and graphs to understand
the point of essays to communicate your
ideas clearly as Karl Popper put it if
you can't say it simply and clearly keep
quiet and keep working on it until you
can and honestly going into an essay
without feeling like you have to dig
into the deep end your vocabulary will
make the writing process a lot faster
because you're gonna be writing in the
way that you naturally think and
speak now well the temptation to use
complicated vocabulary can definitely
slow down the writing process it is but
a tiny speed bump compared to the brick
wall and the middle of the road that is
perfectionism every time you find
yourself staring at a blank page or
blinking cursor and just can't think of
what to write perfectionism is likely to
be the main culprit but luckily there
are some things you can do to get over
it first and foremost I recommend that
you write your body paragraphs first and
save the intro and conclusion for last
see your intro is where you're going to
you know introduce the topic or the
argument that you're writing about but
going into the intro before fleshing out
the body paragraphs is like trying to
give a tour of building that you've
never even been in you need to have a
clear understanding of each point that
you're talking about before you
introduce them and the same thing
applies to your conclusion plus choosing
to go in this order also makes it easier
to get into the flow state of writing
because you know you're making a mess
you know you're gonna have to go back
and edit things later but when you start
from a blank page and you think you have
to write the intro first it's really
easy to succumb to the temptation that
you can do it all in one go and on that
note it can also be really helpful to
separate the drafting stage and the
editing stage as much as you possibly
can and there are lots of ways to do
this you can block off different chunks
of time on different days for each stage
of the process you can have different
locations and you can even work within
different apps for the drafting and the
editing and this is something that I
love doing for video scripts often do my
research am i drafting over in Evernote
and then once that's done I'll move it
over to Google Docs for editing and
final prep and I actually do something
similar with video recording as well
when I want to get some stuff out of my
head often pull my phone out and record
something really casually that I know
I'm not going to use in the final cut
and doing this takes a lot of pressure
off when I'm filming here there is a ton
of pressure because I know I'm probably
gonna use it
[Music]
now this last tip is pretty nuts and
bolts but use a citation generator there
are a ton of these out there almost all
of them are completely free and they
really speed up the process of creating
a bibliography for a works cited I
remember having to do this by hand back
when I was a student and every time I
would do it I would have to constantly
refer back to the style guide so I
didn't make really common mistakes like
Miss placing a comma or accidentally
summoning an Elder God but with sites
like bid me and citation machine you can
put in the details of your sources and
leave all the formatting into the
algorithms now throughout this video
we've covered some specific tactics that
will definitely help you speed up the
writing process without having to resort
to the potato trick but it's important
to note that tactics are exactly what
these are and while the world's most
prolific writers definitely use them to
some degree the honor replacement for
building more foundational skills like
thinking clearly and critically
assessing your sources and building
logical well-structured arguments and
while these types of skills take a lot
more time and effort to build they're
going to speed up your writing process
even more and because you'll be thinking
better you'll also be writing better now
if you want to start improving your
foundations in these areas and learn
something new at the same time you
should try brilliant brian has an entire
course that can actually teach you
formal logic in-depth but the platform
will also help you boost your skills in
these areas more fundamentally due to
their hands-on a challenge based
approach to teaching math science and
computer science all the courses on
brilliant immediately pushed you to
actively start solving problems which
makes you think critically and stretches
your capabilities in a way that doesn't
happen when you just passively sit
through lectures so whether you're
learning probability or digging into
classical mechanics or getting a grip on
computer algorithms which is the course
that I'm taking right now you'll also be
improving your general reasoning skills
as you progress in brilliant also has an
active community where people can ask
questions and get feedback on the
problems they're trying to solve which
really complements their courses because
when you're stuck it can be really
helpful to get an outside perspective so
if you guys want to start learning
something new and stretch your
capabilities give brilliant a try with
link in the description down below and
if you're among the first 200 people to
sign up you'll also get 20% off of an
annual subscription I want to get
brilliant a huge thanks for sponsoring
this video as their support definitely
helps to keep this channel running but
I'm also just a huge fan of their
service and their commitment to
advancing STEM education so I definitely
think you guys should give him a try
as always thanks to you guys so much for
watching as well and if you found this
video helpful
like definitely helps this channel out
and you can also share this video with a
friend if you think they would find it
helpful you're not subscribed yet you
can subscribe right there to get new
videos when I release them and hit that
Bell icon if you want to get
notifications of those videos otherwise
you can grab a free copy of my book on
how to earn better grades right there
you can also check out our latest
podcast episode on increasing your
digital security right there or check
out one additional video on this channel
right there thanks for watching and I'll
see you in the next video