hey what's going on guys so it has been
about two years since I did it what's in
my backpack video and things have
changed some of you guys been asking for
updates so let's just get into it so
let's start right off with the backpack
as you can see this is a different
backpack than what I was using a few
years ago this is the e bags
professional slim laptop backpack and it
is my absolute favorite bag for work
purposes that I have ever used I do have
some other bags for like hiking and for
traveling but this thing is amazing it's
actually a Colorado company which is
pretty cool didn't know that when I
bought it but this thing I think it's
about like 80 bucks right now so it's
definitely not at that higher price
range that my other bags are act it's
also not a $20 backpacks but for my
purposes it is awesome and the price was
pretty good so the main thing I love
about this backpack number one it can
stand up on its own I've never had a
backpack that really like stands up and
doesn't flop over but the big thing I
love here it's got this bottom
compartment here that is just like
perfectly made for my macbook charge
cord every other backpack I've ever used
I've had to have some sort of like weird
you know thing I got to dig into or some
extra case to keep the cord nice and
organized this thing has a little
compartment built right in for it and
the nice thing is if you don't want to
use this as a cord space you can
actually come in here to the top of the
bag and remove this little hard insert
so you can create more space in this
main storage compartment if you want to
but for me this is awesome so the one
caveat I will say about this particular
bag is it is a work bag first in my mind
it doesn't have like a ton more storage
than what you'd see in like a messenger
bag maybe a little bit more but when it
comes to things like stuffing a hoodie
in here or stuffing a jacket in here
that's where you start to push the
limits and I found that I can get a
hoodie in there but I don't think I'd be
able to get a jacket all right that
caveat aside let's talk about some of
the pockets here so the top you've got
your standard laptop compartment
I've got my laptop in here we'll go over
what's in the bag in just a second and
then there's a little divider where I
like to keep notebooks and a couple of
other things in there pretty simple and
straightforward even at the top of the
bag you also have a smaller
I pad compartment and it's actually
padded with like a fabric material
that's very soft so if you didn't have a
case on your iPad this would actually
protect the screen pretty well still but
where it gets really nice for
organizational purposes is this front
compartment I really loved this thing
because it zips on three sides so
instead of digging in and having to
organize my things from the top and find
things I can just open this flap all the
way and as you can see there are tons of
zippers there's mesh there's all sorts
of compartments in here so everything is
able to be kept very organized and for
me at least I really really love that
the one last thing I will mention is it
has a high double water bottle holder
which is pretty sweet on some other bags
you've got the water bottle full holder
was like always just sticking out and
getting in the way if you don't have a
bottle but on some other bags you just
never have one at all so this is a nice
little compromise doesn't have to so I
can't carry like a ton of stuff with me
in terms of drinks but it at least has
this one all right so enough about the
bag itself let's get into what I'm
carrying in this thing on a daily basis
now keep in mind that I haven't been a
student for a few years so this is very
tailored to the specific work that I do
and I'm carrying maybe far fewer papers
and you carry as a student but I still
think there are going to be some things
in here that you might find useful
regardless of where you are as a student
or as a professional
first things first in rocking a 2015
MacBook Pro this thing is pretty
spectacular
a very simple sketchbook I think this is
just for Michaels and I use this to make
sketches for videos occasionally or to
do like maps of things that I'm planning
out for future videos and in addition to
the sketchbook we have got a regular
need five star notebook nothing really
fancy here nothing fancy about the pen I
have in here it's all from Walmart or
Target but I do like having a paper
notebook because sometimes being able to
just write things down while taking
notes on an online course I'm taking or
planning out a videos b-roll I just like
being able to do it on paper I finally I
do have one single very torn up and
battered purple folder so occasionally I
will get receipts and you to keep or
handouts or just random papers there's
like a contract I need to sign in here
now if you're a student and you have
multiple classes one folder is not going
to
it and I've never been a fan of keeping
multiple folders in your backpack rather
I really like those accordion binder
things because they give you multiple
different pockets where you can keep
every class as assignments and handouts
nicely organized and separated but it is
one unit it's not a jumble of folders
the last thing I have in this main
compartment is one of these Apple
Bluetooth keyboards I don't use this
with my laptop but sometimes I like to
be able to write with my iPad because it
creates a much more distraction free
writing experience and when I'm flying
on a plane somewhere using this in
tandem with the iPad Mini works so much
better than using a laptop in those tiny
little coach seats speaking of the iPad
I have an iPad Mini 4 and this is using
a very cheap but very high quality case
from Amazon that I'll link to in the
description below it's got that magnetic
front so you get that same like Smart
Cover on/off thing and it can fold into
multiple different configurations for
typing or watching movies so I really
like this thing and I've come to use
this iPad more than I thought I would
use it for reading I use it for writing
and also basically every video I film I
have this up next to me somewhere kind
of by the camera to bring up the script
outline for reference in the main
storage compartment we have first and
foremost Debose QC 35 noise cancelling
headphones and I got to be honest I was
a little skeptical about noise
cancelling headphones at first
especially given the price at the time
when I bought but my friend Martin got a
free pair of I think they're the beach
ones right yeah yeah get the beach one
and let me try them out and I was like
these are a game changer so I went out I
tried the beats ones I didn't find them
comfortable because I've got kind of a
big head so I just went all the way up
and I got the Bose ones and these things
are great they don't sound better than a
lot of the other non noise cancelling
headphones out there but what they do at
least for me is they open up a hole like
plethora of other study spots that I
wouldn't consider in the past because
now noise is almost like a non-issue
I can go study in a very noisy coffee
shop I can go sitting somewhere where
they'll blasting music and these things
basically just drown up the world allow
me to play my study playlist or brain at
them or whatever I want to listen to
it's just awesome it means I can wake up
I can bike to pretty much wherever I
want to work and no way I can focus
now the one thing about the bose qc25 in
particular is that they are expensive I
think I paid about 350 dollars for these
but like I said earlier that was back
then and noise-canceling technology has
both progressed quite a bit and has
gotten cheaper so if you don't want to
pay this much for these ones and these
probably are the best ones currently but
there's the the cow and a 7 which are
about 70 bucks on Amazon so less than
1/3 the price of these and a lot of
people have said that they do almost
just as good of a job with the noise
cancellation and just a bit of a job of
sound quality so that might be an option
to look into now in addition to the Bose
I also have the Plantronics backbeat fit
bluetooth headphones that I use for both
workouts and when I'm riding my bike on
trails to listen to audiobooks a lot of
you guys have asked me about these on my
Instagram so I wanted to include them in
the video even though they're not always
in my backpack they're often in my
workout bag the other thing that I keep
in the main storage compartment is books
a lot of times when I go to a coffee
shop to write I have a lot of books with
me to research to pull references from
and these this basically helped me to
write my videos and yes I do have the
iPad but I'm a person who really does
like physical books as well so
oftentimes my bag is full of these of
course as I showed you before down on
this cord storage compartment I've got
the charger cord - my macbook pro and
now we're getting into this small
organizer compartment so in here I have
got an extra charge cord for my phone
very useful to have along with the
little charger port thing and this
little accessory thing that goes with
the next book Pro cord I never use this
because I keep it just in case I happen
to need it up in here I've got one of
these multi tools now this isn't like a
professional Gerber one that's like 50
bucks it's like a ten dollar one from
Amazon but it actually does a pretty
good job if I need to like cut something
or be pliers very useful to have and
here's a bunch of business cards that
are not very interesting though I do
have my membership card to the Denver
Botanical Gardens which is a very nice
place to go study sometimes over on this
side first and foremost I have some
sunglasses because I live in Denver
which is about 4,000 feet closer to the
Sun has the place where I previously
lived and I also have some sunscreen for
the exact same reason in here there's
also these dongles for MacBook Pro but
the Ethernet one there's
gum and holes I don't exactly know how
those got in there but I suppose those
are helped and the VGA port as well for
the MacBook Pro just in case I need to
go to a conference and do a presentation
and they don't happen to have a
thunderbolt hookup this is nice to have
and the last couple of items here is
number one I've got an iPad stylus now I
don't use this very often but I did use
it for drawing on the iPad a while ago
and it doesn't take up a whole lot of
space so it's nice to have and lastly I
have got a pack of business cards
neither from Moo and they're just real
simple I designed them myself but
they're nice to have for conferences as
well are you fascinated by this thing it
can live in because that's cool you can
buy it on my overwatching I would be
good point yes you can also get this
particular case on Moo they don't come
with the business cards because like
this nice like faux leather but I don't
know like ten bucks extra I think though
it's nice to have pre classy so guys if
you are curious about anything I talked
about I'm going to link to most of these
things down in the description below and
additionally because near the beginning
of the semester we have a guide over on
college info geek my website called the
ultimate college packing checklist so if
you're going to college and you need
stuff beyond what goes in your backpack
we have compiled like a huge list of all
the things you'll need for your dorm
including school supplies kitchen
supplies bathroom supplies all that
stuff is linked down in that guide which
is fine in description as well other
than that I want to thank you guys as
always for watching I really appreciate
you if you're not subscribed it you can
subscribe with that button right there
in the corner to get new videos every
single week and you can also click right
there to get a free copy of my book on
how to earn better grades also if you do
happen to be starting a new semester
soon you might want to check out our
latest episode on the podcast which is
all about how to get prepared for that
new semester and you can watch one
additional video on this channel if you
want to by clicking your face right
there yes your face not your finger
it won't work is it your finger anyway
thank you guys for watching and I'll see
you next week