so here's a story that I'd bet you are
intimately familiar with I wake up in
the morning I go through my morning
routine and then I eventually sit down
to work and right when I sit down I know
what I need to do I have a video script
I need to finish and I need a sense of
feedback to a partner on a project we're
working on but then I remember that I
also need to send in the rent check for
my apartment and I also have 32
unanswered emails in my inbox and some
of those people are probably getting
annoyed with me at this point and oh the
lawn is getting long as well and needs
to be mowed all of a sudden I have 18
different things I need to do and I
really don't know which one I should be
working on first now if this story does
resonate with you and I'd bet that it
does fortunately there is a tool that
you can use to fix this problem and it's
called the Eisenhower decision matrix
it's a tool that you can use to more
intelligently prioritize everything you
need to do within a day or within a
longer period of time and that will help
you to get started more quickly on the
most important tasks you have to deal
with now as you might have guessed this
tool is named after Dwight D Eisenhower
who in addition to being the 34th
President of the United States was also
an extremely productive person he served
two terms as president and during that
time he introduced both DARPA which was
the agency that helps to create the
modern Internet and NASA which obviously
got us to the moon in addition he was
the supreme commander of the Allied
forces during World War two played a
huge part in the development of the
interstate highway system and was at one
point the president of Columbia
University and the secret behind
Eisenhower's incredible ability to get
things done in addition to just a
massive work ethic was his ability to
prioritize tasks effectively he once
said that what is important is seldom
urgent and what is urgent is seldom
important and this piece of philosophy
this belief that he carried throughout
his life is the foundation of the
Eisenhower matrix so let's briefly talk
about how this matrix is set up
essentially it is a box with four
different quadrants and you have some
labels at the top and on the sides on
the top we have two labels urgent and
not urgent and then on the side we've
got important and not important and each
of the boxes corresponds to a
combination of those two labels so
things that are urgent and important are
things that you should do right now
again going back to that quote things
are seldom both important and urgent and
in the case that they are you
should just do them right now things
that are not urgent but that are
important you should decide what to do
with them later or schedule them
essentially you still need to do them
but they don't need to be done right now
on the flip side we've got things that
are urgent but not important so they do
need to be done fairly soon but they're
not really important for you and in the
case of these things you should either
delegate them give them to someone else
like your little brother or automate
them give them to the machines finally
we've got things that are not important
and not urgent and as you might expect
these are things that should just be
simply deleted from your life all
together now the great thing about the
eisenhower matrix is that you can use it
for both macro level planning and micro
level planning which means that you
could use it for planning out something
like your entire month but also for
planning out a single day so what I want
to do now is go through a couple of
different examples for both macro and
micro level planning and let's start
with macro let's start with planning out
your entire month so if you have your
box drawn out and you've got your list
of tasks maybe in todoist or whatever
task management system you're using you
can start to fill in each quadrant based
on your prioritization based on what's
urgent based on what's important so in
the du box we might have tasks like
saving your grandma from a burning
building probably a big priority for you
but more realistically maybe it's
something like finishing a video script
in my case I need to get this done
before I go off to VidCon so I can give
the footage to my editor that's both
urgent and important now moving over to
the decide box we've got things like
planning out your semester if your
student may be studying for a math test
or buying groceries these things are all
important or at least I think they're
important and you might think they're
important but they don't need to be done
right now so you should put them in the
decide column so that way you're
prioritizing the things in the due
column first that brings us down to the
delegate box which is a bit of a tricky
box for a lot of people because they
often feel like they can't actually
delegate things to other people or they
can't really think of things in their
life so they would give to someone else
so what I'm gonna do is split this box
into two pieces
both delegate and automate should go
here because a lot of people have
opportunities to automate the things
that they are doing manually great
example here if you go into your credit
cards website every single month and you
pay your bill you can actually automate
that you can set up automatic payments
same thing for maybe investing in your
hey or investing in a mutual fund if you
do that and for a much more mundane
example if you are currently washing
your dishes by hand and you happen to
have a dishwasher sitting next to you
well then let the robot take care of
that as well let it wash your dishes but
all those automations aside there may
actually be things that you could
delegate to someone else as well now as
somebody who runs their own business I
delegate things like checking my email
or editing this video for example but
there are other things that you might be
able to delegate maybe you have a lawn
that you don't want to mow well if you
do something where you could you maybe
take the hour that you were using the
mole on to make some extra money that it
would make perfect financial sense for
someone to mow your lawn for you and the
exact same logic applies to something
like changing the oil in your car if
it's worth it financially for you to
just go and pay for some of the change
your oil that saves you a lot of time
finally we have the delete box these are
the things that are both not important
and not urgent and should therefore just
be ruthlessly cut out of your life now
there are some obvious examples here
maybe checking social media playing
video games generally wasting time but I
do want to give you a couple examples of
things that I recently cut out of my
life that I had previously justified as
important one of them is posting on
Instagram for business I had listened to
lots of you know internet marketing guru
is all kinds of people who said this was
super important and I was spending a lot
of my time doing it but I eventually
realized that the payoff I got for it
really wasn't worth my time I was much
better focusing my efforts and attention
on more important tasks like making more
videos or working on secret bigger
projects so I've cut that out of my life
similarly on our podcast the college
info geek podcast we used to have a
three camera setup and we would
constantly switch between camera angles
during the entire course of an episode
but I realized my editor would have to
sit there for at least the runtime of
the podcast episode often 60 to 90
minutes or sometimes even more switching
these camera angles so what I asked her
to do was just post a podcast episode
using only the center angle which
basically meant that she only had to
spend 15 minutes kind of just dropping
the footage into premiere exporting it
and then she was done rather than
watching through the entire thing and
interestingly someone actually commented
saying they liked the center angle more
because they could see the entire view
and see the reactions of the person who
wasn't talking so we both cut something
out that took a lot of time in our
business but also ended up with an
improved product as a result so this
brings me to a really important point
when you're prioritizing the things you
have to do in your life you want to ask
yourself why am i doing each of these
things does my justification actually
hold up to scrutiny in the case of
switching the podcast camera angles we
often use the justification that it was
really effortful we were putting lots of
effort into that production and that
must make it great right but when we
actually put that assumption to the test
we found out that we were wrong and the
simpler approach was actually better so
with that being said let's move on to a
micro example let's talk about how you
can use the Eisenhower matrix on a daily
basis to prioritize all the things on
your daily task list and I'm just gonna
run you through mine real quick
so in the do column I have finishing my
video script because again I'm leaving
in a couple of days I want to get the
footage done as soon as possible and I
want to get it to my editor so that's
thing that I need to be doing first
secondly in my decide area I've got
things like cleaning up the house I've
got mailing in the rent check and I've
got things like guitar practice as well
these are all things that I need to get
done today but they aren't as important
as the first thing that's over in the do
box okay so moving onto that delegate
box honestly today I didn't have
anything that I needed to personally
delegate but something that does happen
on a micro basis on a daily basis is
that you get requests from family
members maybe your girlfriend or your
brother asks you to do the dishes or
clean up a certain room and if you've
already prioritized all the other tasks
on your list you realize you don't have
time for that and a great way to
delegate without actually having to pay
anyone money is to push back on those
requests maybe ask them if they can take
care of it this time and you'll get it
at a later date and finally we have the
delete box and on a daily basis I think
that you're gonna want to list time
wasters here because a lot of us are
prone to say checking social media or
researching things that we really don't
need to be researching like what's the
best gaming laptop right now we do these
things because we don't actually want to
do our work and by actually writing them
down in that delete box and maybe
keeping your Eisenhauer matrix on your
desk or within a quick view you can look
at them anytime you get the temptation
to check Twitter or Instagram and
realize that you have decided in advance
to cut that out of your life and it'll
help you get to the things that you need
to be doing more ease
now if you want to get even better at
structuring your time and prioritizing
your tasks then I'm gonna recommend you
go and take my friend Mike Voorhies
class called productivity habits that
stick using time theming which you'll
find on Skillshare this class teaches
you how to effectively split up your
work and theme your days which will both
improve your focus and increase your
output as well and because it's on
Skillshare once you have your
subscription you've gone to that course
you're also gonna have unlimited access
to more than 28,000 other courses across
a ton of different topic areas that can
both improve your creativity and your
skills and your career prospects
including classes on web development
graphic design digital animation
marketing productivity and lots lots
more plus within their course library
you're also going to find a course from
me which is all about building a
productivity system so if you want to
improve the way user to-do lists your
calendar and your note-taking system and
all kinds of other bits of technology to
help you be more productive you might
want to take that course - now skill
share is already an incredibly
affordable learning platform with their
monthly subscriptions being less than a
Netflix subscription and the heck of a
lot more useful to your future but if
you do want to try it for free first all
you have to do is go to link in the
description down below and sign up to
get a two month free trial with
unlimited learning but thanks as always
goes out to Skillshare for sponsoring
this video and being a big supporter of
my content and thank you for watching as
well hopefully you found this useful
hopefully it helps you to prioritize
your tasks and get more organized and if
you found it useful then definitely hit
that like button and maybe get
subscribed right there if you haven't
done so already you can also click right
there you get a free copy of my book on
how to earn better grades which might
help you since back-to-school is right
around the corner otherwise click right
over here or right over here to find a
couple more episodes on my channel if
you haven't seen them already thanks as
always for watching and I will see you
in the next video