this video is sponsored by Skillshare be
one of the first 1000 people to sign up
at the link below to get a 2 month free
trial about 1 year ago I made a video
about what I thought were the best
note-taking apps in the world and quite
frankly the amount of research I did for
that video almost drove me insane but
guess what we are back baby and that is
because there is a new note-taking app
on the block which has a small but
dedicated base of users who will tell
you that it is the best note-taking app
that has ever been made the tool is
called Rome research and after getting a
not insignificant amount of tweets from
you guys telling me to check it out well
that is exactly what I did
I've been using Rome for about the past
two months on a pretty much daily basis
putting it through its paces so in this
video I'm gonna be breaking down what
Rome is how it differs from other
note-taking apps and giving you some
pros and cons so you can decide whether
it's worth testing out for yourself so
when you start using Rome the first
thing you're gonna notice is that when
you're creating pages here everything is
essentially a gigantic bullet list and
if you're used to tools like workflowy
or Dinah list you're gonna be right at
home with how you actually take notes
everything's a bullet list you can kind
of drill down as much as you want and
what I've found is this kind of bolas
structure here encourages me to write a
lot more when I'm in research mode for
video than I would if I was using
Evernote when I research with Evernote I
eventually end up with just a gigantic
amount of I don't know like the research
vomit on my screen and it gets very
difficult to find certain things after
I've written them but with Rome
everything can be organized through a
couple of different functions first if I
don't want to see everything say I don't
want to see everything in this work from
home tools section here because I'm
working on a different part of this
outline I can just collapse it which is
great so I've already made my crafting
your environment video let's just
collapse that I've already made my
planning and prioritization video let's
just collapse that let's say that I'm in
the research process for my time and
motivation video which actually just
came out a couple of days ago I can just
kind of minimize everything else I want
and work here which is great but if I
really want to focus in on this specific
part of my outline I can actually just
click that bullet and that kind of
becomes the top part of my page so it's
still part of this page and I have some
breadcrumbs here that show me sort of
where I am within my document but this
is all I want to see and this is all
that I'm gonna see which is pretty nice
so so far this is looking kind of like
workflow your Dino list so what's the
difference well the key difference lies
in how pages link together see Rome is a
tool for bottom-up associative thought
it is not a tool for hierarchical
top-down organization unlike almost
every other note-taking app that you're
going to use so the way that you would
do this is you simply put brackets
around a term and if that term is a page
it's going to create a
to that page if it is not a page it's
going to actually create that page so
let me go ahead and find something
within this document that I want to link
to I'm pretty sure I had mentioned I
want to make a huge youtube course
someday kind of a goal of mine not a
super high priority right now but you
know I want to do it and I happen to
know that I've created an outline here
in Rome kind of brain dumping some ideas
so if I highlight this YouTube course
term right here and I just give it
brackets it'll actually give me
suggestions of pages that already exist
in this case just one and I can click it
and I've created a link so if I go ahead
and just click this it's gonna take me
to my YouTube course brain dump here and
if you look at the graph overview which
is another kind of unique element of
Rome research you can see that when you
create these links you start to get this
gigantic web of interlinked pages now
before we go any further into Rome's
feature set I want to talk a little bit
about the point of this linking system
and I was doing a lot of skating while I
thought through the structure of this
video so I'm just gonna play some
footage of that here to make it a little
bit more interesting but when you think
about the way that your brain organizes
information it's very much a tangled web
of ideas which is itself made up of a
tangled web of neurons and whenever you
have a realization or you get an idea or
even when you get a rush of emotion
about a certain experience different
neural networks start to connect to each
other as the neuro psychologist Donald
Hebb famously put it neurons that fire
together wire together and the more
connections a group of neurons has the
more frequently you access it and the
stronger the knowledge at stores becomes
in your mind and rome seems to be built
to emulate this way in which the brain
works and it's also very similar to an
analog system with the exact same
purpose called the Zeno Caston which was
created by the German social theorist
Niklas Luhmann Lewin was incredibly
prolific writing over 70 books and over
400 academic papers during his career
and he managed all his knowledge using a
wooden file box that contained thousands
of paper
each of which represented a specific
idea and links to any other card which
mentioned that idea
now while the analog simulcasting system
used this very complex system of numbers
to link the cards together Rome makes
things infinitely easier by simply
linking the pages together when you
create those bracket links or even when
you don't and this is actually one of
the key features of Rome that makes it
really really nice to use anytime you
mention a page so let me just type the
word books here because I have a page
called books anytime you mentioned the
name of a page within your text even if
you're not thinking about it you create
what's called an unlinked reference so
if I go over here to books I can go down
here and see four linked references but
if I open up this little menu here I'm
gonna get nine unlinked references and
these are just any instances within my
Rome database where I have typed books
but I haven't put the brackets there to
actually link them to my books page now
sometimes I don't really want to make a
link because I'm just saying the word
books but if I do want to make a link I
can come in here I can look at my own
link references and I can just click
link for any one of them and now I've
actually made that link so if I go back
to my how to work from home effectively
series then books is now linked to the
books page where I'm actually tracking
all the books that I'm reading and this
is at least one of the features of Rome
that has the fans of this app calling it
a complete game changer because it kind
of gives you an opportunity to go back
in interact with the notes that you take
and the concepts that you have learned
and taking notes about multiple times
instead of just taking notes and then
having them be siloed in some far-flung
you know subfolder of your hierarchical
system you are constantly linking the
new notes that you're taking back to
older notes and again over time you get
this very complex tangled web of ideas
and you might be wondering but what's
the point of that and it all has to do
with associative thinking when you
combine multiple disparate ideas well
that is when creativity happens I mean
think about like a piano let's take a
guitar and hit the strings with hammers
boom you got something different or how
about you know rollerblades
let's take shoes
put wheels on them when you take
disparate ideas that haven't been
connected before and you give yourself
tools for connecting them then you have
more insights and you become more
creative so that seems to be kind of the
whole point of the underlying kind of
bottom-up linked structure of how
everything works here now before I move
on from linking I think people in the
comments would roast me if I don't
mention this next point which is that
pages are not the only thing that you
can link together anything that is a
block or I guess a bullet can be linked
to any other bullet so let me give you
an example of that I have one called
working from home how to stay focused
okay let's say I want to link to this
from some other part of my outline down
here maybe I'm working on another
section on work-life balance cool so let
me just say I want to you know I want to
link to that other thing all I need to
do is instead of typing brackets which
link to pages I will type parentheses
and then boom now
before you click away from this Bullock
you're going to see just a key reference
to that specific block but the moment
you click away from it boom it is now a
block reference and if I click it it is
going to zoom me right to it and this is
a very very long bowl list so I'm going
to scroll to the top but as you can see
this is that exact subsection of this
page and I've zoomed to it more
importantly now that I've created a
block link I now have this little number
6 here and if I click that I can see in
the sidebar here anytime I have
mentioned this specific block within
this page and I guess that actually
brings us to the sidebar the sidebar is
one of my favorite things in Rome so
basically I can bring up any other note
within Rome in a sidebar next to the
note that I'm working on so let's just
say I'm over here on my books note and I
don't want to click into one of these
books I just want to look at it in a
sidebar if i shift-click it it's just
going to bring it up and then I can
interact with it in the exact same way
that I would over here now of course
there are some cons to using Rome and
there are going to be a couple here that
may be deal-breakers for certain people
the biggest of which is that at present
moment there is no
educated mobile app for Rome research
there's no Android app there's no iPhone
app now that being said there is a
workaround which is that you can bring
up Rome research in Safari or a mobile
browser and it does work pretty well and
I think they kind of know that the
mobile experience isn't super great at
the moment because by default when you
first load up Rome in a mobile browser
you're gonna get a little quick capture
box and anything you submit to it gets
synced to your own database later on and
it gets put under a quick capture tab or
tag so if I actually go and show you my
quick capture thing these are all things
that I've just typed out as I've been
out and about you know going about my
business using my phone not having
access to my computer so it does work
it's just not the most elegant system in
the world and I think it's gonna change
in the future
Khan number two there is also currently
no API so if you are say an Evernote
user and you're used to lots of
integrations with say document scanning
apps like scan BOTS that lets you easily
scan receipts and other kinds of stuff
into Evernote you're not gonna get that
here and you're not gonna get any other
kind of integration right now there's
also not optical character recognition
or OCR so you're not gonna be able to
scan your handwritten notes and digitize
their text and also this is not notion
which means you don't get some of the
really cool features from notion namely
the amazing tables and database things I
do believe you can create tables within
Rome but they're very very simple and
they absolutely do not hold a candle to
notion where I can do you know multiple
views I can create templates for my
databases I can do all kinds of really
really cool stuff so personally notion
is sticking around for many different
purposes not least of which project
management also actual video scripts
because again I love to format them like
this I love to have tables of contents
all kinds of cool stuff but Rome is
awesome for research it kind of makes
sense because research is in the name so
that is what I've been using it for and
I've been outlining my videos in it and
it has been a great tool so far now one
of my additional main uses for Rome has
been to take detailed notes from books
because I've been in the habit of
getting at
morning and spending a little bit of
time reading and when I read nonfiction
I actually I actually mark up the book
with a pen I know that's gonna be
sacrilege to some of you but for me
marking up the book with a pen allows me
to highlight things and kind of makes
the book more valuable overall it also
forces me to really engage with the
material and pay attention to it and I
know if I am daydreaming anyway once I'm
done with a chapter I will go over to
Rome I'll go back through my book and
I'll write detailed notes which I can
actually show you right here here are
some of my notes from the book
hyper-focus I'll write my notes based on
the highlights in my book and writing
these super detailed notes has number
one helped me to actually learn better
from the books that I'm reading and
retain the information more effectively
but number two has given me a ton of
ideas for videos research for videos so
overall this is a great habit to be in
and it's definitely one that I'm going
to keep up going forward into the future
and if you want to build your own strong
habits and actually stick to them then I
would recommend going and taking my
habit building class over on Skillshare
this is the class that will show you how
to break your goals down into small
actionable habits and then show you how
to set up systems that will help you
stick to them over the long term and
turning tasks that take willpower into
habitual actions that really don't is a
huge part of achieving your goals and I
worked really hard to make sure that my
class will help you do just that plus
it's on Skillshare which means that if
you are one of the first 1,000 people to
sign up with link below you're gonna get
a two month free trial and you'll be
able to take that class for free you'll
also have access to thousands of other
great classes on Skillshare including my
friend Ally Abdul's new evidence-based
master class on how to study for exams
plus classes that can teach you new
skills in video editing public speaking
illustration and lots lots more Premium
Membership on Skillshare starts at less
than ten bucks a month so it's also a
very affordable platform and once again
if you're one of the first 1,000 people
to sign up with my link in the
description down below you're gonna get
a two month free trial with unlimited
access to the entire platform so that is
it thank you so much for watching and if
you want to learn more about Rome my
friend NAT is actually one who can't
reduce me to it probably via his
incessant tweeting about it but he's got
a great overview article
you may want to check out so I'll link
to that in description down below along
with the aroma Research subreddit and a
couple of tutorial videos that you may
want to check out if you really want to
dig into it beyond that I'm interested
to hear what you think of both this app
but also note-taking apps in general
what are you using these days are you
doing it on a computer or you doing at
an iPad are you back to a regular pen
and paper system let me know in the
comments down below if you enjoyed this
video definitely hit that like button to
show the YouTube algorithm what's up
subscribe right there or check out one
more video on this channel right over
here you can also follow me on instagram
@ Tom frankly if you want to see some
new bonus tips that I'm putting out from
time to time over there but of course
you don't have to follow me over there
and you don't have to do anything I say
because as always I'm not your dad