a really huge portion of these study
tips you'll get from professors and
other people who want you to be better
in school and maybe that you'll find
here on YouTube are really basic they'll
tell you to sit up front in class scan
your textbooks instead of reading every
single chapter uh bring your cat to
class to reduce stress and so you get to
meet the nights Folks at animal control
and these tips you know while they're
they're good they're really really
useful they are basic and maybe you're
like me you're a classical detail driven
nerd um like when I play fighting games
I want to learn all the Frame data and
every single move set and all the
matchups instead of just playing the
game and having fun quote unquote so
applying to study uh I'm the same way
and I want to find really Advanced tips
ways to sort of hack my learning uh
things that usually don't come up when
you get your basic study tips So to that
end maybe you're like me and want to get
some Advanced study tips and I am happy
to oblige and in this video I'm going to
give you eight of those Advanced study
tips so let's get started so the first
tip is to use the Corson technique when
asking professors for help now Dale
Corson was the eth president of Cornell
University yes the same Cornell
University that spawned the famous
Cornell notetaking system and he was
also a chemistry professor and he said
that students in chemistry and other
science and math programs often have to
really work to crack problems one
sentence at a time as they go through
their textbooks or problem sets um but
sometimes eventually you get to a point
where you just can't crack the problem
on your own and you need to ask for help
right so you go to your professor and
what Dale Corson wants you to think
about before you actually talk to your
professor is pause and ask yourself what
is it that I don't understand like truly
what is it that I don't understand and
what he wants you to get away from is
this thing that a lot of students do
where they go to their professor and
with a general wave of the hand as he
says they say I don't understand what
I'm looking at like this is just
confusing to me I don't get it and what
he wants you to do is avoid that rather
pick apart the problem one sentence at a
time and figure F out the exact point at
which you don't get what's going on so
right here I understand this this
process makes sense to me but here is
where I'm getting a little shaky and I
just don't get this after that I'm cool
when you can pinpoint that you're going
to impress your professor with your
preparation and the amount of effort you
put into the problem so you get some
brownie points there but you're also
working to practice the art of
recognizing confusion and and following
it down to its actual source and this
will help you immensely in all of your
learning going forward tip number two is
to learn facts quickly with a technique
called space repetition now space
repetition is the art of studying things
at increasingly bigger and bigger
intervals of time and it's a very
efficient way to study but it's also uh
it takes advantage of the way your brain
works and uh basically space repetition
is a system where you'll study something
and if you know that individual fact
very well you will not see it for quite
a while but the facts that you don't
know well you're going to see them more
and more frequently and uh the way that
this works on a on a brain level is that
you are trying to recall information
you're forcing your brain to pull it out
at the closest time possible to when you
are about to forget it so your brain
actually has to work as hard as it
possibly can to recall this information
and it encodes it better so it's more
efficient and you can actually learn a
lot faster now the best way to take
advantage of this is to use an SRS or
space repetition software to uh do your
studying for you instead of using index
cards or something now when I was
studying Japanese and I will be doing
this again soon I used one called Wan
Kani that was very very efficient and
helped me learn hundreds of kanji and um
Japanese vocab words but there is
actually a free and generalized one
called Anki and you can find it enys
ss.net where you can actually create
your own card sets for any type of data
that you think you would want to study
with SRS or you can actually find shared
card decks from people who have already
made things so definitely check that out
I think the preparation aspect of making
your own card decks is very useful but
simply going through and studying them
using space repetition is usually going
to be more efficient than using just
typical linear flashcard study methods
on paper all right tip number three and
we are getting a little bit more
advanced here so this one is to try out
the method of Loki for memorization now
the method of Loki goes back to the
Greek and Roman times and it is a memor
memorization technique rather that has
been used by memory champs for a long
time and it essentially takes advantage
of your brain's ability to remember
spatial information very well well it's
all about visualization and the classic
way to do it is to associate certain
sets of the thing the set of data you're
trying to memorize certain groups of
that with different rooms of a house so
let me give you an example this is the
kanji for King in Japanese and the
pronunciation the way that you say King
in Japanese is O and O is kind of a it's
really simple uh pronunciation it
doesn't really lend itself too well to
pneumonics which is a shame because
pneumonic is a great way to learn kanji
now what if I wanted to adapt the method
of Loki to learning this kanji along
with lots of others uh what is a king
sit on a throne or as we could say the
toilet and I am not averse to using
5-year-old humor here and what do you
say when you smell the toilet
oh yeah work with me here also the uh
kanji for King kind of looks like a tow
rack so I could associate King with the
bathroom in a house and if I really
wanted to um make this study technique
useful for me I would go into the
bathroom and I would put up flash cards
on the walls and then I'd walk through
my house and study this now the method
of lokai is kind of difficult or Loki is
kind of difficult to use it's a sort of
an advanced technique and usually you're
going to be better off with SRS or
pneumonics if you have a smaller set of
data but if you've got a lot to work
with and nothing else has worked for you
it's something that you can try tip
number four is to hack Acasia so Acasia
is a term that has been written about
for centuries and it goes back to Plato
and it's essentially a lack of command
hand over oneself and there's another
even more complex term called
picoeconomics which talks about this
hyperbolic discounting that we do
essentially we discount the value of a
task the more it is delayed the more the
reward is pushed off into the future
which in uh in short means that we tend
to procrastinate and do sort of fun
things that don't really align with our
values in the short term and we avoid
doing things that really do line up with
our values because the reward is delayed
so the way you can hack a c or sort of
avoid becoming a victim to it is uh
twofold one use a commitment device bind
yourself to getting your task done on
time and the way I do this is by using a
app called beinder which I've talked
about before I absolutely love beinder
and I've been using it to ensure that I
publish three things a week for quite a
while now and if you look at my graph
here which I'll throw up you can see
that I have actually been publishing
much much much more frequently than I
was before and it's largely because I
use a commitment device to bind myself
to do this now another way that you can
sort of hack Acasia this second part of
the fold is to add a uh shorter term
reward to completing a task and the
classic way you've probably seen this
image before is to put Gummy Bears on
your textbook and as you read paragraphs
you allow yourself to eat them but you
can do all sorts of other things let
yourself watch an episode of Game of
Thrones once you finish an assignment or
maybe use a tool like habit RPG and give
yourself some experience and gold when
you finish the study problem set or
something just find a way to make sure
that the only reward isn't that far off
delayed one that causes aasia all right
tip number five is to improve the
Pomodoro Technique and you may have
heard of the Pomodoro Technique everyone
talks about it but in case you haven't
it's simply a technique where you set a
timer for about 25 minutes classically
and then you work only on one task
during that 25 minute session and I
think a lot of people do this and it's
very useful but there are some areas for
improvement that I don't think a lot of
people take advantage of so let me just
rapid fire give them to you so number
one and I talked about how much I'm a
fan of the beinder app the beinder blog
is also a good resource for productivity
uh techniques and experiments and one of
the things that they talk about is this
thing they do called talks well a talk
is essentially a Pomodoro session except
where they use about 45 minutes and then
take 15minute breaks instead of the
classic 25 minute 5 minute break
structure so uh the tip here is to
experiment with the time intervals don't
just set to 25 minutes and assume that
that's the only potential uh interval
that you could study at find what works
for you and the other one is to put a
piece of paper next to you during your
promodoro session and whenever anything
comes up that distracts you maybe a
phone call or the urge to check Facebook
or something write it down now this lets
you do two things one you can remember
where the distraction was and if it
happened to be something urgent you can
take care of it during your break time
but two as you continue to do lots of
Pomodoro sessions over months and months
you start to see what are the common
problem points what comes up a lot that
distracts you and then you can take
steps to prevent these things so maybe
if it's your phone you forget to put it
in Do Not Disturb mode well you can do
that now if it's a certain website that
you really want to visit because it's
just so distracting and draws you in
then you can use an extension like stay
focused on Chrome to block it during
your study sessions very useful stuff
tip number six is when learning new
Concepts use both focused and diffused
thinking now this is a concept that I
learned about in a book called thinking
in numbers and look at this guy Magnus
Carlson he was uh he is currently the
number one chess player in the world but
back in 2004 when he was just 13 years
old he played Gary Kasparov who was
considered the best chess player in the
world um a couple of decades ago and who
was often considered to be the best
chess player of all time he played Gary
to a draw and look at what he does from
these screenshots here during the match
he actually gets up and walks around
looks at other tables and what he's
doing what the author of this book has
pointed out is he's using diffused
thinking so Focus thinking really takes
advantage of your prefrontal cortex to
focus on one specific set of data one
specific problem and it really
concentrates on that one thing but it
sort of doesn't let the rest of your
brain become activated and a lot of
ideas come from different nodes of your
brain connecting different completely
unrelated ideas in new different ways
and that's the diffused mode of thinking
so when you're learning something new
you want to use diffused thinking so you
can sort of grock it you can sort of tie
it to other nodes in your brain and
understand it if you only try to focus
on the problem and do nothing else
you're going to have a lot harder time
solving the problem now focused thinking
is very very good for problems you
already understand for processes that
you've gone through before and uh that's
why you want to use these two modes of
thinking in combination now tip number
seven and I've talked about this before
in terms of textbooks is to gauge your
classes and uh the specific area I want
you to think about here is gauge the
speed at which your professor moves and
at which you're able to understand so if
your professor tends to go too fast and
you can't really understand everything
he's PR presenting maybe he writes too
fast and you can't take notes fast
enough or he just moves through the
material too fast for you to really
understand it and give it time to
process in your brain then you want to
take some steps to mitigate that problem
and uh one thing you could do is read
through the chapter before a lecture
maybe if you have some material that
outlines what's going to be in the
lecture you can sort of use that to look
at the most uh relevant parts of the
textbook and sort of prime your brain
for the lecture one other thing you can
do if the class paced is just too fast
and I can't really emphasize this enough
is to Simply ask your professor for help
or ask questions in the middle of class
the professors are there to help you and
you should take advantage of that and my
eighth and final tip is to start your
problem sets alone so when I was a
sophomore I had a statistics class and I
actually had a partner and she would
come over to my dorm basically every
time we had a home homework assignment
to do and we would do it together and I
now realize that this isn't really the
best strategy now I got a pretty good
grade in the class anyway but going
forward I wouldn't do this again and
here's the reason why when you do a
problem set with a partner you're kind
of robbing yourself the opportunity to
really pinpoint gaps in your
understanding because two people going
at the same problem at the same time if
one person is able to do the entire
thing then the other person can sort of
kind of get where where the first
person's coming from so if you don't
really understand problem or maybe
there's one tiny little section that you
wouldn't have gotten but your partner
does you're going to latch on to their
answer you're going to say yeah I sort
of get that and you're going to move on
but if you do it alone then you're going
to be able to pinpoint those areas of
confusion and Shore them up before you
get into a group and finish the
assignment so start them alone so those
are my eight Advanced study tips and I
know this video is a bit longer than
normal but if you've got any questions
about these and want to learn more about
any specific ones then be sure to leave
a comment below and let me know
otherwise I will see you in the next
video hey guys thanks so much for
watching my video on Advanced study tips
now if you want to get more study tips
every single week and other tips on
being an awesome college student then
hit that big red subscribe button right
there and you'll get those videos every
single Thursday also if you want to find
the companion blog post where I link to
any resources uh for research I did or
other things I mentioned in the video
you can click the orange button right
there to find that if you missed my last
video there's a clip of it playing right
there and also if you want to get better
grades I wrote a 100 plus page book
called 10 steps to earning awesome
grades while studying less and I want to
give it to you for free so if you want
to get that book just click the picture
of the book right there lastly if you
want to connect with me or ask questions
or submit new ideas for new videos you
can either follow me on Twitter at tomf
Frankle or simply leave a comment in the
video below here and I will respond to
you no matter
what