hey how's it going guys so in today's
video we're going to talk about how to
read more books now maybe you've already
seen my video on how to generally
increase your reading speeds if you
haven't you can check it out right there
but maybe you have and maybe you've
integrated some of those tips into your
life which have helped you get your
reading speeds higher and higher maybe
even up to that generally accepted cap
of 400 to 500 words per minute and yet
you haven't filled in the other part of
the equation which is building a
consistent reading habit so this video
is all about how to do that and I've got
seven specific tips that will help you
become a more consistent reader so in my
experience the most important thing you
can do to read more consistently is to
have a certain number of pages you're
going to read every single day and to
turn it into a habit I was actually out
in Colorado a couple of weeks ago on a
ski trip with a few friends and we were
in the Airbnb one day after skiing ended
and I remember my friends Matt and Ben
were talking about books they' read
recently and both of them are
entrepreneurs so they're really busy
just like me and yet they had all this
time to read all these books and I was
asking like dude how do you guys find so
much time to read when you feel like you
got all these things to do and Matt told
me dude I just wake up every morning and
I have my coffee and I read 25 pages and
after 4 days that's 100 Pages after 40
days it's a th Pages it really adds up
over time and it works better than goals
like saying I'm going to read one book a
month or two books a month because then
it's really easy to justify pushing all
your reading off later into the month
because you've got a lot of work to do
right now moving on to tips two and
three I'm going to group these two
together because they have to do with
how you schedule your reading time now
personally I know the later that it gets
in the the day the less likely it is for
me to read my motivation starts to wne
and other things start to take up my
attention so I try to schedule my
reading time very early in the morning
but tip number three here I do it after
exercise and that's because the book I'm
reading right now which is called spark
the Revolutionary new science of
exercise in the brain talks a lot about
how exercise primes your brain for
learning exercise balances the levels of
chemicals in your brain known as
neurotransmitters which in turn improve
your ability to pay attention and prime
your brain to more efficient absorb and
remember new information and I take
advantage of this by going to the gym
first thing in the morning and then
doing my reading now tip number four is
to do whatever you can to make the
process of reading as enjoyable as
possible because from what I've learned
about how motivation is affected by the
rewards of tasks rewards can really be
split into two different categories
number one the reward you get at the end
of the task whatever the result of the
task is but number two the enjoyment you
get from doing the task itself so
personally I go to a coffee shop and I
get a latte and I read while I have
those things with me and that makes
makes a process much more enjoyable than
trying to do it at home moving along to
tip number five now if you've chosen to
read after exercise your ability to pay
attention and inhibit distractions is at
its peak but you do want to cut out as
many distractions as possible just to
give yourself the best possible chance
for focusing on your reading until
you're done so for me that means turning
my phone onto Dar Not Disturb mode and
packing it away in this bag here
everything goes in this bag and it goes
down by my feet everything is off a
table except for the book when I'm
reading so it's just focus interaction
with the book and nothing else now
distractions are one of the biggest
things that can derail your ability to
get your reading done but there are
certainly others so tip number six is to
anticipate and remove as many barriers
to your success as possible for me that
means making sure my bag is packed every
single night before I go to bed and
making sure the book is in there and
also making sure I have everything I
need like my book flags for making notes
and highlights and my headphones just in
case the coffee shop is noisy basically
I want to anticipate anything that could
give my brain an excuse to not read and
cut it out and finally tip number seven
is to externalize your motivation and
sort of take the choice of reading out
of your hands by making yourself
accountable to somebody else now I do
this in a couple of different ways
number one as I have told my roommate
Martin who reads way more books than me
that if I do not read 25 Pages a day
every single day for at least the next
three months I will pay him $100 so if I
skip even one day I'm going to lose that
on a lot of money and secondly I have
made a public page on my website where
I'll be updating my progress every
single day in an embedded Google
spreadsheet so every day I have to
record how many pages I read and anybody
can see that and call me out if I don't
now in last week's video we talked about
why it's a bad idea in general to tell
people about your goals but I do think
when you build accountability into it
and you're talking to people about your
progress rather than your big Grand
Vision it can actually be much more
motivating than if you kept it to
yourself and I'd be curious to hear what
your thoughts are on that anyway if
you'd like to have a look at my progress
page there will be a link down in the
description below and you can do this
yourself even without being publicly
accountable by using a tool like
habitica or coach.me there's lots of
habit tracking tools that can basically
get you the same result but I've decided
to be be publicly accountable about it
hopefully you enjoyed this video and
found it helpful if you did give it a
like to support this Channel and if
you'd like to get new tips every single
week on being a more effective student
you can click that big red subscribe
button right down there I also wrote a
book on how to earn better grades so if
you'd like to get a free copy sent to
your email you can click the picture of
the book and if you missed last week's
video we talked about why in general
it's a bad idea to tell people about
your goals so check it out if you missed
it you can check out the full article
for this video and get the link to my
reading progress Page by clicking the
orange button right there and lastly if
you want to connect I'm on Instagram and
Twitter at tomf frankley or you can
leave a comment down below thanks for
watching