good morning guys man I feel like that
guy from those YouTube commercials look
at my car that's more important than my
car these books oh there's just a bike
uh so it's 4:00 a.m. and I'm running on
very little sleep because I am headed
down to the airport to go to VidCon
which is awesome my flight is at 6:00
a.m. and is self-imposed torture so I
can only blame myself for it but I am
running out of very little sleep because
of it so I figured why not do a quick
video on sleep now if you've been
watching my channel for any length of
time you probably know that I advocate
getting up at a specific time every
morning I personally like getting up
early because it gives me time to go
through a morning routine but I mainly
just recommend getting up at a
consistent time so uh you have a sleep
schedule now a lot of people say this is
cool and all but how do I reconcile this
with my uh desire to go out and party
and where stay up till 3:00 a.m. every
weekend how do I get up early on the
weekdays but then you know deal with
that on the weekend should I still get
up at the same time and just take the
hit to my sleep schedule and some people
have an even more legitimate reason for
this where they have um inconsistent
work schedules their boss is scheduling
them at all hours of the day and they
don't really know when they're going to
be scheduled until maybe a couple of
days beforehand so here's the quick
answer to the question uh how do I deal
with a lack of a sleep schedule uh tip
number one this is the big tip be young
um and this comes from a lot of personal
experience I know for a fact that when I
was 18 years old I could deal with
getting 3 hours of sleep in a night I
could deal with a completely hectic
erratic sleep schedule it was all hunky
dory I could you know bounce back from
it within a matter of hours and I was
good maybe some coffee now that I'm 24
years old I know for a fact that my
body's ability to adapt to a hectic
sleep schedule or a lack of sleep is
majorly diminished I need my hours of
sleep and I do better when I have a
sleep schedule that being said the hours
of sleep you get are far more important
than the sleep schedule now if you look
at the national sleep foundation's data
on the hours of sleep that people should
get on average for certain age ranges
between the ages of 18 and 25 it's
between 7 to 9 hours some people can
deal with six some people need 10 to 11
so it's very variable very dependent on
the person but on average it's that 7 to
9 hour range
so regardless of what schedule you have
even if it's weird even if it's erratic
you want to be shooting for that 79
hours even if that means on the weekend
mornings if you stay out and party or
you have to work get up later on that
way you're getting those hours of sleep
I'm actually taking a course right now
on corsera called learning how to learn
and one of the videos they talk about
how sleep actually reduces the size of
your brain cells and allows your brain
to flush toxins out that are generated
when you're thinking and conscious
during the day so sleep is very very
important and I actually want to talk
more about sleep on this channel so I'll
be doing some more research but
basically get sleep and make sure you're
getting those recommended number of
hours uh that being said the importance
of a sleep schedule is for a few a few
reasons number one a sleep schedule
allows you to basically get your body's
internal clock to be regulated and what
that does is it helps you fall asleep
more quickly it gets you on a more
consistent schedule it makes sure that
when you wake up in the morning and
consistent time you are more energized
you're basically tuning your body to
waking up at that specific time which
lets you get into the flow of your day
easier so essentially you need to work
within the parameters that your life has
set for you and uh oops I had the light
go off well I guess I'm not really
caring too much about the technical
aspects of this video uh it's just a
time constraint I suppose but yeah work
within those those constraints you know
your your fundamentals are the hours of
sleep you're getting and after that you
can work to tweak other aspects of your
sleep experience to make it better so
maybe you can't be super consistent
about a routine but what you can do is
make sure you're not reading in bed or
uh looking at your phone in bed exposing
your eyes to Blue Light which is uh in
the daylight Spectrum uh doing things
that don't keep your your body
consistent with the Sleep experience of
bed so make sure your bed uh the only
context of your bed is sleep context
that allow you to fall asleep uh easier
and faster and then also if you can
maybe try staying out little less late
on weekends or try getting a a job with
more consistent hours or talking to your
boss about your sleep schedule who knows
maybe they'll be pretty accommodating so
anyway I'm going to go edit this video
while I'm on the plane hopefully catch
some z's when I'm done editing it and
then have fun at VidCon so hey if you're
going to be at VidCon I'll be there all
weekend I'm on Twitter at tomf frankley
you can tweet me up if you want to meet
me if you happen to be there otherwise
next week I've got an excellent video
coming it's going to be much better
filmed than this one it's got a lot of
editing in it um that's the reason it's
not out this week is because VidCon has
cut all my editing time so hopefully
this has helped you in some way and I'll
see you next week
[Music]
[Applause]