it's a question I get pretty often can
listening to music help you study more
effectively or is it just a distraction
well as the journalist HL manin once
said for every complex problem there is
an answer that is clear simple and wrong
I've been curious about this question
myself for years and I've always kind of
secretly hoped that the answer came down
in favor of music because I have almost
always studied with music but from the
research I've done so far the only thing
I can confidently tell you at this point
is that we don't actually know their
answ is going in both directions and to
give you some more detail we're going to
dig into that research in a minute here
but first I want to preface this with my
own experience because as I said I've
almost always studied with music I've
got like a borderline unhealthy
obsession with trying to find new study
music and I've spent more hours than I
can count digging through the charts on
Sputnik Music or going through music
forums trying to find new stuff and when
I've studied or done homework it's
always almost with headphones on or
something coming out of my speakers so
here's what I found works well for me
for tasks that require low mental effort
or tasks that uh deal with very tangible
information that I already am very
familiar with um high energy music can
get me energized and helps me get into
the Flow State faster I'm talking stuff
like statistics homework or accounting
or programming things where I know
basically what needs to be done and it's
just a matter of manipulating numbers or
code to get it done and if you want some
recommendations for albums for this kind
of work I can give you a few here uh
pomeg granic Tiger's boundless is a new
one I've been really digging lately also
the algorithm's polymorphic code any of
the instrumental tracks off of the Metal
Gear Rising soundtrack I absolutely love
that thing and uh ties demands young and
courageous all great albums you should
definitely check out however once we get
into tasks that are more cerebral or
more conceptual or if I'm trying to wrap
my brain around something more
unfamiliar I really need to have either
very calm music or silence and if you
want a few recommendations for tasks
like these I can give you Austin winry's
Journey soundtrack any of the Kingdom
Hearts piano collections albums olaer
Arnold's the chopan project or tian's
amazing Majora's Mask tribute album
times end and regarding silence uh
studying and silence work really well
for me at times but other times it gets
really distracting because my brain
starts picking out all the little
intermittent environmental noises that
you can't really control it's almost as
if my brain knows it's trying to use
silence to concentrate better so it
starts like picking those things out and
being like H uh it's not actually silent
man kind of like what happens if I tell
you whatever you do do not think about
fluffy red pandas what are you thinking
about so if you have this problem as
well calm music isn't the only solution
you can also try like a white noise
generator like simply noise or an
environmental sound gener Ator like
rainy mood or cativity basically if you
deliberately set up the noise yourself I
found that it kind of helps to calm that
distraction a little bit so the other
question I get a lot is is lyrical music
fine or does it have to be instrumental
all the way and what I found is for that
former type of work where it's either
lower mental intensity or very math or
logic based lyrical music is fine
because I can pretty much tune it out
and just kind of focus myself on that
work but once we get into the more
conceptual work or especially when I'm
reading it has to be instrumental all
the way anything with lyrics will just
pull up my attention and distract me ton
and this experience is actually right in
line with the opinion of the late
Stanford University Professor Clifford
nass who was known for his research into
multitasking and Nas said music with
lyrics is very likely to have a
problematic effect when you're writing
or reading but probably less of an
effect on math if you're not using the
language processing parts of your brain
Okay so we've gone over what works for
me and I can confidently say through
years of experimentation that it's
probably going to keep working for me
this way in the future but what does
science have to say about it well as I
alluded to in the intro the answers are
kind of mixed for example one study done
2013 at the University of Maryland
tested 32 students on several different
math tests in different music conditions
they had silent music uh high-intensity
music and low intensity music and what
they found is that the students scored
best under the silence condition with
the low intensity music beating out the
high-intensity music for uh second place
and by low and high I mean like
classical piano music versus death metal
so they didn't really have like a nice
balance between the music they went one
extreme and another extreme still that's
irrelevant to the fact that the silence
condition beat out both music conditions
in that study however another study in
France done with 249 participants found
that the students who watched a lecture
while listening to classical music
scored better on a subsequent test than
the students who watched that same
lecture while listening to nothing so
the answers differ and to my knowledge
there hasn't yet been a truly large
scale study on music's effect on the
brain but with the results we have right
now I think we can still make a couple
of different conclusions first it seems
clear that high-intensity music or music
with lyrics aren't really good choices
when you're reading or when you're doing
something that has to do with language
or when you're trying to wrap your brain
around something that's totally
unfamiliar to you and secondly more
generally it could be that music is a
kind of give and take thing when it
comes to your brain it might be that in
an objective sense it is distracting but
it also raises your positive emotions it
can lessen your anxiety and it raises
your motivation to stay focused and the
net benefit or net deficit is going to
depend on who you are what kind of work
you're doing and what the specific kind
of music you're listening to is and that
third Factor the specific type of music
brings up another question can music be
specifically designed designed to
increase your brain's performance well
stay tuned because in next week's video
that's exactly what we're going to be
covering in the meantime if you want to
check out any of those albums I
mentioned earlier they're going to be
linked up in the blog post for this
video along with my ultimate study
playlist on YouTube here and if you want
to discuss this video or get more music
recommendations from other students you
can check out the official discussion
thread for this video in the College of
Boge Community linked down below that is
it for this week's video so hopefully
you found it useful and if you did you
can give it a like to support this
Channel and I would really be curious to
hear what your experience with studying
with music is so let me know either in
the discussion thread or in the comments
down below and as always thank you so
much for watching and I will see you
next
week hey there guys thank you so much
for watching this video now if you want
to get new videos every single week on
being a more effective student you can
click that big red subscribe button
right there and also I wrote a free book
on earning better grades so you can
click the picture of the book If you
want to get one also if you want to find
the blog post for this video with links
to a lot of the playlists I mentioned
and some of the studies I talked about
as well the orange button right there in
last week's video I talked a bit more
about the College infogeek Community
that just launched to so check it out if
you want some more details on that and
if you want to connect I'm in the
community all the time I'm also on
Twitter and Instagram at tomf Frankle or
you can leave a comment down below