summer vacation it's a gap between your
semesters it's a break from your classes
and when you're a kid it's basically
time to make Pokemon a full-time job but
to me it's more than that summer is a
time to complement everything you get
from your academics to complement your
classes without your full-time schedule
in your way of your courses you have
time to do things that help you gain
experience that'll help you get closer
to your goals things that you can't do
while you're sitting in a classroom so
that's the idea we're going to explore
today in this video and I'm going to
share six different ideas that you can
use to make your sum more productive so
this is an incredibly broad topic it's
basically like asking I've got 3 months
free what do I do with it and to narrow
it down a little bit I thought I would
share just some of the lessons I learned
from my own College Summers including
one of the biggest mistakes I ever made
as a student which cost me a ton of
progress and time but before we get to
that let's start first with fittingly my
first summer which I spent here at Iowa
State University on campus so the first
tip here is going to pertain to you if
you don't really know exactly what you
want to do with your career yet and that
was me after my freshman year I knew I
wanted to do something with computers
but I wasn't really sure what so instead
I decided to just pursue an opportunity
on campus and that's really what you can
do to have a productive summer if you're
not really sure where you're going with
your career if you can find something
that's challenging that's going to help
you meet lots of new people it's going
to help you learn new skills that's
going to be really really valuable and
it will almost definitely be worth your
time in my case I got a job on campus
which here they call Cyclone AIDS but I
think at other schools they just call it
student orientation assistant basically
I helped students sign up for classes I
answered tons of questions from parents
and students alike and I gave lots of
tours of this campus which by the way
did you know that Iowa State University
is one of only three campuses in the
nation to be given distinguished honor
from the American Society of Landscape
Architects I still remember that but
that job was actually really interesting
and I gained a lot of experience and
skills that I didn't think I would need
since I was going into it I got public
speaking experience I got organizational
experience through organizing an event
and hiring a speaker and I met lots of
people on campus that I would have
otherwise met so it was an incredibly
helpful experience little bonus tip here
pay attention to these bulletin boards
you see around campus because that is
actually where I found out about that
job and look employment information grad
student opportunities a lot of
opportunities are going to be listed on
bulletin boards on campus so do that and
also follow your school's social media
accounts as well so on the flip side
from the first tip if you are a little
bit further into your major and you kind
of know what you're going to do in your
career or you at least have an idea of
it then your best probable opportunity
for the summer is going to be looking
for an intern ship that's going to get
you some technical experience in your
major area and that's the best possible
thing to do I think because you can't
get a feel for the kind of work you're
going to be doing in the future just by
sitting in classes you have to get
hands-on experience now we came down to
deine Iowa because during my sophomore
summer I ended up working at an IT
company in the networking department and
that's where I got a lot of the Hands-On
technical experience in my major area
and it's where I learned to manage
computer networks and that was really
helpful because honestly my classes
didn't really prepare me for what the
work would be like and on that note I
have a little bit of a third tip here
this is less of an action of an
opportunity to pursue in the summer but
it is something to be thinking about and
that is to be constantly gauging how you
are enjoying and how you're reacting to
the kind of work you're doing because
when you constantly evaluate how that's
going how you react to it you're going
to be able to make better decisions on
what to do in the future for instance I
liked computers I liked it but I was
maintaining computer network every
single day for 40 hours a week and what
I discovered through that internship
experience that I couldn't discover in a
classroom is that I don't like
maintaining things I like to build
things from scratch and I couldn't have
learned that in a classroom so that
experience actually helped me to start
shifting into being a YouTuber into
being a blogger and I wouldn't have been
able to do that otherwise so definitely
look for internships there are lots of
online resources you can use to find
internships but really the best way to
do it would be to go to your career
center at your school or your school's
career website and uh also book an
appointment with your career counselor
to get your resume reviewed and discuss
your career options you could also if
you're going to be on campus during a
summer book a mock interview these are
one of the best things that I did to
improve my interviewing skills during
the year and I also did a couple during
the Summers as well so for a fourth tip
here beyond the jobs and the internships
you can also look at taking summer
classes um so here's my thoughts on
summer classes in general like I said
summer is basically a time for you to
round out your skill set by doing things
that you can't do in the classroom
because of that I really don't recommend
taking an entire like full-time Suite of
Summer courses because that's basically
constructing an extra semester for
yourself you're risking burnout and
you're not giving yourself that time to
gain those other types of skills but if
you have a really firm grasp on your
graduation plan you could maybe take one
or two summer classes in addition to an
oncampus opportunity or a job and that
could help you potentially graduate
early or just make your next semester
easier and have more time for activities
on campus so it is an option now for the
fifth tip here one potential exception
to My overall beliefs about summer
school is studying abroad because you
can study abroad during the summer and
while you're getting some classes done
while you're getting some degree
requirements out of the way you're also
getting a lot of New Perspectives on the
world now this is actually something
that I never did as a student I did
travel independently to Japan during my
senior summer with a couple of friends
and it was one of the coolest
experiences of my life I definitely
recommend going there but studying
abroad could be a nice combinatorial
experience you could get that uh that
experience of traveling the world but
also get some School requirements out of
the way so we've talked about jobs
internships talked about studying abroad
in summer school and that brings us to
the final thing I wanted to talk about
in this video which is using your summer
to pursue a personal project and this is
actually what I did during my third
summer between my Junior and senior
years and it is also one of the biggest
mistakes that I made as a college
student now I don't think pursuing a
personal project is a mistake at all in
fact if you have a skill that you want
to learn that you can learn well on your
own your summer is probably the best
possible time you're going to have to
sync all the hours you need to syn into
it to truly Master it and if it's going
to benefit you down the road that's an
awesome thing to do what my mistake was
was quitting absolutely everything else
and trying to dedicate my entire summer
to that personal project at the time my
project which was College infog geek was
doing well it was finally getting some
really good traffic finally starting to
make some money and logically I was like
well if I dedicate every single hour of
every single day to that instead of
something else that's the best use of my
time but what I didn't realize was that
without any constraints on my schedule I
wasn't going to use my time efficiently
because there was nothing coming up
during every day I'd wake up and I would
think I have every hour of this day to
do something so I never used any of
those hours very efficiently it's like
Parkinson's law says work expands to
fill the time you allot to it see time
is kind of like air with air when you
compress it you can do some useful
things with it you can pump up your bike
tires for example but as the space the
air is in expands and as that air gets
thinner and thinner it gets less and
less useful to the point where it's so
spread out you can't even breathe it and
your product AC it is affected by time
as well if you allot too much time to
something you're not going to be very
productive you're going to be very
inefficient with your time you'll be
more prone to procrastination so if you
have something in your summer that's
constraining your schedule to a certain
degree doesn't have to be as much as it
is during the semester but just a little
bit that's going to make you use the
time you have left over much more
efficiently so that about does it for
this video guys hopefully you enjoyed it
and if you did you can give it a like to
support this channel wow this looks like
a thumbs down if you want to get new
videos on how to be a more effective
student every single week you can click
that sub subscribe button right above
link and if you want to get a free copy
of my book on how to earn better grades
well a digital one at least you can go
right there previous videos right there
full articles right there I'm about to
pass out and if you want to connect with
me just use the social media links right
there see you