hey what's going on guys so on this
channel in the past we have done several
book recommendation videos i enjoy doing
these things i know you guys really like
them so today we are going to do another
one and it's going to be six books that
changed my life personally now these six
books aren't gonna be books that i think
are the best reads in the world but they
are books that had at least one idea but
in most cases more that actually change
the trajectory of my life or the way
that i act or think on a daily basis and
as you can see from this stack of books
here there are only three print books
and one ipad sitting on top of the stack
because i do own some of these digitally
so with that being said let's get into
my list here starting with one of the
books that i own digitally which is the
motivation hacker by an author named
nick winter so this is probably the book
on my list that is the least well known
but it had a huge impact on my life one
of the main concepts that i remember
from that book was the idea of success
spirals this is a term that encapsulates
one of the fundamental truths in habit
building which is that you have to start
small before you can do something big
and a lot of people don't understand
this they make new year's resolutions
like i'm gonna work out every single day
from now until infinity and what nick
winter says to do in the book instead is
to start with a goal that you can track
that doesn't demand absolute perfection
and that is at your level but to be
honest the part of that book that really
changed my life was the part that talks
about a concept called pre-commitment
and the examples from his own life on
how he used it to achieve some pretty
big goals essentially the idea of
pre-commitment means that you set up
consequences that are going to happen if
you fail to do something that you set
out to do and one of my favorite
youtubers boy in a band calls this a
threat bet which i think is a fantastic
name for the concept in the book the
author talks about two different goals
that he was having a lot of trouble
achieving one was skydiving because he
was very afraid to do it and the other
one ironically was finishing the book
the motivation hacker itself so what he
did to achieve both of those goals was
that he set up those threat bets use a
tool called be minder which is a habit
tracker that actually has you bet money
which will be paid to the company if you
fail to be consistent on your habits and
he went hardcore with his b minor goals
he took half of his wealth for each goal
i think he had 14 000 dollars to his
name at the time so he bet seven
thousand dollars that he would write a
certain amount every single day for the
book and he also bet seven thousand
dollars that he would go skydiving and
wouldn't you know it he both went
skydiving and finished the book and did
not lose 14 000
and that is the thing that really
changed my life i read about beeminder
and i told myself that is what i am
going to use to take my work
professionally because up until then i
had sort of viewed my business and my
blog college info geek as sort of like a
side project i wasn't being very
disciplined about it and as a result my
business had kind of plateaued for about
a year and a half so after i read that
book i went i signed up for beeminder
and i told myself i was going to put out
one blog post and one podcast episode
every single week otherwise i was going
to lose money on beeminder and as a
result my business actually started to
grow wouldn't you know it putting
consistent effort on a day-to-day basis
actually causes things to happen and the
threat of losing money was the catalyst
for that change in my life alright book
number two on my list which is a much
much more famous book is the seven
habits of highly effective people by
stephen covey now this is probably the
most well-known personal development
book in the history of personal
development books and a lot of you have
probably read it but i do want to share
a couple of lessons that really did make
a pretty big impact on my life first and
foremost was the book's advice to seek
first to understand and then to be
understood a lot of us have this problem
where when we're listening to somebody
we're really just kind of formulating
our response and waiting to give it
rather than really trying to understand
what the other person is saying and the
obvious problem here is that when both
people in a conversation are doing this
neither one is really understanding the
other they're just kind of trying to
look cool or express their ideas so when
you really internalize this concept you
start to tap into what other people are
feeling and thinking and then real
communication happens and the other big
lesson in that book for me came from an
account of covey's conversation with
somebody who was having relationship
trouble he didn't know if he wanted to
divorce his wife or not because he felt
like the spark had gone out of the
relationship and i remember covey
telling him something very simple to
love her love as a verb as an action not
as a feeling now i listened to this book
when i was probably 18 years old so this
was kind of a big revelation to me
because up until then society and just
basically everyone i knew in the media
had sort of convinced me that love was
like this feeling that you would have
automatically like you just kind of had
to find it and then it would be there
forever but the opposite is true love is
a verb it's something that you have to
put work into and it is often difficult
and i honestly think that that concept
and my internalization of that concept
is one of the reasons why i'm still with
my girlfriend why i've been with her for
over five years because i've realized
that when the going gets tough you have
to as a verb love the other person it's
hard but you have to do it and yes
sometimes that feeling is going to be
there and it is going to feel like
something that's just in you and it's
going to be with you forever but you
can't rely on that always being the case
all right book number three on my list
is the four hour work week by tim
ferriss now this is the book that
probably changed my professional life
more than any other see this was the
very first book that really and truly
showed me that you could build systems
which enable your business to profit and
make money even while you're not
physically putting effort in before i
read this book i was a freshman in
college that had a freelance web design
business on the side so every dollar
that i made was a direct product of me
putting in the hours and that's kind of
how i viewed entrepreneurship but once i
read that book i started to realize that
i could build systems that would allow
me to essentially make money while i
slept now obviously building those
systems and actually making money is
neither as straightforward nor as easy
as it might seem in the book and i'm
sure that tim mentions that in the book
itself but that book more than any other
source of information drove me to start
treating college info geek more as a
business and less as a blog and that
completely changed the trajectory of my
life before college of bookie became
profitable my plan was to graduate
college moved to minneapolis and become
a web developer for a big company and
now i'm doing something that is
well a little bit different than that
all right moving on to the books that i
own physically starting with number four
the happiness equation by neil basrica
now this book has a lot to say on the
concept of happiness and on how to be
happy on a day-to-day basis consistently
but there is only one idea that i want
to share from this book and that is the
dim view that it takes on the concept of
retirement this book taught me that the
origin of our modern concept of
retirement the idea of stopping work at
age 65 and then just relaxing for the
rest of your days originated in germany
back in 1889. at that time the
government introduced a program that
would allow people who were 65 or older
to stop working in the state would take
care of them and this was meant as a way
to free up jobs for younger people but
as time went on it started to be thought
of as the kind of goal in life you'd
work up until 65 and then you'd retire
to a life of leisure but the problem is
this concept is at odds with the way
that the human body and mind work we are
built to constantly progress we're built
to work we're built to struggle life is
a type of combat and that is what we are
adapted for so this whole idea of just
stopping at a certain age is kind of
awful but it's something that we all
seem to be striving for we don't really
question it so until i read this book
that was basically how i thought my
career was going to go but now i'm
committed to never retire sure i may try
new things as i go on in my career i
might maybe slow down a little bit or
try some things that don't necessarily
make money but i'm never going to stop
learning i'm never going to stop
progressing and i'm never going to stop
working and that is actually very
liberating all right book number five on
my list is pragmatic thinking and
learning by andy hunt and i think this
is actually the first real productivity
book that i ever read one of the most
useful tidbits in the book for me was
the advice to capture insight 24 7 which
was the direct inspiration for my
philosophy that i like to call quick
capture essentially this means always
having a way to get information or ideas
into a system that you trust and that
you can access later on for instance
when i'm taking a shower and i have an
idea that i really want to remember i
actually have a waterproof notebook
suction cupped to the walls of my shower
so i can write down the details of that
idea and then once i'm dried off i can
take a picture of it and then i can get
it into my note-taking system and beyond
that concept i'm actually looking at the
back flap of the book right now there
are about 48 different concepts in this
book so if you are looking for a good
productivity book i do recommend giving
this one a read and that brings us to
the final and easily the most dense book
on this list thinking fast and slow by
daniel kahneman this book more than any
other that i've read gave me a detailed
knowledge of heuristics and biases the
mental shortcuts that our brains
naturally take to make decisions but
that can also lead to faulty thinking
now there are a lot of these to learn
about but to give you one example we
often tend to confuse what is probable
with what is plausible for instance in
one experiment the kahneman did people
were told about a fictitious person
called linda who majored in philosophy
and who's also very concerned with
issues of social justice and
discrimination and then they were asked
what was more probable that linda was a
bank teller or that linda was a bank
teller and heavily involved in the
feminist movement now if you think about
this objectively the second answer
actually contains the first answer
within it linda is a bank teller in
either case but in the second case she
is also involved in the feminist
movement therefore the first case is
more probable but more people actually
thought that the second case was more
probable it's not but it seems more
plausible because it fits the narrative
and once i learned about this along with
many of the other heuristics and biases
reported on in the book i started to
notice them cropping up in my own
thinking and decision making and as a
result i was able to catch them before
they made me make bad decisions and
because i'm able to catch those bad
decisions i can stop them before they
happen i can step back and i can rethink
them now an interesting secondary effect
of this book was that it also got me
interested in a much broader range of
topics before i read this book i kind of
stuck to productivity books and business
books but afterwards my interests really
broadened out and i wanted to start
learning about math and science i read
books like bill bryson's short history
of nearly everything or sam keane's the
disappearing spoon which is all about
the periodic table in chemistry and as a
result from reading those books my
general bank of knowledge really started
to grow and spread out and widen and i
was able to make more connections from
different areas which allowed me to be
more creative now one thing to note is
that if you decide to go out and read
those last couple of books i just
mentioned they definitely will teach you
lots of information about math and about
science but they won't teach you how to
use and apply it but luckily that's what
brilliant is for brilliant is a learning
platform that can help you become a much
better practitioner in the fields of
math science and computer science they
take an incredibly active approach to
learning bring you immediately into
challenging problems right at the start
of their courses that actually give you
something to apply the information
you're learning to which is going to
help it stick much better and which
accelerates the learning process now in
my opinion a great course to start with
would be their course on probabilities
as we talked about a little bit before
in this video if you could learn to
think in probabilities and think about
them accurately you can make much better
decisions and as an interesting tidbit
one of the very first problems in that
course actually features the linda
character from kahneman's work and in
addition to that course you'll also find
math courses on topics ranging from
algebra to calculus science courses on
astronomy quantum theory and coming in
the near future which i'm pretty excited
about an automotive engineering course
and for those of you who are interested
in computer science you'll find courses
on algorithms on machine learning and
neural networks and a lot more so to
start learning for free head on over to
brilliant.org thomasfrank which you'll
find linked in the description down
below and if you're among the first 83
people to sign up with that link you're
also going to get 20
off of their annual premium subscription
big thanks to brilliant for sponsoring
this video and being a big supporter of
this channel and as always thank you
guys so much for watching and before you
go if you haven't followed me on
instagram yet you should definitely
follow me at tomfrankly i'll have a link
in the description down below i'm
posting new stuff basically every single
day so if you want more of what you find
on this channel but in like a shorter
form factor definitely go over there to
get it otherwise you can find one more
video on this channel by clicking right
over here and i will see you in the next
video