it's no secret that our brains remember
different types of information with
differing levels of strength if you're
walking down the street one day and a
grizzly bear pops out and starts chasing
you you are gonna remember that for the
rest of your life no study needed and
that is gonna happen because your brain
is hardwired to keep information like
that up in its archives forever but what
about more mundane information what
about a string of random numbers well I
generated this string of random numbers
on random org just a couple of days ago
and even though I've only looked at at
once since then I know by heart that it
reads five one seven one nine nine two
eight four nine if you were paying close
enough attention there you might have
noticed that there were ten digits on
that piece of paper and 10 is exactly
the number of digits in a phone number
at least a phone number in the United
States in other countries there are
different numbers of digits and
different formatting but what is
universal is the way that most people
try to memorize phone numbers unless
you're already privy to certain memory
techniques you probably try to remember
a phone number the same way that I've
always done it through rote memorization
and this as you are probably already
aware is not a very good way to remember
things I mean yes your brain does have
to recall things on a pretty regular
basis to build strong memories but rote
memorization alone is a very inefficient
study technique especially for numbers
see even if you really want to remember
that phone number because it's the ROC's
phone number most of your brain
perceives that phone number as what it
really is a symbolic representation of
quantity and that's not nearly as
interesting to your brain as a grizzly
bear chasing you down the street but
fortunately there is a method out there
for easily remembering any number that
you want to keep up in your cranium
including this one which is incidentally
not the rock's number I lied about that
but the method is called the major
system and today I'm gonna teach it to
you
this method of memorization has probably
been around in one form or another for
thousands of years but it was most
prominently explained by the popular
mathematics writer Martin Gardner in his
book hexaflexagons probability paradoxes
and the Tower of Hanoi and it works in
three distinct stages first you take
each digit of the sequence that you're
trying to memorize and you encode it as
a specific consonant using a table of
phonetic pairings which I'm going to
explain in a second and which is up
heart of the major system next you take
these consonants that you've just
generated and you smash them together to
create words I'm not talking about
gibberish words here these are real
words that you would use in everyday
speech and finally you take those words
and you encode them as visually striking
interesting images that as you're going
to find out are much easier to recall
than random numbers now we're gonna do a
couple of examples here in a second but
first I do need to explain that table of
phonetic pairings within the major
system every digit from 0 to 9 is paired
with a specific sound that we make in
human speech and this makes the major
system very flexible because there are
multiple consonants that can be bound to
certain digits for example as you can
see in the table here one can be encoded
as either D or T because both of these
have a single down stroke and when you
say D and T they sound quite similar
numbers like 6 are even more flexible
and have even more consonant pairings
well numbers like 4 have only 1 now I'm
not going to go through every single
pairing here in the video because you
can just pause it and look at it and I
am gonna have a web version linked in
the description below but I do want to
note that not every letter in the
alphabet is paired with a number in this
system and all of the vowels are omitted
because these are going to be used for
forming words once you do have your
encoded continents alright enough
fooling around let's do an example so
you can see the system in action so a
couple of days ago I went to the coffee
shop near me to do a little bit of
reading and I started reading this book
called the dip by Seth Godin now this
book is only about 75 pages but I wasn't
able to finish it in the coffee shop I
got to about page 48 and once I got
there and I was ready to stop reading I
realized that I didn't bring a bookmark
with me and because I don't like to dog
here the pages in my books that meant
that I was going to have to memorize the
page that I stopped on so let's use the
major system to do this I've got the
number 48 they need to memorize that
means I'm working with the digits 4 and
8 and if we pull up our handy little
table here we can see that those get
encoded as R and V respectively with
those two letters in mind we've got a
bunch of different choices for words we
could go with ray if we could go with
Ref but I am just going to go with our V
so that means that our V is the word
that's going to get me back to 48 so all
I need to do now is come up with a
visually striking scenario in my head
that helps me easily remember that word
RV when you're doing this part it can be
really helpful to also come up with a
word that represents the context of the
situation in this case the book that
reading and since this book was written
by Seth Godin and since I'd know what he
looks like I'm just going to use him as
the secondary image so to match those
two things together I came up with a
scenario where Seth Godin was hanging
out in that space RV from the movie
space balls with barf and Lone Star and
yes that is absolutely ridiculous but as
you might know your brain remembers odd
and ridiculous things a lot more easily
than it recalls dull things so now I've
got this really easy to remember image
and all I need to do to get back to my
number is work backwards seth godin
chillin in the RV okay RV is my word
which means that R and V are my
consonants translate those two four and
eight boom 48 now at this point you
might be thinking okay Tom that was two
digits that's super-easy what about that
phone number you showed at the beginning
of the video that was ten digits what
happens when we have a lot more digits
to memorize this is the point where you
want to combine the major system with
other memorization systems and the first
step to doing that is to chunk the
digits you're trying to memorize which
means to break them down into smaller
groups technically you could use chunks
of any size but remember you are
translating these digits into consonants
so the bigger your chunks are the harder
it's gonna be to find a word that
represents them all because they all
have to remain in order because of that
I think it's good to work with chunks of
two digits if we go that route with our
ten digit phone number we get five one
seven one nine nine two eight and four
nine then just like before we translate
those digits into consonants and create
words out of them in this case I went
with these and now comes the part where
you combine the major system with
another memory system because now you
need to remember this list of words in
its exact order now there are a ton of
different techniques out there that you
could use to do this one of them being
the method of loci also known as the
memory palace which has you associating
the information you want to remember
with specific locations inside a place
like your house but the method of loci
is pretty complicated and I should
probably do an entire video on it so I'm
going to do that pretty soon and in this
case I'm going to make up a story using
my words instead one of the really
powerful things about creating story is
that our brains naturally latch onto
stories because stories are linear we
understand the order in which events
happen so the words are easy to pull out
in order as well and just like with my
crazy Spaceballs story from before the
more outlandish and odd your story is
the
your time your brain is gonna have
remembering it so there you have it
translate your digits into consonants
create words endless consonants and then
create crazy stories that help you
remember those words and then work
backwards from there to get back to
those numbers that you wanted to
remember at this point you now know how
that one weird kid in your school
managed to memorize PI to 347 digits and
maybe just maybe you can go challenge
him now now there are a lot of other
techniques out there that can help you
improve your memorization skills and
like I said earlier in the video we're
gonna be going over some of them in
future videos including the method of
loci but it's also important to note
that memorization is only one skill and
if you want to be a top performer in
school or in your work then you need to
complement it with other skills like
critical thinking and problem solving
you also need to be able to build mental
models that link concepts together so
you can understand how they all affect
the bigger picture and if you're looking
for a resource that will stretch your
capabilities in those areas check out
brilliant a learning platform that helps
people effectively learn math science
and computer science although building
strong and universally applicable
cognitive skills along the way within
brilliance library you'll find courses
and topics like calculus in linear
algebra and on math and applies to
trading and Finance you also find
courses on gravitational physics and
astronomy machine learning and soon even
of course on automotive engineering
which I am personally pretty excited
about throughout all other courses
brilliant takes an extremely active
approach to learning throwing you
straight into challenging problems that
give you an immediate reason to want to
learn and they back this up with
extensively detailed wiki which you can
use to flesh out your knowledge and any
problems you're stuck on and a community
full of thousands of active learners who
are constantly helping and challenging
each other I'm a huge fan of brilliance
approach to learning and I highly
recommend that you guys give them a try
you can sign up and start learning for
free today at brilliant dot org slash
Thomas Frank and the first 83 people who
sign up will also get 20% off their
annual subscription I want to give a
huge thanks to brilliant for sponsoring
this video and helping to support this
channel and as always guys thank you so
much for watching if you like this video
you can hit that like button down below
and also get subscribed right there so
you don't miss out on any future videos
and you also might want to grab a free
copy of my book on earning better grades
right there lastly you might also want
to follow me over on Instagram I said
doing daily stories now and I'm also
doing regular live streams and if you
want to catch those I will have the link
in the description down
thanks for watching and I will see you
in the next video