I want to show you something cool that I
can do on my Mac here. So, I get a lot
of email and for a lot of these emails,
I have to type the exact same responses.
But instead of typing the same words
over and over and over again, I have
this cool little Chrome extension called
Georgia that lets me bind templates to
little keywords that I can type. So, if
somebody emails me and say they want me
to do something and I just don't have
the time to do it, instead of typing out
a long apology and an explanation, I can
just type the word busy, hit tab, and
the entire response will pop out in less
than a second. Over the past few months,
I've been steadily developing more and
more templates as the need arises. And
according to the app statistics, it's
already saved me over five hours of
typing, which isn't too shabby. But what
if you're using paper? Well, on paper,
we have shorthand writing systems. These
are systems that vastly cut down on the
characters or strokes needed to express
ideas. The process of writing in
shorthand is called stenography, and
it's an art that basically every
journalist had to learn before the
widespread availability of these little
devices. The origins of shorthand date
back to the 4th century BC in ancient
Greece. Though even before that, scribes
in ancient Egypt developed two different
writing systems. The hieratic and later
the demonic, which let them write much
more quickly than they could using
complicated hieroglyphics. Fast forward
to the past couple of centuries and two
systems became dominant in the shorthand
sphere. The Pitman shorthand method and
the Greg shorthand method. Both these
systems are phonetic, that is, their
alphabets aren't onetoone approximations
for Latin characters. Rather, they're
symbols designed to express how words
sound when they're being spoken. Masters
of these two systems have been known to
be able to write at 200 words per minute
or more, which means they can write
basically anything word for word, as it
said. But the problem here is that both
of these systems are incredibly
difficult to learn. They take a lot of
time and practice. And as a student, I'm
betting you probably don't have that
time to dedicate to learning one of
them. For example, here is as best as I
can write it with 10 minutes of
practice, the statement, there is a
ninja standing right behind you. I am
not joking. You seriously need to run.
Written in Greg Shortorthhand. Now, I'd
wager it take you a bit of time to
figure out how to read that, let alone
be able to write it proficiently. So, on
one side of the problem, writing a Greg
or Pitman shortand takes way too long to
learn. But on the other side, writing a
longhand is painful for your wrist and
simply takes too long to do while you're
in class. What's the solution? Well,
actually, I've got two solutions in
mind. The first one is to use a simpler
shorthand writing system. One option is
alphabetic shorthand systems like
speedriting or personal shortorthhand.
Now, these are systems that use the
standard Latin alphabet you're already
familiar with. And while some shorthand
purists may turn their noses up at them
like snooty aristocratic gentleman, and
while indeed you may not be able to
write as fast as you could with Greg or
Pitman, the trade-off here is that they
take far, far less time to learn.
Another option is to use a system with
characters that do differ from that
standard Latin alphabet, but that are
easier to learn than the phonetic
alphabets of Greg or Pitman. The most
famous example I can think of is called
Tline, which is actually still used by a
lot of journalists today. But an even
newer example that I came across
recently is called Ford improved
shorthand which is supposedly designed
to be able to be learned within 15
minutes. So here's that same statement
from before but now written in Ford. And
I have to say that while it took me
probably 10 minutes to puzzle out how to
write it in Greg, it was really really
easy to write it in forward. And I found
myself being able to memorize the new
characters after writing them just once
or twice. The other solution is to
create what amounts to your own
shorthand system. And this is an idea
I've had kicking around in my brain for
a long, long time. And it's actually why
I made this video in the first place.
Because if you're the only one who's
going to review your notes and no one
else is going to need to look at them,
then why not write them in the most
efficient way you can for you? With that
being said, let's get into one of the
experiments that I've been doing in
recent weeks with my notes. So, let's
take three words, allegation,
procrastination, and litigation. All
these three words with the suffix shun,
which in my mind sounds a bit like shin.
So, we could just draw a picture of a
shin with a foot. Now, let's circle the
shin. And then we could simplify that
drawing down. and then simplify it once
more until we have a two-stroke symbol
that resembles a shin. Now I can add
that as the suffix instead of writing
shun which is six strokes and this one
is two. So now we have a reduction of
four strokes. If you want to do another
example, let's take the suffix able.
When I think of able, I think of
somebody who is strong and able to do
things. So let's take a big beefy arm,
draw that, and then simplify that once
again. And now we have yet another
two-stroke symbol. Now going beyond
those two examples that I made up, I
just want to give you a list of good
targets in your notes for developing
potential symbols. And one target is
prefixes and suffixes. And I'm actually
going to link to a big list of these in
the article for this video. Another idea
is function words. Essentially, the
words that make sentences coherent, like
with, and because, or, greater than,
less than, those kind of things. These
words don't really carry a whole lot of
information about the concepts within
them. So, they're prime targets for
shortening. So, that rounds out all the
ideas I had about shorthand right now.
But I did want to leave you with one
final tip before we round out the video.
And that is that shortorthhand isn't the
only way to condense the amount of notes
you have to take and also to cut down on
the amount of carpal tunnel you suffer
from. In fact, you can draw diagrams,
you can use arrows to connect concepts
and ideas. And you can find other ways
to jot down the things you're learning
in class without having to write them
out fully. And as always, if you've
already done your own experiments or
have any tips I didn't mention here, I
would love to hear about them down in
the comments. So let your knowledge flow
forth from your brain. And if you
enjoyed this video, as always, give it a
like to support this channel, and I will
see you in next week's video. Thanks for
watching. Hey there guys, thanks so much
for watching this video. Now, if you
want to get new tips on being a more
effective student every single week, you
can click that big red subscribe button
right there. Also, I wrote an entire
book on how to earn better grades. And
if you want to get a free copy, you can
click the picture of the book and I'll
send you one. And if you want to read
the article for this video and find all
the links to things I mentioned, you can
click the orange button right there.
Last week's video, we talked about
resources for getting cheaper prices on
the textbooks you have to buy. So check
it out if you missed it. And if you want
to connect, I'm Tom Frankley on
Instagram and Twitter, or you can leave
a comment down below.