Hey guys.
This is going to be a pretty quick video, but I have a couple things that I wanted to
talk to about, one of them being the book that I announced in the last video, which
is going to be free and is over getting better grades.
So I'm going to tell you a little bit more about that book and my progress in it, in
just a couple seconds.
But first, I want to just say thank you.
Yesterday we reached 2,500 subscribers on this channel and my mind is just completely
blown.
I had no expectations of even hitting 1,000 before the year was over.
When I started making videos back in August, I was hitting 90 subscribers and I figured
that it would be maybe like 500 by then end of the year.
But we've hit 2,500 and the fact that you guys are ambitious enough and interested enough
in the content that I'm making and the study tips that I'm researching and making videos
about to watch them and subscribe and share and everything is insanely motivating for
me.
I'm going to keep doing my best to make better and better videos every week.
Definitely stick around.
If you want to share this channel with your friends or professors or anybody, that would
be awesome, but seriously, just thank you.
I want to let you know that I have a ton of gratitude for the support that you've given
me so far.
So onto the book.
I'm just going to put a picture of it right here so you can check out more details about
it whenever you want to.
The book's called '10 Steps to Earning Awesome Grades While Studying Less.'
I am currently about 14,000 words into my first draft of the book.
I'm on track to getting it finished and out to you right as January starts and the spring
semester gets underway.
If you want to get that, you can click the annotation that is around this picture of
the book over here.
Just become part of the College Info Geek Newsletter.
You'll get newsletter updates about blog posts and podcasts and new videos every week.
I'll also send you a copy of that book the moment it's out.
Whenever you sign up, you'll get it immediately.
I'm really excited to share that with you.
The book's going to go over how to pay better attention in class, how to take better notes,
defeating procrastination, better study strategies, tackling group projects, writing papers.
Basically everything that I wished I would have had tips and hacks and strategies for
tackling more efficiently in college.
I'm writing that in this book.
I'm trying to make it short, concise, and entertaining.
So hopefully, you guys like it.
That's all I've got for this video.
Once again, thank you so much.
We've hit 2,500 and I'll probably make another one for 5,000.
This is not the only video this week.
I will have one out on Thursday so don't think I'm copping out on that.
I just wanted to make a quick update and say once again, thank you.