this video is sponsored by brilliant do
delay
delegate and delete these are the
classic four d's of time management
which have been described in
countless different productivity books
and articles and together they help you
answer
one big question how should i deal with
all the tasks that i'm supposed to do
most of us have too many things to do
our to-do lists are a mile long we're
stressed out and
half the time we don't even know where
to start and this this
is the problem that a decision-making
framework can help you to solve
the 4ds form one of those such
frameworks but today i would like to
submit for your consideration an
improved version of that framework one
that adds a fifth element
automate now to be fair you could
consider this to be a subtype of
delegate
since you are technically delegating to
a robot but i
prefer to give it its own equal position
and list so that we can form our own
shiny new productivity term the dad
method
so let me level with you here for a
second we productivity gurus
we live and die by the arbitrary
acronyms and methods that we coin
in fact entire careers have been built
off of this practice
gtd the pomodoro technique 80 20. they
are
the bedrock upon which are built
so let's make a deal you and i you
begrudge me
my shiny new productivity term let me
get mine
and in return i will not share with
everyone your secret shameful harry
potter fan fiction
derek so let's get started and let's
start with do
the domain of weddings shia labeouf and
extinct birds if you say it twice fast
in the context of decision making do
really means
do now so how do you know if you should
do something
right now well the answer is simple ask
yourself these two questions
number one is the task at hand both
urgent and
important and number two can you do it
in under two minutes
if the answer to at least one of those
questions is yes then
yes do it right now so answering that
first question is kind of obvious
your house is on fire it's 11 58 pm and
the term paper is due in two minutes the
president has been kidnapped by ninjas
these are all tasks that would be found
in the first quadrant of the classic
eisenhower matrix which is used by
project managers to prioritize tasks
based on
their urgency and on their importance
when a task falls into the fire and
ninjas quadrant it should probably be
done right now
the second question refers to the
two-minute rule that david allen
describes in his book getting things
done
if you can do a task in two minutes or
less then it as well
should be done right now now like the
22nd rule that i've talked about in
other videos the
two minutes here is really just kind of
an arbitrary marker yet another pithy
term that sticks well in the mind and
helps business authors bag those
in general even if it's a little over
two minutes if you can do it quickly
do it now otherwise delay it to remix a
line from toy story delaying
is really just procrastinating with
style
the key to delaying a task strategically
instead of merely procrastinating is to
first
get very specific about the details of
your deferment the what
the when and the how and then secondly
you want to get those details into an
external system
that you trust so what i want to do here
is share two big tips
for improving the way you use your to-do
lists first
create an inbox for yourself so an inbox
is a place where you can quickly dump
tasks wherever they come up and wherever
you are it should be a low friction way
to get things into your system that you
can access
at a moment's notice key point low
friction here
secondly have a specific time for
processing that inbox
and this is the part that most people
tend to skip which is why their to-do
list so often fall victim to
entropy another term that i'm going to
use in my
basically entropy means chaos when
people don't process their inboxes they
become a mile long and eventually they
become this chaotic mess that people no
longer trust
and then they start trusting their
brains when you take time every single
day or at least
each week to process your inbox your
system remains something
that you can trust next up we have
automate which is objectively the
coolest step since it does involve
robots for millennia humans have used
tools to conquer their environment
and shape it to their will now in most
cases these tools have simply made the
work that they were already doing a
little bit faster or a little bit easier
but then somewhere along the line we
started building these rube goldberg
contraptions that in some cases did the
work entirely for us so the line between
automation and mirror optimization gets
pretty blurry pretty fast did the oxtron
plow merely
optimize work once done by hoeing by
humans or
was the man driving that ox forward one
of the world's first automation
engineers
and if so what was the stack overflow
ranking anyway wherever you place that
line doesn't matter so much as long as
you understand that you can use tools to
do things faster and if you can approach
a repeated
process with a creative systems based
mindset then you'll start to see
opportunities for automating
at least some of the pieces of it one
method for doing this is called
templatization this involves basically
boxing pieces of a project up into
a master template which you can then
copy for each new project
instead of making each of those little
pieces over and over and over again in a
row process
for a very very simple example here
let's look at just a slice of the
editing process
for this video to stay organized we make
a video we have folders for the footage
that we shoot that i'm shooting right
now
for the project files for music for
sound effects for images
basically every different type of media
now for each video i could manually
create these folders which i used to do
or i could simply make a folder called
template that already contains all these
folders
then i can just duplicate that folder
and rename it for every new video that
we make
another method is called process
automation which basically means
building a robot to do the job for you
you might use robots to build cars to
cook a chicken by slapping it
in terms of chicken integrity this
chicken's looking pretty good we're up
another degree celsius let's go
or to automate tedious processes on your
computer and tools like
zapier integromat and ifttt are all
great places to start exploring if
you're interested in that last option
though they won't cook chickens for you
of course process automation has existed
for quite a lot longer than robots have
just under a different moniker
delegation now
honestly if i want to break into the
area of business writing where the real
money is
then i should probably flesh this
section out more than any of the others
i should also throw around terms like
management theory
agile framework no bathroom breaks after
all it is the managers who call the
shots in most companies which means that
it's the managers who hire business
authors to come speak at their corporate
retreats and spout motivational
platitudes for fifty thousand dollars
one can dream now if you're watching
this video my guess is that
you don't count yourself amongst the
ranks of these people and you don't know
how to dress for their cocktail parties
you may also think that delegation is
not a strategy for you
but that's probably not true let's
consider for a moment the simplest and
cheapest way to delegate
any task there is could you trick your
little brother into doing it
and will he take payment and left over
halloween candy even if he decides to
demand cold hard cash it still might be
worth taking that deal
and to know for sure you first need to
understand the value of your time
like money time is a resource whenever
you choose to do something
you incur an opportunity cost you're
losing the opportunity to do
literally anything else you could have
done with that time
you are giving something up so one easy
way to value your time to understand
this trade-off
is to take the amount that you make and
figure out your per hour rate
so for example if you make 60 000 a year
and you work an average of 1800 hours a
year which is the average here in the us
then your per hour rate is roughly 33
now this is an incredibly oversimplified
way of valuing your time there's a lot
of other factors we can include here but
for simplicity's sake we're doing it
this way because it's at least a good
way to help yourself be more open
to delegation that would make sense for
instance if your per hour rate is 33
and you can pay someone to mow your lawn
for 30 dollars then
doing so makes sense unless you're
somebody that really likes mowing lawns
the bottom line is that you should start
at least thinking of your time as a
valuable resource
one that is at least as valuable as your
money and honestly probably more
do that and you're gonna start opening
your mind up to more delegation
opportunities
but you're also gonna realize that some
of the tasks on your plate just
aren't worth your time or the money that
you would spend delegating them
and these are the tasks that you should
simply delete but
how do you know whether or not it's a
good idea to snap a task out of
existence
instead of doing it well when faced with
this question i like to remind myself of
the
any benefit approach that cal newport
discusses in his book deep work
as he explains in the book people will
often add new tools
new products and especially new social
networks into their lives
if they provide literally any benefit no
matter how small
and in doing so these people fail to
consider the cost of these additions in
the case of social networks it's
more wasted time scrolling through fees
more cognitive switching penalties to
make you less productive
so newport advocates rejecting this any
benefit approach
instead scrutinizing any new product or
social network or tool
to determine its net benefit i think
that we need to consider this when we're
adding things to our to-do lists as well
i know that i'm guilty of adding tasks
willy-nilly tiny little things that i
just think
have to be done and then when i
scrutinized these things later on
i often realized that i was wrong they
really didn't matter what i try to do
now
is consider the opportunity cost like we
just talked about the delegation section
of each task i ask myself what could i
do instead
as it turns out i usually have quite a
few options that are either more
enjoyable or they're higher value
by thinking about these alternatives it
becomes a lot easier
to just say no to all these little tiny
tasks that really
at the end of the day don't matter so
that in a nutshell
is the dad method now if you are an
agent of a big book publisher i will
take
one please and thank you
for everyone else here is a quick
summary of the process reversed so that
it fits into a nice
neat flowchart for any task that you are
faced with
ask yourself number one does it even
need to be done
number two do i need to be the one to do
it number three
can i automate it and number four do i
need to do it now
out of the five steps in the dad method
perhaps the most rewarding and yet the
hardest to master
is automation at its core automation is
really just
problem solving can you take a problem
and creatively figure out how to solve
it by building a system
instead of by doing it manually peter
parker brilliant but lazy right
and this is a fundamental skill that is
sought after in pretty much every
industry today it is often crucial
in hiring decisions and luckily it's
also something that you can learn
through practice and one great resource
for learning this skill is brilliant
which is a learning library that
actually kills two birds with one stone
their library of more than 60 in-depth
courses teaches you math
science and computer science skills like
how to build a search engine
or how to figure out probabilities while
also building your universally
applicable problem-solving skills
this is because brilliant's entire
approach to learning is based on active
problem-solving so when you're working
through their courses you're not just
passively learning like you often do in
school
you are doing so if you'd like to try
out brilliant for yourself you can
actually start learning for free by
going over to brilliant.org
thomasfrank or by clicking the link in
the description down below and if you're
one of the first 200 people to use that
link and sign up you're also going to
get 20
off your annual premium subscription and
you'll be helping to support this
channel by supporting the sponsors who
support me
that was a lot of instances of the word
support maybe i should automate that
but seriously if you do choose to
support my sponsors thank you so much
you're really helping the channel out
but also if you made it to the end of
this video thank you for putting up with
all my stupid jokes and thank you for
watching my videos
seriously i really appreciate you
hopefully you found something useful in
this video if you haven't subscribed yet
i'll have a little button right there
where you can subscribe to get
notifications of new videos
we'll have a couple of other videos on
screen if you want to watch some more
stuff
that i've made in the past uh if you
want to hit that like button that's
always appreciated but
of course i can't tell you what to do so
if you don't want to do any of that
stuff go fight a shark for all i care
because
i am not your dad