hey guys so today I thought I would make
a list of 20 different useful websites
that I think every student should know
about and this list will include
websites on how to find deals on
textbooks solve math problems and lots
of other things and it's by no means an
exhaustive list and we'll definitely
cover other websites on this channel in
the future but it's a good start so
let's Dive Right In stack exchange is a
gigantic collection of question and
answer communities so if you need help
on any particular subject there's
probably a community for you there if
you need a resource for your math
homework Wolfram Alpha is well what
should I call it a computational
knowledge engine that can actually show
you step byep how to solve math problems
some of the features require a pro
subscription which costs about 375 a
month though so if you're looking for a
free option while it's a little less
convenient gamma. sim.org will do many
of the same things for free student rate
is a website that can help you find
student discounts on all sorts of things
including travel tech school clothes and
textbooks CH is a website where you can
rent or buy textbooks which can save you
hundreds of dollars off the bookstore
prices and they also have electronic
versions that you can use while you're
waiting for your books to ship in
addition they also have apps with
homework answers and a community of
tutors if you need extra help my friends
and I saved a ton of money in college
using CHS so they're definitely one of
my favorite student focused websites
sleepy ti.me and I guess that's how you
pronounce it is a website that can help
you calculate when you should go to bed
if you're looking to get up at a certain
time it uses the science of REM Cycles
to calculate when you should go to sleep
and also factors in the average amount
of time it takes a person to fall asleep
once they actually get into bed if you
want to build strong habits or break bad
ones then habitica is probably my
favorite tool for doing so it used to be
called habit RPG and I have an entire
review of it on my channel they just
changed their name recently but they're
just as good as they used to be and they
keep getting better there are a lot of
to-do managers out there but todoist is
probably my favorite just because it has
a very clean simple interface and syncs
between all my apps as with to-do
managers there are also tons of calendar
apps out there but for me Google
Calendar has been the main stay since I
started college and I still use it today
their smartphone apps have gotten really
really good it's still absolutely free
and it syncs between every single system
you could possibly have Dropbox is a
service that keeps all your files synced
and updated across all your different
platforms they're accessible from the
browser and from your mobile apps gone
the days of using a flash drive to
transfer files from one computer to the
other and I honestly think you should
use some sort of cloud service to make
sure your files are backed up if it's
not Dropbox it could be Google drive or
something else but use one if you want
to learn new skills especially computer
skills or specific computer software
then linda.com is an amazing resource
they offer courses on pretty much every
programming language computer software
you could think of and lots of other
things and it's possible that your
school already subscribes to it so see
if it does and you might have free
access if you want to track your
spending set budgets and basically have
an overall picture of your financial
situation then mint.com is my favorite
resource for doing that rate my
professors is an awesome resource you
should probably hit up anytime you're
signing up for classes well I definitely
wouldn't advise taking every word
written there as the golden truth it has
steered me towards amazing professors in
the past kogle is an awesome mind
mapping tool that lives in your browser
and is completely free so if you don't
want to use paper but you do need to
make a mind map which I've done in the
past it's a cool option Trello is in my
opinion one of the best apps out there
there for managing group projects it
utilizes a Japanese project management
technique called kbon and basically it
allows you to manage things between
lists and different boards super easy
you can add people in collaborate assign
people to tasks add due dates and well I
could probably gush about the site for
hours you might not have expected this
one but your University website is one
of the most useful websites you'll use
as a student I'm using my school's
website as an example here but your
website probably has class cataloges
with descriptions of all the classes a
financial aid website with potential
scholarship listings a semester calendar
with all the important dates that you
should put on your calendar University
events and potentially even a job board
where you can find part-time jobs
internship opportunities or freelance
opportunities written kitten is an
awesome tool my friend Gretchen told me
about which can help you write when you
have writers block for every hundred
words you write you'll get a new cat
picture and I challenge you to name
anything more motivating than cat
pictures it can't be done cheatography
is a website that Aggregates cheat
sheets from around the web on pretty
much any subject so if you're learning
say calculus then you can search that on
the website and you'll probably find a
cheat sheet that condenses a lot of the
most important information and you can
use that to help make your own study
guides bibme is a website that can help
you generate citations for basically any
Source you use in a research project it
can save you a ton of time in creating a
bibliography and the nice thing about
this one in particular is they have a
database full of sources you can search
through if you find the source you're
looking for it can actually
automatically fill out the citation for
you instead of making you fill it all in
manually uny web is the web companion to
eny which is a space repetition software
that can help you study things more
efficiently than you can on regular
paper flashcards and lastly if you want
to do any sort of DIY projects in your
apartment or dorm then instructables.com
is an amazing resource in fact if you
want to build a hanging desk or hanging
loft bed I've put tutorials of my own up
there and there's lots of other more
practical things there as well all right
so that is my list hopefully you find at
least one of the websites on this list
useful and if you found this video
useful leaving a like can definitely
support this channel if you want to find
even more useful websites and also apps
and tools then check out the resources
page in college infogeek which I'm
always adding to you can find it by
clicking the card right now or down to
the link in the description below also
if you know of websites I didn't mention
in this list that would be useful let us
know about them down in the comments
though you should probably use just the
name of the website because the spam
filters tend to catch links also one
last thing my friends over at how to
adult actually let me guest host this
week so if you want to see a video on
how to acquire new skills check the
video out right there or find the link
down in the doobly bobbly thing yeah
that's it so thank you so much for
watching and I'll see you next
week hey guys thanks so much for
watching my video about websites you'll
find useful as a student now if you want
to get more tips every week on becoming
a more effective student you can also
subscribe to this channel by hitting the
big red subscribe button right there I
also wrote a book on how to earn better
grades and if you'd like to get a copy
of that for free click the picture and I
will send you one you can also find a
list of all the websites I talked about
in this video along with links to them
at the companion blog post which you can
access by clicking the orange logo right
there last week's video went over some
ways that you can make a new semester
start smoothly and also keep your
motivation long term so click the
thumbnail if you haven't seen it yet and
also if you want to connect with me I'm
on Twitter at tomf Frankle or you can
leave a comment below with questions
feedback or what have you thanks for
watching