hey guys so let's step away from the
specific study techniques and tactics
today and talk about something a little
bit more overarching graduation so
according to the federal government's
education statistics only about 59% of
the students who started college in 2006
graduated within 6 years those numbers
get even worse when we go down to four
years according to a study from college
complete America only between 19 and 36%
of students based on the type of
institution graduate within that 4-year
time period so why does this happen why
do so few students graduate on time well
there are a lot of factors uh the big
one the elephant in the room is finances
but there are a lot of other ones
changing Majors changing School uh
Netflix gab new steam sales shark Nat
all kinds of stuff but one of the most
common causes and I think one of the
most avoidable is simply poor planning
and that's why in this quick video I
want to show you the way that I planned
my own graduation out and how it helped
me graduate in four years so essentially
My Philosophy since I was a freshman was
that my graduation was really in my own
hands yes I had an academic adviser and
he was great but I knew that he had
hundreds of students that he had to deal
with and the person who was most
responsible for me being able to
graduate in four years was me that's why
every single semester I made sure that I
looked over all the graduation
requirements and I mean all of them
general education requirements major
specific requirements the number of
credits I was required to have to
graduate all that stuff and made sure
that I was on track to hit them all that
meant keeping all the requirement
documents in my Dropbox making sure I
knew exactly where they were at any
given time but I went beyond that I
actually created created an Excel
spreadsheet that charted out my entire
graduation plan and listed out every
class that I intended to take I also
threw a couple of simple formulas in
there to add up the numbers of all these
credits from the classes I was going to
take and make sure that they hit the
requirements both the overall credit
limit and the over 300 level credit
limit if you only get one thing out of
this video it's that you should create a
similar plan of your own and if you go
to the companion blog post for this
video I've actually included my own plan
for you to download and sort of copy off
of and you can find that link down in
the description or you'll find an
annotation in the end card after the
video is done the next thing I want to
talk about though is something that at
least at my school was called a degree
audit and I know it's called a degree
audit at several other schools around
the country maybe it's called something
different at your school but essentially
it was something that I could run on the
computer or have my academic adviser run
that would show me my exact progress
through all my required classes the cool
thing about my school's degree audit
system is that you could actually run it
for a major you weren't in and my
roommate wanted to switch from computer
science to Mis one year and he thought
that it would take him a lot longer to
sort of catch up and after running a
degree audit he found out that was
actually further into the major he
wanted to switch into than he was into
his own major so if you have access to
any sort of tool like this I highly
recommend running it on a regular basis
and if you don't personally know how to
do it ask your academic adviser running
regular degree Audits and making sure
you have an accurate graduation plan
that you edit whenever you get a new
interest or decide to drop a class you
had planned to take is going to help you
graduate on time but there's one other
piece of the puzzle that you want to
make sure you have and that is simply
signing up for classes on time even if
you plan well a lot of times you'll find
that classes fill up very quick quickly
or maybe they're not available during a
certain semester and the best way you
can mitigate this is putting a reminder
on your calendar to sign up for classes
the moment you're able to I know a lot
of people who waited a week or two after
their sign up date to sign up for
classes only to find out the classes
they wanted were full and at best it's
an elective class and you just don't get
to take it you have to find a
replacement but at worst it's a required
class and you end up tacking an extra
semester or two onto your graduation
date so the common thread in all of this
have a good plan be vigilant whenever it
changes and make sure you have it
updated and expose your yourself to
every Advantage you can by signing up
early one last thing though what if you
do all of this and still there's a class
that you can't sign up for because it's
full well one thing you can try doing is
testing out of required classes using KP
tests and other methods and I could do
an entire video on this but I've
actually already done a podcast
interview on it with my friend Jay Cross
and if you click The annotation right
there or down in the description you can
listen to it Jay is an expert on this
subject and he actually tests it out an
entire year of college classes using
these methods so that's it for this
video hopefully you got something useful
out of it and like I said I'll have my
own Excel spreadsheet with my graduation
plan available for download in the blog
post that goes with this video so hit
the link in the description or in the
end card if you want to look at it and
use it as a template for your own plan
now next week I'm actually going to be
in New York City hanging out with my
co-host from the listen Money Matters
podcast Andrew so if you see a video for
me next week it'll be in a different
location because of that and if not I'm
sorry I just got really busy so we'll
see what happens one last thing though
there will be a surprise coming for me
tomorrow so if you follow me on Twitter
at tomf frankley you'll get to see what
that is that's all I got for this week
so thanks for watching and I will see
you in the next
video hey everybody thanks for watching
my video on graduation planning if you
enjoyed it and you want to get more
videos every single week on improving
your college experience then hit that
big red subscribe button right there if
you also want to get a free 100 plus
page book on improving your grades and
studying less then click the picture of
the book and I'll send you a copy you
can find links to any resources I
mentioned in this post including my
Excel template over at the companion
blog post which you can find by clicking
the orange logo right there if you
missed last week's video there's a clip
of it playing so definitely check it out
and if you want to connect or suggest
any ideas for new videos I'm on Twitter
at tomf frankley or you can leave a
comment on this video
[Music]