we are rapidly approaching final exams
right now so hopefully you are aspiring
to greatness because greatness is what
precedes the growing of a great beard so
if you feel a little bit of prickly
stubble coming in well you know your
aspirations are on the right place
anyway today we're going to talk about
how to not make dumb mistakes on exams
I've been emailed about this question a
lot and I want to tackle 10 ways that
you can stop making those stupid
mistakes but first a quick recap just
last week Thomas released a video on
test anxiety as you may be aware Stress
and Anxiety are two abating causes of
stupid mistakes on exams therefore if
you have not yet seen that video it is
highly recommended that you click the
carard right now and go your eyeballs to
it also this is not Thomas it is
obviously the announcer gu from The
Legend of Kora would I lie to
you all right so that out of the way
let's get into our first tip and just to
warn you some of these might seem a
little bit obvious but as is my Mo I
want to be pretty comprehensive in
addition to brief so even if you've
heard these before try to put them into
practice so number one be aware of the
time you have for your test and aim to
finish early put some time pressure on
yourself just like with your homework
assignments time pressure can help you
in the context of an exam so if you've
got 50 minutes prepare to finish in 45
that way you got time to double check
later speaking of double checking that
is tip number two so put the kabash on
the I don't feel like it mindset when it
comes to doing it because I know it's a
pain in the butt but five extra minutes
in the testing room going over your
answers can mean the difference between
an A and A B and what were you going to
do with that extra 5 minutes anyway like
go on Reddit back at your dorm or
something so double check those answers
tip number three has to do with tests
that use Scantron bubble sheets and
that's something that I used to do in my
own tests so basically when you've read
a question on the test and you figured
out the answer and then you're about to
transfer it over to that bubble sheet
first either lightly touch your pencil
or your finger to the letter of the
answer and then say the letter in your
head that will drastically cut down the
chance that you'll bubble in the wrong
letter on your scan trun sheet which is
an incredibly common error on that test
format tip number four has to do with
the work you do on scratch paper and
it's simply to draw a box around each
problem's work that way when you're
looking at your scratch paper to fill in
an answer you don't accidentally pull
data from a different problem tip number
five is to slow down and read the
questions fully and watch out for trick
wording a lot of questions might say
which of these is not instead of which
of these is so if you tend to read
questions too quickly and you're making
mistakes then use a pacing device like
your finger simply move it along the
text of the problem and let your eyes be
paced by that finger I do this every
single week when I'm proofreading the
emails I write for the college infog
geek newsletter subscribers because if
I'm sending out an email to 177,000
people I don't want to make a mistake
and it's pretty easy for me to put typos
tip number six has to do with your
essays and it is to no matter how easy
the essay seems at first create an
outline for that essay before you start
writing yes it's good for organization
but the big thing it helps with is
staying on topic a lot of students
immediately take the prompt and then
start writing from scratch and the
stream of Consciousness style writing
often ends up with their essay going
into territory that the professor didn't
want them to write about now while I'm
all for freedom of expression and
creativity in your writing if you're not
really staying on topic with the essay
you're not going to get a good grade so
make sure you're staying on topic and
use an outline tip number seven
seriously cut down on your test anxiety
tip number eight is to check your
spelling and grammar on essay style
exams wa did I really put that on my
list that is way too obvious anyway
moving on tip number nine is to do a
sanity check after you get your answers
on math problems before you go through
the actual work of solving a problem you
probably have a general ballpark idea in
your head of what the answer should be
so when you actually get that answer
compare it to that ballpark number if
it's way up the mark it doesn't mean
your answer is necessarily wrong but you
should probably double check your work
just to make sure and finally tip number
10 is to Simply know your own brain do
you have specific mistakes that you tend
to make a lot maybe you get the order of
operations wrong or maybe you tend to
multiply things together that should be
added whatever they are do your best to
notice them when they happen and then
when you're taking your next test pay
special attention on those areas so now
that we've gone through those 10 tips
and you've got some ways to combat
making stupid mistakes in your next exam
here's a big related question if you've
already written down an answer and now
you have the compulsion to change it
should you actually change it well
there's actually research on that topic
and we'll be covering it in next week's
video so subscribe to this channel if
you haven't already and hey thanks for
watching this
one hey guys thanks so much for watching
this video on how to combat making
stupid mistakes on your tests if you
like this video you can support it by
leaving a like here on YouTube and also
if you want to get new videos every week
on being a more effective student you
can hit that big red subscribe button
right there if you want to improve your
grades I also wrote a free book on the
subject and if you want to get a free
copy just click the picture of it you
can find links to anything I mentioned
in this video at the companion blog post
which you'll find by clicking the orange
logo right there last week's video
covered test anxiety and it's really
related to this topic so if you missed
it click the thumbnail and check it out
lastly if you have questions or ideas
for new videos or just want to connect
you can follow me on Twitter at tomf
frankley or leave a comment below see
you in the next video
[Music]