hey what is going on guys so when it
comes down to it this channel is kind of
all about building your resources right
I mean we have videos about building
your cognitive abilities so you have the
resources to take on tests and do
challenging work we have videos on
improving your health so you have more
energy on a daily basis and we have
videos talking about a lot of tools that
can help you be more productive and get
a lot more work done but one of the
resources we haven't talked a lot about
on this channel is your money which is
kind of weird because I actually spent
the last three and a half years
co-hosting a personal finance podcast on
the side and I am not too proud to admit
that I have spent many a Saturday night
in the past staring at a financial
spreadsheet does this look dull to you
so now that I have lost all of my
friends I've got time to break down
seven really common financial mistakes
that you're gonna want to make sure you
avoid if you want to start building a
solid financial base queue dilemmas so
our first common financial mistake here
is failing to plan for medium-term
expenses and by this I mean expenses
that are more than a month out but still
coming up in the sort of near future now
if you're like most people you are
probably very well aware of the fact
that you have to pay rent at the end of
the month and you have many other
typical monthly expenses you have to buy
groceries every single week and tomorrow
you need to go out as soon as possible
and by the tim and eric' chrimbus
special DVD you know this but what you
might not be as aware of is the fact
that maybe three months down the line
you've got to buy textbooks for your
next semester or that a holiday is
coming up and you have to buy gifts a
lot of people don't think about these
medium-term expenses and that can get
them into trouble so this is why it's
important to frequently look ahead and
ask yourself the question what is coming
up in my life I think of this as a
mindfulness practice think about all of
your life's dependencies and what you're
going to need to do in the medium-term
future to make sure that they are all
going to continue to run smoothly and
that you're prepared for any expenses
that they might bring
mistake number two is making big
financial decisions in your life without
running a what-if analysis this
basically means you take the data that
applies to your current financial life
and then you ask what if and you ask it
using data you ask what would happen if
I say bought a new car or got a new job
or took a pay cut I'm a current job
because I maybe want to cut down to
part-time hours so I can pursue a
passion a lot of people jump into these
big decisions without actually seeing
but they are going to do to the numbers
that run their financial life now for
all my flaws and all the dumb decisions
that I make in my life one thing that I
am NOT is one of these people because
for the past couple of years I have been
developing this very complicated
spreadsheet that basically runs my
entire financial life and allows me to
easily run these what-if analysis is it
analysis analyses now analyses yeah now
what you're gonna see on the screen here
probably looks a little bit complicated
you definitely don't have to build
something this crazy though I am gonna
have a publicly available demo version
of this spreadsheet in the description
down below if you want to download it
and start playing with it but
essentially I've built this spreadsheet
so that I can put in all of my income
sources and all of my typical monthly
expenses and then over on the left side
I've got cells that add everything up do
subtractions do division addition all
those other math things and tell me
essentially how much money is left over
at the end of the month how much I'm
investing how much I'm spending on
housing and all sorts of other useful
things now to be honest I have gotten
pretty nerdy with this I even have a
second page in the spreadsheet that has
accurate federal tax brackets and state
tax brackets so I can see what I'm going
to be paying in taxes given the amount
of income I bring in during the year and
the best part of this is that I can if I
want to make a change in my life
simulate that change before I actually
make it in reality so whenever you are
contemplating a big financial change in
your own life I would implore you to run
a what-if analysis like this build a
spreadsheet or at least know in your
head how much you roughly make on a
monthly basis and how much you roughly
spend on a monthly basis and then do the
simulation in your head or on paper so
you know it's gonna happen before it
actually happens and you don't get
yourself into hot water
big mistake number three and this can be
a potentially very big mistake is not
having an emergency fund a lot of people
out there are so gung-ho about paying
off their debt quickly or investing
money in the stock market or other risky
investments that they don't take the
time to actually build a base of cash
that they can use if something goes
wrong so to give you a little bit of
insight on my personal finance
philosophy I feel like your number one
goal when trying to establish a
financial base is ensuring that you can
take a punch
what's a punch well a punch is when
someone balls up their fist and they
connect those bones and tissue and skin
with your face and then you get a bruise
but in metaphorical terms a punch is
really anything that sort of requires
you to pay a bunch of money that you
weren't expecting
in order to continue living your life
the way that you want to live it and to
make things really simple the way that
you ensure you're able to take a punch
is by establishing an emergency fund
having a base of cash that you can tap
into if you need it
now a lot of people have asked me how
much do you actually need to have in an
emergency fund how much do you have
saved up and your checking or savings
account before you can start
accelerating debt payments for investing
and well I can't give you exact numbers
here because there are huge
cost-of-living differences all around
the world and many other variables to
work with I do have a couple of ballpark
numbers that I think are good rules of
thumb to start with so goal number one
in my mind would be to establish an
emergency fund of $500 now to be clear
this is just a ballpark number that I
think is a useful figure to start with
but it may be different if you live
somewhere in the world that has a very
different cost-of-living index then say
the average cost of living here in the
United States so if you want to find out
what a good equivalent number might be
for you live you can actually go over to
a site called numb Bo calm and run a
cost-of-living comparison between two
cities for example here I want a
comparison between Des Moines Iowa which
is my hometown and Prague as you can see
it costs 1.3 times as much to live in
Des Moines Iowa as it would to live in
Prague now these are definitely averaged
numbers based on aggregate data so there
are going to be variations in real life
but this is a good planning tool anyway
goal number two after you have
established that $500 emergency fund is
to figure out your
number what is your number well your
number is your minimum monthly expenses
so this means cutting out Netflix
cutting out Spotify cutting out all the
chocolate you buy at the grocery store
yes this is projection and figuring out
how much do you need to basically
maintain a minimum standard of living
where you are actually living so not
getting kicked out of your apartment or
anything but you know buying rice and
beans living in your apartment and all
that stuff so maybe you look at your
bank statement you find out that last
month you spent $1,200 on all of your
expenses and then you look through all
the expenses you cut out the ones that
seem non-essential and you get down to a
number of $800 so $800 a month is your
minimum monthly threshold goal number
two is to build up that amount of cash
in your checking account at all times
which means after all monthly expenses
are taken care of that amount of cash
should be left over in your bank account
you should never go below it and finally
go up number three is simply the
combination of goal number one and goal
number two have a $500 emergency account
somewhere maybe a savings account and
then have your minimum monthly expense
as a cushion in your main checking
account only then should you start
accelerating debt payments and by
accelerating I mean going beyond the
monthly minimums or investing in maybe
riskier investments like the stock
market mutual funds whatever it may be
[Applause]
all right mistake number four is
carrying a credit card balance now I
have had a credit card for about nine
years now and I use it every single day
but I do not view my credit card as
credit I don't view it as borrowing
money I view my credit card as simply an
intermediary step between my bank
account the money that I know I have and
the purchases I want to make this means
that while I do use my credit card for
most everyday purchases I make sure that
I go in every single month and I pay off
the balance in full and as a fail-safe I
also have an auto payment setup so I
know it's always going to be paid now
the reason that this is so important is
that credit cards are in general a very
bad tool for borrowing money I don't
think that the concept of debt itself is
inherently evil but the way that credit
cards do it can get you into trouble
really fast because credit cards often
have a 20 percent interest rate or
higher and if you start building up a
balance the compound interest from that
high interest rate can start to get you
into a position where you can never dig
your way out because the interest is
accumulating faster than you can pay it
down so please raise your hand and swear
to me that if you're going to use a
credit card and I think that you should
always pay your balance off at the end
of the month never carry one and never
pay a dime of interest to the credit
card company now our fifth mistake here
is kind of the opposite side of the coin
from our last mistake and it is refusing
to build credit at all some people out
there are just so fearful of debt that
they refuse to use credit cards outright
they refuse to take on any debt
whatsoever they hate debt but this can
be a destructive mindset think about
this philosophically for a second
there's the saying that goes no man is
an island and it is more true today than
it ever has been in the past to achieve
almost any of your big goals today
requires participation in society and
that participation usually involves
interactions between strangers and like
this are not one of the primary ways
that our society uses to gauge the
trustworthiness of strangers is to use
their credit history can you borrow
money and be trusted to pay it back and
many of the basic things in life used
this as a trust indicator whether it be
something as big as getting a mortgage
for a house or something as relatively
simple as getting approved for an
apartment lease I actually know people
who have applied to live at apartments
and they have had more than enough money
in their bank account to pay for six
months or even a year's worth of rent
but have been rejected because they did
not have an adequate credit history so
as soon as you can start looking for
ways to intelligently build up credit
when I was 18 years old I did this by
getting a credit card with a five
hundred dollar limit and just as I do
now I went in every single month and
paid the balance off in full and
honestly if you do this you don't even
have to use it for every single
transaction you don't even have to carry
it with you on a day-to-day basis and
deal with the temptation to use it you
could lock it in a drawer and just said
to pay something like your Netflix or
Spotify bill all right mistake number
six is failing to invest your money or
waiting far too long to do so Albert
Einstein once may or may not have said
that the most powerful force in the
universe is compound interest it's kind
of one of those quotes that has a less
than trustworthy sourcing but it is true
compound interest can work wonders for
you if you get in on it early enough so
to answer two questions related to
investing
first and foremost where do you invest
this is one of the areas where people
get tripped up because there are so many
choices out there and they just simply
don't know where to start so they get
analysis paralysis now I am NOT a
registered financial adviser by any
means and I don't want to be the kind of
person who's telling you where to put
your money so I will just tell you what
I have done myself when I was a junior
in college I started an account with
Vanguard and I started investing a small
monthly amount with them every single
month and then later I complimented that
with an account over at betterment comm
and aside from those resources there are
many other places to invest your money
out there there are places like fidelity
there are places like probably your
local credit union or bank but the one
thing that I'm going to point out here
is that you want to avoid high fees in
whatever investment you choose anything
more than 1% is probably just a reason
to avoid that investment beyond that
there are great books out there like I
will teach you to be rich where you can
learn more and we actually did an entire
episode on investing on our podcast so
I'll have that in the description below
and there are also websites out there
like Bogle heads which give really solid
and I think sane investing advice so
those might be good places to check out
and that brings us to our second
question I get
quite a bit because I'm in the college
and student space and that is should I
pay off all my student loans as fast as
I possibly can or should I pay the
minimums and use all my excess cash to
start investing early now this is a
nuanced question I should probably make
an entire video on it but I'm going to
give you my abridged thoughts here first
and foremost the answer to this question
is going to be very dependent on how
tolerant of holding debt you are if
you're one of those people who is very
emotionally affected by having debt then
you should probably pay that off as
quickly as possible that being said if
you are more tolerant of holding a
little bit of debt then we can start to
get a little bit nerdier about this so
an investment is going to have a certain
rate of return right and your debt is
going to have a certain interest rate so
if the rate of return on investment is
higher than the interest rate on your
debt then putting money towards that
investment is going to make you a little
bit more money in the long run than if
you were to put more money towards the
debt and not invest at all there's a
spread between those two numbers and
that's where you can make more money but
the problem is that the rate of return
on any investment out there is uncertain
that is the nature of investing you have
to take on some risk to get reward so
because of that you have to be slightly
risk tolerant to use this strategy now
if you invest in something like an index
fund which is just a simple investment
that follows the stock market and you
look at the historical returns of an
investment like that over the long term
then you get a rate of return around 7%
and there's a great blog post that'll
link in the description down below if
you want to see the data behind that now
you might be thinking 7% sounds great
and my student loans are at 4% so it's
clearly a good decision right the one
thing you have to keep in mind here is
that 7% figure is a long term figure
sometimes the market may be way up and
may return like 20% and some years like
2008 you get a negative return you could
lose a bunch of money so we're talking
about long-term returns here and you
have to be risk tolerant and for that
reason I think that it is a good idea to
have a little bit of a cushion between
that 7% figure and your interest rate on
your debt so here is my rule of thumb
for those of you who are a little bit
risk tolerant and want to maximize your
returns as much as you possibly can I
say to pay off any debt that has a 5% or
higher interest rate as fast as possible
don't invest until you do this of course
get your emergency fund but don't
invest in the stock market but for any
debt that is below 5% just pay the
minimums on that debt and take all the
extra money you have at the end of the
month and put that into a responsible
investment like an index fund all right
we have arrived at our final money
mistake which is a bit more of a meta
mistake than some of the other ones on
this list but I think it is still
important and the mistake is focusing on
immediate financial ROI as in return on
investment in all of your decisions what
I mean by this is a lot of people out
there are focused on the money far too
often they chase the money and they turn
down opportunities that could result in
a lot of potential personal growth
career growth relationship growth
because it doesn't come with a paycheck
right now so once you have established
that financial base and this is
important once you are able to take a
punch start thinking a little bit more
long-term start investing in yourself
don't chase money for too long and let
your personal development stagnate and
on a related note and I have to mention
this here make sure that the investments
that you make in yourself aren't only
the result of spending money and what I
mean by that is make sure that you are
investing time and effort into your
development as well as money because a
lot of people out there think that just
by buying productivity books or buying
gym equipment they are going to
magically become stronger or more
productive or smarter and that isn't the
case when it comes to professional
development there are really three
different steps to you know any kind of
improvement there is the purchasing of
new tools which is the most fun part the
most novel part and the part that gives
you the biggest rush when you do it
but then there's also the learning stage
and the practice stage and both of these
stages are harder they're not as fun as
going out and buying something but
ultimately they're more rewarding and
more important now earlier in the video
we made a point about looking ahead and
making sure that all of your life's
dependencies are covered and one area
where people often fail to do this is in
their digital life especially when it
comes to their security I cannot tell
you how many times I've met a friend who
is using the same exact password for
their bank as they are for their final
fantasy 7 fanfiction forum login and
that is a big problem when you repeat
passwords you open yourself up to a lot
of vulnerabilities and the potential of
getting hack
and maybe even having your money stolen
so going forward make sure that you are
always using strong unique passwords for
every single online account that you
have and an easy way to do this and keep
it all managed and organized is by using
a tool like - Lee - Lane is a really
well designed password manager that can
easily generate strong unique passwords
for all of your online accounts and it
can also autofill those password and
login forms so you can easily get into
the websites that you use every single
day and what's even better especially
for me it can automatically fill in any
other form online as well this saves a
ton of time and eliminates a lot of
friction in your everyday life - Lane
can also store things beyond just
passwords that can store secure notes
for you and your payment information so
you can pay for things online really
quickly and all of your information is
stored in a patented security
architecture that has incredibly strong
encryption so if you want to start
improving your online security in a very
easy and convenient way then head on
over to - line.com slash college info
geek - give them a try for free today
and if you want to save a little bit of
money on their premium subscription
which lets you sync passwords across all
of your devices and securely share
passwords with trusted friends and
family members then you can also use the
promo code college info geek at checkout
to get 10% off your order I wanna give a
big thanks to dashlane for sponsoring
this episode and being a supporter of
our show and as always guys thank you so
much for watching if you enjoyed this
video definitely hit that like button
and if you don't want to miss out on
future videos that come out every single
week then click right there to subscribe
to this channel you can also click right
there to get a free copy of my book on
how to earn better grades or click right
here to get one more video on this
channel thanks for watching and as
always I will see you in the next video