this video is sponsored by skillshare i
have
a whole bunch of different things i want
to get good at i want to play the guitar
better i want to edit my videos better
i want to become a better rock climber
and of course i want to stop getting
crushed in fortnite so much
damn it noob master but like you i only
have so much time during the day to
practice
and i've noticed that when i sit down to
practice sometimes i'll make great
strides
but other times i feel like i make no
progress at all
what causes this discrepancy well as it
turns out
improvement isn't only determined by how
many hours you practice
but by the quality of your practice as
well amongst
athletes artists gamers and
practitioners of every other discipline
the people at the top of their game are
almost always the ones who understand
the skill of deliberate
practice like active learning
self-discipline
and even empathy deliberate practice is
really a meta skill
a higher order skill that can be applied
across nearly everything you do
so what's the first step to practicing
more deliberately
intent is i think the biggest thing i
mean you ask the question of like what
separates
a a practice session from just kind of
like playing and i think the answer is
intent like
you you you really want to say um
you know i would like to leave with
something that i didn't have before i
sat down
that's my friend charles cornell who as
you can tell is
a pretty phenomenal jazz piano player in
2019 his online following exploded
after he started posting these piano
memes you might have even seen this one
[Music]
and through years spent a music
conservatory as well as in countless
hours of intense practice alone
charles has learned that the best
practice sessions are the ones that
start out with a goal
in mind where you're going to pick up a
lot of ground and make a lot of headways
when you define
what you are going to do
in the practice room right what can
happen a lot is that you go into the
practice room and you wind up just
playing things that you already know
because it's pleasing to the ears it's
something that we can do that we can
enjoy
it's much harder to say i'm going to do
some of the things that i don't enjoy as
much
but i know why i'm doing them so that's
really the first step to deliberate
practice
know what you want to have accomplished
at the end of the practice session
to give you just one example right now
i'm working on shooting a music video
for a new song that i just released
and all the guitar parts in the song are
improvised but i need to know how to
play them again for the video
so lately all my practice sessions have
had the explicit goal
of learning and perfecting a segment of
the song
[Music]
but it's not enough to just have a goal
like charles said you also need to be
disciplined enough to do the things that
are going to get you
to that goal and to be honest it's only
the looming need to shoot this music
video that has me sitting down
slowly painfully transcribing my own
solo and i know that's the kind of
practice that i should be doing most of
the time
but i still find myself doing exactly
what charles said
sitting down and just noodling playing
things they already know
i find my biggest problem with learning
songs that other people have written
is it's so slow and i can play pretty
well
improv so whenever i sit down with a
guitar within five minutes i find myself
just noodling around improving a lot of
people find themselves falling into this
pattern with their own skills
doing the easy natural things instead of
the hard stuff they know they're
supposed to be doing
and personally i'll take all the help i
can get in overcoming this discipline
problem
whether we're talking about learning
songs in the guitar or drilling build
patterns in fortnite instead of just
lazily jumping into quickplay every time
and one thing charles told me that was
really helpful
is that because he's studied the
fundamentals that
slow painful process of learning a song
is now
almost effortless for him so that goes
into a whole other level too which is
which furthers the point
of like pushing through the things that
maybe are not as is fun
or that seem more difficult right
because what you said is like when you
when
when you learn a song that somebody else
has written that's already decided
it's so long well my solution for you
for that is okay well you need to learn
more music theory because if you if you
equip yourself with the knowledge of
being able to
hear something and understand exactly
what's going on now that process is not
slow anymore
i can hear a song once and i'll
understand like oh okay
i get how this is structured and i could
probably play along and within
you know two or three times i'll have it
down it's instant
just about but the only reason it's
instant is because i've equipped myself
with that knowledge base
they're like okay i understand music
theory and i understand you know how
that's applied
to something that sounds like this and i
can recognize those sounds
so clearly learning these fundamentals
or maybe we should call them
not so fundamentals is a key component
to deliberate practice but
how do you figure out what those
fundamentals are for your particular
skill
well one great method is to seek out
structured educational materials
the author josh kaufman stresses this in
his book the first 20 hours his book on
rapid skill development
in the book he argues that to learn a
skill quickly you should first identify
the sub-skills that matter most to you
for me that might be music theory like
charles said
once you've picked out a few of those
sub-skills the next step in conference
process is to go out and learn enough
about each one to start practicing
and this is all great advice tutorials
courses and coaches can all
offer guidance and sequencing that can
help you make sure you're working on all
the right things
they can also help you avoid hitting
dead ends or developing bad habits that
you'll have to unlearn later
but there's another perhaps even more
important method that charles mentioned
one of my my jazz teacher growing up
would always say
that she learned more from listening
than she ever did from all of the hours
of practicing
the the number of gigs she played like
all of that combined
she learned more from listening and if
we think if we think about
language as a spoken word it's like well
how does a child learn a language
they listen yeah they just listen and
over a long period of time it takes
years for a child to develop that
ability to now start to repeat things
that they're hearing
yeah and even more years for them to be
able to string together
functional sentences and then even more
years for them to be able to
form that vocabulary and those phrases
and sentences into
their own genuine authentic ideas right
that they can then
put out to the world and the world goes
i understand what you're saying
right that is a lifelong process let's
call this idea
observation as practice we are natural
observers
as charles said it's how we pick our
native language as children and when we
apply critical observation to skill
development
we learn our skills much faster so if
you're learning how to skate
watch great skaters if you're trying to
get better at a game study great
gameplay from that game
if you're an aspiring author read other
great authors and
if you want to get better at editing
videos well i follow some really
talented video editors on twitter
and they are constantly watching movies
and breaking down shots of movies like
there's one guy i forget his name but he
he's always posting these just galleries
of
shots from a scene in a movie to show
like here's the cohesion and the color
grading
or here is you know look at the dynamics
between the different shots and
different cameras
and like what that tells me is he's not
spending all of his time editing
he's spending a lot of his time watching
other people's movies
and observing that so i do that a lot
too with with my editing
i'll watch movies more often now with a
critical eye
because i'm trying to see okay what are
you doing and why and why are you
looking at that
you're pulling things that you want to
try
you're pulling bits and pieces of that
maybe at certain angles or a certain
color grading approach that you
specifically want to apply to your own
work yeah
because you want to be like oh i want to
understand how to use this
that is listening to music we hear
things that strike a chord with us
literally and and we go i want to sound
like that i want to play that
sound anywhere where you're attempting
to kind of develop a higher proficiency
with something
looking at the proficient examples and
saying i want to try
this part and i want to take that part
like that is
the best way that you can learn anything
in other words
observe but also copy take what you see
and try it out sometimes the jazz legend
clark terry had a system for learning
improvisation that he called imitate
assimilate innovate at first imitate
what you see
transcribe and then take what you
learned from the people you look up to
and innovate with what you've added to
your repertoire going back to the
editing example
i've watched edgar wright movies like
scott pilgrim vs the world which is my
favorite movie of all time
and tried to essentially imitate what
i've seen in the movies
both to pay homage to my favorite
director but also to learn what he was
doing what he was thinking what
techniques
he was employing and here's one more
beautiful thing about copying
you get a built-in instant and
guaranteed feedback mechanism
and feedback is crucial for skill
development i do want to take a second
to give a quick shout out to my friend
matt diavela
as the video that you're watching right
now is an attempt for me to get a little
bit better at blending interviews and
narration which is a style that matt
employs so well on his channel now some
skills come with it built in
chess is a great example you make a move
somebody makes a move against you
instant feedback for other skills you
can always get a coach
but that costs money or submit your work
for critique but of course that requires
a willing audience
if you have neither copying still gives
you a way to get
feedback you can always compare to the
original to see how you did
now naturally some people are going to
have worries about copying
but it's important to recognize that
there is a big difference between
passing off somebody
else's work as your own and copying
their work as a form
of practice the latter isn't just okay
it's often
crucial in music specifically we
transcribe so in jazz when we talk about
transcribing we are
literally going and listening to an
improvised
solo and we are going to replicate that
identically i mean there are still
things that
that are ingrained in my mind that i
know that i transcribed like like here's
this is a little bit of a barry harris
thing
um
now why do we do that am i gonna get on
stage
and play his solo no of course not there
are no
it's interesting there are no jazz
covers
in the way that take uh john coltrane's
giant step solo
nobody is out there performing john
coltrane
solo if they did they'd be laughed off
stage right
why is that and at the same time why is
it that every saxophone player
ever can play that solo why do we do
that well
the reason that i would transcribe barry
harris like that is
i want to know what are the devices that
he
used to create the sound that we heard
because when i heard that sound i went i
like that
i want to have that in my vocabulary
right what is it but we're not going to
go and simply perform the transcription
that would be pointless because barry
harris already said it
john coltrane already said it we don't
need to say it again we want to say our
own things
but how can we speak in that language if
we don't know
what people have said right so when you
sit down to practice
spend some time deeply observing the
people who are at the level you want to
get to
and also spend some time copying their
work so you can learn
the language that they're speaking in
terms of your skill
if you can do that while also not
ignoring the fundamentals and setting
strong intentions when you practice
you'll find yourself making a lot more
progress than you used to
so throughout this video we've talked
about several specific techniques that
you can use to improve the quality of
your practice time
but there's one final point to keep in
mind no matter the skill
building mastery true mastery takes a
lot of time
it takes self-discipline and above all
it takes strong long-term
practice habits fortunately habits are
one thing that i've learned a lot about
through all my research and
experimentation into productivity over
the last few years
and if you'd like to improve your own
practicing habits then you might want to
take my habit building class
on skillshare this class will help you
break down your goals into actionable
daily habits that have
obvious action items and then stick to
those by tailoring your environment
and by building systems and tools that
can help to bolster your self-discipline
and in addition to that charles actually
just launched his own class called intro
to improvisation
and if you're a musician you'll
definitely want to check it out what
would it be like to sit down at your
instrument
and be able to play anything you want
at the end of the class you're even
going to find a 57-minute bonus lesson
where charles teaches me
some techniques that improve my own
playing here's a trick ready
can we do it in the next key instead of
d can we start on e
another thing you're going to find on
skillshare is live sessions in fact just
recently i did an exclusive q a session
for my skillshare students which just
went up as a live replay
on my profile so in addition to my
classes you're gonna be able to watch
that
as well of course you'll also find
thousands of other classes on skillshare
from tons of talented teachers that can
help you boost your skills in areas like
video editing
photography ui and ux design music
production
and tons more it is a huge resource and
it's also a very affordable one with
your annual plan starting at less than
10 bucks
a month and you can even get a free
trial if you're one of the first 1 000
people to sign up using the link in the
description
down below so use that link sign up go
take one of my classes or go take
charles's class and start boosting your
skills today thanks as always for
watching this video if you found this
video helpful definitely hit that like
button to show the youtube algorithm
what's up and get subscribed right there
if you haven't done so already so you
don't miss out on future videos here on
this channel
also if you want to learn a bit more
about notion i just launched a new
channel
all about notion tutorials at least for
now we might branch into other stuff in
the future
but check it out right there it's called
thomasfrank explains if you're looking
for more videos from yours truly
that is where you're going to find them
in addition to this channel right here
i'll have a couple other videos on
screen so you can smash your nose
onto your phone screen to watch those
for extra style points or just click on
them
like normal and beyond that go do
whatever you want
go spend the rest of your life savings
on a first edition holographic charizard
card on ebay because as always
i'm not your dad
[Music]
that was literally the worst thing i've
ever played