Hey what is going on guys so do you ever
feel like there's just no point to
reading productivity and
self-improvement articles
I mean you pull it up you read it or
scan through it you get vaguely
motivated for ten minutes or so but
after that it really does nothing to
change your life and all these articles
even though they purport to be really
really helpful
don't actually seem to be helping well
that's what I want to talk about today I
want to talk about how to actually use
the productivity tips and the
self-improvement advice that you read
and to start out I want to share one of
my favorite quotes in the world which
comes from Derek Siver's who is a writer
and who was also the guy who founded
cdbaby.com and subsequently sold it for
millions of dollars about 20 years ago
the quote goes like this if more
information was the answer then we'd all
be billionaires with perfect ABS and I
think that today this quote is more
poignant than it has ever been because
we now have unprecedented access to
information and more specifically
self-improvement advice fifty years ago
people probably have the odd copy of how
to win friends and influence people
sitting on their bookshelves but now in
less than 30 seconds you can bombard
your eyes with more productivity tips
and life hacks than you can handle
and literally right now some was
probably publishing another one of those
articles about 47 habits that will make
2019 your best year ever oh and don't
forget that number 18 will literally
blow your mind but again if you're like
most people you probably scan through
that article and then proceed to do
absolutely nothing with it I remember
time back in college when a teacher of
mine was lamenting a very similar
problem in one of my classes he said if
I have a hundred students in this room
probably only 75 are actually going to
pay attention to what I'm saying and of
those 75 people probably 20 of them will
remember what I said after the test is
over and of that group maybe one or two
will actually apply it over the long
term fact of the matter is very few
people actually use the information that
they intake and the problem is
exacerbated on the internet because
there's just so much of it going around
there's so much to take in and you can
feel absolutely overwhelmed when you
read these kinds of articles or watch
these kinds of videos so that begs the
question how do you make sure that you
are among that group of one or two
people who actually applies the
information and makes meaningful
improvements in your life well
today I want to share a process that can
help you do that so here's how to
actually use the productivity tips that
you find on channels like mine or
anywhere else on the internet step
number one find the one problem or goal
that you want to solve above all others
and prioritize it as the author Greg
McCowen talks about in his excellent
book essentialism a true priority is
singular you need to make a decision
here and note that decision originally
comes from a Latin word meaning to cut
off you need to pick one path right now
and cut off the others now note that
this isn't a permanent choice you can
change your priorities later and it also
doesn't mean that you can't be working
on more than one thing at once but to
make notable progress quickly you'll
want to know ahead of time which one is
most important otherwise you're gonna
run into that all-too-common part of the
day where you have very little time or
energy left over but you still have to
read and meditate and exercise
oh and practice guitar as well and then
you don't really know which one to cut
so by setting a priority and by knowing
the answer to that question of which one
is most important beforehand you're
gonna save yourself a lot of time and a
lot of dead ends alright so once you've
decided on your priority it's now time
to go out and try to find resources or
tutorials and guides that can help you
make that goal a reality and if you're a
beginner it can be a really good idea to
go out and find somebody else's tutorial
or someone else's tips and follow them
exactly but if they don't work then you
don't want to reject them outright
instead you want to distill down their
basic concepts and then try to use those
concepts in a way that works for you to
adapt them so for example let's say that
I tell you that I get up every morning
really early and I read for an hour and
you want to do the same but you have
class or work really early in the
morning and you just can't make that
work with your sleep schedule well
realize that the point here is that I'm
carving out a specific time in the day
where no one can interrupt me where I
can actually make that reading happen
not that I'm doing it in the morning so
how could you work with your own
schedule and your own constraints to
gain that same benefit maybe instead of
in the morning you read after lunch or
school the specific way that I'm
implementing the technique often isn't
the point so you need to look a little
bit deeper and find the logic behind why
I'm doing what I'm doing and then adapt
it to your own specific situation case
in point the third step in my process
has a specific prescribed number in it
because I think a really great way to
build a habit to actually put a
Productivity technique into action is to
do a 30-day challenge around it do this
you want to find a way to break your
goal down into measurable steps and then
take at least one of those steps every
single day for 30 days and while you do
this you also want to keep track of your
progress on the calendar or a habit
tracking app or whatever else works for
you I've had some great results doing
challenges like this for one on
Instagram last year I did a challenge
called CID 30-day where I made sure to
do some intense exercise every single
day for thirty days and put it on
Instagram and doing that helped me get
back into the habit of doing intense
exercise on a daily basis which I'd kind
of fallen out of at the time and for
another example that actually tweaks the
concept a little bit a couple of years
ago I gave myself a three-month reading
challenge where every day for three
months I had to read 25 pages I'm a
nonfiction book I could not fail
otherwise I'd have to pay my best friend
Martin $100 and I didn't and it also
helped me to build a really strong
reading habit going forward now I do
want to give you a couple of tips for
doing this successfully first it can be
a really good idea to decide beforehand
what part of the day you're going to
practice your habit or take the steps
you decided to take when you decide
beforehand when you make a plan like I'm
gonna do it in the morning or I'm gonna
do it before bed then you often find
that your motivation to do it is a lot
higher there's a concrete plan up in
your head secondly at least in the
beginning make your steps small and
input based meaning that they can be
accomplished with just an input of time
or effort instead of a specific outcome
so for example if your goal is to write
a novel then a beginning step that's
probably gonna be pretty difficult to
accomplish each day is write an entire
chapter but something that's definitely
doable is write a hundred words or even
500 words that brings us to the fourth
step in the process which is this don't
wait for the perfect time to start
instead just get started now even if
there's a constraint just start now
realize at the time at which you get the
idea or the motivation to do something
is the time where you're gonna be the
most excited to get started so
even if you're going on vacation in two
days from now or you have a bunch of
homework to do if you can carve out the
time to do those beginning steps then
start right now take advantage of that
initial motivation and the novelty
factor that you're experiencing in the
moment also right in the beginning find
a way to keep yourself accountable again
you can mark things off in a calendar
you can use a habit tracking app or you
can even keep a journal and if you need
an extra push it can be a really good
idea to ask somebody who cares about you
maybe a friend or your parents or even a
teacher to be an accountability partner
to at least review your entries or ask
you from time to time how you're doing
finally have a way to review your
progress yourself and remember the 30
day challenge or any similar commitment
device isn't the goal in itself it's
just a device to help you build the
habits and actually make progress but
there should be a larger overarching
goal something that you want to
eventually achieve so at regular
intervals sit down and review your
progress ask yourself is doing what I'm
doing now even if it's been working
really well for 30 days is it actually
getting me any closer to my goal if I've
been writing 500 words a day do these
500 words even matter do I need a shift
gears now and actually start editing
what I've written down or should I keep
forging ahead and even if things are
going well you should still continue to
write down your progress at regular
intervals because by doing this you're
gonna get a record of your successes
which can help to motivate you on any
particularly difficult days in the
future or on the next time you read a
Productivity dips article that makes you
want to switch gears and go do something
entirely different and by successfully
avoiding that temptation and keeping
your motivation levels high through
these reviews you will continue to
actually make progress on your goals so
like I mentioned earlier in the video
one of the methods that I've used to
actually spur action is the 30 day
challenge things like my 30-day exercise
challenge or my reading challenge these
types of challenges are a great way to
get started on something to stay
motivated and to see significant
progress in a relatively short amount of
time and if you want to learn how to set
yourself up for success with this
particular type of challenge then you
might want to go watch through rich
Armstrong's course on Skillshare called
the perfect 100 day project in it he
teaches you how to intelligently pick
the right challenge how to structure it
and how to give yourself the best chance
of sticking with it the entire time plus
some switches courses on Skillshare
taking it mean to also have access to
more than 28,000 other courses many of
which can help you make progress on your
individual goals if you're trying to
improve your web development skills
there is a course for that if you want
to learn how to make great YouTube
videos there are courses for that too
and if you just want to learn how to get
organized and stay on top of things well
I made a course for you all about that
which has already been taken by almost
20,000 people a Premium Membership on
Skillshare gets you unlimited access to
that entire library of courses and it's
really affordable as well as their
annual subscription is less than ten
bucks a month and if you would like to
give it a try first you can use link in
description down below to get a two
month unlimited trial for free big
thanks goes out to Skillshare as always
for sponsoring this video and being a
big supporter of my channel and thank
you for watching as well hopefully this
video in particular was helpful
hopefully it helps you to cut through
all the clutter and actually start
making some progress and if you enjoyed
it definitely hit that like button and
get subscribed right there so you don't
miss out on future videos when they come
out you can also click right there get a
free copy of my book on how to earn
better grades and also join my weekly
newsletter or click right over here to
get one more video on this channel last
but not least if you wanna listen to our
latest podcast episode you can check
that out right over here thanks again
for watching and I will see you in the
next video