in this video I'm going to show you how
I learned to code from scratch in just
one year I'm going to show you the exact
path learning resources tools and most
importantly the learning hacks that I
used to go from a complete beginner to a
self- toop programmer building and
shipping complex apps and workflows that
are now used by thousands of people so
you can do the same thing if you want to
or maybe even get a job as a programmer
if that's a goal you have we're also
going to talk about two secret weapons
that I use both to learn faster and to
build and ship things much more quickly
as well and one of those has even become
a surprisingly good source of side
income for me I think represents a
pretty interesting side hustle
opportunity even for people who are not
expert level coders but I'll talk about
that later on in the video first here's
an outline of everything we're going to
cover here I'm going to try to make this
as comprehensive as possible so it's a
jumping off point that you can use if
you want to learn how to code and we're
going to talk about how I picked my
language how I got started the exact
learning resources that I used all of
which are completely free by the way
we're going to talk about those two
secret weapons I mentioned a few
learning hacks I use to learn even
faster and some of my favorite
programming tools feel free to skip
around this video all you like I have
time stamps in the description down
below we're going to start off with a
bit of a discussion on how I got started
and how I chose my programming language
because one of the most common questions
people have when they want to learn how
to code is what language should I start
with so personally I started with
JavaScript and I focused specifically on
what's called back-end programming and
backend programming has to do with
everything that happens sort of under
the hood or behind the scenes whereas
front-end programming has to do with the
actual interfaces and controls that you
actually interact with on websites and
apps so think of backend coding kind of
like designing or building a car engine
whereas front-end coding would be like
designing the car body itself but also
the controls like the steering wheel or
the ejector seat button so for example
my favorite project that I've built so
far also vastly the most complex project
I've built so far is called notion voice
notes and it's a few thousand lines of
code that essentially take an audio file
like a lecture recording or a voice note
or a podcast transcribes it to text
summarizes that text with AI into lists
like the main points and the action
items and then creates a brand new page
in my notion note taking system with all
of that detail so I can basically take
notes with my voice and to interact with
that system all I have to do is upload
an audio file to Google Drive and then
everything happens automatically in the
background that's what I mean by backend
coding and I'm telling the story because
that workflow taking notes of my voice
is actually one of the primary
Inspirations I had to learn how to code
in the first place I have wanted to be
able to take notes with my voice for
years I go for a lot of long walks and
I've always wished I could just record a
voice note and then get like a perfect
transcription later on that I could read
through skim add highlights to all that
good stuff and then literally in the
airport on the way to my honeymoon after
getting married last year I came across
a blog post in line for coffee uh by
somebody who was using JavaScript and a
few other free tools to transcribe
podcast episodes to text and as I was
scrolling through that blog post I
couldn't understand any of the code in
it at the time but I was confident that
if I could come to learn enough
JavaScript to understand that code I
would be able to modify it and I would
be able to build my voice note taking
workflow so the choice for me was clear
I needed to learn JavaScript there was
another reason as well I wanted to send
my notes to notion and the notion API is
primarily used with JavaScript that made
the choice clear for me and if you're
watching this if you're confused about
what language you should start with note
that I'm not telling you you should
start with JavaScript but I am telling
you you should start with the same kind
of inspiration you should pick a
language that will let you build
something that is interesting to you
personally because at the end of the day
programming languages are just tools so
if you're just saying I want to learn
how to code it's kind of like saying I
want to learn how to use a hammer and
yeah I can get a loose piece of 2x4 and
have some Nails sticking out of it I can
teach you how to swing a hammer but
you're going to have a lot more success
if you start with something that you
actually want to build like I want to
build a house or I want to build a
computer because once you have the
project in mind you're going to know
what tools you actually need for it so
once you understand the project you're
going to understand what tool you should
pick but you're also going to learn a
lot faster for a couple of different
reasons first having a goal in mind
having something that you're interested
to build is going to focus your
attention because programming languages
are full of tons of different subskills
and methods and classes and you kind of
have to know which ones to learn and
focus on at first otherwise you're going
to be very very scatterbrained the other
thing the more important thing is when
you have an end goal in mind your brain
is going to understand that what you're
learning even if it's kind of boring in
the moment or on its own is relevant to
something you care about so it's going
to be stick here you're going to retain
it much more easily now there are some
other factors that go into language
selection like the popularity of the
language how competitive it is in the
job market if you are trying to get a
job as a programmer the difficulty of
learning language in general and there's
a whole great post on free code Camp's
website that goes through these
considerations and talks about them I'll
link to that in the description below
but the really nice thing about starting
with a language that's going to help you
build something interesting uh in the
short term is once you learn that
language if you have to learn a second
language in the future it's going to be
much much easier and the reason for that
is that we can break programming down
into two general categories of subskills
we have language specific subskills so
things like the syntax of the language
its quirks maybe the Frameworks or tools
that you use to work with that language
but then we have a much bigger category
of universal programming skills so
things like uh data structures working
with functions um just The Logical
practice of solving problems with code
and once you kind of hone your skills in
this category with your first language
you take those skills into your second
language and all you have to do is kind
of apply them to the syntax and the
quirks of the new language so learning a
new language if you have to for a job or
anything else is going to go way way way
faster than learning your first language
and speaking of learning let's now talk
about the learning resources that I use
to learn JavaScript so the main one that
I'm going to recommend for anybody who
does want to learn JavaScript which I
think is a great first choice if you are
interested in building web apps or doing
backend programming like I do or
building websites is this JavaScript
algorithms and data structures course on
freecodecamp.org like I said everything
in this learning resources section is
completely free and as the name in free
code Camp implies this is a completely
free course I also think it is
absolutely the best beginner resource
for anybody trying to learn JavaScript
and the reason for that is there are
tons and tons of mini lessons in this
course there's a whole bunch of modules
here and every one of them has a bunch
of different mini lessons each one of
those mini lessons is kind of a
self-contained challenge so you're
immedi Med having to write code while
you're learning so for example we have
Understanding uninitialized Variables
right here it gives you a little bit of
a lesson on what it's trying to teach
you and then it immediately asks you to
write code and it has a button where you
can run tests and see if your code is
actually right or if there's a bug in it
so this immediately gets you writing
code instead of just like reading Theory
or going through a book and I think that
is the best way to learn any programming
language not just JavaScript if you can
get your hands dirty and start coding
right away you're going to learn a lot
faster and you're going to be a lot more
motivated to keep learning now before I
go on to the next Learning Resource that
I want to recommend here I have two
little tips things that I did with this
course that I think are worth mentioning
first and foremost alongside this course
I had a little test folder in my own
programming editor I use vs code right
here and basically when I would run
across a particularly interesting lesson
I would try to take the lesson and remix
it and challenge myself to go do
something different with it so for
example if the lesson was teaching me
how to write a really basic for Loop
where it just prints out 1 2 3 4 5 Etc I
would go into my editor and challenge
myself to kind of up the ante a little
bit instead of going 1 2 3 4 5 what if I
skipped every third number or what if I
went just the even numbers and doing
that is a great way to take a challenge
that's just a tutorial challenge
something that someone else has laid out
for you and turn it into something that
you have more ownership over and
something that you care about more in
business there's this this idea called
the Ikea effect where people have more
Affinity they're more proud of the
furniture they own from Ikea because
they had to actually go through the
process of building it themselves this
is also applied really successfully in
video games like Minecraft even in
software like notion I think a big
reason people love notion is they get to
build stuff and be proud of it and when
you're learning programming you can use
this concept to your advantage you can
take the tutorials and take the concepts
they're trying to teach you remix them a
little bit and kind of turn it into play
almost the second thing and this is
going to be kind of controversial that I
did here uh is I went through if I go
back to the free code Camp course I went
through the basic JavaScript module
which is 113 lessons then I went through
the es6 module which is 29 and then I
actually quit the course I didn't go
through this regular Expressions module
the debugging I didn't go through any of
these because es6 and basic JavaScript
taught me enough to go off and build the
thing I wanted to build at the time I
had two kind of main Inspirations the
first we already covered which which was
me wanting to build a voice notes uh
workflow the other one is I really
wanted to teach the notion API over my
second Channel Thomas Frank explains and
I had this really fun project idea that
I wanted to build I wanted to make an
automated Pokedex generator where I
would pull Pokemon from an API and bring
them in automatically and after going
through those first two modules I felt
that I had enough knowledge and I had
enough Tools in my tool belt to go off
and start building that I also had
enough knowledge to now go out and look
through references look through kind of
like reference resources and figure out
things that I didn't know without having
to go through a structured course so one
thing that I would recommend that you
follow something that I do all the time
is no matter what kind of educational
resource you're going through don't feel
that you have to complete it 100% before
you can go off and try doing your own
stuff instead think of the educational
resource as a reference maybe you need
to go through the first few modules to
sort of just get your feet wet and
understand the basic language of the
skill you're learning but then if you
get into inspiration if you want to go
build something don't feel that you have
to complete the entire course before you
can go do that let the inspiration carry
you okay so I went through the
JavaScript algorithms and data
structures course that is the main
resource I would recommend here the next
one is uh the modern JavaScript tutorial
which you can find over at J javascript.
info so this I think is a great
compliment to that free code Camp course
because where that one is a little bit
light on explanation and heavy on
exercises and actual coding this is the
exact opposite so let's say I search for
arrays here I think they'll probably
have an article on arrays within this
here it is this is basically a really
well-written online free book that
basically can teach you everything that
the other course isn't teaching you so
if you're going through an exercise in
the course and you want to kind of
understand the concept that's teaching a
bit more the modern JavaScript tutorial
is my number one resource recommendation
for going through it um there's also an
actual reference guide which I'm going
to cover next but I think the modern
JavaScript tutorial is a bit easier to
read it's a bit more fun to read so
consider that to be an important tool in
your programming especially JavaScript
focused tool belt and the third one that
I'm going to mention which I think makes
up the trifecta of the ultimate
JavaScript learning resources in my
opinion is the mdn web docs so these are
basically like the de facto official
documentation for uh JavaScript and for
a lot of web Technologies actually but
they have this whole JavaScript uh kind
of guide you can go through I think you
could actually learn JavaScript going
through just this website but the real
strength here is any sort of function
that you're trying to use or piece of
language you're trying to understand
there is comprehensive documentation on
it on this website so for example there
is a function I use all the time called
map and right here array prototype map
they have a whole article on it they
have a demo they have syntax they have
parameters and most importantly they
have examples right here so if you want
to understand how to use a function like
this you would go to the mdn web docs
and for for that reason I would
recommend keeping this in particular as
a bookmark resource on your computer a
couple others that are worth mentioning
first there is a uh weird JavaScript
course by fireship on YouTube which I
think is really really fun it's um kind
of like a high level overview of
JavaScript and all these videos are
super entertaining to watch highly
recommend watching those and also just
subscribing to fireship in general he
has some of the best programming content
on YouTube and then the last Learning
Resource I want to talk about here isn't
anything in particular it's more of a
general recommendation to kind of just
let yourself get obsessed with coding if
you feel the interest just sort of like
start learning by osmosis so this is
something that I definitely did as I was
watching through videos like fire ships
here on YouTube I started to notice that
my recommendations had more and more
stuff about JavaScript and so a lot of
times if I was like eating dinner or
lunch or something instead of going to
Netflix or watching a movie I would
watch programming content on YouTube
instead and just sort of learn by
osmosis for example when I was going
through this fireship course my YouTube
algorithm took notice and started
recommending me lots and lots of
JavaScript related content on my home
feed one of those videos was this video
right here on what the heck is the event
Loop Anyway by Philip Roberts and I just
watched that while eating dinner one
night and now I have a much better
understanding of how a synchronous code
Works in JavaScript I probably wouldn't
have even thought to look that up in the
first place but it was just recommended
to me and I watched it and I'm really
glad that I did okay so it's now time to
go into secret weapon number one in this
video and that secret weapon is chat GPT
but probably not in the way that you
think because a lot of people especially
a lot of people that I follow on Twitter
or that end up in my feed will say chat
jbt can write code for you we have
GitHub co-pilot which uses chat gbt to
basically generate code on the Fly and
if you're already a professional
programmer that can be a great way to
boost your productivity but if you're
trying to learn how to code letting chat
gbt write code for you is actually a bad
idea because you are not going to come
to understand how that code is actually
working you have to write it yourself so
what I did instead was I use chaty PT as
a learning tool and I came to discover
that it has two major strengths that the
courses and reference materials that I
was using primarily kind of lack the
first one is that chaty PT can tailor
the level of the material that it's
generating for you on the Fly to Your
specific needs something like a course
or a reference guide can't do that
because it's written for lots and lots
of people whereas with chat PT you can
say hey I didn't quite understand that
could you give me some more examples
could you bring this down to say like a
10th grade level some something like
that so for example I have uh one piece
of History here where I was asking what
is a set can you teach me about it and
how running the has function in it is
more efficient than some alternative I
can't remember what the context was but
here it basically generates a mini
article for me and if this wasn't enough
I could ask for more examples or more
Guidance just to make sure that my
understanding was clear the other thing
that I've learned with chat gbt is it is
fantastic for eliminating what's called
a second order incompetence which you're
basically basically the things that you
don't know that you don't know literally
the stuff in the skill that you just
don't even know exists yet and I found
that if you prompt it right chat chbt is
really good at helping you discover
these kinds of things so just to give
you an example here uh here's one of the
prompts I gave it I gave it a function
that I wrote myself and I said here's a
function I wrote that fetches Pokemon
from the Poke API creates an array of
objects with their data you don't have
to worry about what this code does in
this video this isn't a technical level
video but this is key how would a senior
J developer improve this code and then I
said for each suggested Improvement
please explain why you've suggested it
as if I'm a student unaware of it so I
pasted my code below the prompt here as
context and then it gives me a whole
list of suggestions here use promised
that all for concurrent requests
refactor error handling separation of
concerns and a lot of these Concepts the
first time that I wrote a prompt like
this I had no idea existed for example
this concurrent requests suggestion here
I didn't know what that was and it
turned out to be one of the most useful
Concepts I ever learned as a programmer
and I'll just take a little bit of an
aside here to explain it so a lot of
what I do with my programming is I write
code that reaches out to apis and then
gets responses so for example if I want
to get a Pokemon from the Poke API I
have to make a request and then I have
to get the response so if I wanted to
get say 100 Pokemon I might write a loop
which is one of the first things you
learn about as a programmer and it would
do it as many times as needed Reach Out
get the response then kick off the next
iteration reach out get the response and
do that 100 times when I learned about
concurrency I learned that you can
basically write code that will reach out
and it doesn't have to actually wait to
get the response before it will send the
next request and just to show you an
example of how powerful this is um over
on a platform called pipe dream which
spoilers is my next secret weapon but
I'm going to show you here I wrote some
code to show just how much faster
concurrency can be than what's called
serial programming where we're just
waiting for the response before before
we kick off the next iteration of our
Loop here so I wrote some code that
grabs the first 50 Pokémon both in
serial and using concurrent code and we
can see here to get these 50 Pokemon
names with serial calls it took 7
seconds or 7,000 milliseconds here
whereas the concurrent calls doing the
exact same thing only took 530
milliseconds just over half a second so
we get this massive speed increase just
by implementing concurrency and again I
didn't know about that at all I didn't
know it existed as a concept until I
asked that magic question how would a
senior JavaScript developer improve this
code and then please explain the
suggested improvements now I could
probably do a whole video in the future
on chat gbt I've used it for a lot more
Beyond coding what I will say to wrap up
this section is still realize that chat
GPT can get things wrong so it is really
important not to lean entirely on chat
GPT as a teaching tool I truly believe
you should go through courses and get
very familiar with the official
documentation at the mdn web docs and
then use chbt as a support tool that
supports those official resources that
brings us to secret weapon number two
which I've already showed you a little
bit in this video but the tool is called
pipe dream and it's kind of like zapier
or make.com it's like a no code
automation tool that allows you to sort
of hook up different tools together but
the real difference between pipe dream
and something like zapier is pipe dream
makes it super easy to write JavaScript
code that can actually support your
workflows and you can even bring in
packages that make your code even more
powerful and the reason that I'm listing
this as a secret weapon is I have found
pip dream allows me to build and ship
really useful workflows in incredibly
quickly and that actually encourages me
to go off and do it one of the biggest
blockers that kept me from learning
programming for a very long time was all
the infrastructure and all the extra
stuff around the actual code that you
want to write traditionally if you want
to ship an app you got to write your
code for the app but you also have to
get servers you have to think about
authentication you have to think about
uh ooth for apis and all kinds of stuff
like that and the beautiful thing about
pipe dream is it's a platform that
basically takes care of all of that for
you so if you're like me and you're very
focused on backend programming where
you're sort of like building Little
Machines That automate uh work between
different tools pipe dream makes that
incredibly fast and I want to show you
an example in this video just to show
you how powerful this tool can actually
be so here I have a very simple workflow
setup which is called audio to notion
this is basically the exact same thing I
talked about in the intro where we are
uploading an audio file to Google Drive
and then we're transcribing it and
sending the transcript to notion and
currently I'm using only no code
components so we have a trigger here
it's going to then download the file to
what's called Temp Storage we're going
to connect with open AI to transcribe
the audio file to text and then we're
going to create a brand new page in a
notet taking system in notion that has
that transcript so here I've got that
note taking system I'm just calling it
voice notes and if I go ahead and test
this workflow right here we get a
success message after a couple seconds
and if I go back over to notion we we
see voic sample. MP3 I can open that up
and you can see we have a full
transcript of an audio file that I
recorded and you could do this in a
traditional no code automation Builder
like zappier or make.com but there's one
problem that I see with this transcript
it's a wall of text there's just so many
lines of text here I would love if this
was broken up into paragraphs but
unfortunately the no code components in
pipe dream don't have an option to do
that so that is where adding code into
the mix becomes is really really useful
and the way we can do that in pipe dream
is just by adding a step and choosing
the node step right here so node.js if
you don't know about it is what's called
a backend run time for JavaScript it
basically lets you run JavaScript
outside of just the browser you can run
it on servers almost like a true backend
language like PHP and here we can use it
to basically write code that acts as
glue to do extra stuff within our
workflows in pipe dream so I'm just
going to grab a hello world component
right here and I've prepared some code
that that I'm just going to copy and
paste directly into the step again this
is not meant to be a technical video so
you don't have to worry about what this
code is doing or how it works but
basically we're importing a really
powerful Library called natural which
can split our transcript into sentences
and then I have some simple code here
that is going to basically make groups
of two sentences per paragraph So if I
test this out you can see what it does
and you can see here on the return value
area we now have our transcript but we
have some line breaks uh between these
groups of paragraphs so if I copy this
path here and I come down into our
create page from database no code action
and I basically replace this page
content call with that variable we can
test it one more time and once again we
get a success message we can go back
over to notion and now we can check out
this brand new page and would you look
at that we have actual paragraphs and
each paragraph is an individual block
inside of notion so that is really what
code can allow you to do once you kind
of come up against the limits of no code
platforms a platform like pipe dream
basically says hey write your own code
work around those limitations and you
can build a workflow that does pretty
much exactly what you want so I started
using pipe dream in that capacity I was
building no code workflows and then
adding little little Snippets of code
just to sort of add things that I wanted
and over time I got more and more
involved in the platform to the point
now where my notion voice notes uh
automation actually works on pipe dream
that is where it lives but it is
entirely based on code nothing is using
a no code component at this point and I
wrote probably 2500 lines of code over
several months uh to make this entire
thing work and that's actually the
reason that I am listing piped dream in
this video Even if you are not a
back-end Focus developer because it
represents a concept that I think is
very important for learning how to code
and that is the removal of friction like
I said before I was originally
intimidated by all the extra stuff you
have to do around coding like
authentication security servers finding
a platform like pip dream basically G
gave me a tool where I could just write
simple code write the code that I knew
how to write and get something that
actually worked and did something
interesting and that gave me enough
momentum it gave me a result that pushed
me to keep improving my scripts until
eventually I was coding uh entirely
code-based scripts that weren't using no
code components and now I'm to the point
where I actually do understand things
like authentication and servers so if I
wanted to go ahead and turn this into a
non- pipe dream based workflow if I
wanted to build a full stack app on it
I'm much better equipped to do that and
I don't think I would have gotten to
that point quite as quickly without an
interim tool like pipe dream now in the
intro I also mentioned that one of those
secret weapons has become a source of
side income for me and represents a
pretty interesting side hustle
opportunity that actually is pipe dream
as well and I want to show you exactly
why so first and foremost pip dream has
a uh a feature that a lot of other no
code tools do not have that I think is
super useful and that is this little
share link feature right here
essentially I can create this I can can
choose some settings and I can generate
a little link that when anyone clicks it
it's going to automatically rebuild this
entire workflow in their pip dream
account so it's almost like a notion
template and the other thing pip dream
has is an affiliate program and a pretty
darn good one at that because uh when
people click through and actually
upgrade to a paid account um the
affiliate gets 33% of their payments for
an entire year now pipe dream is also
incredibly powerful on its free tier so
I've been working with their affiliate
program for the past few months months
and I think only 1% of the people who
have clicked my affiliate link have
actually converted to a paid account but
just that 1% of people about 100
customers so far has generated $4,000 in
commissions over the past few months and
that number is only growing every single
month so it's this really cool thing
that I get to do where I get to
basically build free software share it
with my audience which I mainly do over
on my second Channel Thomas Frank
explains and a small portion of the
people who use that software eventually
upgrade to paid accounts maybe their
teams or just just have a lot of
automation needs and I'm able to earn
some income that way without having to
actually sell anything but if you're
following along you might be getting an
idea here because these share links are
kind of like notion templates in a way
they're just links that kind of help you
duplicate something that I've built and
uh if you've been following me on
Twitter you might know that a large part
of my business these days is selling
paid notion templates over on my website
well I think you could do the exact same
thing with Pip dream you could either
build bespoke workflows for clients in
fact I've done that for nebula or you
could build workflow templates like the
notion voice notes template that I made
or notion voice tasks template that I
made and you can actually sell those as
useful paid software I don't have the
capacity to do that right now because I
would want to offer support for it it's
just one of my values but I think
somebody who had a bit more time and a
little bit of programming skill could
really deliver value by putting together
workflows in pipe dream and then selling
them so keep that in mind as a potential
source of side income at this point in
the video we are now going to move on to
the next section which is three of my
top learning hacks for learning
programming even faster the first one is
the simplest write code often write code
as much as you can and I'm saying this
explicitly because a lot of people when
they try to learn programming get caught
up in tutorials and they get caught up
in watching Learning Materials that's
important but it's much more important
than you actually go write code and try
to build things and anything you can do
to make the process of writing code
easier for yourself anything you can do
to remove friction from that process you
should do it is one of the main reasons
I chose to feature pipe dream so
prominently in this video because it's
the tool that allows me to just spin up
useful workflows really quickly where
otherwise I might say oh that's too much
of a hassle right now I'm too busy I'm
not going to do it for example a few
months ago I was on a Discord with some
people and one person was like man I
really wish I could pull Magic the
Gathering card art into my notion
database and I was like there's a magic
the Gathering API it's called the
scryfall API I think I could whip up
something really quickly in pipe dream
that would pull the cards this person
wants from scryfall and put them into
notion so I built that in just about 20
minutes using pipe dream gave them the
share link and they were able to use it
and I learned a whole bunch of cool code
tricks along the way because it was a
new and novel challenge if I didn't have
a tool like pipe dream I might not have
taken that on because I only had about
an hour of time worth in that evening to
do it and I will recommend another tool
aside from pipe dream uh for this
purpose and that's called repet so pipe
dream is really about building
automations between apis repet is
actually almost like a full coding
platform in the cloud you can write code
in tons of different languages you can
actually run that code you can deploy
full apps I've used it I've even
embedded um some repet EDS in some of my
coding tutorials on my blog and you can
literally run code in them so definitely
check that out because it's yet another
platform that will allow you to spin up
something very quickly and again it
removes that friction from the process
of trying something out or starting a
quick project learning hack number two
is once you start building projects that
get pretty sizable you want to have a
testing folder aside from that project
where you can write specific functions
in isolation and test them and I want to
show you kind of an example here so once
again to jog your memory this is my
biggest project it's called notion voice
notes and it is absolutely massive now
typically you probably wouldn't write
code files this long in normal modern
projects that use modern design patterns
my code is in one gigantic file here
because I started on pipe dream and uh
initially I was writing in the actual
pipe dream app where you kind of have to
have everything in one file so I could
split this up but still this is a
gigantic project and it has a lot of
moving parts and if I want to test
something in the middle of the project
then uh the testing process can get
really really tedious and lengthy
because it's sort of like handing stuff
off to other functions so instead once
you get a project around this size maybe
a little smaller you want to give
yourself like a testing folder here and
this will essentially allow you to write
small functions and then test them out
directly to make sure they work before
you plug them in to your bigger project
so here I have a very small function
that is going to take a list of Pokemon
objects and I can sort them by a
specific criteria so down here just to
point this out I'm sorting my Pokemon
object by their type and if I run this
code I get an error and it says type is
not defined this is an example of quick
iteration here I can immediately get my
error where as if I was writing this
function in my giant project I would
have to go through this entire build
process and it would take me a lot
longer to get this exact error message
so here I get it right away I can go
whoops I accidentally forgot to put my
quotation marks around this word type
here let's go ahead and save the file
let's run the code again and do we get
an error message this time no we don't
and we do see that we have our Pokemon
objects sorted in reverse order by their
type water grass and fire so again give
yourself a little test area where you
can write functions in isolation and
you're going to tighten those feedback
loops and make much quicker progress and
speaking of progress learning hack
number three is to build yourself a code
Snippets note or maybe even a code
Snippets database so I want to show you
mine really quickly here to show you
what this is here in my note taking
system in notion I've got a note called
code Snippets and basically whenever I
find myself using a snippet of code all
the time in my projects I will create a
snippet for it in this note so I've got
one here this one's kind of uh verious I
don't know if that's word but I'm going
to come down here to show you this one
import the notion SDK into pipe dream so
basically if I want to work with the
notion API there is this import
statement and then there's some specific
code for creating an instance of a
client that I can use to work with the
notion API I often forget how to
actually type this out and that's kind
of okay because memorizing coding syntax
specifically for like libraries here is
probably one of the least valuable
skills you can have as a programmer
especially as AI starts to become more
and more part of our workflow it's much
more important to understand the logic
and the creative problem solving process
so here if I need to import the notion
SDK into pipe dream I'm just going to
come grab my snippet I'm going to paste
it in and then I'm going to start coding
from this base and that is going to
allow me to code much more quickly and
spend a lot less time trying to remember
hey how do I do this thing that I've
done a million times before it's all
about efficiency and speaking of
efficiency I want to now talk about some
of my favorite programming tools that
speed up my workflow and basically make
work a lot easier as well the first one
is what's called VSS code or Visual
Studio code this is an editor and there
are a lot of editors out there there's
like Sublime Text there's like notepad++
if you're really old school but vs code
is kind of seen as one of the most
popular one of the most powerful out
there it's the one that I use and um for
basically any programming language that
you're working in you can probably use
vs code uh and in particular I want to
point out a few different extensions
that you can actually add to VSS code to
make it really powerful as a learning
tool so here in VSS code which is free
it's on basically all the major systems
I can open up my little extensions area
and you can see that I have five
installed Cod Runner is the number one
extension that I would recommend
installing I think you also need to
install node.js which is pretty easy you
can just go to the website which I'll
link below install that in your computer
and the reason I love code Runner so
much is it lets you run code really
really quickly I've already shown it in
this video but I'll show it one more
time basically if I clear the output
here in the uh output tab if I just
right click and hit run code it runs the
code and I can see the results and I can
see any errors if it's going to throw an
error so this is the fastest way to just
run a snippet of code get an answer and
tighten those feedback loops there's
another extension that does a very
similar thing it is called live preview
and this one instead of basically
outputting the results of your code in
this little output tab here actually
creates like a mini browser window
inside a vs code so this can be very
helpful if you're actually writing HTML
around your JavaScript um so just like
before I have this very simple HTML file
but we have this Pokemon sorting
function that I've built here and if I
just click this little preview button
right here I can actually see what the
table is going to look like inside of a
mini browser window and the cool thing
about this extension is it will
automatically update if I change the
code so let's say I come down here and I
change my sorting criteria from Attack
to let's say name now we can see it is
uh sorting by name in reverse order if I
remove this reverse call here now it's
sorting in alphabetical order ascending
order and again this is just a super
quick way to iterate on your code make
changes and actually see the results in
real time another extension that I
highly recommend that is a great
learning tool is called quaka uh quaka
JS right here this will basically
execute code directly inside of your
editor on a line byline basis so to show
you an example of that I've got this uh
loop test.js file here it's doing
something very very simple it's just
doing a 99 Loop here that it's basically
just printing uh 99 bottles of beer on
the wall 98 97 Etc and you can see here
quaca actually will output the result of
this console log statement in the editor
itself this is a great way to learn and
to show you a very very simple example
just to drive it home let's do something
super duper easy we'll do console.log 2
* 2 and you can see immediately goes
four so you can see exactly what's
happening maybe if we use a division
operator we'll get one and again this
just teaches you in the moment what your
code is actually doing a couple more
extensions before we move on to some
other tools uh I really like eslint
which is just this great extension that
basically adds what's called linting to
your JavaScript it will uh basically
change the colors it'll highlight errors
things like that and then we also have
prettier which is a formatter that will
basically just format your code with
indentations and line breaks as needed I
love that okay a few more tools Beyond
uh VSS code that I want to recommend
here first one is called Dev utils this
is a Mac OS app that basically just has
a huge toolbox of little utilities that
come in real handy when you're
programming so for example there's like
a Json validator and formatter there's a
text difference Checker there is like a
Rex tester I believe there's all kinds
of really really useful utilities that
before I was using Dev utils I would
often have to Google for so if you are
on a Mac check that out if there is a
Windows alternative I will link to it in
the description not aware of one right
now another really useful one is called
W bin this is just a website that allows
you to send API requests or send uh
posts or get requests to apis I use this
all the time when I'm building pipe
dream workflows it's just a really easy
way to send those requests without
needing like a special piece of software
for it so I'll recommend that and then I
also recommend of course GitHub GitHub
is probably something every programmer
should get familiar with or at least
some kind of what's called version
control system so basically I can write
code on my computer I can commit it to
what's called a repository or repo and
here on GitHub this is an example of a
repo I have my notion voicenotes MJS
file it's a Javascript file just with an
m in front of it for uh I believe it's
module and I can go into the history of
this file and for any given commit I can
literally see what was changed and what
was added so all of these lines here
were added in this commit these lines in
red were uh deleted and replaced with
these lines here so if there's like a
screwup or you're working with uh
collaborators and they need to
understand what is changed about a piece
of code that's what version control is
really really good for and I would
highly recommend learning at least a
little bit about GitHub and how to use
it if you are getting into programming
okay I want to share one more tool with
you in this video and it's actually a
tool that you might find useful even
outside of programming so earlier I
showed you my code Snippets page inside
of my notion note taking database and
that notes page is inside a greater
system that I built for myself called
ultimate brain which is an entire
productivity system inside of notion a
few years ago I got really tired of
juggling all kinds of productivity apps
I had a notetaking app I had a to-do
list app I had another task management
app for my team and I eventually got to
the point where I just wished everything
could be in one place and when I found
notion I started to realize that I think
I could build a system that would
accomplish that goal inside of notion so
I spent months tinkering experimenting
learning how to use the tool and
eventually I was able to build a system
where I have my tasks my notes my goal
tracking my project management
everything I need to organize my
day-to-day life is now inside of notion
inside of a system I built called
ultimate brain and in particular my
favorite part of the system is the
project manager that I built because for
any given project I can see both the
tasks for that project and the notes for
that project all on one page and I find
that super helpful because I'm often
creating tasks as part of a project
using the context from those notes and
in addition to just using this myself I
also released it as a product last year
and since then over 25,000 people have
bought it and my team and I have
collected dozens and dozens of
testimonials from people who find it
just as useful as I do now you probably
know if you've been watching this
channel for quite a while that
traditionally we've always Rel ried on
brand deals and sponsorships as our main
source of income and that's been great
but I have to say being able to build
something that is both useful for me and
for my audience is even better
especially since we're not just selling
a notion template we also include access
to an active support Community where you
can not only get answers to every single
question you have but you can also swap
tips with other people on how to improve
your template add additions to it
customize it and improve your overall
productivity system and your workflow
and if you haven't already picked up
your own copy of ultimate brand now is
actually the best time to do it because
we are running our first ever Black
Friday sale for the rest of this month
you can get ultimate brain at a huge
discount 50% off by going over to
thomasj frank.com srain and using the
Code Black Friday 23 at checkout now you
might be asking yourself why is Tom
running a Black Friday deal he's never
done it before it's a valid question but
in this instance we actually have a very
good reason for doing it and that reason
is we're actually building another tool
that's going to make both ultimate brain
even better but also notion better for
anybody who uses it that tool is called
fly lighter and it is going to be the
ultimate Web Clipper and idea capture
tool for notion it is a great tool it's
going to help you capture screenshots
highlights add annotations to those
highlights basically it is the idea and
knowledge capture tool that I have
always wanted and the thing is we want
to build this sustainably we want to
build it in a bootstrapped way and we
don't want to take VC money I actually
already have VCS in my inbox asking
about this but I think that if we took
VC money we would eventually be forced
or at least pressured into making
decisions that weren't aligned with what
you actually want so instead what I
would love to do is be able to use the
products we already sell as a way to
self-fund the building of this new tool
and allow us to have a great free tier
in addition to the premium features that
we're planning so that is what ultimate
brain allows us to do right now and
there's also a ton of synergy here
because ultimate brain is already the
best organizational and productivity
system for notion and fly letter is
going to basically make the capture part
of that system even better so if you
want to help us build this tool you want
to also super charge your productivity
and get the best organizational system
for notion the best second brain for
notion you can go over to Thomas JF
frank.com brain and again use that Code
Black Friday 23 at checkout to get 50%
off of any edition of the template you
can pick up the Standalone Edition or if
you're Creator you can also get the
ultimate brain plus creators companion
bundle and that also gets you the exact
system that my team and I use to manage
all the content on this channel on
Thomas Frank explains on Twitter on
basically all the places where I put out
content onto the internet if you're a
serious content creator and you want to
put out more and better content I think
you're going to love Creator companion
as well so once again you can go to
thomasj frank.com brain and use that
Code Black Friday 23 at checkout to get
50% off of either edition of the
template and with that ad read over
because it's kind of an ad read but it's
my product uh to wrap this video up
seriously I want to say thank you
because not only do I get to make this
kind of content for a living but now
it's so cool I get to make a literal
startup for a living and I feel feel
like there's a way forward we don't have
to take VC money to literally build this
really cool piece of tech and that's all
thanks to you I've been putting out
content for 10 years but if you weren't
watching it then we wouldn't be able to
do any of this so seriously if you've uh
bought one of my products if you've
supported us on nebula if you have uh
supported my sponsors or even just
watched this content and help boost it
in the algorithm thank you we would not
be able to do this without you seriously
I appreciate you so much to wrap this
video up because this is a coding
focused video uh I have a couple of
different resources that I want to point
you to first and foremost if you want a
project that kind of just like takes
everything I've covered in this video
and shoves it into something you can
actually do my notion API Pokedex
project is something you might want to
go through it's a 2-hour video and
there's also a written version of it
that links to literally all the
resources I talked about in this video
secondly if you do want to learn to code
then learning how to learn more
efficiently is going to help you in your
journey and that video right there will
help you with that as well thanks as
always for watching and I will see you
in the next one