hey what's up guys so in today's video
I'm going to go over my entire planning
system that I use to get things done now
there's one thing I've learned over the
past like six to seven years of
experimenting with tons of different
apps and productivity systems and
reading the daily habits of famous
people it's that productivity is a very
individual thing we all have our own
little idiosyncrasies and weird quirks
and ways that we like to work so
different systems are going to fit
different people and your system might
be a weird Frankenstein amalgamation of
different systems that you've seen from
other people which mine is all this goes
to say that you don't need to look at my
system and think that it needs to be
your system but you might find specific
components that work well within the
things you're already doing with that
caveat out of the way I will start this
off by showing you that my system has
three specific tiers tier one which is
for idea capture and organization tier
two for weekly planning and tier three
for daily planning where all the actual
action happens so tier one I call idea
capture because I don't think calling it
task capture does it justice now in a
task management sense at least to me an
idea is any piece of information that
you want to process and take action on
later and that could include a specific
task but it could also include an event
or a free form idea that doesn't exactly
have concrete action items attached to
it yet but that you still want to save
since ideas can take a number of
different forms I use several different
apps to capture them based on their
category or action type and then process
them as efficiently as I can so specific
tasks or action items go into todoist
and I've used a number of different
to-do managers over the years like
Wonder list and productive and all sorts
of other kinds of apps and I've kind of
settled on todoist now because it's very
minimalist list it has a clean design I
can use labels to assign contexts uh
energy levels or locations to my tasks
and it also syncs between all my
different devices events will go into
Google Calendar which I've probably been
using for six or seven years at this
point and if I'm out and about away from
my computer and just have my iPhone then
I use an app called Sunrise calendar
which syncs nicely to it anything that's
not a task or an event will go into
evernote where I have lots of different
notebooks and I kind of consider
Evernote my second brain it's where all
my ideas get stored so I don't have to
keep them jumbled up in my head and then
I can process them later now tier one is
all about idea capture so I'm using
these apps on a daily basis whenever
things come up to capture things quickly
but then I don't really have to mess
with them later on Sundays I have my
planning sessions where I actually take
these ideas from all these different
tier one systems and figure out what I'm
going to do with them in any given week
and I do all that in my handy
environotes sustainable cardboard not
very attractive looking notebook now on
the current week's page I put the week's
dates at the top and then I make three
different sections events tasks and
maybe so events are things that I have
scheduled on the calend maybe meetings
with people or events I want to go to
conferences things like that and I'll
write them down there to keep them
separate from the actual tasks the task
section makes up the bulk of the weekly
plan and it basically holds all the
different tasks I want to get done in a
given week and at the top I always have
the video and the podcast because I'm a
content creator but I'll also have lots
of little things that just need to get
done and finally the maybe section holds
some tasks that I'm not exactly sure
I'll have time to do but I'd like to get
done if everything goes well and that
brings us to tier three which is my
daily plan so when I wake up at 6:00
a.m. every morning morning I come into
my office and I look at both the
notebook and my calendar and from that I
create a daily plan on my whiteboard now
the daily plan is all about action I
want it to drive me through the day and
take away all ambiguity over what I
should be doing at any given time to
help with that I try as hard as I
possibly can to write the daily plan in
the exact order that I want to do the
tasks and I also estimate at what time I
should get each one done using a fudge
ratio to account for the planning
fallacy and this helps me with lots of
practice mind you be able to basically
predict how many tasks I'll be able to
get done in a given day using the time
estimates also puts a bit of time
pressure on me which makes me work a bit
more efficiently and that's always
helpful now as I go through my day and
complete tasks I'll check them off on
the Whiteboard and then once I'm
finished with my work for the day I'll
also check off everything I got done in
the weekly plan so hopefully you enjoyed
this video and got something out of it
if you've got other planning tips I
didn't mention here or want to talk
about your own system then let me know
about it down in the comments otherwise
I will see you next
week hey there thanks for watching this
video about my planning process now i'
just like to let you know that I also
wrote a 100 plus page book on getting
better grades and chapter 4 of that book
is all about planning so if you want
some additional tips then click the
picture of the book and I will send you
a free copy if you want to get more
videos every single week on being an
awesome college student then hit that
big red subscribe button right there and
you can also find any of the resources I
talked about in this video at the
companion blog post which you can find
by clicking right there if you missed
last week's video is a clip of playing
so definitely check it out and if you
want to connect with me I'm @ tomf
frankley on Twitter or you can leave a
comment comment on this video and let me
know if you have other ideas for new
videos thanks for
watching