let's talk about resumes at some point
in your life probably sooner than you
think you're gonna have to write one of
these things and whether you're applying
for a job or an internship or in some
cases even a scholarship your resume is
likely to be the first thing that the
decision-maker sees when they're
evaluating you which means they're
important now because these things are
so important than any recruiter or
hiring manager is obviously gonna give
every single one that received the
utmost care and attention right wrong in
reality most resumes are never actually
seen by a human recruiter and if those
that actually do make it to a recruiters
desk most are unceremoniously thrown in
the trash after just a few seconds and
this is just a numbers game in fact
Google alone gets over 1 million resumes
per year and that breaks down to over
2,700 a day now those numbers seem
daunting and it can be a little bit
intimidating but there is some good news
because a lot of people make some really
common mistakes on their resumes that
can put them out of the running and if
you could learn to avoid those mistakes
you're gonna have a huge leg up on the
competition so today we are going over 5
of the worst resume mistakes you can
make and we're gonna talk about how you
can avoid them so that you get that
dream job that you are going for the
first big mistake we're gonna go over is
a tendency for people to write their
experience section in a way it lists
their job duties rather than their jobs
accomplishments but the thing is
employers do not care about what you
were expected to do at your last job
they care about what you can do for them
and they want to see concrete examples
from your past experience that point to
that and since most of them are not
albus dumbledore and they don't have a
Pensieve sitting in the corner they
can't just peer into the past and watch
you at work which means it's your
responsibility to clearly and succinctly
show what you accomplished in that
little amount of space you have here's
an example from my own resume during my
senior year I had a job on campus at a
research department and I got hired as a
web developer and I did maintain the
website I did make changes to it but at
one point I also had a small probably
three-hour project where I created an
automation script that ended up saving
the company about 240 hours of work and
since people they were getting paid
about 9 bucks an hour you can do the
math on how much money that saved now
even though the project only took me a
few hours to do in the eyes of a hiring
manager it would have been by far the
best indication to my creative
problem-solving abilities and my ability
to save their company money in the
future out of anything I did there
now you
be thinking to yourself right now I
don't have a story like this I haven't
saved a company ton of hours or
thousands of dollars yet but what you do
have is the ability to make your
achievements as concrete as specific as
possible and to quantify them to look at
another example for my resume during my
junior year I was a resident advisor at
my University and I could have just said
helped to smoothly run a community of
students but I put 62 students because
that gives a more concrete and
quantified example of how many students
I was managing big mistake number two is
believe it or not typos and grammatical
errors and you might be thinking this is
the most obvious boring tip that could
ever be on a video like this but it
needs to be said because I myself have
fallen victim to it during the summer
before my sophomore year I was getting
ready for the career fair and I created
what I thought was the perfect resume I
had a ton of experience tons of clubs
tons of part-time jobs that I could show
off I was thinking I'm gonna go into
that career fair and I'm going to crush
all the competition but to check off all
the boxes I decided to get a resume
review from my career counselor first so
I go into her office I sit down and I'm
thinking this is gonna be a five-minute
meeting she's gonna give me a gold star
and say Thomas this was the best resume
I've ever reviewed but instead she pulls
out a red pen and starts marking stuff
up and as she's marking things I start
to see that she's marking out typos
things that I did not catch myself and I
thought my resume was perfect so if you
can get your resume review to buy your
career counselor and if you can't at
least have somebody that you trust who
isn't you run over it before you start
handing it out because we are always
more scrutinizing and more careful when
we're proofreading somebody else's work
than our own
the third big mistake is listing all of
your experience and purely chronological
order instead of its relevancy to the
position you're applying to a lot of
people think they're actually supposed
to list their experience in
chronological order but this is
something that you shouldn't do because
you really don't have a whole lot of
time to catch the recruiters eye so you
want to put the most relevant thing
first in fact according to a study done
by the ladders comm recruiter spend an
average of just six seconds looking at a
resume before throwing it into the trash
and going on to the next one so if
you're computer science major applying
for a job and last summer you did an
internship and software development
where you literally built and shipped
software but then after that you just
like worked at Burger King during the
year you definitely want to put that
software development internship at the
top because the recruiter and a computer
science company is not going to care so
much about Burger King now you can
definitely go too far here which means
that there is a balance that has to be
struck in fact I got an email from
somebody in their mid-20s recently who
asked me if it would be a good idea to
put the mission trip they did when they
over eleven years old on their resume
and as I was trying to answer that
person's question I imagined myself as
the hiring director of looking at that
person's resume and all I could think of
is that something like that on a resume
is gonna look like just grasping at
straws I'm gonna think why isn't there
anything else you've done in the
intervening 15 years that deserves to
kick that thing off the resume now maybe
this doesn't apply to people who have
already had long and illustrious careers
who have 20 page CVS and tons of awards
on their shelf in their office but if
you are just looking for an entry-level
position or you're just a few years into
your career then recency does matter
the fourth big mistake that is really
common to students especially is placing
too much emphasis on paid work a lot of
students think that if they didn't get
paid for it it doesn't really count and
it doesn't belong in that experience
section but here's the thing employers
don't actually look at it that way maybe
you're like Ron Swanson you've been
working in the quarry since you were 12
years old and you have tons of part-time
jobs you were paid for that you can put
on your resume but most students don't
have that kind of experience for the
most part when students are looking for
their first entry-level job they don't
have a whole lot of paid work under
their belt and when they do it's often
stuff like working at Subway or flipping
burgers or working as a cashier
honorable work to be sure but it often
doesn't exemplify the traits that
recruiters are looking for in more
technical positions but many times those
same students have volunteer experiences
extracurriculars and clubs where they
did gain experience and what the
recruiters are looking for and if that's
you you should definitely put those
experiences right at the top of your
experience section don't hide them away
in a clubs and volunteering section and
that brings us to our final big mistake
on the list which is using the same
resume to apply for every single
position you go for this is a huge
mistake because again you've got just
six seconds to catch a recruiters eye so
make sure you're tailoring your resume
to every single position that you're
applying for if you're an active student
and it's more than likely you have a
diverse set of experiences and skills so
when you're going for a position ask
yourself what are the exact skills that
are going to look the best to a
recruiter hiring for this position and
make sure you tell your resume to show
those things first if you have both
freelance writing experience and coding
experience then a writing job is going
to take a different resume than a coding
job and the other important thing to
note here to be honest is that using the
same resume to apply for every single
job is downright lazy and it shows which
is bad because honestly one of the top
qualities that recruiters across every
single industry is looking for is a
clear indication that this candidate is
going to go above and beyond and I can
kind of wait and hear myself at this
point because I actually have eight
people on my team now and what I'm
looking to hire somebody the top
qualities in my mind are clear work
ethic a clear ability to solve problems
independently and culture fit if
somebody doesn't take those three boxes
then their technical skills don't really
matter to me and on the flip side if
they do check those boxes and they have
a slight deficiency in the technical
skills that often doesn't matter because
I know as long as they're a quick
learner and can solve problems I can
train them in those technical areas now
when it comes to your resume the best
way you're going to demonstrate these
qualities is by letting your past
accomplishments to speak for themselves
by making sure that experience section
shows off accomplishments in a very
clear and specific way but tailoring
your resume to the company and showing
that you put effort into the application
process goes a long way as well now that
being said when it comes to showing off
those more intrinsic qualities your
resume is not the best tool for the job
honestly those are probably got to come
out most in the interview when you have
real face-to-face interaction with that
hiring manager but before the interview
happens another great tool for showing
those qualities is having a website if
you have your own website then you can
build a portfolio that shows off your
work in the way that it was meant to be
seen you can show it off in all its
details and you can also show the
process that you used which shows your
work ethic and your problem-solving
abilities it also just gives you a much
more customized and vibrant way to
present yourself as you can see from my
website here which is why I think that
every ambitious student should have
their own website now if you're in high
school you're early on in college and
you're not ready to build a website for
yourself just yet I do think that you
should at the very least go and secure
your domain name I was born just a bit
too late to get Thomas Frank calm but I
was able to get my hands on Thomas J
Frank calm which is pretty good and the
earlier that you go and get your domain
name the less likely it's gonna be that
someone's gonna go take it before you
have the chance now when you are ready
to go secure that domain name the best
place to do it is over at hover with
hover buying a domain is easy its quick
and best of all it doesn't involve a
bunch of annoying upsells when it comes
to picking out that domain name you have
a ton of choice this hover has hundreds
of extensions ranging from the fun ones
like Band limo to the classics that we
all know and love like calm and dot me
also with however you can get a
personalized email address with your
domain name which can further boost your
professional presence and if you want
you can even set it up so that you can
send and receive email straight from
your Gmail inbox which I've been doing
for years and I absolutely love and once
you are ready to build that website
hover us connect feature will allow you
to easily attach your domain name to
tons of different web services including
Squarespace and Shopify so if you do
want to go lock down the domain name
then go over to hover comm slash Thomas
Frank and the first 100 people to do so
are gonna get 10% off of their first
order
thanks so much to hover for sponsoring
this video and helping to support this
channel and as always guys then
you so much for watching for something I
didn't cover in this video that you
think would be helpful definitely share
it in the comments down below and if
you'd like this video give it a like to
support this channel you can also
subscribe right there to get new videos
every single week or go right there to
get a free copy of my book on how to
earn better grades if you want you can
also check out our latest podcast
episode right there which is on how to
be a better significant otter or if you
don't want to do any of those
YouTube has algorithmically selected a
video for you to watch right there so
click it to end keep on watching so
thanks for hanging out today guys and I
will see you as always next week