oh hey there we need to have a chat
because if you're watching this I'm
guessing you're watching it in the
morning in bed as part of a social media
scroll session that you told yourself
you were not going to do when you went
to bed last night you told yourself I'm
going to get up immediately tomorrow
morning my alarm's going to go off I'm
out of bed I'm getting stuff done maybe
you have a morning routine you're trying
to go through maybe you're trying to
read maybe you had plans to go to the
gym maybe you've got an hour of time in
the morning if you wake up early enough
before you have to go to work and you
can work on that side project you're
trying to get built but instead you
grabbed your phone off of your
nightstand and you started scrolling now
I'm not going to cyber bully you in this
video because I've done the same thing
more times than I care to admit I make
productivity content on this channel but
I will be the first to admit that I'm
not always the world's most productive
person I go through phases sometimes I'm
right out of bed and I'm going into a
morning routine sometimes I just roll
right into work other times I've grabbed
my phone off my nightstand and I've
opened up Twitter and lost sometimes an
hour to social media scrolling in my
case the problem app was always Twitter
and it always starts the same right you
grab the phone you're a little groggy
you're just like I'm just going to check
my mentions while I wake up it'll take 5
seconds it's like the same lie every
single time just going to check the
mentions before I know it I'm scrolling
through the home feed I'm scrolling
through the replies on a tweet on the
home feed worst thing you can do and now
I'm looking at a tweet from somebody who
has a frog profile picture just saying
the most ignorant crap ever I want to
dunk on him I don't realize I've wasted
an hour of my life but ever since 2024
started all the way back in January I
haven't done this once and that is due
to one simple action I decided to take
when this year started it was so easy to
do physically and yet I don't know why
it took me this long to convince myself
it is what needed to be done I deleted
social media off my phone and it won't
be back Twitter is gone Facebook gone
Instagram out out of there I still check
these things on my desktop deliberately
I am a social media person after all and
I have a lot of friends who I interact
with especially on Twitter I've made a
lot of genuine great friends through
Twitter but I don't do it on my phone
now because there's a difference between
checking social media on your phone and
checking it at a desktop computer at
least in my opinion when you sit down
and decide to check it at a desktop
computer it is
intentional or at least it's more likely
to be when it's on your phone it's
likely you grab off your nightstand and
you're scrolling it unconsciously just
because it's easy it's habitual and it
promises a quick dopamine hit in 30
seconds or less and I decided that I
didn't want that to be part of my life
anymore so I took the simple 10-second
action of holding the screen hitting
remove app and getting those apps off my
phone and I'm never putting them back
again even if it's inconvenient even if
I don't have someone's phoneone number
and I'm trying to set up like a lunch
date or something I'm dming them on my
computer saying here's my phone number
call me text me
beat me if you want to reach me because
I won't have to it on my phone and this
has caused a genuinely positive change
in my life beyond just the fact that I'm
not scrolling my phone in bed in the
morning because I'm also not pulling it
out in the checkout lane to idly scroll
I'm not pushing my workout rest periods
to 10 minutes or 15 minutes cuz I get
caught up in social media it just makes
life better and I've also noticed that I
now have more energy to do things like
cooking before I feel like the constant
access to that dopamine hit that you can
just get by pulling your phone out and
opening social media makes certain
non-essential activities like if you can
order takeout cooking is non-essential
it makes non-essential activities like
that seem like too much of a pain in the
butt and when you get rid of those
social media apps at least for me you
kind of deprogram your brain a little
bit I once read in a book on habit
building could have been the Power of
Habit could have been Atomic habits
credit to you James if it's the ladder
that we don't get rid of bad habits we
replace them with better ones and I
think that's what happened here I've
replaced the bad habit of constantly
going for my phone to get that dopamine
hit with other more positive things I
find fulfillment in cooking I find
fulfillment in keeping my house cleaner
actually it's been this interesting
change and a lot of this Probably sounds
obvious to people who don't keep these
apps on their phone but I know a lot of
you watching this video have the exact
same problem you're constantly scrolling
constantly filling all those little dead
moments of the day with those dopamine
hits what would your life be like
without them well one way to potentially
find out is to try removing the apps
from your phone this is an exercise in
environmental design there's a book I
read a while back called The Happiness
Advantage by Sean AER and he coins this
term called activation energy
essentially the more activation energy
the more friction there is involved in
doing something the less likely you're
going to do it especially on a whim so
we coined this thing called the 22 rule
if you want to do something more often
make it take less than 20 seconds to
start it AKA reduce the activation
energy if I want to play guitar it's
right there I can grab it start playing
right away and conversely if you want to
do something less often make it take
more than 20 seconds to do delete the
apps off your phone if you have a
problem with ice cream like I honestly
do don't keep it in your freezer every
single day don't constantly buy a new
pint if the activation energy goes up
you are much less likely to engage in
the behavior that you don't want to be
engaging in I'm not going to tell you
you need Del delete social media off
your phone but I will report that it has
been very beneficial to me and it might
be worth trying no sponsor on this
one that's
it there might be another video right
there but um I don't know maybe clicking
another video is actually what you
shouldn't be doing right now maybe
there's something else in the real world
you should go do instead so uh touch
grass