I'm the CEO of happy gorilla vegan
protein bars we make vegan protein bars
that are 150 percent vegan last year we
did 11 billion dollars in revenue I
think the most important aspect like
literally the most important thing is my
morning routine I get up at 3 a.m. every
single morning and I meditate for 6
hours after that I'll write my gratitude
journal for a bit run about 14 miles and
after that I read 2 books I use
bulletproof coffee every single morning
it's super super good for your brain
because it has butter and midi-chlorians
in it and alongside that I usually fry
up about eight slices of black pepper
bacon a slice of beef liver and three
hard-boiled eggs and that's why my
business is so successful morning
routines it seems that no matter where I
go on the internet I'm constantly seeing
articles videos and books about why
building a morning routine is the most
important thing I could ever do how it's
gonna help me build a billion-dollar
business and basically become the next
Elon Musk
but despite the oversaturation of
morning routine related articles on the
internet and the hyperbole a lot of them
I do think this is an important topic to
talk about building a morning routine is
actually very meaningful to me now I'm
not gonna say it changed my life for
helped me build a billion-dollar
business but it really did build some
structure into the flow of my day so in
this video I want to share some of the
things I've learned for creating a
productive morning routine and also
sticking with it over the long term
[Music]
the first thing we gotta tackle right
off the bat is getting up earlier and
this was really the first challenge for
me because for many many years I was
that kind of person who would roll out
of bed 15 or 20 minutes before my first
scheduled thing throw some clothes on
and basically rush out the door I didn't
have time to make breakfast let alone
read or do any of the other things that
I wished I could have done so I had to
build some structures to make sure I
would get out of bed earlier and if this
is something that you need to do I do
already have a video on this channel
that I'll link to down in the
description below that you can check out
for lots and lots of tips on this
subject but I do want to share one
additional idea that my friend Evan
Carmichael shared with me last week and
that is to never hit the snooze button
this is one of those things that seems
obvious in theory but difficult to put
into practice but the way that Evan
framed this really stuck in my head
because he said if you hit the snooze
button in the morning then you are
accepting that the first thing you do
that day is fail and that made a lot of
sense to me because if you're gonna set
an alarm for yourself you are
essentially setting a goal for yourself
so instead of taking that extra 10
minutes of sleep just grit your teeth
jump in a bed as fast as you can and
make that first act of the day a win
[Music]
tip number two is to start small and
track your progress
the investor John Templeton once said
that the four most expensive words in
the English language are this time it's
different
and you're probably familiar with this
maybe you failed at a gym routine or a
New Year's resolution only to come back
and say this time it'll be different
this time I'll have more motivation more
willpower more discipline and I will win
but this is self delusion right you
don't just magically increase your
willpower reserves overnight you don't
magically build habits overnight these
things take time in fact one study in
the UK found that a habit can take on
average 66 days to fully crystallized
and become concrete so if you just jump
in and try to copy the morning routine
of someone like Elon Musk or that
blogger you read last week the novelty
might carry you through a couple of days
but that is far short of habit building
territory and you're probably going to
derail instead pick a couple of habits
that are meaningful to you and prove to
yourself that you can do those
consistently over time just stretch a
bit beyond your comfort zone and once
you've established a new comfort zone
then add more along the way you should
also have a method for tracking your
progress
doing so will essentially give you a
chain of successes and you're not going
to want to break that chain you can look
back on it so you're gonna be motivated
to keep up your morning routine in the
future now if you want to use the app
that I use to build my routine
it's called hebediah and it's
essentially a game of 5 way to build
habits every time you check off a habit
you get experience points that build up
a character and it's very final fantasy
esque like an RPG if that's a bit too
nerdy for you and you want something a
little simpler there are apps like today
on iOS and habit bowl on Android
[Music]
so at this point you're probably
wondering okay Tom but what do I
actually do in my morning routine and
we're gonna get into all the specifics
in a second but I want to start this
section off with a quote from the writer
Leo bababa the reason I like having a
morning routine is not only does it
instill a sense of purpose peace and
ritual to my day but it ensures that I'm
getting certain things done every
morning namely my goals what I want to
point out from that quote is that Leo
mentioned two main benefits to his
morning routine number one it gives him
a sense of ritual to his day some peace
in the morning and number two it helps
him make some progress on his goals and
it's important to highlight both of
these benefits because I personally know
people who do get up early but who just
used that extra time as quiet time as
some space to be alone to think and to
start their morning slowly and
deliberately if all you want to do is
get up early and make some tea and then
take your morning slow do it and don't
feel guilty about it if however you do
want to fill your morning with
productive habits in a few I might
suggest include having a glass of water
right after you wake up meditating for
five or ten minutes going and doing a
workout or some cardio to give yourself
some energy for the day
and cooking a good healthy breakfast one
thing that you should definitely leave
out of your morning routine though at
least for the most part is your phone
now I do use a timer app for meditating
in the morning and I also listen to
Spotify our audio books while I'm in the
gym but I'm really deliberate about not
looking at email or social media or
anything of that type in the morning at
all
that's because those things are really
likely to derail me from my habits and
my routine finally if you want to stick
to your morning routine for a long
period of time then you need to put some
thought into your evening routine as
well when I've been derailed from my
routine in the past two the most likely
culprits have been a lack of sleep and
the lack of organization and preparation
for each habit and an evening routine
can make both less likely to happen for
example because I go to the gym every
single morning I always make sure to
have my water bottle filled my gym bag
packed and my headphones charged before
I go to bed and because I do these
things at a specific time each night I'm
also less likely to stay up too late and
that gets me into bed at the correct
time for what I want to get up and on
that note if you don't know when you
should be going to bed you can use a
site like sleepy type me to set when you
want to wake up and it will tell you
when you should go to bed based on the
science of sleep cycles now neck sleep
cycles now
through my entire morning routine so if
you're curious you can keep your eyes
peeled for that but one thing I can
mention right now is that a big part of
my morning routine involves listening to
audiobooks not only do I often listen to
books oh I'm in the gym we're out doing
cardio but I also usually listen to them
while I'm walking to the coffee shop
where I start my days writing and the
place where I get my audiobooks is
audible which is this week's sponsor
audible has an unmatched library of
audiobooks and pretty much every genre
you can think of they also have a great
app for managing them all and one of my
favorite features of that app is their
bookmarking tool which allows me to add
bookmarks and notes which is great for
nonfiction because sometimes you want to
go back and review things later on now
if you'd like to give audible a try and
see how it fits into your morning
routine you can get a 30 day free trial
over at audible.com slash Thomas that
trial also comes with a free audio book
of your choosing that's yours to keep
forever and if you'd like a
recommendation I'm just gonna recommend
the book that I'm listening to right now
which is Steve Jobs by Walter Isaacson
this book is a really insightful look at
both the history of Apple and what made
Steve's brain tick and if you're
interested in Apple itself or the
history of computing in general it's a
great book to pick up thank you so much
to audible for sponsoring this video and
guys thank you so much for watching
seriously I appreciate each and every
one of you and if you want to subscribe
to this channel you haven't done already
you can click right there to do so I'm
also going to put a couple of video
suggestions right here that you might
find interesting as well thanks for
watching and I will see you next week
dank means