just finished reading my sixth book this
week man I just love reading books cuz
they're so like packed full of knowledge
you know luckily for me I know secret
speed reading techniques passed down
from a twenty second degree black belt
kung-fu master who reached enlightenment
by eating an entire library and if you
want to learn those same secrets and
read eighteen books a week just like me
take my speed reading course only
fourteen easy payments and one hard
payment of $19.99 tax title license fees
shipping handling and itching pad
removal fee not included now if you'll
excuse me
I need to get back to gaining vast
amounts of knowledge okay let's be real
here
the idea that you can learn to speed
read that is learn to drastically
increase your reading speeds and plow
through more books than you ever thought
possible that's been around for quite a
long time if you're in college you'll
probably see a flyer on campus at some
point advertising a speed reading
seminar that can teach you how to read
at 900 words per minute 1200 words per
minute or even beyond that and countless
bloggers have talked about the supposed
techniques you can use to learn how to
speed read and so much of it is BS so I
wanted to create a little series to set
the record straight on speed reading and
also show you how you can actually
realistically increase your reading
speeds and what I want to do with this
video in particular is lay out the
science of how reading actually works
now reading is possible through wait for
it I movement I know crazy right but
there are actually several different
types of eye movement for instance
there's something called smooth pursuit
which our eyes do when we're tracking a
moving subject and you can do it right
now just follow my finger on screen and
you might be feeling a little bit sleepy
which in that case give me all your
money
there's also vergence which is what
happens when your eyes move closer
together to focus on a subject in the
middle of your field of vision and also
something called vestibular eye movement
which is what happens when your eyes are
fixed upon a fixed subject but your head
moves in your eyes compensate for the
head movement when reading though our
eyes moving quick jerky movements called
seconds when we're reading silently to
ourselves the average saccade length is
about two visual degrees which equates
to about eight letters on a page and
this takes about 30 milliseconds to do
now when your eye stops and focuses in
the text that's called a fixation to
understand fixations first you need to
know about the three ranges of vision
your eyes have first there's the fovea
which spans about two visual degrees
right in the center
the retina then the para phobia which
goes about five degrees on either side
of any given fixation and finally your
peripheral vision your peripheral vision
is pretty blurry you can make up shapes
and movement but it can't really pick up
a whole lot of detail the fovea by
contrast picks up detail really really
well and this is absolutely critical for
reading most of what you can understand
and any given fixation needs to be in
that full range maybe one or two letters
can be in the para phobia range but
that's it and the average fixation when
you're reading silently takes about 225
milliseconds though this is an average
the range is typically anywhere from 100
milliseconds to 500 milliseconds
furthermore your reading speed isn't
just determined by fixations and cicadas
there's also the actual cognitive
processing time that you have to go
through in order to understand what you
just read we'll get more into cognition
and how your brain learns in future
videos but for now I want to make a
brief note about your working memory
which is what you're using when you read
research is showing that our working
memory can really only handle about four
chunks of information at any given time
a chunk being a bundle of information
that is loosely connected through
meaning chunks for a difficult material
or things you're unfamiliar with will be
small whereas chunks for things that you
are familiar with will be bigger but for
both the concept here is the same your
brain can only handle so many at a time
and reading too quickly can result in a
loss of comprehension that being said a
good figure to keep in mind is that
pauses for comprehension while your
reading will generally take between 300
and 500 milliseconds so essentially
reading breaks down into a three-step
process we have the secod that moves on
to the fixation and finally the
cognitive processing pause now even
though we have average duration data for
all three of these things it's not like
we can just add it up together and get
an average reading speed a number of
other factors come into play including
the fact that when we read we actually
skip a lot of the words on the page
words can be separated into two
different types there's content words
the words that actually express the
ideas you're reading about and function
words words that express the grammatical
relationships between those content
words research has shown that readers
fixate on about 85% of the content words
in any given text while they only focus
on about 35% of the function words on
the other hand reading also includes a
lot of regression going back to read
over previously read words some
regressions are small Corrections when a
saccade distance is too long whereas
longer regressions will be to go over
material that you already read once but
didn't really understand the first time
for skilled readers about 15% of the
reading
time will be made up of these
regressions now that you have a grasp of
the main factors that go into the
process of reading let's look at what a
realistic reading speed really is some
speed reading experts will tell you that
you can boost your reading rate to
around 1,200 words per minute which is a
figure that many people cite John F
Kennedy reading at and some even say you
can get higher than that but according
to Keith Raynor who's a psycho linguist
at the University of Massachusetts
Amherst and who did a huge study on 20
years of research in both eye movement
tracking and reading speed studies
observations of college level readers
showed that most people read between 200
and 400 words per minute and lastly
there's the concept of rating
flexibility a lot of the advice on speed
reading assumes that you should be
reading at a constant rate but in the
real world this really isn't the case
when you're reading something where the
concepts are presented more closely or
the materials more difficult you're
going to slow your reading rate down so
you can keep understanding but it is
your reading and by contrast when you're
reading something where the concepts are
more spaced out or you're already
familiar with what it is you're reading
you can increase that reading rate
without a huge loss of comprehension so
here is the final conclusion that I want
you to take from this first video in the
speed reading series if you're reading
between 200 and 400 words per minute
already you're in the norm you're fine
my friend Shane who runs the incredibly
smart blog Farnam Street is a great
example of this
Shane reads about three to five books a
week but he's very clear on his site
that he reads at an average pace speed
readers who claim that they can do any
more than 400 maybe 500 words per minute
tops are doing so at a loss of
comprehension in general reading at
lower comprehension rates should be
considered skimming and that's what
speed reading is it's skimming after a
certain reasonable point you get an
inverse relationship between your
reading speed and your level of
comprehension
which one is more important to you so
that is what we're going to end this
video if you'd like to dig a little bit
deeper into the research I did for it
I've linked to a lot of sources in the
companion blog post for this video so
you can click the card right now or the
link down in the description to read
them next week we're going to look at
some of the common techniques that speed
readers claim will increase your reading
speed and see if there's any validity
whatsoever to them and then after that
we're going to do a video on how you can
actually increase your reading speeds so
stay tuned for those videos coming in
the next couple of weeks if you enjoyed
this video giving it a like definitely
helps this channel and I will see you in
the next video
hey guys thanks so much for watching
this first video of my speed reading
series now if you want to get new videos
every single week on being a more
effective student including the further
speed reading videos you can click that
big red subscribe button right there
also if you want to read a book on how
to earn better grades I wrote one it's
absolutely free and I'll send you a copy
if you click the picture of the book
right there like I said if you want to
get the sources that I use for the
research in this video and there are a
lot of them as well as a summary you can
go to the companion blog post by
clicking the orange logo right there
last week was a little bit more of a
philosophical video on how we should
give more appreciation to people in all
sorts of different jobs so check that
out if you haven't seen it and if you
want to connect with me i'm on twitter
@tomfrankly or you can leave a comment
below thanks for watching