when i think about managing my money i
tend to center around an idea that
you've probably seen in video games
before the idea of the war chest think
about a game like civilization in that
game you need resources both to expand
your empire but also to be able to
essentially take a punch to deal with
enemies attacking you train up soldiers
to go to war for you and the resources
you build and gain in that game like
gold and food and production other
things they represent your war chest if
they run out then there's not a whole
lot you're gonna do and you're probably
going to lose the game now in the real
world your money is your war chest and
it serves pretty much the exact same
purpose it lets you number one take
advantage of opportunities like getting
a better place to live or investing in
your education but it's also there to
help you take punches like your car
getting a flat tire when it comes to
building my own war chest when it comes
to managing my own money responsibly i
have always had some rules that i
followed ever since i became an adult
and left my parents house so what i want
to do in this video is actually share
some of those roles with you including
some rules on saving money on using
credit cards responsibly and on
investing for the future and to give you
a bit of a sneak peek on what's actually
coming on this channel in the future i
want to build a more detailed library of
personal finance videos here in 2022
because i want this channel to evolve
past just covering productivity or
academic success and to start to
encompass more of what it means to live
a fuller more capable life and i kind of
center on that term capability so think
of this video as a bit of a foundation
to the more detailed topics that we're
going to be covering in the future and
with that let's jump into our first rule
build up an emergency fund and a cash
buffer so as i mentioned earlier your
war chest is what allows you to take
advantage of opportunities but also to
take punches and stand easily back up
now unfortunately a lot of people live
paycheck to paycheck which means they
spend almost everything they make in the
month that they make it they don't have
a war chest so to become financially
independent financially secure your
first priority should be to build one
and in the game civilization there's
something called the tech tree it's this
list of technologies that your people
can research and it's laid out in a
certain order so for example you have to
research pottery before you can research
writing and civ is my favorite video
game analog for personal finance because
we can actually think of the financial
journey as a tech tree as well and in
fact i have actually built that tech
tree and i've shared a link to it in the
description down below they've also
included detailed comments for each
checkpoint on the tech tree so if
something i say here isn't clear you can
check those comments and there's
probably more detail for it now there
are four main branches on the tree
savings income debt and budgeting and
along the savings path you will notice
the very first checkpoint is a 500
emergency fund this is a savings account
separate from your checking account that
you do not tap unless you absolutely
have to unless something unforeseen
comes up for which you absolutely need
that account like bursting a tire on
your car which you need to get to work
and the reason that having this account
is so important is that if you don't
have one and something unexpected comes
up you might be forced to borrow money
to handle it or even put the expense on
your credit card which could put you
into a debt spiral so if you don't have
an emergency fund yet build one at all
costs and the next thing you want to do
after that is to build what's called a
one month cash buffer and you can do
this by first figuring out how much you
need each month to pay your necessary
expenses like rent and groceries and
debt minimums and then making sure you
at least have that much in your checking
account even after all this month's
expenses are paid this concept can also
be called living on last month's income
and doing so gives you a ton of peace of
mind because at this point you're no
longer living a paycheck to paycheck and
this brings us to rule number two which
is to invest as much as you can into
what are called taxed advantaged
retirement accounts these include
accounts like 401ks and iras and if you
use them strategically you're going to
end up with a lot more money during
retirement than you otherwise would now
you've probably heard of these types of
accounts before 401k ira but what
exactly do they do besides adding more
acronyms to your life well a 401k is an
account usually managed by your employer
whereas an ira is something that you
typically open and manage yourself but
both of these accounts let you do
essentially the same thing that you
invest money into stocks or bonds or
other kinds of investments that you
can't touch or withdraw until you're at
least 59 and a half years old which
sounds like kind of a bad deal until you
realize that in exchange you get to
defer the taxes that you pay on some of
your income by investing into them so
for example if you normally make 80 000
a year but you contribute 5 000 of your
salary to your 401k then you're actually
only taxed on 75 000 that year instead
of 80k which reduces your taxable income
and hence reduces your taxes this is
called a pre-tax contribution now there
are a ton of details around this whole
tax deferral thing there are roth iras
which work quite differently so i'm
going to cover all that in a future
video but the other huge benefit to
using iras and 401ks is that money
invested in these types of accounts
tends to grow a lot faster than
otherwise would if you just invested it
normally in normal taxable accounts an
example in the book a random walk down
wall street shows how 5500 invested each
year for 45 years grows to 1.6
million dollars inside of an ira well
the same money only grows to 938 000
invested in a taxable account even
though it was put into the exact same
investments the exact same mix of stocks
or bonds or mutual funds that's a
difference of over 600 000
and the reason for it is something
called tax drag this is when taxes act
like molasses slowing down the growth of
your investments see anytime you make
income off of your investments you have
to pay what are called capital gains
taxes on that income and to give you a
very simple example of this one form of
income that most people get off of their
investments at least if they hold stocks
are called dividends these are just
regular payments that shareholders get
literally just for holding the stock now
not all stocks pay dividends some stocks
are called growth stocks they're
companies that basically want to take
all of their income to grow the company
so they don't pay a dividend instead
reinvest the money to grow the company
but a lot of older more mature bigger
companies do choose to pay a dividend
either because they can't find anything
else that would be a better investment
for that extra money or because they
have investors who want dividends the
greedy bastards and nintendo is one of
those companies they do pay out a
dividend so for every share that
somebody holds currently nintendo is
paying out about two dollars and 30
cents per year so for example right now
i have about 140 shares in nintendo in
my fidelity account so they are
currently paying me about 322 each year
in dividends now older investors might
take these dividends and actually live
on them but most younger investors
myself included who are trying to grow
their investments as much as possible
choose to automatically reinvest their
dividends instead and it's the smart
play because every single dollar
invested is going to grow over time so
in my case it means buying another 322
of nintendo stock automatically or at
least it would
if not for taxes see since those
dividends are income the government
comes in and takes 20 percent of my
dividends in taxes capital gains taxes
so i actually only get to reinvest about
not 322. and that's 65 that i don't get
to invest and grow over the next 20 or
30 years and that's tax drag now the
great thing about iras and 401ks tax
advantaged retirement accounts is that
they are not subject to capital gains
tax when things like this happened so if
my nintendo stock were in ira i would
actually get to invest the entire 332
dollars instead of the 257 and with
compound interest working the way that
does and with a long period of time
ahead of me that tax drag or lack
thereof makes a huge difference on my
overall returns so for this reason i do
my best to contribute as much as i
possibly can to my retirement accounts
each and every single year now one
caveat that i will throw out there
before we move on is that it's generally
impossible to take money out of one of
these accounts early without paying a
huge penalty and then also paying taxes
on them so if you're saving it for
something big like a down payment on a
house you may want to consider that when
deciding how much to split out into an
ira or 401k and into maybe a savings
vehicle or a taxable investment account
now there are ways to take some money
out of an ira for a first-time home
purchase and you may want to look up
that but in general it's good to know
about the withdrawal penalties as well
now our next rule sounds kind of bad at
first glance b
a deadbeat but this is actually a really
good thing to aspire to be this term has
to do with how you use credit cards see
in the credit card industry a deadbeat
is somebody who always pays their entire
balance on time every single month and
if you know anything about how credit
cards work you probably know that they
come with some pretty insanely high
interest rates often over 20 percent but
if you pay off the entire balance every
single month you actually don't pay any
of that interest at all and since the
credit card company isn't making any
money off of charging you interest you
my friend are considered a deadbeat now
i got my first credit card when i was 18
years old and i have been a deadbeat
ever since not once have i ever let the
credit card company charge me interest
which means that i've gotten all the
benefits of credit cards essentially for
free and there are quite a lot of
benefits notice how this rule isn't
don't use a credit card it's be a
deadbeat because i truly do believe that
you should have and use credit cards
there are several reasons for this that
we could list off for when credit cards
generally have better fraud protection
for online shopping than debit cards do
and a lot of them also give you cash
back rewards travel points miles all
kinds of nice little bonuses which are
cool to get but the main reason that you
should have a credit card is to build
your credit score now i've got a whole
video on credit scores in the works with
lots more detail coming down the
pipeline and you can also learn more
about credit scores in the tech tree as
well but what i'll mention here is that
your credit score controls a lot of what
you can do in life honestly it probably
controls a bit too much but hey we gotta
play the hand that we're dealt and your
credit score right now determines
whether you're gonna get approved for a
home loan for one what interest rates
you're gonna pay for home loans for
literally any other kind of loan the
higher your score the lower the interest
rate so it literally saves you money to
build your credit score and it can even
decide whether or not you're getting
approved as a renter for rental units
townhomes apartments things like that i
recently saw a townhome for rent here in
denver that actually requires a minimum
700 credit score just to get approved
but the problem when you're young is
that you probably don't have a whole lot
of experience using credit cards or
using loans which means that you don't
have much credit history and you might
not even have a credit score at all you
need at least one loan or credit card on
your report to have a credit score and
while you can build up that credit
history with things like car loans or
student loans the nice thing about a
credit card is that it actually allows
you to build up your credit score
essentially for free as long as you're a
deadbeat now essentially is the key word
there because ever since 2009 actually
the year i graduated high school it's
harder for people who are 18 to 21 and
it's harder for people who don't have
credit history to get a credit card back
when i was in high school and college
they were shooting credit cards out of
t-shirt cans of people it was really
easy to get one back then not the case
today so today typically the easiest way
to get a card with no credit history is
to get what's called a secured card
where you make a deposit up front then
becomes your credit limit so for example
you give the bank 200 you receive a
secured credit card with a 200 limit now
eventually you can get that deposit back
and the card goes from being secured to
being unsecured like a regular credit
card and once you've got it you can
start building up your score over time
by following tom's three golden rules of
dead beatitude number one always pay
your balance on time on-time payments
unsurprisingly are the biggest single
factor in determining your credit score
number two always pay your balance in
full again so you don't get charged any
interest on that credit card and finally
number three never use more than about
30 of your credit limit now this last
rule has to do with something called
credit utilization which is your current
balance divided by your credit limit and
the lower that ratio is the better your
score is going to be so by keeping it
under 30 you are going to be building a
good score over time 30 isn't a hard
rule but it's a good rule of thumb
additionally is a great idea to set up
automatic payments for your card as well
so you're guaranteed to never miss a
payment and i actually made a whole
video about that so you can check that
out after this one now one final rule
that i'm gonna mention is to
consistently be investing not in stocks
not in bonds not in mutual funds but in
yourself so my second rule was to
maximize your retirement accounts and
that is a great idea but i truly believe
the best investment i am ever going to
make is in improving myself which means
continually improving my current skill
set learning new skills and most
importantly looking at the world with a
beginner's mindset rather than assuming
that i know everything already i want to
be open to learning new things it also
means taking advantage of opportunities
by connecting with new people maybe even
traveling to conferences and
professional events to deepen
relationships you've made online and it
can also mean improving your meta skills
like your ability to solve problems
creatively since easy problems are very
easily automated in pretty much every
single industry out there the people who
can innovatively solve complex problems
are the ones who are most in demand and
if you want to improve your skill in
this area one great resource that you
can practice it at is brilliant who have
kindly sponsored this video and who have
been an amazing supporter of my channel
brilliant if you haven't heard about it
is an online learning library that
teaches you math science and computer
science while also helping you become an
all-around better problem solver and
they do this by creating courses that
are entirely based on the principle of
active learning the vast majority of the
time you're going through any of their
courses you're not reading walls of text
you're not watching videos you're
actually solving interactive puzzles and
challenges and brilliance library has
more than 60 of these courses that cover
topics like calculus statistics logic
computer algorithms and lots more so if
you want to start building your stem
expertise if you want to get better at
problem solving and if you want to
support this channel you can head over
to brilliant.org thomasfrank to start
learning today or you can click that
link on screen right there if you
enjoyed this video if you learned
something you might also want to check
out the video i mentioned earlier on
automating your finances or this video
here which youtube has kindly picked for
you if you enjoyed this video definitely
hit that like button for the algorithm
hopefully you learned something useful
here let me know if you have questions
in the comments down below and i'll see
you in the next one