I don't know about you but I have always
had a problem sticking with just one
interest I want to do everything and I
don't just want to do everything I want
to get good at everything now normally
this is a pretty poor strategy for
building skills if you jump between
things too frequently you never put in
the number of hours needed to get truly
good at any one thing but given enough
time energy and let's be honest here
unhealthy obsession one can become a
Renaissance person now one such
Renaissance person probably the og
Renaissance person was Leonardo da Vinci
you might have heard of him before from
this little-known project is called the
Mona Lisa or through his much more
impressive accomplishment of being
immortalized as a ninja turtle more
recently though he was also immortalized
in a huge biographical tome called
simply Leonardo da Vinci by Walter
Isaacson this book gives us some
fascinating insights into what made
Leonardo the man that he was and today I
want to share some of those insights
with you so that you can use them to
become more powerful than you could
possibly imagine or you know at least a
little bit more productive in your daily
life so here are five lessons from the
life of da Vinci or as my best friend
Martin likes to call him my boy Leo DV
lesson number one present yourself based
on what you would like to become not
just on what you are right now or what
you have been in the past many of us
know DaVinci as the mastermind behind
the Mona Lisa or his painting the Last
Supper but there were actually periods
in Leonardo's life where he didn't even
want to look at a paintbrush during one
of these episodes when he was looking
for a new patron in Milan he drafted a
letter describing his various talents
mostly in engineering and military
endeavors the letter he drafted lists 10
specific areas in which he might be of
service before mentioning painting at
all of which he writes likewise in
painting I can do everything possible
basically this is an early example of a
custom-tailored resume which Leonardo
wrote to get the job that he wanted so
here's what you can take with this when
you're presenting yourself to others
whether it be in the form of a resume or
even a Twitter bio don't talk about
things that you don't want to be known
about or that you don't want to be doing
in the near future
instead work to highlight your current
interests if you have to pad things out
with your past experience you might need
to do that but don't put them first and
foremost
but on the other hand don't list things
that you can't actually do yet just
because you want to do them you actually
do have to be able to deliver to some
degree as it turns out Leonardo actually
hadn't done many of the things that he
listed in his letter a lot of them were
just ambitions or ideas but because he
had this genius ability to innovate
usually things worked out pretty well
for him but today things are a lot more
competitive and people don't want to
waste time with somebody who really
doesn't have experience so make sure
that you can back up what you're talking
about make sure you have at least some
of the skills and experience that you
want to present to the world now that
isn't to say that you need years of
experience in a particular discipline
before you can present it because many
things can actually be learned in a very
short period of time for example one of
our friends was applying for a job a few
years ago in which having experience
with a lamp stack which is a web hosting
stack consisting of Apache my sequel and
PHP all running on Linux would have been
very beneficial so in just one weekend
he taught himself how to set this up
because it's a pretty easy skill to
learn actually and that experience
actually helped him to land the job
lesson number two become a t-shaped
person and luckily I've got a head start
on this because my name starts with T
for the rest of you guys you may have to
put a little bit more work into us but
it's worth it
Leonardo's willingness to shift his
focus to entirely new things is part of
what made him great he didn't get caught
up in past identities and he didn't
limit himself based on what he was
already good at instead he relentlessly
followed his curiosity wherever it led
him and he filled notebook after
notebook with constant observations and
questions and thoughts and due to this
constant practice he not only made
himself familiar with many different
disciplines but he became quite
knowledgeable in several of them human
anatomy optics military engineering
hydrodynamics and theatrical productions
just to name a few
yes and painting as well and it was
partially due to this variety that he
was able to excel in so many talents his
creativity and understanding was
bolstered heavily by his ability to see
and apply patterns from one discipline
to another for just one example let's
take a look at the Mona Lisa's smile the
greatness of the smile in the painting
was not an accident it was informed by
obsessive anatomical studies and a
desire to understand each of the muscles
that control facial expressions without
this extra layer of learning to pull
from the greatness of the painting
overall would have suffered
lesson number three know when you are
wrong
Leonardo thought deeply and critically
about almost everything which means that
he was bound to be wrong at one point or
another now in some circles the practice
of sticking to your guns is seen as a
good thing and people who change their
mind from one position to another are
often labeled flip-floppers but this
kind of a mindset can really keep you
from growing in reaching your highest
potential an important part of what made
Leonardo who he was was his willingness
to adjust his beliefs to fit new
information not the other way around and
he did this even with beliefs and
theories that he held dear for instance
he really liked finding comparisons
between the human body and the earth and
1/3 that he held for a while was that
the Earth's waters might circulate
similarly to that of the human bodies
blood vessels but as meaningful as this
analogy was to him as beautiful as it
seemed once he realized that it did not
fit the facts he dropped it and went
looking for a new theory that did so
follow in Leonardo's footsteps in this
area don't hold yourself to your past
beliefs if they do not fit the facts use
the facts to find a more accurate theory
to live by lesson number four is to
collaborate with others popular culture
often sees genius as a lonely trait but
genius doesn't always hide out in
solitude just waiting for inspiration to
strike inspiration often comes from
working with others and even when genius
comes up with an idea on its own a team
is often needed to realize and perfect
that vision for example Terry Pratchett
came together with Neil Gaiman to write
good omens all the engineers and
technicians at NASA put their collective
heads together to get us to space and of
course where would little john be
without the East Side boys in da Vinci's
time paintings were often done
collaboratively in studio and because of
this determining whether or not a work
is an original Leonardo is difficult
because many of his works weren't done
alone even if the original vision was
his the work itself was often done by a
team both early in his career and his
mentor of Rocio studio and then later on
in his own studio now this might seem
crazy to think about at first but given
the time it's really not that different
than multiple people working together
today to create an animated character
and a movie or a video game most 3d
characters are created by multiple
artists some work on textures of his
work on rigging and still others study
reference material to make sure the
animation itself is realistic and even
putting painting aside many of the other
great
as da Vinci had were inspired by his
conversations and his work with others
others whose names have been forgotten
but whose contributions lived on as the
Jesuit priest Father Strickland once
said a man may do an immense deal of
good if he does not care who gets the
credit
today we seem to have this particularly
strong fixation with building a personal
brand both online and offline we want to
make sure that our work has our name on
it but if you can get away from this
temptation a bit if you can embrace
collaboration and be quick to credit
people for their ideas and contributions
you're gonna get a lot farther because
your work will be better also somewhat
ironically people will tend to like you
more if you're quick to credit others
because well you won't look selfish that
brings us to lesson number five which is
to be wary of perfectionism looking at
Leonardo's accomplishments in retrospect
can make him look almost superhuman in
his brilliance but while he was still
alive it wasn't the only thing he was
known for these same perfectionism that
drove him to new heights also kept him
from being very reliable to others he
rarely finished anything including some
large projects that he had been paid to
do and had agreed to finish after
procrastinating and what could have been
one of his greatest achievements a mural
commemorating the Battle of Anghiari
eventually getting a new contract with a
later deadline failing that deadline as
well and then eventually just abandoning
the entire project altogether he never
again received a public commission and
not only did this trait make it
difficult for Leonardo to find work
compared to his more flexible peers it
also didn't seem to sit well with
Leonardo himself as he obsessed with
leaving a legacy while simultaneously
leaving project after project unfinished
he repeatedly scrawled in his notebooks
tell me if anything was ever done tell
me tell me tell me if I ever did a thing
tell me if anything was ever made
hundreds of years later Leonardo may now
be more respected for his unwillingness
to produce work that was just good
enough and you may well respect him for
that yourself but it's also important to
know when to just be done it is okay to
simply finish something to the best of
your ability right now and move forward
and it's far better than just not
finishing it at all and this is
especially true because regardless of
what you view as perfection right now
what you're going to be able to produce
in the future will be far better every
single time you finish a project you
gain new skills you gain new insights
and you become more
capable of creating better and better
work now perfectionism is a big problem
so let me imperfectly solve it here with
just one quick tip give your
perfectionism constraints don't say I'm
going to set out to make the best thing
ever as that's impossible you can always
put more time and energy and effort into
it instead say I'm gonna make the best
thing that I can reasonably make within
this time frame and this set of
constraints in the long term just
remember that trying new things and
making mistakes is a large part of how
we improve ourselves
much like Frieza you have to lose a few
times in order to reach your final form
and the faster and more often you can
embrace imperfection the faster and
closer you'll get to your highest
potential in any area your version of
perfect so to quickly summarize first
present yourself based on what you want
to become second become a t-shaped
person third know when you're wrong
fourth collaborate with other people and
fifth be wary of perfectionism now in
the intro for this video I mentioned
that all the lessons we just talked
about were inspired by Walter Isaacson's
biography of Leonardo da Vinci which was
simply titled Leonardo da Vinci and if
you'd like to experience this book for
yourself and also start learning a bit
more about his life you can actually
start listening to it today for free on
audible by going over to audible.com
slash Thomas or by texting Thomas to
five hundred five hundred on your phone
to activate a free 30-day trial of
audible service and get a free audiobook
download of your choosing audible is the
Internet's best place to get your hands
on audiobooks not only do they have all
the bestsellers and lots of obscure
titles but they also have titles across
every kind of genre you're going to want
to listen to science fiction biographies
psychology titles and when you remember
you get one credit that is good for any
audiobook you every single month plus
two audible originals that you cannot
get anywhere else and access to over a
hundred different exercise and
meditation programs additionally they
have a really well designed app with a
lot of great features including a sleep
timer and the ability to make notes of
specific timestamps in any audiobook
you're listening to so once again if you
want to start listening to Leonardo da
Vinci or any other audio book of your
choosing head over to audible.com slash
Thomas or text Thomas to five hundred
five hundred on your phone to get that
free 30-day trial of audible service
along with a free audiobook download big
thanks as always to audible for
sponsoring this video and supporting my
channel and thanks to you for watching
and supporting a channel
as well you enjoyed this video maybe hit
that like button and also get subscribed
right there so you don't miss out on new
videos when they come out and click
right there to get a free copy of my
book on how to earn better grades if you
haven't done so already otherwise you
can watch one more video on this channel
right here or listen to our podcast
episode on lessons from the inaudible
Vinci's life which is a lot more
in-depth than this video ranked over
here thanks as always for watching and
I'll see you in the next video