thanks to brilliant for sponsoring this
video and supporting my channel
every year millions of people try to
build new habits
some adopt new exercise programs others
pick up that instrument they've been
meaning to learn
and still others decide to finally get
serious about reading every day
some of these people will succeed in
getting their new habit to stick
while others will quickly give up and
fail but all them will learn
the same lesson building a new habit is
hard
whether you want to chalk it up to
laziness or overly busy schedules
or the fact that our phones tend to suck
up a ton of our time tempting us in much
the same way that a slot machine temps a
gambler
the conclusion is the same if you want
to adopt a new habit
you'd better prepare yourself for an
uphill battle
luckily one of the things that you can
always count on in our market-driven
economy
is that when there's a problem people
will inevitably try to create solutions
for it
necessity is the mother of all invention
as people like to say
and our publishing industry is no
exception here having pumped out
more than a handful of books aimed at
helping you build better habits
but of all these books my absolute
favorite one is james clear's
atomic habits and that's not just
because it mentions my twitter wake up
system
on page 210 though that is pretty cool
but seriously more than any other book
that i've read on habits i found the
ideas in
atomic habits to be incredibly helpful
for adopting
the mindset required to actually stick
to habits
over the long term so while i would
absolutely recommend reading this book
in its entirety if you have the time
today what i want to do is share three
of those key ideas starting with a
principle that claire calls
one percent better every day this idea
has its roots in the compounding effect
which you'll probably recognize most
readily if we're talking about
compound interest albert einstein once
called compound interest the eighth
wonder of the world
and for pretty good reason given a good
amount of time
the interest on your interest can result
in huge returns
compound interest is why you can invest
a hundred dollars a month and if we
assume a modest seven percent return in
the stock market
you'll end up with over a hundred and
twenty two thousand dollars after thirty
years
even though during that time you only
contributed thirty six
thousand dollars of your money into that
fund and it turns out that this
compounding effect
also applies to the world of skill
building and habit formation
if you pick a skill and you focus on
just getting one percent
better at it each day your cumulative
skill growth
and the rewards you reap from it
accelerate faster and faster
over time atomic habits illustrates this
idea using a metaphorical graph
which shows the difference between small
daily actions in both positive
and negative directions at first the
results are minuscule
but over time they ramp up just like
that investment balance
now this all sounds great in theory but
unfortunately as you probably well know
the level of consistency required to
maintain this
growth over time is really difficult to
maintain especially in the beginning
when you're just starting to build a
habit
big dramatic changes as overwhelming and
as unsustainable as you and i
know they could be are exciting because
they seem to propel us forward really
quickly and our mammalian brains really
love
short-term exciting rewards and
meanwhile the much more reasonable one
percent rule simply doesn't do a whole
lot for us
in the short term which is what we're
often concerned with
even if we don't like to be for example
let's say you want to learn how to
produce music
and you decide to do that by spending at
least some time every single day
learning and practicing and making songs
if you start this new goal on january
1st
then by the end of the first month using
clear's model
your daily one percent gains only result
in a 37
gain overall and that's progress to be
sure but
it's nothing dramatic and you're still
producing music that was only
barely outside of your grasp before and
that to the average listener sounds like
it was made on like a preschool piano
thing from walmart now after six months
of effort you're now doing a bit more
than six
times better than when you started funny
how those numbers seem to line up
now this is actually pretty good
progress but we are not done yet
because the compounding effect has only
just begun
to show how powerful it can be keep
pushing on and
suddenly a one percent improvement every
day since you started
gets interesting because at the end of
the year you've somehow reached a mind
bending
37 times better than when you started
the first six months
gets you to six times better but the
second six months
adds an extra 31 times now
obviously we cannot literally measure
out one percent skill changes in most
cases
but the concept still works here and the
results
still come as clear writes in the book
these small improvements or declines
compound and suddenly you find a very
big gap between the people who make
slightly better decisions on a daily
basis
and those who don't of course this is
all easy to agree with in theory
but as we mentioned before long-term
consistency is a lot easier planned
than maintained as you well know most
new year's resolutions
don't even make it to february so they
can't even go through the example that
we put out here
just as many people fail to remain
disciplined enough to keep investing for
30 years
and hence we'll never see those amazing
returns
now part of this might be straight up
difficulty or life circumstances or
simply boredom
but even an incredibly simple easy habit
can be difficult to stick to long term
if it goes too far against how we view
ourselves
so if we want to make long-term change
that change
has to become part of who we are we'll
have to build up a sense of what i'm
going to call
identity habit harmony picture yourself
out for a run
and imagine that it's really hot outside
or maybe it's really cold or maybe it's
a torrential downpour whichever of those
is the one that you like the least and
now picture that you're only
halfway through a particularly difficult
last mile
and you're now feeling the desperate
urge to quit in that moment
ask yourself who are you well if you
consider yourself to be a runner
then this scenario is not a big deal the
occasional hard mile is part of the
territory
in fact it only reinforces your strength
and your pride as a runner as an athlete
so as a result you push through but on
the other hand if you see yourself not
as an athlete or a runner but as more of
a homebody
just trying to get in shape because
you're supposed to or because you have
this
light desire to do it then you're gonna
start questioning
why you're doing what you're doing when
things get difficult you're gonna ask
why am i doing this to myself this isn't
who i am
and one day you're gonna decide to quit
i think this is one of the biggest
reasons why people fail in building
habits they don't build
a harmony between their identity and the
habit they're trying to make stick
long term that's one of the biggest
ideas in this book
see people will go to great lengths to
protect their self-image it's part of
this consistency principle which is also
talked about in robert cieldini's book
influence
just try arguing with somebody about a
dearly held belief they have and you're
gonna find
just how hard we all work to keep our
self-image intact
even if it's to our own detriment even
if we argue against
what would be good for us and it's
because of this that clear suggests we
pay closer attention to what that image
is when we're trying to change something
about our lives as he says in the book
your behaviors are usually a reflection
of your identity
whatever you do is an indication of the
type of person you believe
that you are either consciously or
non-consciously but there's also a bit
of a feedback loop here
as he says just a bit later on whatever
your identity is right now
you only believe it because you have
proof of it
in short long-term habit changes come
more easily with long-term
identity changes and to get those you'll
have to give yourself as much
evidence as you can that your new
identity is really who you're becoming
so if you want to run that 5k someday
take a second to think about the kind of
person who might do that sort of thing
automatically or naturally that person
would be a runner or an
athlete then whenever an opportunity to
reinforce
that identity in yourself comes up ask
yourself what would a runner do
in this situation eventually by acting
like a runner
you become one and if that identity
makes you feel good then you won't want
to lose it and you'll work
that much harder to keep it the longer
you fight for it truer that identity
becomes and the harder it is to go back
to who you were
before i've personally found this whole
philosophy and mindset change to be
extremely helpful for taking side
projects more seriously
as well let's take guitar for example if
i don't think of myself as a musician
then whenever i get busy with work or if
i have something stressful pop up
surprisingly in my life then i'm gonna
tend to
let guitar practice go by the wayside
because it's just a hobby right
so it's important to get overshadowed by
whatever urgent thing
has come up in my life but if being a
musician
is part of my identity then i'm gonna
see guitar practice as something
much more important and i'll be a lot
less likely to throw it by the wayside
when something does come up
in other words i will make time for it
because that
is what a musician would do of course
this process of assuming a new identity
and taking it seriously
isn't always easy when you start a new
habit you often have that
novelty factor that initial surge of
motivation and energy
working for you but those two things
inevitably run out pretty quickly and
when that happens
you're probably gonna have to deal with
your first failure some point
soon after it can be hard to get over
that when it happens
especially if you tend to have
perfectionist tendencies like i do
and dealing with just this situation is
where the third big idea from atomic
habits comes in
so let's call it the democracy of the
self
see in an election there are almost
always going to be votes for both sides
given enough people in the voting pool
it's not plausible for
anything no matter how right no matter
how obviously superior
to get 100 of the vote there is always
going to be that troll that just wants
to see the world burn
so they hit the down vote button but
luckily that doesn't matter to win an
election you don't need
every single vote to be cast in the
exact same way you just need a majority
and as clear helpfully points out every
action you take
is a vote for the type of person you
wish to become
no single instance will transform your
beliefs
but as the votes build up so too does
the evidence of your new
identity so maybe today you voted for
lazy you
you didn't go for that run you didn't
practice guitar well that's
okay because tomorrow you get another
vote you can make sure that vote is cast
correctly
if you keep at that making sure your
successes outnumber your setbacks
that is how long-term habits are built
in other words focus
not on never failing but on never
letting failure become a habit
of its own clear actually has a term for
this he calls it the second mistake you
want to avoid making
the second mistake and if you can do
that then your first mistake just
remains a failing vote it remains
an outlier now there's a bit of a hidden
insight that i found in the interplay
between identity habit harmony and this
whole democracy
of the self-concept which is that if you
haven't cast
enough votes for a particular identity
then you may not know if it's possible
to
assume that identity in the first place
and a lot of people
assume that many identities are simply
not for them
how many people do you know who think
that learning a foreign language is not
for them
becoming a musician is not for them
learning complex math or engineering
is simply not for them i remember this
was a big problem for me in high school
especially on that issue of you know
learning engineering and complex math
i had a tough time in calculus so i
naturally assumed i was not
cut out for calculus and not cut out for
engineering school this is actually one
of the big reasons that i chose to go to
business school
and while i don't really regret going to
business school in general
i do regret having that belief at first
and i now know
that if i had simply cast enough votes
if i had simply put in
daily effort to learn complex math to
get a better grade in calculus
i would have absolutely been able to
become an engineer if i wanted to do
that
so if you ever have these doubts in your
head if you ever feel like
an identity is not for you ask yourself
how many votes have i
cast have i started building this habit
or if i simply assumed
that this identity is not for me and if
the latter is true
then start casting some votes of course
if
something like engineering and complex
math is something that you want to learn
then using better learning resources is
also really going to help you make
progress and one of those great learning
resources is brilliant
brilliant has over 60 in-depth courses
that can help you master your abilities
in math
science and computer science and they
help you learn efficiently with a focus
on
active learning instead of just
passively going through text or watching
videos like a lot of traditional
educational sources
you're instead thrown into logically
sequenced bite-sized yet
challenging interactive problems that
complement any of those more traditional
sources
you're using and because you're
wrangling with the material right away
you learn more efficiently you progress
faster and you also keep your interest
up
as you're going through it additionally
because you're solving problems the
entire time
your universal problem-solving skills
improve along the way
whenever we apply our skills to a
specific challenge
we often reap more universal benefits
now if you've heard me talk about
brilliant in the past you'll know they
have a comprehensive math suite ranging
from the basics of number theory going
all the way up to very complex topics
like differential equations and
high-level probability and statistics
along with science courses including
classical mechanics and gravitational
physics and computer science courses
like their python programming course but
recently they came out with a brand new
course all about knowledge and
uncertainty which is all about the math
that we use to quantify and get precise
about how uncertain we are about
questions we have which is very
important in making
better decisions and i think if you have
any interest in math or probability or
statistics or maybe
investing or simply making better
decisions this is going to be a really
interesting course
to take so if you want to take that
course or any of the other courses in
their library you can go over to
brilliant.org
thomasfrank and sign up and if you're
one of the first 200 people to use that
url and sign up you're going to get 20
off their annual premium subscription
which is a pretty great deal thanks as
always for watching hopefully you
enjoyed this video if you did hitting
that like button is a great way to tell
the youtube algorithm that this content
is worth watching which can cause it to
push it out to more people so it's a
great way to support the channel and
huge thank you to you if you do that and
if you haven't subscribed already make
sure you hit that subscribe button right
there because later this month we are
making another video all about
the actual habit building process
outlined in atomic habits again
pick this book up and read it if you
have the chance it's a great read but
i hope you also come back to check out
that video which will be a little bit
more
you know in the trenches and practical
hopefully beyond that if you haven't
followed me on instagram at tomfrankly
you might want to do so as i'm making
little uh q a videos every week so if
you have a question that might not
constitute a huge video
here on this channel which takes many
many many hours to make
ask it to me in the content in the
comments below or over on instagram
and i might make a little igtv video for
it beyond that i'm gonna have
playlists right here of additional
videos on this channel that can help you
build your self-discipline so if you
enjoyed this video
you might enjoy some of those videos as
well otherwise i'll put my music
channel right there and if you don't
want to click any of these things don't
do that go drink a gallon of coffee for
all i care because
as always i'm not your dad