say hello unpaid camera labor
hello hello everybody Welcome to my day
one uh accelerated Japanese learning
challenge review from Japan so I
actually did this about a week ago at
this point and um through this little
three three-part series I'm going to
just basically show you how I did my
little Japanese learning Challenge and
uh for this one I'm going to show you my
goals that I set for the challenge and
also give you 10 different resources
that I use to learn Japanese so here's a
shot of my notebook and basically what I
did to learn Japanese was I set out
specific goals of what I wanted to learn
during the challenge because become
fluent in language is a bit too uh broad
of a goal to really give you something
actionable to work towards so I actually
wrote down these things I wanted to
become a fluent in pagana and Katakana
again I wanted to go through several
different resources so I wrote These
down and then I also wrote down the
resources which I will go through right
now Tex Fugu is an online Japanese
textbook that covers the building blocks
of the language Grammer kanji and lots
more for more in-depth Kani learning I
primarily use Wan Connie a space
repetition based web app by the same
people who made Tex Fugu italki is an
amazing site that leted you hire
professional language tutors who can
teach you via Skype for learning
hiragana one of Japanese is simpler
quote unquote alphabets I used an
earlier version of something called The
Ultimate Guide to learning hiragana on
tofugu Rana is a website and iPhone app
that lets me quickly review both
hiragana and Katakana another Japanese
alphabet or cabber is a more accurate
term for it in addition to that I use
another tool called drag and drop heron
which lets me keep my knowledge solid
when I've got time to kill on the go I
use an app called Mind snacks which
offers pretty fun games that teach
several different vocab lists another
resource I use frequently is Google
translate while I don't trust it 100%
it's a good place to start when I want
to know how to construct a sentence once
it gets me started I'll use G show a
fantastic online Japanese dictionary to
learn any new VAB I'm not familiar with
lastly I use Anki to do both vocabulary
and sentence practice if you want to
find even more language learning
resources for any language the language
learning community on Reddit has a
massive list of resources that you can
check out link is in the description
so those are my 10 resources and I will
see you next week for the day five
middle of the challenge review and until
then I'm going to go enjoy my vacation
so thanks for watching this a bit more
low five video and uh enjoy your day
[Music]
[Applause]