thanks to brilliant for sponsoring this
video and supporting my channel
you've probably already heard about the
magical life-changing powers
of morning routine it's a phenomenon
that scientists don't quite understand
yet
but when you wake up early brew a cup of
coffee using the most
hipster method possible and copy the
morning routine of a powerful ceo
or youtuber then you're virtually
guaranteed to become
just as successful as they are why else
would morning routine videos be so
popular
but if you've already created a morning
routine for yourself and you haven't yet
gained your guaranteed fame
success and superpowers it might be
because you skipped out
on the most important step
a good night's sleep many animals have
evolved to be
nocturnal but humans are not among them
still that hasn't stopped us from
covering our cities and homes with a
blanket of artificial light
and concocting an ever expanding number
of reasons to remain awake
long after the sun has gone down and so
often we do this
at our detriment delaying the onset of
sleep even as tomorrow's work keeps our
wake up time
stubbornly fixed in place so many of us
can't seem to break this habit
our good intentions being overwhelmed by
short-term desires and pleasures
if you're anything like me then you
probably find yourself dealing with this
problem on a fairly regular basis
you should be going to bed but there are
just so many more interesting things
to do at night so what can we do about
this problem
well one simple solution is to create a
night routine
a night routine is just like a morning
routine
but in reverse instead of helping you
wake up and get ready for the day it
helps you to smoothly end your day and
also make sure
that you get to bed in time to get
enough sleep
but there is another benefit to having a
good night routine
in addition to helping you wind down
today it also helps you prepare
for the next day as well so just like we
did with my one hour morning routine
video today we are constructing a
one-hour
nighttime routine and with this routine
we've got three different goals in mind
number one wind down the day so you feel
relaxed when it's time to go to bed
number two actually get yourself in bed
on time so you're getting enough sleep
and number three do a few things to help
you prepare
for the next day and to achieve all
those goals we first have to go through
a couple of
preparatory steps number one you need to
figure out what time
you should go to bed everyone has a
specific and unique amount of time when
they're getting the optimal amount of
sleep we're all unique in that way
but according to the national sleep
foundation there are some generally
recommended times for each age group
so if you have a specific wake-up time
in mind you can use the information on
this chart to figure out when
in general you should be heading to bed
beyond that it's also worth knowing a
little bit about
the sleep cycle when we sleep we go
through a cycle
of stages a couple of lighter stages at
first and then moving into a
stage of deep sleep finally moving into
that rem
stage where you dream and you also
consolidate memories the main thing you
want to know about this sleep cycle now
is that on
average it takes about 90 minutes to
complete and
ideally you want to be waking up near
the end of one of those cycles
if you have an alarm that forces you
awake during one of the deep stages then
you are not going to have a good time
anyway armed with this knowledge you can
now start to hone in on an ideal bedtime
for yourself
and once you know that it is time for
the other preparatory step which is to
create
a wind-down alarm or as my friend martin
who wrote the first draft for this video
called it
a start winding down yadoofis alarm
and personally i think i'm going to use
that name for my own wind down alarm
so you want to set this for about an
hour before your bedtime and when it
goes off give yourself about 10 minutes
to wind up whatever it was that you were
doing
at this point it's also a good time to
be done with screens for the night
because the artificial light emitted by
screens can mess with the circadian
rhythm and sometimes even harm
the quality of your sleep and while
features like the iphone's night shift
can help
somewhat simply just being dumb with
screens near bedtime
is gonna help a lot more especially if
you're someone who finds it hard
to fall asleep if you're one of those
people who just is out like a light the
moment your head hits the pillow
well number one lucky you and number two
maybe this isn't going to matter that
much but it's at least good to know
so like i mentioned earlier one of the
qualities of a good nighttime routine is
that it prepares you for
the next day and that is what this next
15-minute chunk is all
about i think this starts with cleaning
up your workspace and in general
resetting your environment this evokes a
concept called
mizonplace which roughly translates to
everything
in its place and is a huge concept in
the world
of professional cooking chefs and
professional cooks know that to work
clean to constantly reset the
environment to make sure everything is
in its place before work starts
is going to number one cut down on
friction number two reduce accidents
and number three just make everything
work more efficiently
and this is a concept that is not
limited to just professional kitchens
everyone can use this to their advantage
so i think it's a great idea to take
some time before you go to bed to clean
up a little bit
tidy up your desk do the dishes
basically reset your living space so
it's not stressing you out
the next day you can also get ahead a
little bit and cut down the number of
decisions you have to make in the
morning by number one
laying out your clothes for the next day
and number two if you need to go
somewhere packing up
your bag though personally i work from
home now and i think a lot of you are
working from home or doing school from
home
so maybe that one doesn't apply right
now but hey one can dream right
the next 15-minute segment should be
dedicated to reviewing how your day went
so if you track your habits with maybe a
habit tracking app or maybe a pen and
paper system
like the martin system that i made a
video about earlier this year
now is a great time to make sure that
everything has been checked off for the
day
additionally this is also a good time to
ask yourself if there's anything that
you could improve
going forward for example if something
popped up today unexpected that
prevented you from getting everything
done on your plan
you can make a note about it and
hopefully it's not going to derail you
in the future
after that take five minutes to do
whatever it is you gotta do to get ready
for bed
like as dull the funky homo sapien once
said in that song that was i think
in tony hawk's pro skater three you
gotta brush your teeth
so you know at least do that and then
finally take 15 minutes to just
relax do some light stretches do some
yoga read a fiction book
whatever it is just do something that
relaxes you and puts you in a state
where it's easy
to fall asleep this nighttime routine
isn't some hardcore regimen with a ton
of habits
but it really doesn't have to be for me
all it needs to do is help me get to bed
on time and allow me to start the next
day with a plan
and a clean workspace and as i mentioned
in my last morning routine video
when i do start that new day one of the
best parts of that morning routine is
the time that i spend on
independent learning projects i never
want to rest on my laurels i always want
to be learning something new
for the rest of my entire life and if
you are the same way that one resource
that you might want to check out
is brilliant brilliant has a library of
more than 60 courses that can help you
gain a deeper understanding of the
complex topics within math
science and computer science in a way
that's different from most traditional
methods
all brilliance courses are based on
active learning principles
quickly throwing you into smartly laid
out sequences of problems and
interactive challenges
that let you actually use what you're
learning basically right away
this is one of the most effective ways
to learn by getting your hands dirty
right away
instead of passively intaking material
you learn more quickly you stay
interested for longer
and you even develop this universally
applicable problem-solving skill set
along the way and this month i want to
recommend one of their newest courses
which is all about the mathematics
behind
uncertainty i have always been
fascinated with how people make
decisions and our decision-making
process is often guided
by irrational thinking and this course
especially the section on bayesian
thinking will help you to start taking a
more
scientific and probability driven look
at the decisions that you make in your
everyday life
and if you want to start taking that
course or any of the other courses in
brilliance library you can start by
signing up over at brilliant.org
thomasfrank and if you're one of the
first 200 people to sign up with that
link you're going to get 20
off your annual premium subscription
thanks so much for watching this video
if you found it useful hitting that like
button gently with your middle knuckle
is always appreciated and lets the
youtube algorithm know that this video
is
well i guess good as good as a robot can
think it is
but it will maybe push it out to more
people so that's always appreciated but
again thank you just for watching and
paying attention to the stuff that i
throw up on the internet seriously you
guys are awesome
if you haven't subscribed already and
you want to get new videos when they
come out
i'll have a subscribe link right over
there i'll also have my music channel
right over there if you want to check
that out
also on my instagram over at tomfrankly
i'm doing question and answer videos
every single
week so if you have a question that i
could answer a bit more quickly than i
would normally take to make a big video
like this
then it might get turned into a video
over there and you may want to go follow
me there and last but not least i'll
have a couple more videos on screen that
you can smash your face into your phone
screen to watch but of course
if you don't want to do that then i
don't know go skateboard an empty pool
or something because i'm not your dad