hey what's up everybody I'm Tom from
college infog geek.com and today I want
to talk about a study tip that I
recently learned when I interviewed
somebody for my podcast and the guy
interviewed is named Cal Newport and if
you haven't heard of him he's written a
lot of different books for students that
help them be better in college and
there's something he told me that really
really stuck with me in the interview
that I want to share with you so what
Cal told me is creating things of value
requires that you go to intellectual
combat and this is something that I
think I intrinsically knew and you might
know yourself but it's good to have it
reiterated because when you want to
create something when you want to learn
something or do something that's
difficult you really have to reach and
dive deep and give it the time it
deserves and I think that we don't give
this concept enough respect in today's
world I'm guilty of it myself because I
run this blog and I run this podcast and
this YouTube channel and I want to share
tools and techniques to make you more
efficient but I think when we're
focusing on these time management and
task management tools and we're focusing
on study tactics like space repetition
method of Loi all this kind of stuff we
don't give creative work and we don't
give learning the respect they deserve
they really require concentrated
difficult effort learning is reaching
and this is something we need to
intrinsically know and understand when
we build our schedules so recently I
experimented with a productivity
technique called time boxing and
basically what time boxing is is you
create a minute uh minute not my minute
but uh hour by hour schedule of your
entire week or maybe day or whatever
time period you choose but you basically
plan ahead what you're going to do hour
by hour so I took a Sunday to plan all
the content I wanted to create all the
video shooting I wanted to do editing I
wanted to do blog posts I wanted to
write things I wanted to read Etc and I
actually went hour by hour and said okay
Monday morning I'm going to write 500
words for this post I'm going to work on
uh then I'm going to start working on a
video I've got an interview to do this
is all scheduled out and my intent was
that I would be externalizing some of
the motivation to do all this work and
and I was hoping that I would be more
productive because I would have this
preset schedule that was driving me
forward instead of me having to make a
decision every time I finish a task now
I knew going into the time boxing
experiment that this first week was
going to be inaccurate because there's
this thing called the fudge ratio and a
fudge ratio is the difference between
your mind's estimate of how long it's
going to take to do a task and the
actual amount of time it does take and
the problem with human brains is we
can't differentiate between best case
scenario and the average case scenario
so when we estimate the time it's going
to take to do something we think of the
average case like I think on average
it's going to take me 15 minutes to get
to work but our our minds are actually
generating a best case scenario because
we don't think of things that can go
wrong and things do go wrong in the real
world and we can't really think about
these things that happened beforehand so
hence the fudge ratio the time it takes
beyond your initial estimate it's also
called Hoffer's law so Douglas Hoffer
the author of a book on my shelf godell
ebach and a couple of other books said
that hofstetter's law is um you know
take your time estimate for something
and double it even if you're taking into
account hoffet law already so it's kind
of recursive and a torous but it does
have a good point that you need to um
take your initial estimates and give it
a fudge ratio so it's probably going to
taking a little bit longer I tried to
implement a fudge ratio into my time
boxing experiment but I knew I wouldn't
be perfect and as I went through as you
can see here on the screen there are a
lot of boxes later on in the week that
weren't checked off and there's a Common
Thread between those boxes the common
thread being these tasks were creative
thought intensive tasks and I didn't
give them enough time for two reasons
the first one and the base reason is I
just didn't schedule enough time I
didn't give these tasks the respect they
deserved as somebody who's been writing
for about 4 and a half years now I sort
of assume that I'm going to be able to
create something really really good in a
short amount of time but when I'm
wrangling Concepts that I don't know a
whole lot about and when I need to do
research and learn it does take longer
and the other thing is I really
sandwiched these creative thought
intensive tasks between other things and
the other things weren't always
perfectly efficient I might not have
gotten something done the exact time
that I scheduled it so it sort of uh
eats into the time that I've already
scheduled for the creative task and as a
result my brain goes I don't have time
to think about you know I don't have
time to really dive into this creative
task I'm just not going to work on it
and this is something that I learned
during the time boxing experiment so if
I do this again I know going forward
that I have to respect the creative
tasks I have to give them the time that
they deserve deserve so here is the best
way that you can Implement my experience
into your own life number one think of
your tasks in context there's two
different contexts that I see for task
management one is high thought intensity
tasks tasks that really require you to
think buckle down and reach and these
tasks require a lot of time and
dedicated effort uninterrupted work time
there's also low intensity tasks things
like doing your laundry going to eat
with friends going to class there's just
things that don't require as much mental
reaching and the best thing that you can
do to really set yourself up for Success
on the high-intensity tasks is batch the
low intensity tasks so plan your week
ahead in advance maybe take Sunday to do
a whole week of planning if you can and
think about what are all these low
intensity tasks that I need to get done
and how can I squeeze them into as few
sections or segments of work as possible
doing this lets you have open time for
the high-intensity tasks time that you
need to really dive in and work hard
hard the other thing you can do is to do
regular self- evaluations to see what
times of the day you are best primed to
do high intensity tasks so maybe you are
a really good morning writer or somebody
who can study well in the early morning
maybe it's early afternoon for you or
maybe you're a night out and you found
that like wow it's midnight to 1:00 a.m.
and this is like my on fire time but be
deliberate in paying attention to those
times because when you do that you can
intelligently schedule your classes your
social life and your work schedule
around that to leave un interrupted
blocks of time at those optimal time of
the day and if you notice the awkward
jump cut there well I kind of forgot the
exact linage but it works right so those
are the main ideas in this video number
one creating things of value and
learning difficult material both require
going to intellectual combat as Cal says
you have to respect the task you have to
give it the time it deserves and don't
allow yourself to be interrupted during
that work time the other two ideas are
supporting this main idea number one
look at your tasks in term of context
and try to batch the low intensity ones
and secondly try to evaluate what the
best times of the day are for you to
work by deliberately implementing these
ideas into your life you're going to be
a lot more efficient in your studying
and get a lot more
done hey thanks for watching my video If
you enjoyed it then you can support me
by giving it a like on YouTube or
sharing it with a friend if you want to
get more videos just like this every
single week on being a better college
student then click the Subscribe button
right there if you missed the last video
a clip of it is playing right below
there and you can click that to watch it
also you can get a summary in links to
anything I mentioned in the video by
going to the companion blog post which
you can find by clicking on the orange
logo right there lastly if you want to
get a free chapter of my book that it
comes out then you can click that book
and subscribe to the College of
newsletter you'll also get notified when
new podcast episodes and blog posts come
out every week lastly if you have ideas
for new videos or you just want to
connect with me you can do so on Twitter
or leave a comment on this video thanks