hey there guys today I wanted to give
you five lessons that I learned from
reading the book The Power of Habit by
Charles dug now I read this book a
little while ago I took a lot of notes
on it and learned a ton from it and
actually helped me start to change a lot
of my habits which led to some pretty
drastic changes in my life so I wanted
to share some of the most important
things that I've learned from this book
and the first lesson is simply that all
habits can be broken down into a
three-step process habits are triggered
by cues which then lead into a routine
and the routine ultimately culminates in
a reward one of the key things to note
in this lesson is that habits are
delicate things they don't trigger
unless the queue triggers them so if you
don't expose yourself to a queue you're
not going to do a habit now this is
important for both good habits and bad
habits you need to build cues that
trigger good habits and you want to try
to avoid cues that trigger the bad ones
now speaking of cues that trigger habits
the second lesson I learned from this
book that I want to share with you is
that almost all cues fall into one of
five different categories they either
fall into the category of location time
emotional state
actions of other people or the
immediately preceding action knowing
these five categories of cues is useful
when you want to start changing bad
habits because they'll allow you to pick
out the cues of each individual specific
habit that you're targeting now the
third lesson that I learned from this
book is that there's actually a fourth
component of the Habit Loop when I read
the first chapter it presented the first
three parts of that Loop but then later
on in the book you learn about the
fourth one which is craving through an
experiment done on a monkey scientists
have been able to figure out that in the
initial stages of building a habit the
brain receives a spike of activity
basically a dopamine surge when the
actual reward of the Habit is achieved
however as time goes on and the Habit is
done over and over and over again it
becomes more ingrained the spike of
activity starts to come before the
routine is even gone through it comes
when the queue happens and what this
means for you is that when you're
exposed to a queue for a habit that
you've already had for a while and have
gone through many different times your
brain gets that Spike of activity before
even going through the routine at that
point you get this craving this need to
get the reward and it's a
self-perpetuating cycle that keeps the
habit going now the book talks a lot
about how to change your habits how to
actually break bad habits and start
building new ones but one of the most
interesting parts of this that I read
about which I want to make the subject
of this fourth lesson is that people who
want to break bad habits or who are
trying to make a change in their life
are often more successful if they plan
in advance what they're going to do when
there's a pain point when something
difficult comes up the example doit gave
in the book was of people who had knee
replacement surgeries people who have
this surgery have to go through lots of
painful Rehabilitation and walking
exercising to actually regain full
functionality of their knees but this
Rehabilitation is actually really
painful and a lot of patients just can't
muster The Willpower to go through it
now what researchers found is patients
who actually wrote down a plan of what
they were going to do at specific times
during the day to rehabilitate their
knee were much more likely to go through
that painful Rehabilitation process and
were in turn much more likely to recover
and finally the last lesson that I want
to share from this book is that some
habits have a tendency to spawn other
habits and these habits are called
Keystone habits the book mentions that
for people people trying to lose weight
one of the most successful methods that
has been used is simply having them keep
a daily food journal by establishing
this one little easy to- maintain habit
dieters were actually able to recognize
patterns in their life they hadn't
noticed before and that spurred them on
to start making more positive changes to
tackle those patterns essentially
Keystone habits help to create small
wins which in turn boost your overall
motivation and give you some momentum to
build even more habits in your life to
give you a personal example I started
getting serious about building new
habits back in 2014 and my Keystone
habit was simply waking up early every
day by establishing that habit I was
waking up early and feeling really
productive in the morning and that gave
me the motivation to start creating
morning routine full of other good
habits so those are my Five Lessons I
wanted to share from you from the Power
of Habit overall I learned a lot from
this book and I highly recommend reading
it and if you want to find it I've
linked to it down in the description
below by the way this video is a start
of a new series on this channel that I'm
calling Five Lessons essentially when I
finish a book that I really want to
share lessons from with you guys I'm
going to create a video that shares
those lessons and I'm doing this because
I'm not that good at criticizing books
I'm not really a reviewer of sorts but I
am a good curator and I do like sharing
the things that I learn now these videos
won't be replacing the weekly videos
that are already coming out on this
channel they actually be an addition to
those videos and they won't be weekly
themselves because I don't read a book
every single week I actually take my
time to read books and I make sure to
take really good notes on them and I
think that'll enable me to share better
lessons from them as well so if you're
already a subscriber to this channel
don't worry the other content's not
going away this is simply an addition to
it and if you're new here this channel
is actually all about studying more
effective itively and being a better
student so if you enjoyed this video and
you want to learn how to learn more
effectively try subscribing also if
you've already read this book or you're
a voracious reader and just want more
book recommendations I've got a whole
list of books that I've enjoyed and
think are really good for students on my
site and you can click the card or the
link down in the description to find
them right now that's all I got so
thanks so much for watching and I'll
will see you on
Thursday hey guys thanks so much for
watching this inaugural video on my Five
Lessons series now if you enjoyed it you
can support this channel by leaving a
like and if you want to get more videos
on being a more effective AC student
every week and more Five Lessons videos
in the future click the big red
subscribe button right there if you want
to read a book on earning better grades
I happen to write one and it's
absolutely free so if you want a copy
click the picture of the book and I will
send you one if you want to read a
summary for all five of these lessons
and get links to this book and others I
recommend click the orange logo right
there to go to the companion block post
you can click the thumbnail to see
another video of mine with book
recommendations and if you want to
connect I'm on Twitter or you can leave
a comment below with any questions you
have
thanks