thanks to audible for sponsoring this
video and supporting my channel
[Music]
so like many people on the internet as
of late i've been playing a fair bit of
this game called
among us but as many of my friends will
tell you
i'm not a very good liar wait what do
you think it's me that's what you did
right let's run away from you
electrical i think he was scared that we
would find something
that he wasn't running i think it's him
and i'm also not very good at telling
that other people are lying which means
i lose
my fair share of games but i am good at
a few other things
including building tools in this little
app called notion
now if you've watched any videos on my
channel before you probably heard a
notion in the past
if you haven't notion is an app that a
lot of people use as a note-taking
app but it can be used for a lot more
than that including
building what could be the ultimate
among us tracker tool
which i'm going to talk about in this
video you read the title right
so this might blow up my face i'm going
to attempt to make a video explaining
some high-level concepts in notion
while also explaining some high-level
concepts in among
us and also show you this template that
i've built and also let you use it if
you want to
and i guess we'll just get that out of
the way right up front if you want to
use this
template it is public you can duplicate
it you're going to find it over at
thomasjfrank.com
templates and i'll have a link in the
description down below so go and
duplicate it and follow along if you
would like otherwise
sit back grab a bag of popcorn or
whatever it is that you eat when you
watch
my youtube videos maybe nothing i i
would hope that my videos are worth
popcorn but we're gonna get into this
so we've got this among us game tracker
here which i was too busy figuring out
if i could build to wonder whether or
not
i should your scientists were so
preoccupied with whether or not they
could they didn't stop to think if they
should
and i've seen versions of this sus
tracker before i don't know who built
this but i've seen another youtuber
using
a little tool where they could
essentially drag around little cards for
each character
and you know mark if they were suss mark
if they were innocent mark if they were
dead
so that was my initial inspiration to
build this template i wanted to see if i
could recreate that a notion but once
i did that i got to thinking what else
can we do and as it turns out there's
quite a bit that you could do so like i
said earlier we have our original sus
tracker but if we switch over to one of
these views skelet game mirror hq game
polis game
these are tailored for the three
different maps in the game so let's just
click skelet which is the first map in
the game and we got this
table with all kinds of information
first off we have a column here that can
show the sus level for any player and
this is a great way for tracking
who is suspicious and who's not
suspicious so let's say we see one
player coming out of electrical and then
a few moments later there's a dead body
in there we can go ahead and mark
them as a sus and anybody marked as us
is going to be
sorted down to the bottom of the chart
so you get a bit of a sort order here
and you can see who has the most
suspicion on them
as the game goes on we've also got a
vote tracker so you can track
who voted on who which can also give you
some crucial information for deducing
who may be the imposter
i'll show you a little bit about that
later it's kind of an advanced thing so
i want to talk about some other features
first we also have a location area and
this is really cool because it also ties
into a column called
vent info so if you've played at least
one game among us
you've probably seen somebody pop out of
a vent and possibly kill you before
jumping back into that vent
and scurrying away to basically go
scot-free
and if you're trying to figure out who
might have killed another player
and you're asking them where they are on
the map this could be very useful for
you so let's just say purple
said that they were in electricity we
can tag them with electrical
and we can see here that in scaled there
is a vent loop between med bay
security and electrical this is pretty
helpful
because let's say somebody finds a dead
body in med bay and you saw a player
running out of electrical
now you know there's a pretty decent
chance that they could have killed in
med bay
jumped in the vent over into electrical
and walked out of the bottom
acting as if they were never in the
place where the murder happened
but you know better now so this event
info column is just a great way to learn
the layouts of the maps and to learn
where the vents are which is going to
help you make better deductions
but that is not even close to where i
stopped when it comes to
locations we've also got a location
reference
a task reference and an abilities
reference and these are hidden in
toggles
so by default you're not going to see
them you're going to have a clean view
but if you need to look something up
this is where you're going to want to go
so let's take a look first at this
tasks list here for among us again we
can switch our view right now we're
looking at all tasks but if we're
playing a game in the skeleton well then
we only want to see the tasks that are
in the skilled and that's what we can do
by switching over to this view so here
you're going to see all the tasks in
alphabetical order along with their type
and their location
both of these types of information are
very very important for being able to
make deductions
and to be able to catch imposters out in
their lives or maybe lie better
if you're an imposter for instance there
are different types of tasks in the game
there are short tasks and long tasks so
short tasks take very little time to
complete like clean the o2 filter
long tasks take a bit longer and can
have multiple stages sometimes like
filling up the engines
and then there are the common tasks so
each map has between two and four common
tasks
and the unique thing about these is that
if you are given a common task
every other player gets it as well and
there are also
visual tasks so this is kind of like a
subtask it's usually attached to long
tasks but sometimes to short ones
and a visual task has a visual
indication that you've completed it
which means it's a great way to prove
that you're innocent if you're a
crewmate
and it's something that you want to
avoid faking if you're an imposter so
here's a great example of why it's
important to know which tasks are visual
here's an older clip of me faking prime
shields which is a terrible task to fake
as the imposter
because if somebody had walked in they
would see that there was no visual
confirmation
but of course among us is a bit deeper
than that so if you open up this entire
database and you look at the notes tab
you're going to see that there are some
notes for certain tasks
for instance fix wiring is a very
interesting one
because it is a common task and if
you're assigned it you have three panels
at random that you're assigned to go fix
however there is an order to those
panels an order that i have listed
exactly as it is in the game here in the
notion tracker
so if you see somebody going immediately
to cafeteria to
fix wires right when the game starts
well then you know they're faking that
task
and lastly we have the location tab so
this is very useful for learning
the layout of the map learning where
things are catching people out in lies
but with this notion tracker tool we
have something else interesting that we
can do
we have this tasks table which lists the
location for each task
but if we go back to the tracker and we
come down to this location reference
you'll see that i've got a location page
for each of the three maps in the game
scaled mira hq and polis and if we go
into the scaled page
we can see that all the same data is
here but it's displayed in a different
way
so now we can see all of our different
locations in this map we've got admin
we've got cafeteria communications and
we can see the tasks that are in
each area the abilities like the admin
ability or
the emergency button and we can also see
the vents
so for instance if you look at the admin
location here we can see that
it vents to the cafeteria and also to
the right cam zone which is in between
navigation
o2 and shields so again this location
reference will make you a better player
by helping you
learn the maps more effectively and how
we do this in notion
is with a feature called relations you
can either relate one database to
another
or relate one database to itself in this
case we're taking advantage of both
different methods we're relating the
tasks database to the location database
to get our little task groupings here
and then relating this location database
to itself
so we can get the event locations and
just as a side note
making an among us template is not the
only way you can use relations to
great effect with a notion for instance
what if you wanted to make a task
manager that also managed
large projects well you could do that if
you use a template like the one i just
released called ultimate tasks so here
in ultimate tasks just to show you real
quick
if we open the views toggle here we can
see different views like today
where we can see all the different tasks
that are due today or that are overdue
but we can also see that
some of these tasks are associated with
different projects
and if we go back to the dashboard of
the task system we have a different
projects database for instance this one
right here is for website redesign
and if we go into it it's looking a lot
like our scaled map reference we have
all the tasks related to this project
within one table or if we want we can
switch over to
a kanban style board but when you come
back over to this today view you see the
tasks listed there
as well and if you're interested in this
template is completely free and i'll
have a link to it in the description
down below
you can also get all of my templates
over at thomasjfrank.com
templates and related to this i actually
launched a brand new channel recently
called thomas frank explains which has a
lot more notion tutorials on it
and there's already a video up
explaining this template in detail
explaining how you can use notion
for robust task and project management
so check that out link will be in the
description down below
but as for this video let's get back
into some among us strategies
okay so we're back in our location
reference and hopefully i've explained
the concept of relations enough that i
can go back to our original tracker and
show
the vote tracker so just like we did
with the event reference in location
tracker
the vote tracker is a self-relation to
the same database
so if people are voting on purple for
whatever reason purple did some
suspicious stuff
well then we can go and track who voted
on purple let's just say that black did
lyme did cyan did red did and when i
click out of here we're going to see
that
the voted by column now lists everyone
who voted for purple
but we also see everyone who voted for
purple
in the voted for column so this feature
can give you extra information you can
essentially track
where people are voting track who they
weren't voting for and you can make
deductions
based on that lastly we have a couple of
other columns in this tracker here
one is just called travel direction so
if you see somebody running a specific
direction out of a room you may want to
tag that for extra information
and then this active check box controls
a filter to show
only characters who have their active
checkbox checked so if you have a game
with only 10 players which i believe is
the max
you could uncheck two of them to make
sure they're not showing up and gunking
up your tracker
now speaking of gunking up your tracker
once you're done with the game
what do you do to reset it back to its
original state so you can play another
one
well you could go through here and
delete everything and that would be kind
of a pain but you could do it
or you could take advantage of one of
notions other very powerful features
which is its
template feature so down here i've got a
little button called
new among us game and if you click that
button
it's going to generate a brand new
squeaky clean tracker
and actually if we go inside this button
by clicking the little gear button right
here we can see that
inside this template block is an exact
copy of this tracker
so if you wanted to start from scratch
without having to
go back and reset everything you could
simply delete this one
like so and now you have your tracker
right here
and if you're playing on mira go ahead
and switch to the mirror game if you're
playing on polis go ahead and switch to
the polis game
they're all set up and there's filters
and property selections to basically
give you only the information that you
need
now one potential problem with this
setup
you deleted the past tracker and what if
you're a hyper competitive super
hardcore among us player like matpat
from game theory who said in one of his
videos that he actually tracks
his win loss percentage and had it about
87 wins
and you want to go back and study all
your previous games to make sure
that you're as strategic as possible
well you don't want to be deleting your
trackers do you so if you go to the
bottom here
we have another database called among us
game record
and there's a template in here it's
actually several templates one for each
map of the game
so if we click a scaled game template
we're gonna generate
a brand new game that has everything
that we just went over
hidden inside of it so if i open this as
a page we can go ahead and call this
maybe
game two we can tag it with the players
if we want to let's just say i was
playing with toast and corpse
and pokey uh and it's an imposter game
or a crew game maybe it's a crew game
i can go in here and i can do everything
that i just showed you but
now it's in its own little database
record so you can keep
all of your play stats you can keep
everything you did
and then you can go back and just uh
create a new game from the template
and save the record of all of your games
so if you want to study your past
performance if you want to study things
people said and go review your game play
this could be a tool that would help you
do that so that brings us to the final
question
will using this template make you a
better among us
player well i hopped on with a few of my
friends patrick from tearzoo
my agent dave a few other people and i
tried using this template during some
gameplay and i have
some thoughts number one this template
absolutely does help with memorizing
certain things
that reference is very very helpful but
i also found that it sort of pulled my
focus away from the game and because i
was trying to tag things it made it a
little bit harder to pay attention to
the discussion
when we found a dead body or when an
emergency was called so
what i would consider this to be is a
training tool you could use it during
certain games to learn maps more
efficiently
or to learn the play styles of your
friends or you could use it after the
fact
to study the different maps of the game
or study your own gameplay by tagging
things from memory
either way hopefully you find it helpful
and like i said there's going to be that
template link in the description down
below where you can grab it and
duplicate it for yourself
oh and one last thing bring it on toast
so hopefully some of the stuff you saw
on this fun little video gave you some
new ideas for pushing notion in
directions that you hadn't thought of
before
personally i love finding new ways to
use this app as you might have also seen
in my recent video on how i've built
shortcuts
into my ios home screen to launch
specific notion pages
instantly and of course i've got notion
right on the home screen as well but
there's another app on my home screen
that i want to talk about for a moment
which is audible audible is one of my
absolute favorite apps because i
love to listen to audio books and if
you've got lots of time during the day
where you do chores or you're commuting
taking walks or even when you're just
trying to fall asleep listening to
audiobooks can be a way to make that
time
a bit more enjoyable or possibly even a
bit more useful
and of course the best place on the
internet to get your hands on audiobooks
is audible they have an absolutely
unmatched library of not just audiobooks
but podcasts guided wellness programs
comedy and even audible originals
that you can't get anywhere else and
something new about those originals is
that as a member you can now listen to
every single one that comes out each
month instead of only having to pick
two which is a pretty great deal and
what's also a great deal is that if you
go over to audible.com
thomas or text thomas to 500 500 on your
phone you're gonna get a free 30-day
trial of audible
along with a free audiobook download of
your choosing from their entire library
now that library is huge so if you're
looking for recommendation this month i
want to recommend one of my favorite
narrative nonfiction books of all time i
listen to it almost
every night when i go to sleep it's
called ghost in the wires by kevin
mitnick and if you like the social
engineering and the sort of cat and
mouse games from among us but you also
like computers then you're really going
to enjoy ghosts and the wires
of course if you're looking for
something more along these
self-development lines then you may also
want to check out james clear's atomic
habits which is narrated by james clare
himself and it'll be a great pick to use
your free trial on but of course there
are thousands of titles in the library
and you can pick any single one of them
with that free audiobook so once again
go over to audible.com
thomas or text thomas to 500 500 on your
phone to get started with that free
trial
beyond that if you enjoyed this video
well number one hit that like button to
show the youtube algorithm what's up and
number two
definitely go check out my brand new
channel thomasfrank explains where i've
got a new video all about turning notion
into a great task management app
i've also got a couple of other videos
with some additional notion tips and
i've got new videos coming all the time
so hopefully you enjoy it and if you do
hit that subscribe button
beyond that i'll have a couple of other
videos on screen that you can check out
on this channel or at least
one and if you don't want to click that
if you don't want to subscribe
well don't and go play video games for
the next 16 hours because as always i
am not your dad thomas frank
you i don't respect you and you're
a bad liar
do better