most people have to go to work but what
if your work could go with you wherever
you went maybe you follow one of those
vloggers who seems to be in a different
country every month or one of those
internet people who says they work from
a beach in Thailand and now you're like
that lady from Napoleon Dynamite you're
like I want that or maybe you just want
to work from home and not go to an
office every day either way I want to
cover what you can do to start building
that kind of a work life balance in this
video so before we get started let's
address the elephant in the room which
is that I'm in my room in my apartment
in Denver Colorado I'm not a full-time
traveler and I'm certainly not making
this video from a beach in Thailand I
prefer to get my horrible sunburns on
top of mountains but for the past 5
years I have had the ability to travel
and work basically whenever I want and
in those years I've gone to Japan three
times I've gone to New York City
Portland San Diego San Francisco Austin
a ton of different cities around the
country and I've been able to work and
have fun in each one of them now before
any of you cynical people start typing
away in the comments no I am not a trust
fun baby my parents don't pay for me to
travel the world in fact they weren't
even able to contribute to my college
fund at all so I've had to do this on my
own the way that I do it is through
building a business that I can work on
from anywhere but that's not the only
solution so I want to give you a few
starting points in this video and I want
to tackle two main topics number one the
cost of traveling uh doing it full-time
or just doing it on a irregular basis
and also how to make money while doing
it the first thing I I want to cover
here is the cost of traveling because
while it does definitely cost money to
travel and for some people it can be
very expensive it's not as expensive as
you might think and I just want to jump
into a concrete example here to
illustrate this so if you go to Nomad
list.com you can see a bunch of
different statistics on all sorts of
cities that are good for digital Nomads
those kind of people who roam the world
with their laptops doing all kinds of
different work that can be done from
basically anywhere and Nomad list is a
great resource because it can give you
tons of information on these cities
incling including their estimated costs
of living and I want to do a quick
comparison here so let's take the number
one city over on Nomad list Budapest
Hungary they have two different cost of
living scores on this site there's The
Nomad price and then there's the local
price so in Budapest The Nomad price is
just over $1,000 per month and that is
if you're staying in cheap hotels every
single day eating out three times a day
basically living the life of a traveler
just over $1,000 a month now for a lot
of people around the world that is
certainly a lot of money but if you live
in a big city especially like here in
the US that's actually kind of cheap
let's compare that to Denver Colorado
where I live and the local cost of
living is over $1,800 a month so if you
were to travel around the world in
cities like Budapest or even cheaper
cities like Bangkok Thailand you would
be spending $800 per month less than
you'll be spending to live the life of a
local in Denver the other thing is
prioritization I know a lot of people
who have single location Lifestyles who
have expensive Apartments they have car
payments they eat out a lot at
restaurants they've got the new video
game that comes out every single month
that is an example of prioritization
that costs a lot of money and if you
were to travel around the world and
spend you know a little bit of money on
hosts every night and plane tickets yes
that does cost money but it could
actually end up being cheaper than that
single location lifestyle and a good
example of this are my friends Sid Macky
who are Pro mountain bike racers they
actually live in a van and travel all
around the country and also to other
countries as well and uh they don't make
a whole lot of money but they're able to
do it because they have their priorities
geared towards travel so if you want to
do this ask yourself what could I give
up to make my lifestyle cheaper and to
enable
travel now the one big advantage that my
single location friends have is the
ability to go to a job and actually you
know make money to support their
expensive Lifestyles so if you want to
travel or if you don't want to go to an
office every day how do you do that well
there are two main pretty obvious
options there's the employed route and
there is the selfy route and I'm going
to give you some specific tips for each
one in just a second here but there is
one overarching factor that applies to
both of them and that's that you need to
build portable skills when most people
think of portable skills they're
thinking of computer skills web design
graphic design programming writing
editing all that kind of stuff and for
the rest of this video I am going to
focus on those sort of digital Nomad
skills that you can do from anywhere but
I do want to make a quick point that
there are other options out there as
well in fact Matt from expert
vagabond.com has an entire article on
all the different kinds of jobs you can
do as a traveler and he breaks them down
into three different categories there's
the expat jobs the Vagabond jobs and the
digital Nomad jobs expat jobs are
basically the kind of jobs where you
move to another country and you find a
regular job there a good example is
teaching English and uh if you wanted to
go to Japan say you could get involved
in the jet program which allows you to
teach English in public schools while
living in Japan that's a great way to
get experience living in that country
and interacting with the locals on the
Vagabond side you have jobs that aren't
really based on computer skills these
are things like working on farms through
programs like woofing or working at
hosts and as somebody who's been in
Japan many different times I have
firsthand experience seeing people who
worked at hosts and got free lodging and
pay sometimes in exchange however the
most flexible kinds of jobs either
self-employed or employed are going to
be those digital Nomad type jobs
basically anything you can do from a
computer or from the Internet is going
to allow you a lot of flexibility in
where you are when you do that work now
you do have your usual suspects like
like I said web design programming all
that stuff there's also social media
management customer service for startups
all those kind of jobs but there are
also other options out there that you
might not think of for example my friend
Gretchen is a tutor for high school and
middle school students and she can do
that from Skype and my friend Ryan from
Medical School HQ helps Premed students
with their medical school applications
again that can be done through Skype and
through email and other tools so he
could do it from
[Music]
anywhere all right so now we are getting
into specific tips for each individual
ual path and I want to start with the
employed path working for somebody else
so if you want to either work from home
while being employed or be able to
travel while you work I have a couple of
specific tips for you the first one is
to look for remote friendly companies
here's the thing a lot of companies out
there are looking to build a very
specific culture where they're building
face-to-face teams that have in-person
interaction and other companies just
might want to control the work
environment or the tools you use or your
schedule but there are a lot of other
companies out there that are embracing a
remote first approach for example buffer
which is a company I've been following
for about 6 or seven years now and use
myself it's a social media scheduler
they have over 80 people all over the
globe tons of different time zones and
some of their employees actually travel
full-time while doing work for them so
if this is something that you want to do
look for companies that have a remote
friendly culture there are actually
several websites online where you can go
to look for remote only jobs including
remote based. remote.co and
weworkremotely.com the other thing you
can do is to Simply ask about the
company's culture during the interview
ask them if they have anybody who works
from home or anybody who's ever worked
while traveling and if they'd ever be
open to that situation because if that's
something you want to do you need to
figure out if that company's culture is
going to be a fit remember an interview
is not just an audition it's not just an
audience with some all powerful
recruiter that you prostrate yourself in
front of it is a negotiation between two
parties who are trying to figure out if
they can work well together the other
huge thing to consider is that any sort
of arrangement where you're traveling
and working creates uncertainty for your
potential employer you're no longer in
the building you're not working on their
schedule you're possibly Halfway Around
the World in a different time zone with
unreliable internet and that can make
them a little bit uncertain as to
whether you're going to actually be able
to deliver on what they need you to do
so you're going to need to build trust
and prove your value before you ask for
something like this and unfortunately
you're not always going to be able to
build that trust through the strength of
your portfolio or through the interview
sometimes it just takes time and put in
your dues in I found a great example of
this concept over on Hacker News when I
found a thread called best place to look
for remote jobs and the top comment read
like this an old colleague of mine who'
worked at an LA based tech company for
10 years went to hand in his resignation
he was moving to Charlotte so he could
be with his girlfriend his boss begged
him to stay he could even work remotely
my friend took the deal he lives in
Charlotte now and flies to La every 2 or
3 months the best place to look for
remote jobs is to talk to people who
have worked with you in the past and
trust
you the other main route for being able
to travel and work at the same time is
the self-employed route and this is the
one that most people think of this is
the one that all those internet gurus
sitting on beaches in Bangkok are there
beaches in Bangkok are trying to sell
you courses on how to do and it is what
I do so we're going to talk a little bit
about that now my particular business
model is content creation I spend most
of my time making YouTube videos and
blog posts and podcasts for you guys but
my business model comes through
advertising and brand deals so I'm
essentially selling access to my
audience to these companies and the
disadvantage there is that that this
takes a long time to do it took me about
2 and a/ half years to build up my
audience to the point where I can
actually make enough money to pay my
expenses and that's why while this is
definitely something you can do if
you're passionate about making videos or
making podcasts or whatever it's not
exactly the best option for being able
to create a situation where you can
travel and work in the short term for
that you're going to want to find a
situation where you can apply your
skills in such a way that a small group
of clients or customers can pay for most
of your expenses and that's why I think
freelancing is a great option if you
have a skill maybe web development
programming writing or editing or
anything else that you can do from the
internet and if it's valuable enough
that a small group of people could pay
your bills then you could spin that up
pretty quickly and then get on the road
now freelancing is a huge topic so we
can't talk about it too much in this
video but I do have an article over on
my site College infogeek called The
Ultimate Guide to freelancing in college
and even if you're not in college this
article will be helpful for you it goes
through how to pick your skill how to
find clients how to reach out to those
clients how to set prices all that good
stuff so definitely check out the link
in the description below if that is
something that's interesting to you
couple of additional resources before I
leave you today first some recommended
reading and the first one is the
personal MBA by Josh Kaufman now this
book is not a travel book it's not a
vagabonding book it's nothing so Niche
it's more an overall introduction to
most of the main Concepts in business
value creation value delivery Marketing
sales all that kind of stuff and while
that may sound a little bit boring to
you right now I think that any student
and any person in the Working World
should read this book because when you
have a better grasp of business as a
whole you're going to understand the
incentives that drive your boss or your
clients which in turn makes you a better
freelancer or employer and when you
increase your skills in either of those
categories you increase your ability to
do things like travel and work at the
same time the other book is vagabonding
by Rolf Potts and this is the full-time
travel book this is the book to read if
you want to be going all over the world
to multiple different countries I read
this when I went to Japan a few years
ago go and uh it was very helpful for me
and it does have a chapter on financing
your travels but it also answers lots of
other questions like how to pick where
to go where to stay once you're there
all sorts of stuff like that so it's
definitely a good resource some of the
links are kind of outdated in it but as
a whole the information is good and my
last recommendation is for any of you
who are interested in starting to
freelance because my friend Roberto
Blake who has a channel here on YouTube
has a ton of great videos that you're
going to want to check out and I'm going
to put a card to one of his videos right
there definitely go subscribe to his
channel if you want to learn how to do
that you can also subscribe to my
channel right there if you haven't done
so already and give this video a like if
you enjoyed it you can also find that
Ultimate Guide to freelancing article
right there and another one of my videos
right there thanks for watching and I'll
see you next week