tucked within the training programs of
many an athletic discipline is a
particularly challenging type of workout
called the MRAP workout standing for as
many reps as possible these types of
workouts challenge athletes to do a
specific move as many times as they
possibly can within a set amount of time
these types of workouts are intense and
they can be a great way to track the
progress of your fitness over time in
fact the climbing gym that I go to
actually uses the AMRAP format to test
our fitness in their general exercise
classes but aside from its benefits in
the gym the idea behind the amrap
workout can also help you become more
productive as well this is an idea that
I learned about from jason khalipa an
athlete and successful entrepreneur who
competed in the crossfit games eight
times and actually won it in 2008 among
other feats Jason is back squat at 450
pounds dead lifted 550 pounds and done a
single set of 64 pull-ups which makes
the 13 that I did for this video's
opening shot looked pretty pathetic by
comparison in addition to being an elite
athlete though Jason is also the owner
of a successful gym business with six
different locations and his ability to
manage that business along with his
athletic and his family stems from a
concept that he calls the AMRAP
mentality I first learned about this
concept when I listen to Jason's
interview on the Tim Ferriss show which
is one of my favorite podcasts and ever
since it has been a very helpful mental
tool for me which is why I want to share
with you today to start I want to pose
to a question that Jason brought up in
that interview are we more productive
today than we were 20 years ago it's
tempting to jump to an immediate yes
since we now have access to vastly
better technology information and
automation than we had back when a bug's
life came out but is that actually a
good thing sure I can now tell a robot
to put things on my calendar which is
admittedly pretty cool but all this
technology also makes it so much easier
for us to constantly pull our attention
away from the present and this becomes
habitual how many times have you been
out to dinner with friends and had the
urge to check your phone for text
messages even though you're literally
sitting across the table from people you
could talk to in person and how often do
you feel your attention being pulled
away from your work because you just
have to know what the best-selling
Godzilla movie is it's become easier
than ever for us to spend almost all of
our time in a distracted unfocused state
however in the
modern times there is still one
situation where you almost never find
your mind wandering from the present as
Jason points out in that interview when
you're in the middle of an AMRAP workout
when you're trying as hard as you can to
raise your chin to that bar just one
more time that's when your mind is
completely focused on the task at hand
the level of sheer intensity involved an
AMRAP round makes it impossible to focus
on your weekend plans or that video game
you played last night and this leads to
the core idea behind Jason's MRAP
mentality channeling that intense focus
that present mindedness that you
experienced during the intense workout
and applying it to the rest of your life
whether it be your homework or the time
you spend with friends and family Jason
breaks the process of using this
mentality into four steps first you need
to work to identify your areas of focus
ideally you should only have a few of
these and each of them should have
what's called a strong internal lie a
compelling reason for why you're
focusing on them instead of something
else and this part of the process might
also involve abandoning certain areas of
focus or at least putting them on the
back burner if you have too many
remember you can only spend so many
plates at once actually I can't spend
any plates
anyway the areas of focus that I've
chosen for myself include one creating
videos with a specific focus on the
writing process and filming process now
that I have an editor number two my
athletics specifically training in rock
climbing and figure skating three
spending time with my girlfriend Anna
and for working out talk for a
conference that's coming up in a couple
of weeks now before we move on to the
second step in the process I want to
mention that you should be doing this on
a more micro level as well these are all
macro goals that I just outlined but
every day I also try to write down a
list of the things that I want to
accomplish by the end of the day and for
each item on the list I ask myself does
that item have a strong internal why
alright so after you chose in all those
areas of focus the next step is simple
choose one area focus on it with all of
your attention and work hard at it
or in other words and wrap it and one of
his talks about the MRAP mentality Jason
gave this concept weight by using the
image of a bicycle when you're riding a
bike your only focus is on where you're
going it's not you're probably going to
crash and if you want to get where
you're going with any amount of speed
you're gonna have to crank those pedals
hard and this metaphor was especially
fitting for me just a couple of days ago
because over the weekend I decided that
I was gonna ride my bike from my place
in Denver over to a friend's place in
Boulder
and then back the total distance that
ride is 70 miles which is actually the
longest that I've ever ridden a bicycle
now I made pretty good time and I ended
up driving a boulder around 2:30 p.m. in
the afternoon but since I stayed and
hung out my friend's place for a while I
didn't start heading back until around 6
p.m. and before I even hit the halfway
mark on that ride back it started
getting dark which meant that I had to
spend about 20 miles riding with my
bike's headlamp it was a perfect example
of the AMRAP mentality in action the
dark forced me to concentrate intensely
on where I was going in my surroundings
and the fact that it was getting darker
and darker motivated me to pedal quickly
even though the previous 50 miles had
already worn me out I was in a word and
wrapping the entire way home putting in
focused intense effort until the job was
done and I was ready to switch to
something else which as it happens is
the third step in the amrap mentality
switch gears and do it deliberately and
of course when this happens you then go
right back to step 2 right back to
focusing intensely and working hard at
that next thing the idea here is that
mentally switching from your math
homework to say hanging out with a
friend it should be exactly like going
from an AMRAP set of pull-ups to another
am rep set of push-ups your focus calm
is switches to the new thing and then
all of your attention becomes fixated
upon it lastly the MRAP mentality
requires frequent periods of
reevaluation you need to sit down quite
often and ask yourself do my areas of
focus still make sense ask yourself if
there's still a strong internal Y for
each one and whether or not there's
still room in your life for all of them
and Jason gives a great example of this
in his interview on Tim Ferriss show
after competing in the CrossFit Games
for eight years jason sat down and
realized that his business was growing
his family was growing and the
competition in the games was getting
tougher and tougher each year
so after re-evaluating his priorities he
decided to stop competing so we could be
a better father and husband and business
owner he realized that if you wanted to
excel up these things there wasn't
enough room in his life to also be a
serious competitor and this act of
reevaluating is something that you need
to do as well especially during periods
of change in your life even though the
AMRAP mentality will enable you to be
more productive you always need to keep
in mind that your time attention and
energy are all limited resources so to
recap the MRAP mentality involves one
identifying your areas of focus and
defining a strong internal Y for each
one to choosing a single area of focus
working to remain mentally
the entire time you're doing it and
going at it hard three switch gears
deliberately and have a good reason for
doing so don't just jump back and forth
between focuses and four take time to
reevaluate your areas of focus often
especially when you go through a life
change or you decide you want to start
spinning another plate now the steps
outlined in this process might seem
similar to other concepts that I've
shared in the past but there's a reason
that I wanted to share with you now
namely that it's been a very useful
visual metaphor for me as an athlete I
often do amrap workouts as well as other
high-intensity forms of training I'm
well acquainted with the
all-encompassing focus that comes with
trying to do as many pull-ups as I can
or trying to do a difficult bouldering
problem or trying to climb a big hill on
my bike and when I remind myself of what
it's like to be in those situations I
find it easier to slip into the flow
state with my work as well in fact I've
actually started writing and rap at the
top of my daily to-do lists I am a huge
believer in the idea that visual
metaphors can be strong motivators when
I'm out on a long bike ride I often
picture the Pistons in a car engine
moving which helps me regard my own legs
as similar machines that won't be
influenced by whatever complaints my
brain wants to throw up about them this
type of visualization is powerful and
many elite athletes actually use it
before competing so even if you already
know that you should be focusing
intensely or switching gears
deliberately ask yourself are you if
you're not currently doing as well as
you'd like
well maybe give the MRAP mentality a try
because you might find it just as
helpful as I did now there is one last
thing we need to talk about here a lot
of you have readily admitted to the fact
that you watch my videos as a way to
procrastinate on your work and while I'm
flattered and well it's definitely a
better way to procrastinate than
watching baby otter videos which I did
yesterday you need to get back to work
now I know what some of you are going to
say here but Tom I'm completely stuck on
my homework I've got a bunch of problems
I've worked as hard as I can but I can't
solve them and my professor doesn't have
office hours until next April well if
that is you then one app that you might
want to consider adding to your phone's
home screen is the Chang study app this
app along with their website for your
desktop users gives you access to step
by step solutions to the problems that
you're gonna find in your textbooks and
their library is massive spanning over
twenty-two thousand different textbooks
including because I wanted to test the
service out for myself the Java
programming textbook that gave me so
much trouble back in college
additionally if you get stuck on a
problem that's not one of your textbooks
you can also use the app to
the picture to take steam of Q&A experts
who can then send you an answer as
little as two hours and this is a great
tool to have your disposal when you're
in a pinch
check studies subscription is super
affordable and can be cancelled at any
time you found yourself not using it and
what's better you can also get five
bucks off your first month subscription
by going over to cheng comm slash thomas
frank when I was in college I used to
use checks market-place have used in
rental textbooks to save myself a ton of
money so I've been a fan of the company
for quite some time and it's cool to see
them adding these new features to help
students even more without being said I
want to get a big thanks to Jake for
sponsoring this video of being support
of this channel and as always guys thank
you so much for watching if you found
the ideas in this video helpful maybe
give it a like to support this channel
and you can also subscribe right there
to get new videos on this channel every
single week you can also click right
over there to get a free copy of my book
and how to earn better grades click
right over here for one more video on
this channel or follow me on instagram
over at tom frankly thanks for watching
and I will see you guys in the next one