guys today we are tackling probably the
number one issue that I get emailed
about tweeted about YouTube commented
about whatever and that is
procrastination so here's the deal for
me procrastination is one of my biggest
productivity struggles but it really
only rears its ugly head at one step in
the process and that's at the beginning
of a task because when I'm looking at a
task after I planned it out and I'm
basically like staring at a blank screen
with blinking cursor there's this
initial mental resistance to getting
into the task and once I can get over it
I can get into that flow State and work
really really intensely for a long
period of time the problem is getting
over that mental resistance is pretty
tough and more often than not I'll go do
something easier like check my email or
look at Facebook or really anything else
now I'd say it's pretty likely that you
struggle with this problem as well so
today we are going to go over my number
one technique for getting over this
problem which is called the Pomodoro
Technique now it would not surprise me
if you've heard of this technique before
because a lot of people have talked
about it and I'm honestly surprised I
haven't done a video about it yet but in
case you haven't we're going to talk
exactly about how you can use this
technique but we're also going to talk
about how you can improve it and I'm
going to link you to some apps and other
tools that you can use to augment it as
well so to start this out here is
exactly how to put the pomodora
technique into action step number one
you pick one particular task that you
need to work on not a list of tasks not
multiple tasks just one once you've
decided on it set a timer for 25 minutes
once that timer starts work as intensely
as you can on that one task for for the
entire 25-minute duration and crucially
if something happens to distract you
during that time whether it's a call or
a text from a friend or whether you get
really curious about how much a great
white shark weighs write that
distraction down on a piece of paper and
save it for later lastly once that timer
goes off you take a 5minute Min break
and then you repeat that process three
more times after you've done four
Pomodoro sessions then you take a longer
break and then if you want you can start
the process all over again this
technique is admittedly very simple but
it's also incredibly powerful and I find
it more powerful than almost anything
else forgetting me over my
procrastination Tendencies and the
reasons it works are three-fold in my
mind number one it externalizes the
discipline aspect of how long you're
supposed to work by using a timer as the
author Robert Shalini points out in his
book influence the psychology of
persuasion humans have a strong drive to
act consistently with their decisions
and that drive becomes even more
powerful if there is a public or
concrete commitment to those decisions
like writing him down or using a timer
so if you take nothing else away from
this video make sure that you actually
do use a timer when you're using this
technique it'll allow you to take
advantage of those commitment benefits
and from personal experience I know that
when I get lazy and tell myself I'll
just mentally keep track of the time I
always end up more distracted and less
productive than when I do use a timer
another benefit of the pomodora
technique is it reframes your task in
terms of input rather than output and
this might seem like a subtle difference
but it really helps you get over that
mental resistance to starting which as
we said was the main cause of
procrastination and it does this because
because it Narrows the scope of your
task and it sets a hard fixed end time
so when you have an output based task
like write a paper or write a script on
the pomodora technique there's some end
in mind but you know that you have to
get there yourself and you're not
exactly sure when that's going to happen
but by reframing your task in terms of
input simply WR for 25 minutes you know
that no matter what you do you can stop
working after 25 minutes and that makes
it much easier to get started and the
last main benefit here is having that
piece of paper next to you to write down
your distractions and this is really
really important not only because it
lets you write down your distractions
and get them out of your mind into a
place that you trust but it also helps
to sever that connection between the
craving for a distraction and the action
you take to go get that distraction and
every time you do that every time you
deny your brain's craving for a
distraction you are building that Focus
muscle and better enabling yourself to
resist distractions in the future making
you naturally more productive of course
I'm not satisfied to just tell you about
the pador technique and leave it at that
because like anything else you can
optimize this technique and make it even
more useful and in this video I've got
three additional steps that you can take
to make it work even better for you
first see if you can combine the
pomodora technique with other
productivity tools and methods to make
it even more effective and the example
I'll give you here is that I combine
this technique with cold turkey Rider
which is an app that basically turns my
computer into a typewriter that can do
nothing else until I hit a word count
goal now one of the features of cold
turkey writer is that in addition to
setting a word count goal you can also
set a time goal so in effect you could
make it a Pomodoro app and that is
exactly what I do on a weekly basis
secondly feel free to experiment with
the time intervals that you use because
25 minutes isn't some Universal
productivity constant burned into the
human psyche forever it's just what the
creator of the technique used himself
for my part I do use 25 minutes on the
clock when I'm starting out but I don't
actually take a break after that 25
minutes is up and the reason is that I
use the pador technique to get over that
initial mental hurdle to get into my
work but once I'm there I'm in the Flow
State and I don't want to stop after 25
minutes is up it's just a starting
technique for me finally before you
start a pomodora session it can be
useful to adopt a concept from The
Culinary World which is called and my
French is terrible so I need some help
on this Mison plus that's right Mison
plus and that basically means everything
in its place now in kitchens in The
Culinary world that basically means that
the chef needs to get out everything he
needs to use before starting the meal so
all the food all the ingredients all the
condiments all the cooking utensils
everything and this is really useful for
you as well because if you get into a
session and you're not prepared that can
disrupt your work so make sure you have
all of your tools out all of your apps
all of your books all of your resources
pens pencils and that distraction sheet
next to you but just as importantly make
sure that everything you don't need is
put away so close any distracting
websites any tabs you don't need any
programs put your phone away all that
good stuff all right so to round this
video out I want to point point you to
some timer apps that you can use because
I'm sure that not all of you want to use
an actual physical kitchen timer to time
your sessions so if you're on a computer
my favorite app which is free and open
source is called toighty and it's on Mac
and PC and you'll find it linked in the
description down below now a lot of you
are probably going to want to use your
phones instead so and this is different
than what I've recommended in the past
because it's new the absolute best
pomodora app that I have ever found is
called tide it is free it is wonderfully
designed it has immersive mode which
basically means that if you exit the app
during a session it will fail that
session so it's kind of like helping you
not use your phone as a distraction kind
of like that Forest app and it also
includes ambient noise aside from those
apps another option is actually to use
my study with me video that I recorded a
couple of months ago and that's actually
just 25 minutes of me studying so if you
happen to want a study buddy and you
don't have somebody nearby and you want
a timer on the screen that's 25 minutes
long definitely check that out you might
also like this video over here which
will tell you more about the optimal
work and break time cycles and and if
you like this video definitely give it a
like to support this channel And
subscribe right there if you haven't
done so already lastly if you want to
get a free copy of my book on earning
better grades check out that link right
there and thanks for watching