hey what's up guys so finals are upon us
I know some of you guys have already
started finals some of you guys have
them coming very soon and for that
reason I'm releasing this video early
this week so hopefully it can help you
in creating a study schedule and what I
want to do specifically in this video is
actually give you a look at one of the
schedules I built for my final exams as
a student but before that I've got some
general tips and principles that you can
use to build your study schedule so
hopefully you can frontload all the work
and plan effectively and that will help
you study in the most efficient way
possible through the weeks leading up to
finals and through that actual finals
week now I think there are some guiding
principles that you should keep in mind
when you're building your study schedule
these will help you make it as effective
as possible and number one you want to
minimize the time that you spend
procrastinating and maximize the time
you spend studying effectively you also
want to study the most important
material in the right order and lastly
you want to manage your energy and
stress levels so with those guiding
principles in mind the first step to
building your study schedule is to
figure out when your finals are and I
have to mention because I remember my
school did not have final exams during
the actual class periods that I went to
instead they had this convoluted formula
algorithm thing where you had to go on
the website and figure out the first
time of the week when your first class
met and that would correlate to some
other exam date probably in the evening
when you want to be eating dinner and I
can only assume they like put a bunch of
dice into a yatsi jar and that's how
they figured it out once you know those
exam dates and you're sure you're not
going to be showing up to an empty
classroom an hour after the exam ends
which by the way Pro tip is the easiest
way to to fail an exam then what you
want to do is arm yourself with as much
knowledge as possible to help you build
that study schedule I'm talking the
format of your exams multiple choice
true false essay style what have you the
material that's going to cover is it
comprehensive or is it only going to
cover what you had since the last exam
and how much of your grade this exam is
going to count for you also want to keep
in mind any homework assignments or
projects that you have due during the
exam week and speaking of that it's good
to step back for a second and ask
yourself what kind of person am I when
it comes to scheduling study sessions
and project and homework sessions maybe
you're the kind of person who likes to
intersperse the project work with the
study sessions to kind of give your
brain a break and a change of pace or
maybe you're like me and you do better
to put all of your project and homework
work on one day and then put all the
study sessions on another day and keep
it all compartmentalized so your brain
is in the right frame of reference on
each day after that take stock of your
resources make sure you have the syllabi
all the course materials handouts from
your professors notes and textbooks and
at this point your number one priority
is to assess your knowledge for each
class try to figure out exactly what's
going to be covered on each exam and
figure out where the gaps in your
knowledge are one final step before we
begin actually scheduling things and
that is to prioritize your classes and
figure out which ones you should study
for the most and in what order you want
to study them and to figure that out you
want to figure out which classes are
most important there are a few different
factors that go into this one of them is
which finals count for the most points
the percentage of your grade and those
are usually listed on your syllabuses
syllabi you also want to take into
account your current standing in each
class if in one class you have a solid a
then maybe your final performance is not
going to influence that grade too much
and maybe in another class you're kind
of on the precipice between one grade
and another and that final will really
count for what your actual grade is
going to be once you've taken those
factors into account you can compare
them against the knowledge gaps you
identified earlier to figure out which
classes are the most important and which
classes you're struggling the most in
and those two pieces of information
together will help you more accurately
prioritize how long you should study for
each class and in what order you should
schedule your sessions all right now we
are ready to begin scheduling so in the
book had a study for college which was
written by the Cornell University
Professor Walter Pac the same guy who
made the Cornell notetaking system he
recommends creating something called a
home stretch schedule for finals this is
basically a schedule much like your
normal weekly schedule but like Ultra
detailed you want to put lots of things
in there like your meal times all little
tasks you have to take care of and this
can help you figure out where the gaps
are that you can schedule study sessions
for your finals one thing I'd like to
add to this is you should try to group
and batch your small tasks into as few
sessions as possible that way you'll
have more uninterrupted blocks of time
where you can actually get studying done
now personally my tool of choice for
this has always been Google Calendar
I've been using it ever since I was a
freshman and if you're more of a paper
planner person that's more your speed
that's totally cool but at this point in
the video I want to go into Google
Calendar and show you one of my own
finals week study schedules all right so
here we are looking at the week of April
25th to May 1st 2010 this was the second
semester of my freshman year and this is
the week leading up to finals which I
have uh my exams scheduled in blue to
let me know when they are and I've
looked up when they're scheduled so
let's look at this week leading up to
finals uh it's looking pretty crazy
right now so I'm going to turn off the
homework and the other and work so this
is my class schedule I've got I believe
six classes here two of them meet only
once per week so they're pretty easy and
then I've got a Java review session that
I remember was like a whole classwide
thing the professor was running
definitely wanted to be at that and also
adding in my work I worked probably 20
hours a week or more basically all
through college so I was balancing that
with classes and actually this semester
there were more than 20 hours a week
because I had training sessions for the
summer job I was training for so I had
to balance all of this and uh because it
was so hectic I wanted to make sure that
I was getting my meals and workouts in
so that on my other calendar I had
lunches which were usually very quick
and then dinners which were with friends
and I wanted to make sure those were
longer because I really valued them also
had gym times to make sure that I was
staying healthy during this studying
week so as pox says in the book about
the home stretch schedule I now can
identify gaps of time where I can start
scheduling my study sessions and that's
exactly what I did what I want to point
out here is I have finishing my homework
on one day I've got one other homework
on this other day and then when
reviewing I tried to be very specific
about what I was going to review
remember what we talked about with the
uh Parkinson's law work expands to fill
the time allotted for it you shouldn't
show up to the library and just tell
yourself I'm going to study for 5 hours
because you're going to end up just
working on one thing for five straight
hours instead keep Parkinson's lot in
mind and also realize that your brain's
efficiency is going to take a dive after
25 to 30 minutes so you can try
scheduling your study sessions with the
Pomodoro Technique in mind and try to
accomplish a specific set of things
within 25 or 30 minutes and then give
yourself a small break that being said
let's go over to the finals week and you
can see I have my finals labeled in blue
so I know exactly when they are and I
just have work there were no classes
during that week so I didn't schedule
things here because I was not perfect as
a student but you could keep scheduling
things and being efficient up until your
finals are done and then you are home
free all right so to round this video
out I've got three final quick tips that
can hopefully make your study schedule
even better and the first one is to pay
attention to the es and flows of your
body's energy levels throughout the day
for instance maybe your energy levels
are highest in the morning in which case
maybe you should schedule your hardest
study session for then but also make
sure you're going to bed early enough
that you're well rested to get up early
or maybe you're night owl and you find
that you're really really focused at
night in which case don't worry about
getting up too early number two remember
that the performance of your brain is
connected to the well-being of your body
so schedule time to exercise and
schedule time for breaks so you can
reduce stress and lastly ask for help
when you need it be sure to challenge
yourself and try to work through
problems but if you really get stuck
asking your professor can accelerate
your review process and save you a lot
of stress if you've seen my video with
tips on starting a new semester you'll
remember I had a hidden calendar with my
professor's office hours on it and I
could activate it at any time to figure
out when a certain Professor would be in
the office and when I could go get help
so that's it for this video if you check
the companion article for it you'll find
screenshots of my Google Calendar in
case you want to use it as a guide for
your own otherwise if you like this
video give it a like to support this
Channel and I will see you in next
week's
video hey guys thanks so much for
watching this video If you want to get
new tips every week on being a more
effective student you can click that big
red subscribe button right there and
also if you want to get a free copy of
my book on earning better grades click
the picture of the book and I'll send
you one if you want to see that
companion blog post click the orang
button right there and if you missed
last week's video we talked about a
brain hack of sorts for performing
better on your exams so check it out if
you haven't seen it lastly I'm Tom
frankly on Instagram or Twitter if you
want to connect or you can leave a
comment down below