here's a question that I think is pretty
important to ponder how should you fill
your brain or more specifically who
should you trust to learn from what
qualifies a Learning Resource as uh
worthy of your attention and once that
qualification is set how much of what
they communicate should you actually
incorporate into your own life these
questions can be thought of in the
context of an idea I had a while ago
which I like to call the stuff that
works Library your brain among the C of
all the brains out there holds a unique
mix of facts and Concepts and practices
advice and anecdotes that you've heard
throughout your life and that you deem
to be particularly useful to your
situation it's different from all the
content and all the other brains out
there because you have your own unique
set of learning resources that you
expose yourself to in addition to your
own unique set of goals and aspirations
and limitations and environment
relationships Etc now as a content
creator this actually takes a lot of
pressure off of my shoulders because I
know I'm allowed to be imperfect as a
teacher there's no way I could ever be
perfect and in turn you can allow
yourself to learn from me even though
you know my output can never be 100%
correct true and applicable to your
specific situation if I put out a video
with five tips on how to focus better
the average viewer might only get use
out of one or two of them and that's
okay because another viewer might get
use out of the other ones when I go into
the content creation process it's a lot
easier for me to flesh out my ideas
knowing that no matter how hard I try
not every single person is going to get
used out of every single idea I put out
there but in all likelihood there's
probably one or two things in each video
that you as an individual will find
helpful however this puts a bit of
responsibility on you as the learner
because it means that yes you can learn
from anyone but you have to be
Discerning about what's said to you no
matter what source it comes from you
should look for the logic and objective
truth in a statement rather than just
judging it on the merits of the source
that it came from logos not ethos the
French philosopher Montaine wrote we
take other men's knowledge and opinions
upon trust which is an idol and
superficial learning we must make them
our own we were just like a man who
needing fire went to a neighbor's house
to fetch it and finding a very good one
there sat down to himself without
remembering to carry any back home what
good does it do us to have a belly full
of meat if it is not digested if it is
not transformed into us if it does not
nourish and support us the stuff that
works concept encourages us to dig past
implicit trust and to think critically
to as Bruce Lee once said adapt what is
useful reject what is useless and add
what is specifically your own so don't
take things at face value and don't
think that a Learning Resource is an All
or Nothing deal take uh my channel for
example you might find one video to be
incredibly useful but another video is
completely useless for you and that's
okay remember you're a unique individual
and that means your learning
requirements and the things that are
going to help you are different from the
next person but as a content creator I'm
trying to make things that can teach
people on a large scale in addition I'm
also imperfect as a person so I can't
always be right 100% of the time
additionally learn to recognize when
you're confused if you hear something
that doesn't really jive with your model
of reality that doesn't match up then
stop and actually think about that if a
red flag pops up in your head don't
ignore it when that happens either your
model of reality is wrong or what you
just heard is wrong one of them needs to
be reconciled and it's not always going
to be your model of reality think
critically about whether something
deserves to become part of your own
personal stuff that works Library even
if it's from a source you already trust
the proper State of Mind for learning
well is a mix of humility
open-mindedness and healthy skepticism
so hey thanks for watching this video I
know it was a bit more philosophical
than usual but I hope you found it
useful and next week we'll be tackling
something I've gotten a lot of requests
on test anxiety so if you want to get
that video make sure you subscribe and
thanks for watching this one
hey guys thanks so much for watching my
video If you want to get new videos
every single week on being a more
effective student you can click that big
red subscribe button right there if you
also want to get a free 100 plus page
book on getting better grades I wrote
one and I would love to send you a free
copy so just click the picture of the
book you can also get links to anything
I talked about in this video and notes
by clicking the orange logo to go to the
companion blog post right there and if
you missed last week's video there's a
clip of it playing so definitely check
it out lastly if you want to connect or
suggest new topics for new videos I'm on
Twitter at tomf Frankle or you can just
leave a comment thanks
[Music]