i have a central tenant that i follow
for any kind of work that i'm doing and
it's this if i find myself doing
something repeatedly there is a process
i have to follow all the time over and
over again then anything i can do to
make that process more efficient either
by making it faster removing steps or
automating steps i should do and it's
with that idea in mind that today i
would like to share with you my top 10
favorite productivity apps specifically
for windows now i've got a couple of
friends who have done these kind of app
roundup lists for the mac and i do use
mac os i use a lot of those apps but i
actually use windows more often i prefer
on the desktop platforms and i haven't
seen a whole lot of these videos for us
windows folk so today i'm going to be
breaking down my top 10 including the
one that i think is probably going to be
the most interesting for you
my surprise pick one that you're
probably not expecting a pair that work
insanely well together they're the ones
that i'm most excited to share with you
in this video and finally the one that
is objectively the most useful app on
this list one other great thing about
this list is that every app on it is
actually free so let's get into this
list starting with the one that i think
you might find most interesting which is
an app called sharix sharex is a
screenshot tool for windows it's free
it's open source and i use the heck out
of it because i take a ton of
screenshots in my work and i do this for
multiple different purposes i do it for
content creation if you've seen any of
my written notion tutorials over on my
website you've probably seen my
screenshots and animated gifs but i also
use it to communicate more efficiently
with my team for instance the other day
my personal website had a bug on it and
i was able to just take screenshots of
the bug and send them in slack to my
developer martin to show him exactly
what was going on it's a lot more
efficient than trying to type up a long
description but sharex has a trick up a
sleeve that a lot of other screenshot
apps do not have which is optical
character recognition you can actually
take a screenshot of some text within a
picture or a youtube video and it will
pull that text out and put it right on
your clipboard so you can then paste it
into your note-taking application now i
should mention that there is a built-in
screenshot tool within windows called
snip and sketch and it's honestly very
capable you can use it by hitting
windows key shift s you can take
screenshots put them on your clipboard
draw on them but the editor that comes
within sharex is just vastly more
powerful and lets you do things like
adding boxes drawing arrows adding
pixelation and blurring for sensitive
info it's just overall a lot better and
that's why i personally like using it
over snip and sketch now there are a
couple of little tweaks that i add to
share x to make it a little bit better
first i add multiple hotkeys for
different jobs so i like to use ctrl
shift f to add a screenshot directly to
my clipboard or ctrl shift c to open up
the editor so i can make boxes or arrows
or what have you and then i use ctrl
shift alt c if i want to use that
optical character recognition and pull
text out of an image and i also
configure my default screenshots folder
to live inside of google drive so all my
screenshots are available to me across
all my different devices app number two
on this list is called quick look and if
you've ever used mac os you probably
know there is a function built into the
operating system called quick look which
is sadly absent on windows well this app
brings it in there now on mac os quick
look is a function in finder where you
can basically click on a file without
opening it and see information about
that file in the sidebar you can see an
image preview if it's an image you can
see text inside of a text file and the
quick look app instead of the microsoft
windows store adds this to windows you
can click on a file and without opening
it you can just hit the space bar to
preview it now this is less useful for
really simple file types like images or
text because notepad and the windows
photo viewer open pretty quickly but
this also works on photoshop files so i
can preview photoshop files in a very
big window without opening up photoshop
i can open up animated gifs or videos
and preview them without launching a
dedicated app for it so overall really
useful tool and i love that it has a
button that will let me make the preview
stay on top of other windows as i
sometimes want to say take a screenshot
and make sure it floats on top of
something else just so i can reference
it app number three on this list and you
probably saw this coming is notion i
can't make this list complete without
notion because i use it every single day
and there is in fact desktop app so i
can use it directly on windows which
means i'm not breaking the rules of this
list now i do have a confession to make
which is that i think that mac os has a
greater number of top-tier note-taking
applications than windows does it has
ulysses it has bear it has apple notes
which is frankly fantastic but at this
point notion has made enough
improvements both in its speed and
fixing some of the annoyances i used to
have with it that it is now my favorite
note-taking application in particular
just recently they fixed the bug where
you couldn't select text precisely
across blocks which was actually kind of
a bug in pretty much all block-based
text editors i think whimsical was the
first one to really fix it at least that
i noticed but now notion is done as well
which means that i can select text like
i could in a regular word processor like
google docs and that means i can write
and i can edit precisely inside of
notion and notion runs a lot more than
just my note taking in fact i run my
entire content creation process inside
of notion we capture ideas there we run
the entire content pipeline in there
from research to scripting to editing
and we even have a library of all of our
past videos so we can pull information
from them when we need it that system is
called creators companion i've actually
turned it into a template and you can
check it out over at thomasjfrank.com
cc and for personal productivity i like
to manage my tasks in notion i have a
full template for that i do my note
taking a notion but what i've really
wanted ever since i discovered this app
is a full-on second brain template
something that would marry tasks and
projects and notes and goals and have
them all work in harmony but kicking
around this design in my head for a very
long time it's very tough to get right
to get the ux to be easily usable so it
won't turn into a mess later on but i
think i'm just about done designing this
template and i've got a second channel
called thomas frank explains that's all
about notion build guides and tutorials
so if you are interested in that kind of
thing check that channel out i'll have a
link to the description down below and
let's move on to our fourth app in this
list which actually takes our word for
the most surprising app on the list and
it's actually microsoft edge the browser
that comes built into windows yes i've
had microsoft popping up little things
telling me to switch over from chrome to
edge for years now but i've always
ignored it until i looked up some stats
and found out that edge is actually a
faster browser than chrome i was getting
kind of tired of chrome just hogging up
tons of resources on my system so i
decided to give edge a try and what do
you know it's actually kind of great at
this point it's built on top of chromium
which is the engine that chrome is built
on so it's very familiar all the
keyboard shortcuts are the same and
crucially you can install extensions
from the chrome web store into edge
pretty much any extension that works
inside of chrome now works in edge which
means that i'm not losing anything by
making the switch and i'm gaining quite
a few things number one edge does feel
snappier and it feels like it takes up
less resources than chrome does there's
even a built-in feature that will put
tabs to sleep after two hours by default
if you're not using them which frees up
system resources even more but maybe my
favorite feature in edge is if you go up
to your tab bar and right click you can
turn on vertical tabs which will move
your tabs from being a horizontal list
across the top of the bar to a vertical
list on the side which means that even
if you are a tab hoarder like i am you
can still see the names of all your tabs
which you cannot do in chrome without a
third party extension app number five on
our list is actually one that is built
right into windows and it's the windows
clipboard manager so if you've ever used
a clipboard before you've ever copied
and pasted you probably know the
clipboard is one of the most useful
functions in any operating system but by
default it has one major limitation it
only remembers the last thing you copied
it's a lot more useful if you have
clipboard history turned on so you can
see everything you've copied and you can
go back and paste something old and that
is exactly what the clipboard history
feature does so if you want to turn it
on all you got to do is hit windows key
v it will ask you if you want to turn it
on and then you can even sync your
clipboard history across devices if you
want to i don't do that because i put
passwords on my clipboard and i don't
really like the idea of having it
transmitted across anything that isn't
my password manager but it is an option
if you want to use it and that brings us
to one of two apps that i am personally
most excited to share with you in this
video these two apps work really well as
a pair so that first app is called flow
launcher and all full launcher does is
bring up a small text window on your
computer when you hit a key command by
default alt space but once it's there
you can type commands to do pretty much
anything on your computer quite a bit
faster than you would by doing it
normally again we're going back to that
concept of taking repeat processes and
making them more efficient so with flow
launcher i can launch websites i can do
google searches i can bring up files or
directories on my computer i can even do
calculations quite a bit faster than i
would with the stock calculator app and
i can even control spotify i can type sp
in the name of a playlist or a song and
i can start playing it i can turn on
shuffle i can do all kinds of cool stuff
i absolutely love flow launcher and you
can customize the heck out of it to just
bring up this little thing and do stuff
quite a bit faster and i'm just gonna
roll right to the seventh app on the
list which is called espanzo and espanzo
is a text expander app which you'll find
very useful if you often find yourself
typing the same long strings of text
like your email address or common urls
or if you do customer support or
something the same exact response to
customers you can define these very
short key snippets that when you type
they automatically expand into that
longer snippet of text so for instance i
can type emt to auto expand my email
address i can type pwf to auto expand my
notion fundamentals url which i'm
constantly pasting inside of comments i
can even expand really really long
strings of text as well and i personally
love espanzo more than say auto hotkey
which i used to use for this purpose
because espanzo also comes with a search
bar that you can bring up very similar
to flow launchers but you can search
your snippets and then automatically
paste them without having to type the
entire thing which is really really nice
and i'm putting flow launcher and
espanol together because in my workflow
they work very well in tandem personally
i have to bring up a lot of different
directories on my computer very often
i've got one for video thumbnails i've
got one for current projects being
edited i've got one for my second
channel so i've defined little key
snippets in espanzo that i can type into
flow launcher to automatically launch
those directories way quicker than i
would get to them if i was navigating
normally and to continue my complaints
about windows explorer we're gonna move
on to app number eight which is called
everything and everything is a simple
utility lets you search your files and
folders in windows because windows
folder search and file search is
famously slow it takes forever and for
whatever reason everything indexes your
hard drive and lets you search pretty
much instantly now there was also an
everything plug-in for flow launcher so
you can actually use flow launcher to
search your computer pretty well but
sometimes you're looking for a file and
you want to be able to browse a lot more
on your screen than flow launcher will
show you so i also recommend having
everything installed by default so you
can use it when you need it app number
nine on this list is good old google
drive i don't think this list will be
complete without an app that gets files
off of your computer and syncs them to
another destination so they are backed
up and also available on other devices
as well google drive i think is the best
option still even though there is also
dropbox and onedrive and other options
because for free they give you the most
storage space they give you 15 gigs
versus one drives five and dropbox is
paltry two and my tip for using google
drive efficiently is to ignore the
documents pictures music all those
different directories on your computer
and instead create a sort of root file
system within your google drive folder
that way you're going to have a single
place that you know to go to to start
looking for files if you're not choosing
to search for them using say everything
and that brings us to our final app on
this list which is probably objectively
the most useful app out of any that i've
covered here and that is flux or maybe f
lux if you want to pronounce it that way
this is a very small tiny utility that
does one thing as it gets closer to dark
to your bedtime it dims your screen and
it makes it warmer and the reason it
does this is that light be it artificial
light or sunlight messes with our
circadian rhythms there's a little part
of your brain called the suprachiasmatic
nucleus that is connected to your eyes
and when your eyes intake light waves it
essentially adjusts your circadian
rhythm and can make it harder to fall
asleep or to get quality sleep if you're
exposed to artificial light late at
night and as it turns out blue light
affects this more than other types of
visible light so the idea behind flux
and the idea behind those blue blocker
glasses you probably heard about is it
gets rid of some of that blue light and
possibly makes it easier for you to fall
asleep or to have better quality sleep
so if you find yourself on the computer
late at night or on your phone late at
night using something like flux may
actually help you sleep better and as
we've talked about in many different
videos sleep is one of the three pillars
of health but the other two being your
nutrition and your exercise that really
form the foundation of your ability to
get things done so all these other tools
we've talked about are kind of just you
know extra icing on the cake flux may
actually help you live a more healthy
life and hence a more productive one now
earlier i talked about how notion was my
constant companion for my video
production process one of my most
essential tools for getting these videos
done and done more efficiently let me
share one additional resource that
really helps my video production process
as well and that is storyblocks who have
kindly sponsored this video if you are a
creator if you make videos like i do you
definitely want to check out storyblocks
because they give you access to a
library of more than one million
creative assets that you get unlimited
access to to use inside your content
that includes a b-roll and stock footage
it includes sound effects and music so
you can level up your sound design it
includes after effects templates motion
graphics templates tons of stuff that
can level up your content and to give
you a bit of an insight into our actual
video production process we cut down
this talking head footage to what we
call an a-roll cut at that point my team
and i come up with b-roll ideas to go on
top of that a-roll and we do shoot some
of that b-roll ourselves but often there
are shots that we just can't get on our
own and storyblocks allows us to get a
lot of that which allows us to make our
content a lot more engaging and another
great thing about storyblocks is that
they are extremely affordable normally
if you want to license stock footage a
lot of sites want to charge you hundreds
of dollars per clip seriously but with
storyblocks you have one low monthly
subscription that gets you unlimited
access to as many assets as you want
they have plans to fit pretty much any
budget whether you're a solo creator or
running a large team so if you want to
start leveling up your content and get
started go over to storyblocks.com
thomas to sign up or go to the link
right there on screen if you do choose
to use storyblocks thank you so much
supporting my sponsors is a great way to
support this channel as well hopefully
you enjoyed this if you found something
useful maybe a brand new tool that's
going to help your workflow hit that
like button for the algorithm and if
you're looking for something else to
watch i've got a great companion video
for this one on the best browser
extensions for productivity or if you
are a notion user i just made a brand
new video on 10 things you might be
doing wrong in your notion workspace
check those out and i'll see you in the
next one