tell me how familiar this sounds to you
you've got some work to do so you pack
up your backpack you find the perfect
study space perfect amount of sunlight
plenty of space to work in a little bit
of nature thrown in a bottle a picture
nick offerman staring down at you you
bring yourself a fresh cup of coffee
I'm good the noise canceling headphones
and you find yourself an excellently
tailored study playlist to accompany
your impending deep dive into the
practical uses of l'hopital's rule for
Monday's calc assignment everything is
set up perfectly for you to start doing
some good old-fashioned deep work and
then alright um productivity guru said
uh set the IKEA cabinet planner no it's
for research you're disgusting
now I know what you're thinking it's the
same thing that I think all the time how
can I make sure that when I sit down to
do my work I actually do my work instead
of falling into a distracted rut after
all just sitting down at my desk isn't
gonna result in really anything getting
done one of my favorite lines in Cal
Newports book deep work is his
productivity equation time times
intensity a focus equals quality of work
produced one of his case studies in the
book Peter Roosevelt though at this time
of freshman Harvard University and knew
this rule really really well
his biographer Edmund Morris wrote that
every single day Roosevelt would look at
his schedule between the hours of 8:30
and 4:30 and block off everything that
was already scheduled things like
classes and recitations lunch and his
athletic training anything left over it
was time spent for studying and Morris
noted that these fragments didn't
usually add up to a large number of
total hours but he would get the most
out of them by working only unscored
during these periods and doing so with a
blistering intensity so the question
that we want to answer today is how do
you achieve that ability to work with
that blistering intensity like Roosevelt
did and hopefully the following 7 tips
that I've compiled will help you get
started
[Music]
first off when you go into a work
session have a single target of focus
one of my biggest pitfalls in my
professional life is that I'll wake up
in the morning and I'll create a list of
the things that I need to do
but then when I sit down I don't choose
one to work on
I'll get confused and I don't really
know which one that I want to start with
which leads to me just getting
distracted and looking at car specs on
the internet so one piece of advice that
I'm really trying to apply in my own
life and that you should too is that
before you earnestly start a work
session decide on the one task that
you're going to work on this creates
limitation for yourself which can be
very very helpful as is emphasized by
one of my favorite quotes from all time
which comes from the eaching unlimited
possibilities are not suited to man if
they existed his life would only
dissolve in the boundless to become
strong a man's life needs the
limitations ordained by duty and
voluntarily accepted now there is a lot
more that could be said about this
passage as it applies to many many areas
of life but in this particular context
just remember that one particular single
focus creates a limitation that narrows
and strengthens your level of focus tip
number two is to keep the work session
sacred and what I mean by this is that
when you sit down to do your work and
you've chosen your one task only work on
that task don't do anything before even
if it's light even if it's checking your
email even if it's watching a little
video on YouTube or even if it's eating
so this comes from a common pitfall that
I've noticed in my own work I will get
it into my head that I need to go to a
coffee shop because that's my favorite
place to focus so I'll go to Starbucks
and then sometimes I'm a little hungry
so I'll get like a little breakfast
sandwich one of those little protein
packs and a coffee and of course I don't
want to do real work while I'm eating so
I'll look at reddit or I'll look at
YouTube or I'll do something really
really like while I eat that sandwich
the problem is now I've gotten myself
into a distracted rut and it's very hard
for me to transition myself into the
real work that actually went to
Starbucks to do so the change for me is
eat breakfast at home eat whatever meal
it is at home and then only go to the
coffee shop to get coffee and to do work
no food
a third way to keep your level of focus
high is to ensure that you're using the
right tools and maintaining them I love
to cook it's one of my favorite things
to do at night when I'm done working but
one of the things that can make me
really not want to cook is a dull chef's
knife if you've ever tried to cut an
onion or an eggplant really anything
with a dull knife it is not fun to do it
all and actually it's pretty dangerous
as well now on occasions in the past
I've let my knife get dull and a lot of
times when that happens I'll start using
it they'll start cooking a meal but then
I'll get frustrated and then will just
end up ordering takeout so I've learned
that if I want to be cooking on a
consistent basis which I do because it's
healthy and it's fun to do I need to
sharpen my knife on a consistent basis
as well every couple of weeks or every
month at the very least now this doesn't
mean that you need to wait around to
have the perfect tools to start doing
your work because that is a road you
don't want to go down but just like a
knife's edge dulls a little bit every
single time you use it something like
say your computers file system gets
unorganized every time you use it so
build some time of your schedule to
maintain the tools that you already have
and if an opportunity presents itself to
acquire a better tool that's not gonna
take a ton of time or resources take it
now for the fourth and least fun tip on
this list if you want to work with that
blistering level of intensity you want
to be like Teddy Roosevelt you need to
practice an intense work ethic is
something that is built over time just
like the calluses on the hands of a
lumberjack when you start out you might
be able to focus intensely for it's 8 20
minutes but day after day after you keep
doing it again and again that ability is
going to grow and strengthen a couple of
years ago I realized that I wasn't
reading as many books as I wanted to so
I bet my friend Martin $100.00 that I
would read 25 pages every single day for
three months now when that challenge
started I found it really hard to read
25 pages a day especially if the book
that I'd selected was really technical
or detail oriented but something
interesting happened as the months went
on later in the challenge I found it
really easy to intensely focus on those
25 pages even if they took like a full
hour to read until I was done so if your
initial attempts to work with that
intense level focus seemed difficult
just remember that over time it's going
to get easier and your ability to do it
is going to improve
[Music]
tip number five is to use timers to
guide your work but to leave some buffer
room at the end of those timers in your
schedule now I talked a lot on this
channel about the Pomodoro Technique
setting a timer for 25 minutes and
working on that single task you selected
and nothing else until the timer goes
off but a lot of people seem to think
that they're obligated to take a break
at the end of that Pomodoro session and
I don't do this for me the Pomodoro
session is just a way to get started to
overcome that initial resistance to
doing the work but once I get into it I
often work for an hour or more I ignore
the timer when it goes off the thing is
it can really take some time to get into
that state of mind where you're really
intensely focused on your task you can't
do it within five or ten minutes so
again the Pomodoro Technique is just a
way to get yourself started let yourself
work past the end of that timer that
being said don't give yourself too much
time either because time pressure can be
a very powerful motivator as the author
Adriana trade you got anyone said
there's nothing an artist needs more
even more than excellent tools and
stamina then a deadline our sixth
principle was best expressed by the
artist Pablo Picasso without great
solitude no serious work is possible if
you want to be able to focus on your
work intensely and get really good
creative work done for the most part you
need to be doing it alone now there are
obviously caveats to this a lot of good
collaborative work is done in teams but
often the best way the team's work is by
coming together for short little bursts
communicating collaborating and then
having everyone go off to work in
solitude to really focus on their
assigned part of the project and there
are even some times when working
together with a partner for a full work
session does work well when I took
statistics back in my sophomore year I
did have a partner who had come to my
dorm every single time we had an
assignment and we would do it together
but what I've concluded about that
experience is number one I wasn't good
friends with this person at all she
would show up we would do our work and
that was basically the extent of our
relationship and secondly statistics is
a particular kind of subject where you
can kind of come to the answer very
logically math works that way but if you
are writing something or doing anything
that requires more of a creative mindset
it's better to do it alone and to
reiterate that statistics partner was
somebody I didn't really know well a lot
of times working with study partners
means
you're working with friends which means
the conversation inevitably drifts into
other things besides your assignment and
finally tip number seven give yourself
time for recovery nobody can work
intensely all the time and if you try to
you're eventually going to burn out so
take advantage of the flip side of that
productivity equation you want to have
intense focus use a little bit of time
on your studies and the time left over
you can use to relax you can use to play
video games or pursue something that's
really interesting to you to hang out
with friends all that time spent
relaxing may not seem productive in the
moment but it's gonna leave you
refreshed and able to focus with that
all-important blistering intensity the
next time that you do need to work now
in addition to all the practices that
we've gone over in this video another
essential ingredient in the formula for
intense focus is interest without some
amount of interest in your subject your
brain is going to resist all of your
attempts to focus on it and one of the
best ways to spark that interest is to
give yourself a challenge something to
actively work on that's why you should
check out brilliant especially if you're
at all interested in improving your
mastery and anything related to math
science or computer science brilliant is
a learning platform built around the
principle of active learning and
throughout the courses on calculus
machine learning logic astronomy
algorithms and many many more you'll
find yourself immediately presented with
challenges that build interest and
encourage the intense focus that's
crucial for efficient learning for
example within the first 10 minutes
there entered a probability course I
found myself having to learn how to
multiply probabilities in a normal
classroom I probably would've had to
start out by introducing myself with a
class telling everyone my favorite dog
is and then passively sitting through a
lecture for quite a while before
actively being challenged and while this
active approach to learning will help
you more quickly reach mastery of the
specific concepts you're studying it
also serves as crucial practice for
building a mental framework that will
allow you to apply your critical
reasoning skills to any problem you face
in the future it makes you a flexible
thinker so if you want to start learning
more effectively I highly recommend
giving brilliant a try you can use link
down the description below to start
learning for free and the first 83
people who sign up using that link will
also get 20% off of their subscription
only have a huge thanks to brilliant for
sponsoring this video and helping to
support this channel and as always thank
you guys so much for watching you
enjoyed this video you can hit that like
button down below and maybe share it
with a friend who would find it useful
and if you want to get notified
published new videos you could subscribe
to this channel right there you could
also get a free copy of my book on how
to earn better grades by clicking right
there and if you want to watch one more
video on this channel smash your face
into your phone screen right around here
thanks for watching and I will see you
guys in the next video