There comes a time in the life of every
student when inevitably they'll lose
some very important school file and then
they'll have to make an excuse to their
teacher. My flash drive got lost or my
dog ate my homework. Please do not
consider the fact that dogs are not
allowed in the dorms. That kind of
thing. But this is the rule and you can
be the exception to that rule. Now, when
I was in high school, I was often a
bonehead who would just put my files on
flash drives and then inevitably lose
those flash drives. But when I got to
college, I got my act together and I can
brag truthfully about this. I never once
arrived at a class and realized I didn't
have an assignment that I needed to
bring with me because of the system I
built. So, in this quick video, I want
to show you the system for organizing my
files that I built over the four years I
was in college. We'll talk about the
best ways to store your files so you
always have access to them, the actual
hierarchy of folders I built in my
computer so everything was really easy
to find, and also ways to organize your
paper files. So, first let's talk about
file storage. Now, whether you have one
computer or multiple computers, I
recommend using a cloud storage system.
And the one I've been using for multiple
multiple years is Dropbox. I absolutely
love Dropbox and their free option comes
with 2 GB of storage, which is pretty
much good for anybody who isn't going to
be doing design or a lot of photography
or video work. And they offer apps for
almost every platform out there, as well
as an app that is accessible through the
browser. So, keeping your file stored in
Dropbox means that even if you forgot to
bring your computer to class for some
reason, or hey, maybe it's dead, you can
go to a computer lab in the building,
access the file right on the browser,
and print it out. Now, in doing some
research for this video, I did some
poking into other cloud storage options.
And I want to say that Google Drive is
also a really strong competitor to
Dropbox, and it might even work better
for you. Reason being is that Google
Docs actually gives you 15 GB as opposed
to Dropboxes, too. So, it's a heck of a
lot more free storage, and it also
integrates really well with Google's
other products. So, if you already use
Gmail or Calendar a lot, or you like to
write papers collaboratively in Google
Docs when you're doing group projects,
then Drive is a perfect option.
Whichever one you choose will give you
the option to organize folders however
you like. And I'd like to submit my own
system as something that will work
really well for you. So, in my top level
Dropbox directory, I've got multiple
folders that each represent different
areas of my life. And everything related
to school goes into my college folder.
My next level folder separates
everything by year. And after that, I
have everything separated by class.
Inside of individual class folders, I'll
usually keep all the regular assignments
just sitting there, but projects get
their own special folders as well. This
well-designed tree structure ensures
that I'm always able to find the files I
need right away, rather than hunting
around a giant jumble of files on my
desktop looking for the right exact
name. Now, the one thing I'll note here,
and this applies to every organizational
system you use, is that you have to be
constantly vigilant about keeping it in
working order. It's easy to initially
set up this pristine, welloiled system,
but then when you're working on an
actual paper and maybe you need to go to
bed or you need to rush off to a class,
it's also really easy to save that
document straight to the desktop. And
over time, doing this will ensure that
you're going to have that jumbled mess
you wanted to avoid in the first place.
So, be kind to your future self and make
sure you take that extra 30 seconds to
find the correct folder for an
assignment and also give it a name that
makes sense. Speaking of naming files, I
know a lot of students will make
multiple copies of an assignment because
they want to save old versions. And a
cool thing about Dropbox and also Drive
is it has version history. This means
that you can actually log into your
Dropbox account and see previous
versions of a file that you've worked
on. If you find that you've screwed up a
file and already saved it, you can
actually roll back to a previous version
and erase those mistakes. Now, let's
talk about notes. I actually don't keep
my notes in Dropbox, and that's because
I took almost all of my notes on
Evernote. The structure of my Evernote
account is very similar to my Dropbox. I
have notebook stacks which represent
areas of my life and then inside those
stacks there are individual notebooks
for classes or different projects or
just places I want to keep notes. As an
example, here's my classes notebook
stack. I used to have two of these, one
for current classes and one for old
classes. Now all my classes are old, so
it's just one. But as you can see, all
of my classes are listed here. And in
each notebook, you'll find all the notes
I took for that class. Evernote also
allows you to put tags on your notes. So
maybe you want to tag certain notes as
lecture notes and other notes as final
exam review. This allows you to easily
filter through all the notes you have
for one class and find what you're
looking for fast. Now, Evernote also has
other features and uses that can be
really beneficial to you as a student.
And I actually wrote a blog post
featuring many of these uses, which you
can find by clicking the card right now
or looking down in the description. To
round out this video, let's talk about
paper notes. So, I was kind of a
minimalist when I was in college, and I
didn't want to have too many notebooks
in my bag. So, I actually got a
refillable notebook, which I would use
for all my subjects. I divided the
notebook with the same colored flags
that I've marked up this book with. And
when I'd run out of paper in one
section, I would just take all the notes
out of it and add new paper. The old
notes would go into subject specific
folders back in my dorm room. And I
always made sure to mark page numbers on
them so I could put them back together
easily when I was reviewing at the end
of the semester. And these folders in
turn were stored in a black file box
that I kept in my dorm room. And I
highly recommend getting one of these if
you don't have one. So that's it for
this video. Hopefully some of these tips
will help you become a more organized
student, which in turn should help you
cut down on stress when the demands of
the semester start piling on. If you
enjoyed this video or found it helpful,
then leaving a like is much appreciated,
and I will see you next week.
Hey guys, thank you so much for watching
this uh incredibly exciting video about
file organization. Yeah. Well, if you
want to get new videos every single week
about being a more effective student,
you can click that big red subscribe
button right there. I also wrote a book
on how to improve your grades, and it's
absolutely free. So, if you want to get
a copy, click the picture of the book,
and I'll send you one. You can find
notes in a summary of this video by
going to the companion blog post of the
orange logo right there. And if you
missed last week's video, we talked
about Marcus Aurelius's thoughts on
self-discipline. And a lot of people
like that one, so definitely check it
out. Lastly, if you've got questions or
just want to connect with me, I'm Tom
Frankly on Twitter, or you can leave a
comment below. Thanks for watching.