So, you failed a test or maybe this
entire semester's just been terrible and
you feel like the whole thing has been a
failure and now your life basically
boils down to nothing but this. Where do
you go from there? Well, that's what I
want to talk about today. And I feel
like this video boils down really to
just two main points. Number one,
failure is not the end of the world.
It's not nearly as bad as you think it
is, and it happens to absolutely
everyone. And number two, learning from
that failure, becoming resilient to it,
and retrying in a smarter way. These are
all essential skills to learn. And I
think failure seems so monumental and
terrible because we don't talk about it.
Even though it happens to everyone, none
of us wants to like be vulnerable enough
to put our failures out there. It's
uncomfortable. So, we tend to just sort
of project our successes and keep the
failures bottled up inside. And each of
us has to deal with them alone. So,
that's where I want to start. I want to
put a few of my own personal demons and
failures out there to let you know that
if you're currently dealing with a
failed test or something else, we're
both standing on the exact same playing
field. Off just the top of my head, I
can think of two instances where I
failed exams in college. There was a
physics exam I failed during my freshman
year. And then in my junior year, there
was a core part of my major, a computer
networking class, and I failed an exam
because I was just like not paying
attention during that semester. And
those two failures were pretty bad, but
they pale in comparison to something
that happened in high school that I have
not wanted to talk about ever since it
happened. But I'm going to put it out
there because hopefully it's useful to
you guys. So, in high school, my senior
year, I got this really cool part-time
job. And I worked a lot of part-time
jobs in high school, ever since I was
14, in fact. But this one was really
cool, which makes it all the more worse
that I only was there for 3 months. And
I was only there for 3 months because I
got fired. and not because of some like
politics or like the economy or whatever
or like Godzilla was about to like smash
my cubicle. I got fired because I was
crappy at my job and I didn't respect
the position and they fired me totally
justifiably. It was like a flat on my
face failure. And I remember walking out
of the building. I was like, "That's it.
My life is over. No one will ever hire
me again. Why would they hire me? I've
already violated somebody's trust." And
I was like, "Might as well give up now,
right?" But looking back, everything was
fine. I still went to college. I had a
lot of part-time jobs in college. I did
really well at all of them. I even went
to a full-time internship and now I'm
running my own business because I
learned from those mistakes. And with
the exams, it was the exact same thing.
I learned from my mistakes. I learned
that I wasn't paying attention. I had to
buckle down. And that's what those
failures were. There were just valleys
in this overall crazy graph trend of our
life's progress because it isn't just
this linear nice curve upward. There's
going to be peaks and valleys, successes
and failures. Hopefully, the overall
trend is upward, but it's really
volatile. So, if you find yourself in a
valley right now of failure, that's just
part of your journey. You're going to
get out of it. But how do you get out of
it? What's the best way to potentially
get out? Well, that's what the rest of
this video is about. And I really think
it boils down to six steps in a process.
And I want to lay this process out for
you. But first, I just got to warn you.
Near the end of this video, I am going
to drill into your soul. Okay? Maybe
nothing that heavy, but I am going to
take I'm going to say some words to you
that might pull you out of your warm
little comfort zone because I think you
might need to hear them. But let's lay
the foundation first with that six-step
process. The first step is to figure
out, do you need to do damage control
right away? Is there some sort of
reaction that the failure warrants right
away to make sure that like further bad
stuff doesn't happen? For instance,
maybe you just completely skipped the
test for some reason. Well, obviously
you need to contact the professor right
away to see if there's any way you can
make up the test because obviously it
wasn't your fault that ninjas attacked
you on your way to the testing center.
It just happens. Like these things
happen and hopefully your professor will
understand. But if you have if you found
out that there's basically nothing you
need to do right away, you just need to
kind of move on over time gradually,
then I think the first thing to do is to
give yourself some distance from the
problem. Like right away failures seem
monumental. They seem earthc crushing
like everything is bad and your emotions
are just blaring sirens in your brain
and you really can just only give
yourself distance. There's nothing
really good that's going to happen right
away because you need to let these
emotions subside. So sleep on it or talk
with a friend, vent a little bit or play
a stupid video game and forget the
world. And once those emotions do go
away, then that's when logic can take
over and start to do some more useful
stuff. And at that point, what you need
to do is to figure out what caused the
failure. Like when you play a video game
and you die, you do retry, but you're
also trying to figure out like why did I
die? Okay, this pit was too far to jump
over without getting a running start
first, so now I need to run. Identifying
the points of failure is critical for
retrying and succeeding. That's what
engineers do and that's what you need to
do. So figure out what was it that
caused me to fail this test. Was I
overwhelmed? Did I just take too hard of
a class? Did I need a tutor? Or was I
just completely like distracted and
unmotivated to pay attention in class?
Now once you figured out the problem,
once you figured out the most likely
cause, then the next step is to develop
a plan for retrying in a smarter way,
adapting and dealing with that point of
failure. You can't just try in the exact
same way, right? That's the definition
of insanity. So if you were like
unmotivated to study, then maybe you
need to get like a tutor or just an
accountability buddy or maybe you need
to say like, I'm not going to study in
my dorm. I'm going to commit myself to
going to the library three days a week.
I'm going to meet with my study buddy
and we're going to study for at least
three hours cumulatively over the week.
Now you've got that plan. And step five
is to retry just like you do in a video
game. And also the last step, be willing
to ask for help if you need it. I've had
some people who have asked questions on
my videos and the comments being like,
"How do I get help because I'm too
embarrassed or too scared to ask for
help in class because I don't want to
look stupid." And that couldn't be
further from the truth. Asking for help
is showing that you're smart enough not
to accept ignorance out of pride or some
fear of embarrassment. And now that
you've failed something, you know for a
fact the writing is on the wall that
you're not above needing help. So if
people are willing to provide
assistance, be humble enough to accept
it. If you're like on a sinking ship and
somebody comes by in a rowboat to save
you, jump on that rowboat. So that is
the process for dealing with failure.
And to end this video, I just want to
give you a little bit of motivation
because to be honest, a lot of people,
and this is a sad truth, but a lot of
people just kind of let life happen to
them. And a lot of people let their past
decisions, past bad decisions, and past
failures set the course for the rest of
their lives. Don't be one of those
people. Very few failures will keep you
down and prevent you from retrying and
building back up. Most failures, as long
as you're willing to work and willing to
analyze what caused a failure, most of
them are just opportunities for you to
get smarter and for you to adapt and for
you to become resilient. In a speech she
gave at Harvard University back in 2008,
JK Rowling once said that the knowledge
that you have emerged wiser and stronger
from setbacks means that you are ever
after secure in your ability to survive.
Failure is not the end. It's just an
opportunity to gain insight. So, if you
don't like where your past failures and
past decisions have gotten you, then
start looking at what caused those
failures and retry in a smarter way. Or
to reframe that statement, if you don't
like who you were yesterday, then be
willing to put some steps into action
today and tomorrow and the next day to
start changing that person. Now,
hopefully I didn't get too heavy at the
end here for you, and hopefully this
video was helpful to you in some way.
Either way, thanks so much for watching,
and as always, I'll see you next week.
[Music]