let's be honest with each other here
you're not actually supposed to be on
YouTube right now right now you probably
have some huge assignment that's staring
at you from your desk right now but the
thought of doing any work on that
assignment right now is the last thing
on your mind because you have literally
no motivation to do it and if you're
feeling that way well you're not alone I
feel that way all the time and despite
all the years I have put into
productivity research in all the videos
you see on this channel at least once a
week I run into a situation where I have
to do something and I have basically no
motivation to do it so this is a pretty
common problem and despite those
immortal words from Shia LaBeouf
constantly ringing in our heads a lot of
us continually deal with it now within
the realm of productivity there are both
long term fixes and short-term fixes and
for a problem like this a problem of
motivation long term fixes would be
things like building better
self-discipline or building strong
habits or creating a better study space
but today I want to focus on these
short-term fixes if you have something
that you need to get done today but
you're feeling completely unmotivated
what can you do well today I'm going to
go through a four step process that I go
through every single time that I'm
feeling this way and through personal
experience over several years I have
learned that doing these things really
does help even if my brain tells me that
this time I really am having an off day
this time it's not going to work when I
actually take the time and put in the
effort to put these things into practice
that they really do help and the first
one on the list is to simply go outside
and go for a walk this is probably the
simplest practice on the list but it's
also the one that my brain always tries
to convince itself that it doesn't need
to do because when I have a lot of work
to do the thought of getting up for my
desk and going outside it seems like a
huge waste of time but every single time
that I do it when I'm feeling I'm
motivated or I'm dealing with brain fog
it always helps to raise my motivation
levels and clear my head now I could
send you all sorts of scientific
evidence about why this is true for
instance dr. John Rae Dee's book spark
goes into all sorts of detail about how
exercise raises your cognitive abilities
after you do it and there are also
studies to show that vitamin D which you
get primarily through sunlight exposure
can help with symptoms of fatigue and
there's also the Japanese concept of
shinrin yoku or forest bathing which
asserts that exposure to nature
forests and trees like this
all sorts of health benefits but the
main thing I want to share here is my
personal experience with this practice
because my ability to focus is always
100% of the time improved when I choose
to go for a walk or to be more accurate
whenever I choose to go outside to do
any kind of exercise could be playing
basketball or skateboarding the reason I
chose to focus on walking here is that
it's easy you don't need any equipment
you don't need a basketball you don't
need a bike and you can even do it if
it's cold as they say in Norway there is
no such thing as bad weather only bad
clothes now let's go back to the studio
so once you've gone out and you finish
that walk and you brought your mental
energy up just a little bit the next
thing on the list to do is to decide on
one specific task to work on if you have
a to-do list with multiple items on it
put it away you need to commit to a
single task and you don't want that
to-do list to be a temptation to jump to
something else once it gets difficult
it's all about committing
imagine a hamster ball with three
different hamsters in it if all those
hamsters are trying to go their own
little separate direction then that
hamster ball is going to go nowhere but
if they all decide to go in one
direction well they're probably going to
trip all over each other because hamster
balls were not designed for multiple
hamsters but luckily your brain is not a
hamster ball and when you decide on one
specific direction to go in and you
commit to it you make progress now you
can make this commitment purely mental
but I also find that it sometimes works
to pull out a scrap of paper and write
down the tasks that you decided to work
on so that way it can be sitting next to
you on your desk and constantly
reminding you if you start to forget and
if you want an electronic solution
there's also a Chrome extension called
momentum which basically replaces your
new tab screen with a cool wallpaper and
it lets you decide on one singular focus
that you can type in and then set all
right on to step three in the process
once you've decided on that one task
you're going to work on the next step is
to clear to neutral this means to clear
up your workspace your desk and your
desktop on your computer and setting
that space back to a state where it's
prepped for that single task you decided
to work on and nothing else
anthony bourdain talks about a similar
concept in his book Kitchen Confidential
it talks about how a chef that he used
to work with went up to when it was line
cooks and ran his hand across the cooks
really dirty crumb filled cutting board
put it up to his face and said this is
what your brain looks like work clean
every chef knows the value of meson plus
did I get that right this time
yes which is a French term that
essentially means everything in its
place when your work area is organized
and set up for the task that you have
decided on you are going to work on the
task a lot more effectively again
remember that hamster ball finally to
actually get yourself into the process
of doing the task utilize what I like to
call the low effort hack this is a
useful little mental hack that I use on
pretty much a daily basis because
usually when I feel mental resistance to
a task like researching for a video or
writing a video script that mental
resistance is usually because of how
difficult it is to do a task well if I'm
writing a video script usually I feel
resistance to writing the next paragraph
because I feel like it needs to have
clever wordplay or a funny reference and
when I'm researching I know that it's
gonna be difficult to actually find the
scientific studies that will back up
what I'm trying to say but and this is
where the whole low effort thing comes
in what isn't difficult is just writing
what's on the top of my mind right now
if I can't come up with a joke or a
reference that will make the segments
I'm writing funnier that's fine I'll
just write what's in my head right now
and I'll come back and make it funnier
later and it's the exact same story when
I'm referencing research I really don't
want to go find the exact source of that
one fact that I'm trying to reference
them I won't in the script I'll put in
brackets and all caps reference that one
study and figure out where it came from
and then I'll do that later
now doing this means that you're
creating something that you're gonna
have to come back and fix later on but
that's okay remember the blank page is
the enemy it's far easier to come back
and fix an imperfect mess later on than
it is to create something perfect from
scratch on the first try that imperfect
mess gives you handholds that you can
grab on to additionally another huge
benefit of starting from a place of low
effort is that sometimes you just need a
little bit of a warm-up to get yourself
into a place where you're really
creative and in the zone back when I was
a teenager my dad had a weight training
schedule for me and my brother we had to
work out at least three times a week and
sometimes I'd come down into the gym
with him and I'd say dad today is an off
day I really just want to go light I'm
not feeling it and I will never forget
what he told me out in one of those
occasions he said that sometimes you hit
your pr's or your personal records on
off dates and I'm actually not making
this up this really did happen one of
those days I came down to the basement I
said dad it's an off day so he had me go
through a longer than normal warm-up
period and on that day I actually hit a
PR in fact I think it was actually 225
which if your weight lifter you know is
two plates on each side of the
bar and that was one of the mentally
most difficult PRS for me to hit it took
me a really long time to get so that
should serve as an illustration even if
you feel like today is an off day just
use that low effort hack and put some
time in there is a big difference
between your state of mind before you
start working and your state of mind
once you're in the flow state once
you're immersed in your project the
trick is just getting yourself there so
one of the things I've been working on
for a while now kind of behind the
scenes is a brand new design for my
website college info geek which is where
you may have seen some of the articles
that go along with the videos I make so
I should probably say we've been working
on a new design because I'm just doing
the visual design component of it all
the actual code that's gonna run the
site it's being written by my friend
Martin who's also the co-host on my
podcast and lately he's been working on
actually Martin what are you working on
do you want the one-hour version or the
five-hour version he you will not
understand either one fair enough though
to be fair to myself I did do some of
the code that is live on the site right
now and back when I was in college and
couldn't afford to have anybody on my
team I had to do all of the coding on my
website it turns out that learning to
code was actually a pretty good skill to
pick up and luckily it's not something
that's actually that difficult to learn
and if you're interested in picking it
up yourself you might want to check out
some of the basic web development
courses over on Skillshare if you're
just starting out in this there's one
called hand coding your first website by
a guy named rich Armstrong which goes
in-depth on the basics of HTML and CSS
and there's another course by the same
teacher that's all about web layout
which is also very important to learn
and even if you're interested in
something besides web development two
skill shows library probably has
something for you because they've got
over 19,000 courses and topics like
design digital animation photography
programming and all of these courses
have hands-on components and projects
that you can immediately sink your teeth
into so that you're learning actively
skill sure is also more affordable than
most other online learning platforms
with their annual subscription being
less than $10 a month for unlimited
access and what's more the first 500
people that click the link in the
description down below and sign up will
get their first two months for just 99
cents big thanks to skill share for
sponsoring this video and helping to
support this channel and as always thank
you guys so much for watching
if you found this video helpful give it
a like to support this channel and you
might also want to get subscribed so you
don't miss future videos when
come out you can also click right there
to get a free copy of my book on how to
earn better grades or right around there
to watch one more video on this channel
thanks for watching and I will see you
in the next one