Thanks to Hover for sponsoring this
video and supporting my channel. I talk
a lot about productivity apps in this
channel, but for the most part, the apps
that I cover tend to be the more
well-known ones, Notion, To-Doist. So,
today I want to flip the script a little
bit. Today, I'm going to be joined by my
friend Ali Abd Doll, who is a doctor, a
YouTuber, and a productivity expert in
his own right to talk about some of the
lesserk known productivity apps that
both of us use on a daily basis to
improve our respective workflows. Here
are six productivity apps that you
probably haven't heard of before. What's
up, Ollie?
Hey, man. I'm doing very well, thank
you. How are you?
Good. Doing well as well. So, what I
wanted to do today is give people a
glimpse into some of the more maybe
obscure productivity apps that we use,
maybe like little utilities, things that
just help us get things done a little
bit better, go that extra 10%. So, I
brought three and you brought three as
well, right?
Absolutely. The first one I want to
mention isn't really an app. It's
something that's built into every uh
Apple device. So, iOS, iPad OS, Mac OS.
Uh, and it's something that a lot of
people don't know about, and that is
keyboard replacement. So, if you go on
your system preferences on your Mac and
you hit keyboard
Mhm.
Uh, then under this text thing, what you
can actually do is create these like
little keyboard replacementy thingies
for whatever you want. So, often I'll
I'll get a question from people being
like, "Hey, how do you study for exams?"
And if I type in exclamation mark AR
across any of my devices, so iPhone,
iPad, Mac, it will replace it with how
to study for exams, evidence-based
revision tips, and a link to my YouTube
video. If I type in exclamation desk
setup across any device, it will say my
productivity desk setup 2019 or 2020 and
and a link to the video. Basically, any
important thing that I find myself
typing out more than once, I will turn
into one of these keyboard replacement
thingies and it will just be synced
across all my devices. And I think
that's completely magical and I think
more people should do this. In fact, if
I show you my iPhone screen. So on my on
my iPhone, I'm going to go into
settings. Uh, and it's got text
replacement and you'll see it's got all
of the same ones and it's synced across
my Mac and across my iPhone. So, okay.
So, the first app that I'm going to
share is not actually a a Windows
specific app. It's a Chrome extension.
Uh, so I don't know about you, but I am
absolutely terrible with tabs. I'll just
have like a million tabs open.
And then I go like to shut my computer
down at the end of the night, but I want
a lot of these tabs. Like I want to know
what they were at least. So there's a
little extension called tab copy. And
you can just click this little button
here and copy the URLs to all of your
open tabs. And you can choose to have
like expanded where it'll have the the
title and the metad description. Compact
is just the title or just the link. So
I'll copy all the tabs. And then I can
just open up Notion and I can go to my
little dashboard or my note-taking
system. I'm just going to put them in my
little daily tasks scratchpad here. But
just boom, every URL that I had open is
now here. Wow.
So I can finally close down my browser
at the end of the night but not lose
anything cuz I know it's it's been
tracked here in notion.
Have you ever needed to use this to
resurface old tabs or is it more like a
security blanket?
Absolutely. I use it all the time.
Actually, I'll show you for the the
course that I'm building. These are all
of the links that I have saved from my
browser just for like plugins for
shopping carts or Cloudflare
optimizations or all kinds of stuff.
Like, this is a project that's ongoing,
so I'll work on it a little bit every
day, but I don't want to lose this stuff
before I'm done using it. As long as I
have the URLs, I'm good to go.
All right. Next, we have an amazing Mac
app. And this is one of the most
powerful things about a Mac which is
unfortunately not quite built into the
operating system. And this is an app
called Alfred. Uh and the cool thing
thing about Alfred is you press command
and space and then it brings up this box
that essentially lets you type anything.
The Windows equivalent it is it's sort
of like hitting the Windows logo key.
And on Mac it's sort of like using
Spotlight search, but Alfred is just a
lot a lot more powerful than the default
built-in options. So there's there's
lots of things you can do with Alfred,
but uh the simple ones is you can use it
to open any kind of app. So let's say I
want to open Chrome. I would hit command
spacebar and I would just type in Cro
and I'd hit enter and Chrome will open.
My whole philosophy around this and I'm
I'm sure you feel the same way is that
when it comes to productivity like it's
you know on on a macro level it's
important to do the right things and
then do those things right. But then on
a very micro level if you can just shave
off milliseconds off any any interaction
that you have with a computer that is
really going to add up over the long
term. And so normally if I want to open
Chrome, it would take me at least 2
seconds to go all the way across my
ultrawide monitor and click on it.
Whereas with Alfred,
it's sort of done in less than half a
second.
And there's there's like a lot more you
can do with Alfred, right? Like it's not
just launching apps. You could like
actually do a Google search or open a
website pretty instantly, right?
Yeah. And that's what I that's what I
like about it compared to just usual Max
Spotlight. Max Spotlight lets you open
apps. It's reasonable. But let's say I
want to search something on Google.
Mhm. I can just type in whatever I want
and hit enter and it will just
automatically realize that I'm trying to
search Google. If I want to search
Amazon, I type in AMA tab and then I can
search Amazon for whatever. So, it's
kind of like my home base for anything I
want to do in the computer. If I want to
open a file, I press spacebar and then I
can open any kind of file. So, if I know
what like a title for a video is called,
I can just type it in and then it'll I
can open it in downloads or I can open
the file directly or whatever. The other
the the other really cool thing is that
it's got these custom workflows that you
can put into Alfred.
So the one that I use
Yeah. So the one I use is an integration
with Fantastical. Okay.
So Fantastical Calal is my calendar app
and you can just type in Cal. So meeting
tomorrow at 2:00 p.m. in Oxford. Uh and
it will natural language processing that
and automatically say see it's it's
added the location, it's added meeting,
it's added the time.
That's awesome. And so this makes it
super easy to input calendar events uh
as soon as like you know I find out
about them. The other really cool thing
about Alfred is the the clipboard
saving. I don't know if you use this.
Yes, I use the crap out of the clipboard
saver.
Yeah, it's so helpful because like how
many times have you sort of copied
something and then overwritten it by
copying something else, but this gives
you unlimited basically keyboard
history.
Yeah.
Um it's quite handy.
So the app that I want to talk about is
actually one that is not exclusive to
Windows. It is on both Mac OS and
Windows. So anybody using it or anybody
on any OS can use it. Uh, it's called
Loom. So, I take a lot of screenshots
and a lot of screencasts to essentially
document what I'm doing, but Loom lets
you quickly record your screen and then
instantly gives you a link you can copy
and paste to share with somebody. Um, so
I use the crap out of this because it
has a notion integration. So, we have a
knowledge base in our notion workspace
and anytime I want to document a process
really quickly for somebody on my team,
I can create a page for it and then I
will just do whatever I need to do uh in
a Loom recording and once I'm done, it
immediately copies your to my clipboard
and I can paste it right here into a
notion page. Damn, that's really
helpful. I should do this a lot more for
team documentation because I I don't
document anything right now and I know
it's really bad and every time I do
something I think, oh, I wish I'd
recorded a loom right now. But
yeah, yeah, it's pretty helpful.
All right, so the final app I want to
talk about is a podcast app which is
unfortunately available for iOS only.
Uh, sorry Android heathens out there.
Uh, and that is called Air. Uh, AI RR.
Now, Air is amazing because Air is a
podcast app that lets you save the best
moments from podcasts and they call them
air quotes. So, the idea is that let's
say you're listening to an episode of
the Knowledge Project where Derek Civers
uh is being interviewed. cuz obviously
I'm listening to this at 2x speed and
anytime I come across something where I
think, "Oh, this is a really interesting
uh sort of insight or an interesting
viewpoint. I can hit the air quote
button and it will save the last 30
seconds of what I just heard." And for
most of these kind of big podcasts,
they've got transcripts available for
them. So, it will automatically
transcribe and and figure out what Derek
was saying. And therefore, I've got a
written record of the bits from the
podcast that I want to save. And so,
right now, I can title it. So Derek uh
thoughts on happiness or whatever it was
that he's talking about. I hit done and
now whenever I want I can look at my air
quotes and I can see this library of
quotes that I've saved from various
different podcasts. So you can see I'm a
big fan of the Tim Ferrris show and I've
got tons and tons of quotes saved from
Naval Rabbit, another one from Esther
Prell, loads from Seth Goden, loads from
Derek Civers. The other really cool
thing about this is that this actually
integrates with another app called
Readwise. Um, which is what I use to
help resurface my highlights from Kindle
and from Insta Paper and from Twitter.
But the really cool thing is that
Readwise has an integration with Notion
where anytime I make any Kindle
highlights, so I've got 116 of those, it
will automatically import into this
really nice libraries thing in Notion
where I can see all my books.
So all of your highlights, they they go
into the correct book row.
Abs. Absolutely. So let's see. Let's
perennial celebrate by Ryan Holiday. And
here are highlights that I made like a
few days ago while I was reading the
book.
It's really awesome. And more relevant
to us, it also works for podcasts. So
here is this episode of the Tim F Show
with Seth Goden. And these are all of
the times where I pressed the air quote
button while listening to this episode.
And now if I want to revisit this stuff,
whether I'm making a video or an email
newsletter or even just to revisit stuff
that I found meaningful in the past,
I can read the transcript and it will
give me a timestamp which will take me
to the air quote where I can listen.
Okay, so for my last one, we're going to
go a little bit back to a concept you
had talked about at the beginning of
this video, which was the whole text
snippet replacement. On Windows, there
are many apps that can do this, but the
one that I use is called Auto Hotkey.
And essentially, you can write out
scripts that will let you define
keyboard shortcuts to do almost
anything. And I honestly have only just
barely scratched the surface. So, I've
got a demo script here, and all of these
are little scripts that will do specific
things. So, these are some of my
keyboard snippets here. I've uh
anonymized some of the addresses. But if
I'm filling out a form or if I'm maybe
talking to somebody in Slack, I can just
put like h a r hit space and it will
automatically expand to have that
address in there. Or if I'm going
through and like one of these is
affiliate commissions. Um I have to type
this a million times every time I'm
doing my bookkeeping in zero. So I can
just put AC1 space affiliate
commissions. And that is probably the
simplest thing you can do. Uh this one's
fun. So these is these are some
clipboard replacement scripts. So like I
said earlier with notion, if I want to
share a link to a notion page, if I
click this and I copy the link and I
want to share it in Slack, by default
it's going to be this HTTPS version. If
I click that, it opens in my browser
where I don't want it. I could edit this
to have the notion slash thing, but it's
on my clipboard. So if I just hit Ctrl
AltV which is the keyboard shortcut I
have defined here with uh these symbols.
So this means control this means alt and
then v then it's automatically that
notion version link and it will open up
in my desktop app. And then the last
thing that I've done here is I want a
way to very quickly open folders that I
use all the time. So this is like my uh
main YouTube folder. This is the Google
Drive folder with all of the thumbnails
so I can access it if I'm traveling. And
these are just opening instantly when
I'm hitting a hotkey. So what I've done
is defined a series of keyboard
shortcuts. So this is controlalttshift4
that opens a specific file path. But I
don't want to hit controlalttshift 4 cuz
it's a really weird awkward hand
position. So I've got a Corsair K95
keyboard and that comes with this
Corsair software and I have multiple
profiles on here. So this one is called
every day and I've got actions defined.
So these are just macros of me hitting
this short code or this key. So control
shift alt7 for example uh is recorded
here and then it's just bound to one of
these G keys on the side. Well thanks
for joining me Ollie. Uh if people want
to find you, where should they go?
Thank you very much for having me. Um my
YouTube channel will be linked in the
video description, I'm sure. Uh and
yeah, you can check out my stuff there.
Thanks for having me. It's a it's a real
honor. Absolutely. Now, before we wrap
this video up, I want to clue you in on
a couple more resources that you might
not know about if you tend to watch Ali
and myself here on YouTube exclusively,
which are our respective websites. Both
Ali and I have personal websites where
we create content and also let the world
know about ourselves. And I don't know
about Ali, but personally, I view my
personal website as my online home base.
My biggest audience exists here on
YouTube. Yes, but at any time YouTube
could go away or it could change in a
way that I don't like or that's
disadvantageous to me. And with my
personal website, that's not really a
threat because it's a platform that I
control 100%. I can do whatever I want
with it. And I can make it the sort of
home base for all my online operations.
And for that reason, and for other
reasons as well, I think it's a great
idea to start thinking about building a
personal website for yourself if you
haven't done so already. And of course,
the first step to getting started along
this path is to get yourself a domain
name such as mine, which is
thomasjfrank.com.
I was born a little bit too late to snag
thomasfrank.com, but I was at least able
to get the one with my middle initial.
But that's the thing about domain names.
Once somebody grabs it, if they don't
let it expire, that's kind of taken and
you can't get it. Which is why you want
to get your domain name as quickly as
possible. Even if you're not ready to
start building that website, get that
domain name locked down and go over to
Hover to do it. Hover is the best place
on the internet to get your hands on a
domain name. Not least of which because
they have an extremely streamlined and
hassle-free checkout process where you
can actually buy a domain in less than
30 seconds. I have timed myself on this
before when I bought thomas.lol and I've
also bought thomas.blog and all sorts of
other interesting ones. And that's
because hover also has over 400 domain
extensions. You got your classic.com.me
which are great for a personal website
but you've also gotlol.limmo.blog.
There's tons to choose from. And of
course, once you have your domain on
Hover, you got a ton of different
options for how to use it. You can build
a professional email address like Thomas
at collegefogeeek.com or use their
connect feature to hook it up to website
builders or even online store builders.
So, to lock down that domain name that
you want so no one else can take it and
to save 10% off your first purchase, go
over to hover.com/thomasfrank
and sign up. Big thanks as always to
Hover for sponsoring this video. And
thank you as well for watching it.
Hopefully, you found something in this
video that can be a useful resource for
you in the future. And if you did enjoy
it, hit that like button to show the
YouTube algorithm what's up and get
subscribed if you haven't done so
already. Beyond that, my new channel,
Thomas Frank Explains, has plenty of
Notion tutorials going live all the time
on that. So, check that out if you're
interested in learning how to use Notion
more effectively. Otherwise, I'll have a
couple of other videos here on the
screen right here and right here that
you can click on or smash your face into
your phone screen for extra style points
to watch. Beyond that, maybe consider
following me on Instagram and Twitter at
Tom Frankley.