Hey, what's up guys? Today we are going
to tackle one of the most highly
requested topics on this channel, which
is how to become a better public
speaker. Now, this is actually perfect
timing for this topic because last month
I went down to South Carolina to give a
talk at a conference called FinCon where
I talked about building a YouTube
channel, something I'm pretty passionate
about. And actually this month I'll be
going to Vermont in a couple weeks to
give my first paid speaking engagement.
So speaking is becoming a larger part of
my life. And while I'm not a
professional speaker, I do have a lot of
experience speaking in public. And I've
gained a lot of insights and skills over
the years through practice. And I want
to help impart some of the knowledge
I've been able to gain to you so you can
become a better public speaker
technically and also start to calm some
of the nerves and anxiety that you might
get when you have to get on stage in
front of a bunch of people. So to that
end, I've got nine specific public
speaking tips for you this week that can
help you become a better speaker. And
the first one is to pay very very close
attention to your rate of speech when
you're on stage. Most inexperienced
speakers tend to speak a lot more
quickly than they think they're
speaking. And it's because when you're
on stage, you have all this anxiety and
you have all the material up in your
head and you're just trying to get
through it as quickly as possible
because the number one thing you want to
do is get off stage to where nobody's
judging you anymore, right? But the
problem is this isn't YouTube. The
people sitting in the audience aren't
looking at a bunch of other tabs and
they're not liable to click away after
two minutes. They've sat there and
they've dedicated some time to listening
to what you have to say. So, if you can
slow down and give them some breathing
room, then they're going to be able to
contemplate what you've said and more
easily follow along with what you're
talking about. Also, your rate of speech
isn't the only thing you can control to
make your speech better. You can also
employ strategic pauses to highlight
certain points. Now, there's a lot of
speeches that I've watched to study to
become a better speaker myself, but
there's actually a fake one that I
really, really like and want to use as
an example here, and it's this 2023 TED
talk that the producers of the movie
Prometheus put out as an advertisement
for the movie. And in this TED talk, Guy
Pierce's character is talking about
cybernetic individuals and basically his
ambitions to take over the world. But
when I watched this, I thought it was a
fantastic piece to study for public
speaking because he employs these pauses
so dramatically and so effectively. So
check that video out after you watch
this one and start to learn from it.
Now, another thing Guy Pierce does
amazingly in that video is my second
tip, which is to pay attention to your
body language. And this is important for
two specific reasons. Number one, your
body language forms a large part of the
nonverbal communication that complements
the verbal communication of your words.
The way you hold yourself, the way
you're poised, your posture, the way you
move your hands and gesture to highlight
certain points, these all go handinhand
with the words you're speaking and can
help to compliment and drive home those
points. But the other reason is that the
unconscious body language that a lot of
inexperienced speakers have is something
that can harm you. We have a lot of
nervous ticks. Uh, for example, when I
was an inexperienced speaker just
starting out, a lot of things that I
would do, uh, I would put my hands in my
pockets, and I guess the camera's fixed
right there, but I can try to show you,
right? I put my hands in and out of my
pockets over and over again while I was
speaking. And I would also pace around
the stage really distractedly, kind of
moving, and I wasn't really consciously
pacing and using that to effect. I was
just doing it unconsciously. So these
are things that you can control to both
not distract your audience but also to
help bolster your points. Now my third
tip is to consciously try to improve
your ability to make eye contact with
your entire audience. Now one thing
rookie speakers do a lot of times is
they'll fixate on one section of the
audience and they'll stay there during
their entire speech because they're
nervous. But the problem is there are
people over here and over here and your
entire audience are the people you're
addressing. So, you want to make sure
you're trying to make eye contact with
each and every single person during your
speech. Now, I know it can be difficult
to make eye contact when you're already
nervous about being on stage. So, you
can employ a classic speaker trick,
which is to simply look over the heads
of the people in the back row who are
far enough away that they probably won't
be able to tell that you're not looking
them directly in the eye. But, I do want
to challenge you. The next time you have
to make a speech, if you're feeling
nervous and you find it difficult to
make eye contact and you want to employ
this trick, I do challenge you to at
least try to make eye contact with a
couple of people throughout your talk
because this is something that gets
easier to do over time and it will make
you a more engaging, effective, and more
human speaker. Now, speaking of
practicing that eye contact, the fourth
tip is to in general practice, practice,
practice, practice. And when you think
you have practiced all you could
potentially ever practice, do it again.
The idea here is not to practice your
speech until you get it right, but to
practice your speech until you can't get
it wrong. And this is because mastery
helps to get you through any anxiety
you're feeling. As we talked about in my
test anxiety video, anxiety can actually
block your brain from making
connections. So, the more of a concrete
grasp you have on your material, the
more likely you're going to be able to
get past those anxiety blockers, get the
thoughts out of your brain through your
lips and into the ears of the eager
audience. Also, mastery is important
because when you're getting something
right in your practice situation, it
doesn't necessarily mean you're going to
be able to get it right in the more
stressful situation where you're
addressing real living, breathing,
farting human beings, right? So, make
sure you practice until you know your
material cold. Now, on that note, you
might be thinking, "Well, my speech
teacher told me not to memorize my
speech." And in general, I do agree with
that piece of advice, but I want to
drill into it and give a little bit more
of a specific opinion on it. So, in my
mind, you should not write your speech
out like an essay and try to memorize it
word for word. If you do that, you're
going to sound unnatural. You're going
to sound robotic. You're going to sound
well like you're reading. But I do think
you should write your speech out in the
form of bullet points. Have the main
points listed out. Have any details and
facts and and statistics and figures you
want to site written out and memorize
those. So when you get on stage, you
don't have anything in your hands except
maybe a presentation remote or prop and
you can you can recite the entire speech
from memory because you know your points
cold. You know exactly what it is that
you need to communicate to your
audience. Now, another final note on
practice is that practice works for
individual speeches, but it's also
something that's going to make you a
better speaker over time. So, if you
feel like right now your public speaking
skills aren't at the level you want them
to be, the best way to get better is to
simply speak again and again and again,
there's an organization called Toast
Masters where you can get with other
budding speakers and people who want to
improve their skills and actually get up
and give speeches in a non-threatening
environment. You can take a speech class
at your school, which I definitely
recommend you should do. And you can
also do things that aren't really public
speaking, but just things that give you
performance anxiety. If I'm being
honest, the thing that has helped me
become a better public speaker the most
is running my podcast and my YouTube
channel, because each and every week I
have to create something where I'm
speaking to an audience. Yes, my actual
public speaking experiences have
contributed to my skills, but I've done
way more videos and way more podcasts,
and those have helped me as well. So, if
there's something that gives you
performance anxiety, whether it be
dancing in public or doing karaoke with
your friends or something, anything that
gives you a little bit of anxiety at
upfront, but then afterwards you realize
that the world didn't end even though
you did it. That's going to help build
your confidence and decrease the amount
of care you have for what people think.
And those improvements will all feed
back into your speaking ability. Now, my
fifth tip is also related to practice,
but it's a little bit of a technical
improvement you can make to your
practice, and it's to do exactly what
I'm doing right now. When you practice,
take a video camera with you and film
yourself. This is what I would do every
single time I had a speech in college. I
would go find an empty classroom. And
with my first few runs, I wouldn't
videotape it because I was just trying
to get the material down in my head, so
I memorized it all. But once I had the
material down, then I would film myself
doing each and every take. And
afterwards, I would watch the take,
review each aspect of my performance,
and pick out the things that could be
improved. This is a huge upgrade over
just practicing for an empty room
because you're not always aware of the
things you're doing. Maybe you have a
nervous tick, maybe you're looking back
at the slides too often, or maybe you're
pacing too much. But the tape doesn't
lie. So, if you can watch that tape, see
your mistakes, you can know what to
correct, and you're going to be able to
practice more effectively and maybe have
to practice even less than you would
originally need to. So, tip number six
is to know who your audience is. And by
that, I mean realize the people in your
audience will most likely fall into one
of two categories. Number one, over here
you have the people who are rooting for
you. They want to see you succeed.
They're invested in your topic, and
these are your champions, like your
fans, right? And over here you have the
evil people who are going to laugh at
you and throw tomatoes at you and curse
your family for all eternity, right? Or
not. Over here, actually, you have
people who are bored. And that's not
because of you. It's because their minds
are elsewhere. They don't want to be
there. They'd rather be off doing
something else. And whatever you do, if
you perform badly, if you perform really
good, or if you're more in the middle
and just doing a mediocre job, it's
likely that that's not going to have
much of an effect on them at all. Now,
you do want to get the most number of
people possible into that that that
former category of the people who are
really invested in your topic. And
that's what the other tips in this video
can help you do. But I want you to
realize that the people in that latter
category, the people who just don't
care, they don't matter. So, don't worry
about what they're going to think when
you're creating your speech or when
you're up on stage delivering it because
that anxiety isn't worth it. If you get
feedback later on after the speech that
you can use to constructively improve,
that's good. But don't let it worry you
in the moment. Moving right along, my
seventh tip is to focus more on the
topic and less on the aspects of your
performance when you're delivering your
speech and also when you're preparing. I
found through experience that when I'm
really invested in what I'm talking
about and more specifically when I'm
invested in the transformation I want it
to have on the audience, I don't care so
much about the technical aspects of my
speech. I don't care about my body
language. I don't care about my eye
contact. I'm not even thinking about it
because it's become almost as if I was
explaining something I cared about to a
dear friend and I want them to learn
what it is that I know. So the the focus
comes off the nervousness of standing on
stage and addressing a bunch of people
and it's placed on this is what I know
and this is what I really want you to
learn. I'm really excited about it and I
hope that what I say can teach you or
persuade you to to take some action. Tip
number eight, don't have a stupid
haircut. And what I mean by that is
think about your appearance, dress well
and try to make a great first impression
when you step on stage. This is
important because of the halo effect,
which is also known as exaggerated
emotional coherence. And it's basically
a term to explain the fact that humans
make split-second first impressions of
people right when they meet them. So the
problem with this is that well maybe
it's not a problem, maybe it's just a
fact of life. What happens is people use
those first impressions to essentially
fill in what they don't know about the
person and also make judgments about
what comes next. So, if you get on stage
and you're dressed well, you hold
yourself well, and people are impressed
with you, then they're more likely to
forgive any mistakes you make, and
they're also more likely to be receptive
to whatever it is you're saying. But if
you don't look good, then it's going to
be a lot harder for you to convince
people of what you're talking about, and
those mistakes will be all the more
glaring. So, first impressions matter.
And my ninth and final tip is take a
breath. Don't think you need to be
perfect.
Focusing on perfection is the number one
way to trip yourself up, to give
yourself massive amounts of anxiety, and
to fail. Don't worry about being
perfect. Just get on stage and deliver
the best speech that you can give.
There's a book I read in college called
Confessions of a Public Speaker by a guy
named Scott Berkin, and I highly
recommend it if you want to get better
at speaking. It's on my essential books
list, but there's a passage in here that
really resonated with me when I read it.
And he says, "I don't want to be
perfect. I want to be useful. I want to
be good and I want to sound like myself.
Nobody gives a perfect speech. Even if
you think somebody gave a perfect
speech, that person can point out all
the errors and all the things they wish
they would have done better. So get on
stage, focus on doing good, focus on
improving over your previous performance
and then just focus on that topic. Like
I said, try to enact a transformation in
your audience and you're not going to
care so much about your nerves and your
performance. So those are the nine tips
I wrote down for this video. But I do
have a little bonus tip of sorts for
you, and it's to study people who are
great public speakers. I have a playlist
of videos here on YouTube that I've been
building for a few years, and whenever I
need to make a speech of my own, I'll go
study some of those speeches and try to
pinpoint exactly what they're doing that
I'd like to improve on with my own
skills. So, in the companion blog post
for this video, I've linked to that
playlist. And as a bonus, I've also
linked to some of my earlier speaking
videos. And just to forewarn you, one of
the earlier ones is really, really bad.
So, laugh at me all you want. I don't
care because I have improved. And I just
kind of want to show you guys that
practice does make better, not perfect.
So, that's it for this video. Hopefully,
it helped you out. And if it did, I just
want to let you know that next week
we're going to follow up this topic with
an additional video on how to craft
great presentations. So, we'll talk
about making great slides and using
story and narrative to keep your
audience engaged. So, if you haven't
subscribed to this channel, you can
click the subscribe button to get
notified about that video and others in
the future. And if you like this video,
click that like button to support this
channel. And other than that, I will see
you guys next week.
Hey guys, thanks so much for watching
this video. If you want to get new
videos on being a more effective student
every single week, click that big red
subscribe button right there. I also
wrote a book on how to earn better
grades. So, if you want to get a free
copy of that, click a picture of the
book. And you can find those speeches in
my playlist along with notes and a
summary of this video in the companion
blog post, which you can find by
clicking the orange button right there.
Last week's video was over some of the
struggles I'm dealing with in my work
life and what I'm doing about it. So,
check it out. Also, you can see a pretty
cool skateboarding skill in that video,
which I enjoyed filming. And if you want
to connect, I'm on Twitter, Tom
Frankley. That's also my Instagram. And
otherwise, you can leave a comment
below.