in our wide world there exists a variety
of objects that generally should not be
dropped bowling balls containers of pure
sodium that kind of thing however by
contrast there are also several things
that should be dropped such as fire ants
in fact that's probably the most
important thing you should drop also the
subject when your uncle Gary brings up
politics at Thanksgiving dinner and also
classes in last week's video we looked
at some research which showed that
academic overload is the most common
cause for long-term student stress and
burnout and that's why in this one I
want argue that it's okay to drop
classes when you need to now many
students view dropping a class as tan
amount to actually failing that class
flat out and I understand their
reasoning we have ideals that tell us to
stick with our commitments to follow
through those that persevere through
adversity will succeed while those who
don't are doomed to a life of regret and
a distinct lack of sports car purchases
but let's dispense with the inspiring
platitudes here yes perseverance is a
virtue worth cultivating and yes in
general you should approach each of the
things you commit to with the intention
of seeing them through but there's an
element of tactical decision- making to
be injected here especially with respect
to your class schedule and the reason
for that is that many ambitious students
tend to overcommit when they're signing
up for classes I've been in the same
exact position that you probably found
yourself in it's time to sign up for
classes and you're thinking about the
new semester and in addition to that
you're thinking about new semesters in
general which brings about associations
of new beginnings and full stocks of
willpower as a result you tend to
overcommit when you're signing up so say
you've Fallen victim to this line of
thinking and now you realize that the
workload you've signed yourself up up
for is too much what's the solution well
simple drop a class if you're diligent
about gauging your classes early on it's
likely that dropping a class will have
no negative effect on you my university
for example let people drop unlimited
classes with no marks on their
transcripts up to 5 days after the
semester started even after that you
could drop a limited amount of courses
up to halfway through the semester
though if you're going to do this you
should probably know the exact limit
that your university has I dropped
courses several times as a student for a
variety of reasons a couple of elective
classes I took ended up having way
higher workloads than I anticipated so I
dropped those for another class I
eventually realized I was only part of
the program that required it because I
wanted to pad my resume out I didn't
actually really care about the program
and it wasn't going to help me achieve
my goals so I eventually just dropped
the class actually dropped out of the
program and used the time it freed up to
do things I actually cared about there
are other valid reasons for dropping
classes as well such as a professor
whose teaching Style just doesn't work
for you you can mitigate some of these
risks before the semester starts by
using things like rate my professors and
reading the syi to get a feel for the
workload but you won't know for sure how
a class goes until you're sitting in it
so here is express permission drop
classes when you need to find out what
your University's drop policy is and
then use it to your advantage to create
a schedule that you control rather than
one that takes over your life this gives
you time to fill your schedule with
other useful Pursuits like part-time
jobs extracurriculars events and much
needed relaxation time in the case of a
bad Professor it also gives you the
chance to look for a different section
of the same class that might have a
better Professor now one caveat here
though when you drop a class make sure
you open open your graduation plan and
update the change if you don't have a
graduation plan that lays out the
courses you plan to take up until
graduation I highly recommend creating
one if you want you can get a copy of
the spreadsheet that I used for my own
graduation plan and I've included it as
a free download along with my free book
that you can get by clicking on the card
or the link in the description now I
realized that this might not be a viable
strategy for every single student out
there maybe you're in a program or a
college that requires you to take a
strict set of classes every single
semester and you can't drop any of them
or maybe you need to take college at an
accelerated Pace in order to be able to
afford it likewise it's a strategy that
might not solve all of your time
management problems especially if you're
a student who has to spend a lot of
hours at a part-time job in addition to
your studies and classes still it's
something that deserves consideration
and I think the biggest takeaway here is
that dropping a class should not be seen
as a failure it should be seen as a
tactical decision now I'm not the only
person who will Advocate this strategy
my friend Cal Newport who's a computer
science professor and the author of
several books included this advice near
the start of his book how to win at
College which I actually used as a high
school student in preparation from my
own college experience as he interviewed
top students from all around the country
for his book he realized that one of the
main strategies they used to stay on top
of their classes was creating a schedule
that they felt in control of careful
course selection is one of the best
tools for retaining that control and
dropping classes is a part of that
course selection process that you should
be taking advantage
of hey guys thanks so much for watching
my video on why you should drop classes
if you want to get new videos every
single week on being a more effective
student you can click that big red
subscribe button right there you can
also get a free copy of my book on
earning better grades by clicking the
book's picture and that also comes with
a copy of my graduation planning
spreadsheet like I mentioned earlier so
if you want to get that click the
picture and I will send you both if you
want to see the companion blog post for
this episode or read Cal's thoughts on
this exact same topic then you click the
orange logo to head her to my website if
you missed last week's video we talked
about how to avoid burnout as a student
or deal with it if you're already
feeling it and also if you'd like to
connect with me ask questions or give
feedback you can follow me on Twitter
@tomfrankly or leave a comment below
thanks for watching he