hey what is going on guys so we are
right at the tail end of December right
now and what I wanted to do for the last
video of 2017 on my channel is give you
guys 10 ideas for starting out 2018 more
productively and you know what I don't
think we really need a whole lot more
preamble than that so let's get started
tip number one if you have not done this
already try using a habit tracking app
in 2018 there are a ton of these out
there my personal favorite is called
hebediah because it basically turns
habit tracking into an RPG like video
game where you get stat boosts and
weapons and gear and go on quests you
can even partner up with people who'll
keep you accountable but there are also
a bunch of decidedly less nerdy options
out there including momentum and today
which are both on iOS and loop which is
an Android exclusive I find that using a
habit tracker is really useful for me
because the act of marking down when I
actually do a habit creates a streak and
when I look back on that streak I don't
want to break it as Peter Drucker once
may have said what gets measured gets
managed tip number two and this one is
really really simple try experimenting
with pre-planned blocks of uninterrupted
single focus time on your calendar
we've talked a lot on this channel about
the power of focusing on one task for a
long uninterrupted period of time but a
lot of times it's really easy to
convince yourself that more urgent but
easier tasks or less important tasks
should be done right now so if you start
your week or at least your day with a
plan that I'm gonna say do my homework
from 2:00 to 6:00 p.m. and do nothing
else then you're more likely to do it
and you're more likely to focus only on
that task which is difficult alright tip
number three is to start an
accomplishment journal this is exactly
what it sounds like you're keeping a
simple record of everything that you've
done either on a daily basis or maybe on
a weekly or longer basis depending on
how much effort you want to put into it
but I find this practice to be really
useful because as you get older and as
you get into more of a schedule whether
it be with school or work the days can
start to blend together everything
becomes a routine and when this starts
to happen you can start to feel like you
haven't really accomplished anything in
a while because your brain is sort of
filed it away and that could D motivate
you but if you have an accomplishment
journal look back on you can see that
yes you actually have accomplished a
good deal now my impossible list that's
over on my website college info geek is
a form of an accomplishment journal I
basically mark off any
time I achieve something really big that
I set out to do but my suggestion here
is actually you try doing an
accomplishment journal on a daily basis
essentially as you finish tasks during
the day write them down in a note on
Evernote or your note-taking app of
choice or on just a scrap of paper and
then at the end of the day or possibly
at the end of the week review them and
see what you did and this can actually
have benefits beyond just looking at the
checked off items on your to-do list
because as you probably know pretty well
a lot of times tasks come up in the
middle of day and interrupt you and
things that you didn't anticipate just
happen so by keeping a record of all
these things you're gonna have a more
accurate picture of what you were
actually able to accomplish and when
you're going through your review
sessions that more accurate picture is
gonna enable you to make better and more
intelligent changes to the way that you
work ok so you probably saw this fourth
tip coming but in 2018 you should make a
lot more time for sitting on the couch
eating Doritos drinking Mountain Dew and
playing Halo just kidding you should
make a lot more time for exercise and
yes this is a pretty cliche tip but a
lot of people don't prioritize exercise
especially when they're ambitious their
work takes up all of their hours and
they just don't make it a priority
now it's also true that when a New Year
rolls around a lot of people get into
their heads that they are finally going
to exercise consistently this year and
maybe you're thinking that my one
recommendation here echoes what I talked
about last week
start small restrict your time scale and
don't bite off more than you can chew
because when you start the new year you
have a lot of motivation and you might
not have a whole lot on your plate so
it's really easy to stick with a goal
but later on down the line when stuff
starts to get into your way your
schedule starts to get a bit more busy
that's when your self-discipline is
truly tested so if you set a goal that
stretches your capabilities and
challenges you a bit but it's still
doable within your schedule even at its
most challenging points you're going to
stick with it one additional thing that
I'll mention here is that if you want to
exercise more regularly it can be very
helpful to sign up for a class at your
school or your rec center and this could
be a class that teaches you a new sport
you haven't tried before which can be
really fun and which I did with ice
skating or it can just be a workout
class in either case signing up for a
class gives you one a community of
people who are doing the same thing as
you which is a lot of fun but to an
obligation that doesn't exist just in
your head you're not relying only on
your self-discipline you now have other
people who are expecting you to be there
tip number five is something that you
can take advantage of while you're on
winter break or you're not otherwise
were loaded with tons of classes and
homework take some time to redesign your
living space or room to take advantage
of the twenty second rule if you haven't
seen it already I did an entire video a
while back on the twenty second rule and
I'll have that linked in the description
down below but essentially the twenty
second rule is all about increasing the
difficulty and the time that it takes to
get into the things that you don't want
to do so often the bad habits and
reducing the time and the friction that
it takes to do the things that you want
to do more often so if right now you
play way too many video games maybe put
your game controllers in a drawer
somewhere or maybe even take the cord
out of your PlayStation and put it in a
closet that way it's kind of a pain in
the butt to set it up and on the other
hand if you want to read more often or
maybe practice an instrument buy an
instrument and put your guitar right
where you can pick it up and play it
within five seconds or put your book
right on the table so you can walk in
from class grab it and start reading for
a bit anything you can do to reduce the
friction between you and a good habit is
gonna reduce the willpower required to
remain consistent in doing it and the
same is true of avoiding bad habits tip
number six is to start looking for
regular parts of your work process that
you could either automate or make more
efficient for example I recently set
both of my credit cards to auto pay so
every month I no longer have to log in
and pay them manually and another thing
that I've been doing on a regular basis
is that when I start noticing that I
have to go to a folder on my computer
really really often I will pin it to my
quick access toolbar so that way I can
easily click it instead of having to
navigate through the entire tree not one
word of warning here not everything that
you do is a candidate for automation or
even more efficiency and actually is a
really good comic over on xkcd called is
it worth the time that essentially
breaks down the threshold at which you
should actually start thinking about
spending time automating something or
rather than just doing it though I'm
gonna be honest sometimes I just like to
automate things for fun and if you find
that fun then do that tip number eight
is to go and disable all the
notifications and badges on your phone
or at least most of them in the past I'd
always unconsciously let apps have
notifications turned on they'd have
badges turned on and eventually my home
screen would turn into this mess of
badges and little red numbers up in the
corners and distractions and I really
don't want to be giving that much
attention to my phone it should be
working for me not sucking up all of my
time so at one point during this year I
went into my phone settings and I
disabled basically every notification
every little sound and every little
badge in the homescreen that I could
other than the ones that were completely
essential and speaking of things that
are essential or rather
nonessential tip number nine is to take
the apps off of your phone you don't
need or otherwise block access to them
for example my friend Martin actually
went into his ad blocker settings on his
iPhone and disabled basically every
single site in the world except for
language translation sites and doing
this eventually changed his brains
automatic response whenever he got the
urge to look something up rather than
getting distracted on safari and
probably click it a bunch of links he
never meant to click in the first place
he just made a voice reminder of it and
then later on when he was at his
computer if it was still important
enough and it often wasn't he could look
it up for a less drastic example I've
often had email apps taken off my phone
I've often had social media apps taken
off my phone in fact there are certain
apps that I only have on my phone when
I'm traveling essentially I don't want
to have access to those apps on my phone
because access to them while I'm trying
to work represents a mental burden tip
number 9 again because I realize
accidentally skipped eight is to
identify the time at which you regularly
consume media online and replace it with
reading I think it's pretty safe to say
that most you are like me and you have
certain times the day where you just
automatically go to Reddit you go to
Facebook you go to Twitter and these
times are probably not all that valuable
valuable and you also probably don't
read as much as you'd like to
so by consciously identifying these
times and then maybe scheduling some
reading time during the exact same times
you'll start to avoid this unconscious
social media consumption and finally tip
number 10 when you're setting your goals
for 2018 or whenever you set goals make
sure that you prioritize them and
understand which of those goals is the
most important one doing this is
absolutely crucial if you want to remain
consistent on those most important goals
because inevitably you're gonna run into
absolutely chaotic days where you just
don't have time to do all of them and
when that happens or when you're feeling
too motivated and you just don't want to
do anything you can think back to what
you've prioritized and you can tell
yourself I'm going to do that no matter
what and these things that are less
important I can let fall to the wayside
that way well you may derail on certain
things and you can always get back on
those things later you're always gonna
remain consistent on what's most
important now one additional thing you
should do this year while your
motivation is high is establish an
online presence for yourself
and whether you're looking for an
internship or maybe a full-time job or
applying for a scholarship or just
looking for a place to build a portfolio
for your art the first step to
establishing that online presence is
eating cheese and the second step is
getting yourself a professional domain
name you
mine over at Thomas J Frank calm which I
got in college which actually helped me
to land an internship and as I
progressed in my career I've redesigned
the website a few times to match my
progression now if you're ready to lock
down your own domain name the best place
on the internet to get it is hovered
hover has over 400 domain extensions for
you to choose from ranging from the
classics like calm and org to more
interesting ones like limo and ninja and
unlike a lot of other registrar's out
there they don't have any annoying
upsells or pop-ups during the sales
process it's super easy and you can get
the entire thing done in under a minute
once you have your domain you can also
use hover to easily connect it to the
web service of your choice including
medium and Squarespace using their
connect feature and they also have a
tool for setting up a professional email
address so if you wanted to say Thomas
at Thomas J Frank calm well you can't
have that one but you could have one
linked to your domain so if you're ready
to start establishing the online
presence give hover try and get 10% off
to your first purchase by going to hover
calm slash Thomas Frank which you'll
find the description down below I want
to give a huge thanks to hover for
sponsoring this episode and supporting
this channel and as always guys thank
you for supporting this channel by
watching if you enjoyed this video you
can hit that like button and you can
also subscribe right there if you want
to get notifications when I publish new
videos you can also get a free copy of
my book on how to earn better grades
right there and check out our latest
podcast episode where we recap the year
right over there lastly you can watch
one more video on this channel by
smashing your face into your phone right
around this area of the screen and other
than that I will see you in the next
video