hey what is going on guys so today I
want to make a really quick video to
share an app that I just found actually
just a couple of hours ago that's going
to be really really helpful for you the
next time you need to write a paper
because I don't know about you but for
me when it comes to the tasks that I
procrastinate on the most writing is way
at the top of the list every time I need
to write which is basically every single
week for writing scripts for this
channel I will open my editor I'll start
writing and then I will almost
immediately get distracted I'll go check
Facebook or Twitter my email and for me
writing is often a huge Battle of trying
to fight the urge to go do anything else
because writing is painful until I can
get into that blow state but it takes me
a while so wouldn't it be great if you
had an app that just didn't let you get
distracted and go to all those
distracting websites oh there actually
is I just found it and it's called cold
turkey Rider and the great thing about
this app is it's actually free and it's
for both Windows and Mac OS and what you
do is you basically open it you tell it
how many words you want to write or for
how many minutes you want to write and
then you hit go and once you do that you
can't do anything else on your computer
until you hit the goal I mean nothing
you can't alt tab you can't go to
another space you can't open another app
you can't do anything you can't even get
out you would have to shut your computer
off to get out of the app so check it
out uh there is a pro Edition that you
can buy for I think $10 which gets you
like a dark mode theme and gets you some
other Advanced features but for the
basic functionality of just keeping you
from getting distracted and going over
Facebook it works pretty well now some
of you clever people might tell me that
there is already an app that does this
and it's called shutting your computer
off and writing in a notebook on paper
with a pencil and yes you can do that it
works pretty well people have been doing
it for Millennia but personally I find
that I write better when I'm typing
because I can type a heck of a lot
faster than I write so I love having an
option for doing it on a computer
without having to contend with lots of
distractions and that's what cold turkey
riter does for me so that's all I've got
for this video just wanted to share this
app with you because I'm finding it
really really helpful for my own work
and I think you will as well and I also
did another video with 15 additional
writing apps so you might find that
useful and if you missed it you can
check it out right there you should also
subscribe to this channel if you want to
get more content like this because
spoilers later on this week I'll be
doing a video about how to decrease
internet distractions as a whole so you
can click right there to subscribe
anyway if you're using this video to
procrastinate on a writing assignment
stop it and I will see you in the next
video