hey what's going on guys so today we're
gonna be covering six important
strategies for improving your level of
self-discipline now before we get into
the Nitty Gritty I do want to take a
brief moment to define what exactly
self-discipline is because when I asked
you guys to tell me about your problems
with discipline on Twitter the other day
I got a lot of answers ranging from
motivation to distractions to cell phone
addiction all kinds of things in between
and while all these answers are
legitimate problems I don't think that
all of them fit neatly into the category
of self-discipline where they do fit is
in the broader category of behavior
change and that is the big goal for most
of us we want to change your behaviors
to be more aligned with our goals and
our long-term desires and when it comes
to that general mission to change your
behaviors I see four main areas that we
need to focus on one of which is the
cultivation of self-discipline which
we're going to tackle in this video but
also the building of new habits which
can make that behavior automatic the
customization of our environment which
can remove roadblocks and help us resist
temptations by basically removing them
and of course the consumption of as much
bran dough as possible since it is the
thirst mutilator but as you may have
guessed this video is only about that
first area self-discipline and where I
want to start is by asking and answering
two questions number one what exactly is
self-discipline and number two how does
it differ from motivation because I
think a lot of people get these two
terms confused to start I want to share
a quote from the writer Samuel Thomas
Davies because it actually answers both
those questions in a pretty tidy way
self-discipline is about leaning into
resistance taking action in spite of how
you feel living life by design not by
default but most importantly its acting
in accordance with your thoughts not
your feelings
put another way motivation is your
overall level of desire to do something
whereas discipline is your ability to do
it regardless of how you feel and for
any of you who've ever woken up thinking
I don't feel like it which is all of you
myself included you can see now how
important self-discipline is it's
building that baseline that allows you
to act in accordance with your long-term
goals no matter how motivated you feel
so with that being said let's cover six
important strategies for building
yourself discipline we're gonna start
with one that doesn't seem very tangible
or actionable at first but stick with me
here because this is a mindset shift
that I found more helpful than any other
self-improvement technique I've tried in
recent memory to put it simply when
you're trying to change your behavior
forget about the goal you're trying to
achieve the external outcome and instead
focus on the change in identity you want
to happen this is a concept that I first
read about in James Clare's book atomic
habits which I highly recommend by the
way and there's this passage near the
beginning of the book that really
encapsulates it well so I'm just gonna
read it to you here imagine two people
resisting a cigarette when offered a
smoke the first person says no thanks
I'm trying to quit it sounds like a
reasonable response but this person
still believes they are a smoker who is
trying to be something else they are
hoping that their behavior will change
while carrying around the same beliefs
the second person declines by saying no
thanks I'm not a smoker it's a small
difference but the statement signals a
shift in identity smoking was a part of
their former life not their current one
they no longer identify as someone who
smokes so the general idea here is that
once you've embraced a change in your
identity you're gonna find yourself
acting in alignment with that change and
if you're wondering why exactly this
happens the third chapter of Roberts
Hilding these book influence the
psychology of persuasion has a great
explanation for it
essentially humans feel this natural
compulsion to act consistently with
their past decisions as he writes in the
book once we have made a choice or
taking a stand we will encounter
personal and interpersonal pressures to
behave consistently with that commitment
those pressures will cause us to respond
in ways that justify our earlier
decision and shifting my mindset in this
way has been incredibly helpful in the
past couple of months
the first way that I implemented it was
by starting to think of myself as an
athlete now I've always been a pretty
active person and I've had a laundry
list of athletic goals on my website for
quite a long time now but I never really
took the leap and started thinking of
myself as an athlete and there was some
impostor syndrome reasons for this but
after reading that passage in the book I
decided to take the leap and start
thinking myself as an athlete not just
as somebody who does active things
and that shift in mindset has done
wonders for my levels of self-discipline
in many different areas from going to
the gym more consistently to training
harver while I'm there too even
improving my diet which has been a lot
better than it used to be over the past
couple
months so seriously if you take nothing
else from this video I'm putting this
first for a reason start thinking about
behavior change in terms of the identity
that you want to embody rather than the
goals that you want to achieve alright
strategy number two is to frequently
remind yourself of why you're being
disciplined in the first place at the
end of the day we have to have a strong
why for our actions if we want to do
them consistently and every time I think
about this concept I'm reminded of a
story about the actor Jim Carrey and
that goes like this after he had arrived
in Hollywood and he was still kind of an
impoverished actor one day he took out a
napkin and he drew himself a check made
out to himself for ten million dollars
and post-dated for ten years in the
future and then you put that check in
his wallet so that every time he'd bring
out his wallet he could see it and
remind himself of why he was working so
hard what he was working towards and
this is something that you might find
very helpful to do as well try writing
down your goal or the identity you want
to assume and put it maybe on a sticky
note next to your desk or by your
computer so you can see it every single
day and know that this is why I'm
building my self-discipline this is the
reason for all the work I'm putting in
[Music]
all right strategy number three is to
find ways to embrace discomfort and
embrace the resistance you feel towards
doing something that takes hard work or
that's unpleasant just like going to an
actual gym and lifting weights makes you
better at lifting weights in the future
and able to lift more weight the next
time you go in every time you embrace
discomfort you are essentially doing a
rep of the exercise that is self
discipline because it is a skill that
can be learned it is a muscle that can
be built over time this is why I'm such
a proponent of taking cold showers
because a cold shower is something that
most people don't want to do it's not
very comfortable standing underneath
that stream of ice-cold water and that's
the point every morning that you get
into the shower and you choose to turn
that handle to cold instead of hot you
are embracing discomfort you're leaning
into the resistance and that makes you
better at doing so in the future
regardless of what the task is so as you
go through your daily life find ways to
embrace discomfort it could be cold
showers it could be setting up for a 6
a.m.
ROTC fitness class it can be taking the
stairs instead of the elevator basically
whatever your brain throws up that I
don't feel like an excuse that is an
opportunity
to build that self-discipline muscle and
you should take it okay we are on to
item number four of our list which is to
target the fundamentals first and by the
fundamentals I mean the biological
necessities of life your sleep your
nutrition and your exercise habits these
are all crucial to pay attention to
because the part of your brain that
handles executive functioning part that
regulates your desires and your impulses
requires a lot of energy and regular
rest to function at peak levels always
remember that you are first and foremost
a collection of biological systems all
of which require the right inputs if you
want to get the best outputs out of them
and I know it's easy to picture the
brain as separate from all of this as
existing in this metaphysical realm but
the only needed fuel sources are
motivation and determination and
wholesome memes
but the brain needs rest and needs
exercise and it needs the right balance
of nutrients just as the rest of your
body does so if you're sleep deprived
which judging from the amount of views
on this video you probably are or you
haven't gotten enough exercise regularly
or your diet is crap that is where you
should focus your discipline first and
that brings us to our fifth item on the
list and it pains me to say this one
because I personally hate doing it but
you may want to try meditation and the
reason you might want to do this is that
meditation has been shown scientifically
to help people improve their levels of
self-discipline in fact a 2013 study at
Stanford University showed that people
who went through compassion training
which was a specific meditation program
we're better able to regulate their
emotions afterwards and this is crucial
for remaining disciplined and being able
to make rational decisions now an easy
way to get started would be by using
guided meditation which you can use
through apps like headspace and calm or
through many free videos here on YouTube
but the form of meditation that I've
always practiced which i think is better
for the development of self-discipline
specifically is a form of what's called
zazen meditation where I simply sit and
concentrate on my breath with my eyes
closed and when my attention is
inevitably pulled away by a random
thought I work to notice that and let
that thought go and then bring my
attention back to my breath and doing
this over the long term has helped with
both self-discipline and concentration
and like I said I'm not a huge fan of
meditation it's probably the self
development practice that I hate doing
the most but the benefits of doing so
are on
and that brings us to our final item on
the list which is to practice building
new habits now like I said earlier
building new habits is kind of a
separate discipline in the overall
pursuit of changing your behavior but
the initial stages of building a new
habit often require self discipline
because the behavior isn't automatic yet
so this can be a great way to not only
establish a new habit but become more
disciplined in the process now I've got
an entire video on building new habits
coming out for you guys in the next
couple of weeks but until then remember
that for whatever habit you choose to
build start small track your progress
maybe use an app like abetik ax or
strides which is my current favorite one
or have a bull on Android celebrate your
wins and also remember to not focus too
much on purity on perfect streaks
instead focus on making sure that your
trend is going in an overall positive
direction and remember that as it is
doing that and as that behavior is
becoming more automatic your
self-discipline is improving in the
process now if you've already taken care
of those health fundamentals we talked
about earlier and you're looking for a
new habit to sink your teeth into and
you get this process started with then
one that I might suggest will be taking
on an independent learning project and
putting some daily effort into learning
something and new perhaps you have the
same interests that I do in the area of
computer science and algorithms not only
of these two topics incredibly
fascinating but if you happen to be the
kind of person who wants to be a web
developer someday or wants to be a
programmer then learning these computer
science fundamentals can really give you
a leg up on the competition and if
you're looking for a good place to get
started then you should check out the
computer science courses over on
brilliant really is a fantastic learning
platform for anyone wanted to learn math
science and yes computer science much
more effectively and much faster than
they normally would this is because
brilliant takes an incredibly active
approach to learning so to just
passively deliver a material like in a
lecture they immediately throw you into
challenging problems that keep your
interest high and give you something to
apply your current skill set to right
from the get-go
now with this approach you are going to
get stuck sometimes like I got stuck
with the sorting algorithms parked in
their computer science algorithms course
but when you find yourself in that stuck
situation they do have this incredibly
detailed wiki where you can go look at
example problems and detailed
explanations of all the concepts within
their courses and once you've done that
you can then go back to those problems
armed with new knowledge and solve it
and the best part is while you're doing
this while you're solving these problems
in their computer science courses or
maybe in their calculus course or their
course on classical
you're not just getting better at
solving problems within that one topical
area that you're focused on you're
becoming a better problem solver in
general so if you want to start
improving your analytical and creative
problem-solving skills across the board
and start learning something new then
you should go over to brilliant org
slash Thomas Frank and sign up start
learning for free today and if you're
one of the first 83 people to sign up
with that link you're also going to get
20% off their annual premium
subscription I want to give a big thanks
to brilliant as always for sponsoring
this video and being a huge supporter of
my channel and thank you so much for
watching as well if you enjoyed this
video give it a thumbs up and definitely
get subscribed so you don't miss out on
new videos when they come out every
single week and you can also get a free
copy of my book and how to earn better
grades right there last but not least
you can follow me over on Instagram and
check out one more video on this channel
right here and I will see you in the
next one