hey what is up guys and welcome to a new
series that I am for now calling this is
how I get stuff done and I'm here with
my friend and competing a beard model on
the internet Matson Avella is a know him
from his channel what Matt developer
Matt Savelle yeah it's very simple
he's got a lot of videos on habits
productivity minimalism is something
that you focus on for the most part I
would say right yeah minimalism is
definitely kind of that's definitely
where I kind of formed my initial start
on YouTube was going about simple living
and you came to YouTube from the
documentary world right yeah documentary
on Netflix with the minimalists who have
actually met once before yeah yeah
really cool guys yeah I think it was I
think it was either watching a video of
yours or read a blog post where you were
talking about that experience of kind of
seeing the minimalist and meeting I'm
with Colin right yeah we got burritos is
an excellent night so what I want to do
with this series is sort of explore how
other insanely productive people get
things done kind of dig into their
processes the systems they use all that
kind of stuff and you're my guinea pig
right this is the first one we're just
going to see how it turns out and I
guess the first thing I want to start
with is just sort of getting an overview
of what you what what do you say you do
here essentially yeah so I'm a filmmaker
that's the the craft and then it's I
make one video every week from my
channel I also have a podcast that I've
released on a usually weekly basis yeah
I mean I really I was consistent for
about a year and a half of releasing a
podcast every single week and lately
it's I've just been experimenting and
trying some different models out but I
would say the core of what I do is just
one eight to ten minute video every week
on my youtube channel okay is there
anything else that's sort of a ancillary
to that yeah like a blog or a newsletter
yes so yeah like everybody like
everybody else like I have social media
I've got the newsletter okay and I have
yeah like I said the podcast so I would
say when I'm really looking and planning
at the beginning of the year what
channels and mediums I want to focus on
I would say the two big ones one is
definitely the YouTube channel yeah and
that's just from the overall response
and reception of the channel itself and
also just what I'd love to do most yeah
and then I would say the runner-up is
probably the either the podcast or the
newsletter because the newsletter is
generally once a week again I'm not as
strict with that I I don't let myself
slip up very often at all with the
YouTube channel like that's the thing
that I'm like I have to release a video
every single week yeah I take a few
weeks off every year or a little bit
more maybe like three or four weeks
total in the year that I might take off
but overall those are kind of my main
channels that I create for and when you
take time off do you just not publish
during those times sometimes sometimes I
don't videos in the can
yeah sometimes I do have videos in the
can okay I think the one thing that I've
learned is that I can put a lot of
pressure on myself to keep getting ahead
in the head and ahead and the problem
with that is that you can never get
ahead like there's always so much is up
with you exactly like so I will get to a
point where I was four weeks ahead I
took a really long like two-and-a-half
week vacation and I felt amazing I just
felt so good about getting that far out
and then when I came back from vacation
all my runway was gone yeah and I'm like
I had to start over and I was just so
bummed out about it and it really like
it was hard to restart again mm-hmm so
I've started to pull that pressure back
a little bit on myself and say you know
what if instead of going for weeks six
weeks and just trying to always get
ahead what if I just created in the
moment and then just I was just week to
week or maybe two weeks most and not
feeling like I always had to get ahead
and that's helped so much with my sanity
yeah there's a certain beauty of that
too right I think there's like this
preoccupation with getting ahead to the
pourable you'll never have to work again
maybe that's the fantasy but there is a
certain beauty to just knowing you have
to get up and do your craft everyday
yeah and it yeah I do think that that's
something that we kind of like idolized
in our head as this idea of I can just
sit back and relax and I want to do
anything I think there's an element of
it that in the short term it takes
pressure off yourself at least
have one or two weeks ahead yeah but I
do really like releasing more closer to
the moment like I just finished up a
video two days ago and I release it
today and that to me I feel closer to
the project I feel closer to the
feedback that it gets and I can
understand how people are responding to
it more but when you're for six weeks
ahead it gets to the point where you
just kind of like pushing it out there
you know what I mean it's more like a
factory and less of an art mm-hmm
so you briefly mentioned that when you
we sit down the plan you're looking at
the year do you actually plan a whole
year and ahead like what is your
planning process for all of your
different channels like and how far in
advance is it yeah so I usually kind of
put together like a business strategy
plan around the beginning of the year
that's usually when it feels right no
but I'll usually kind of recalibrate six
months into the year but it basically
kind of drol up a note document on my
Mac and I just work through what are the
main channels and the mediums that I
want to focus on I usually I used to in
the past focus on growth metrics but we
were talking about this before where
it's like you could always just keep
wanting more and more and more and like
generally I get pretty happy with like
I'm totally content with where I'm at
right now with like numbers so these
days I don't include that but it's just
like God what do I want to get out of it
what are my expectations for the kind of
content I want to create and the kind of
message that I want to put out there
what I like the topics I want to talk
about and it's usually no more than one
page to kind of this is just kind of the
jump start the direction of where things
are gonna go okay and when you sit down
to plan or you sedona take notes is it
always on your mac is it always in the
Notes app yeah so I use the Notes app on
Mac and I have it on my phone a lot of
times you know when I'm out I'll pop it
open and I'll take a couple of notes
down you sometimes what I actually do is
productivity hack here when I'm with NAT
my wife and we're driving I will ask her
to text me an idea i'ma go I got an idea
like smart yeah it text me but sweat and
they detect me but sweat and then all
like oh yeah and I don't forget what
that what's about why did you text me
but swear that makes no sense at all no
that's like how I'll do it like on the
on the road or if I'm driving but
otherwise I'll just open up the Notes
app and I'll simply write out a couple
of notes of you know the idea that I
have I usually don't go to long form
sometimes if it's like a really
important idea I might actually put it
on my to-do list as something that I
have to do now and with to-do lists what
are you use for that
yeah I use an app called to do its few
UX de UX oh okay that yeah yeah yes
really awesome I you know found out
about them probably the five or six
years ago and I've been using them ever
since
it is crazy simple it's when you open it
up on your web browser all you see are I
think it's five days of the week and
then it continually just shifts over and
if something's done you obviously check
it off and then it Gray's out and if you
haven't done it that day it'll just
automatically move to the next day so
it's like is it like Kanban is it's kind
of like sideways then it's not just a
straight-up list of tasks yeah it'll be
like yeah it'll be like you know Monday
Tuesday Wednesday Thursday Friday
basically each day so then I could also
like add things to my to do this video
I'm not gonna go to get that done today
I'll put it tomorrow or the next day I
think one of the biggest things for me
is making sure that I'm not overloading
my to-do list and I'm not doing too much
so I usually pick around two to three
really important tasks that I want to do
that day okay and when you're planning
out your day is it the night before is
it like a week in advance how are you
planning out individual days yeah when
I'm planning my days it varies you know
I I'm pretty type-a okay but there
there's a part of me that's also kind of
flexible and needs to go with things in
the moment and like what I feel like
doing so I mean I could have a task that
says like right next week's video
but then when I wake up in the morning
like I try and I'm just like I just
don't like I'm not inspired right now
you know what I'd rather right now to
start like editing my video that's going
live this week and let me just work
through that a little bit to feel a
little bit productive to kind of build
that momentum of work it's still on my
to-do list and I'll probably get to it
but at least I could it's kind of I'm
willing to be flexible in the moment if
I have
- so what you're saying is as one of you
twos productivity gurus you don't stick
to your plan I don't no no no he's got
scandal
yeah a hundred percent you throw the
plane out the window like what once you
get everybody has a plan until you get
punched in the face I think Mike Tyson
said that yep so yeah actually Michael
Scott Michael Scott said that you know
yeah I was most of the time I would say
I stick to it I what I also do is I will
sometimes add my personal tasks to my
professional to-do list like a lot of
people talk about work-life balance so
do you usually keep them separate no I
don't so I kind of I always bring them
all together the kind of thing for me -
yeah and but it's not like I'm not
putting every single thing that I would
do personally on this list but it's like
the big things like I will put my the
workout or the exercise routine that I'm
doing for the gym okay one thing it's
actually surprisingly difficult to
remember when you're going to the gym
four or five days a week to remember did
I workout biceps yesterday or did I do
back or legs and like it's very easy to
kind of mix those up so that way I know
that it's there and I can also keep
track of what I'm working out but I will
also like there's actually a separate
section on the to-do list where you can
add groceries and other stuff so oh cool
yeah I will kind of I don't know that
people believe in this the work/life
balance that everything needs to be
separated but at least with the work I
do I feel like my life is so intertwined
with it like I really love my work I
wake up every morning really excited to
work yeah and so I I don't mind like
bringing my personal life together with
it
yeah and the way I see it unless the
corporation is forcing you to use a
specific tool like I don't know Outlook
or something for your job you know one
tool can kind of work for everything as
long as you know how to split things up
whether it be by labels or projects or
what-have-you
yeah that works pretty well yeah so you
use one to-do app mhm and do use like a
calendar app as well as a calendar app I
guess the regular Apple one I use Google
actually yeah I use Google calendars and
like within the calendar you would see
that I have I usually create like a day
then for each piece of content I'm gonna
create okay it's all under a different
calendar so has a different color label
so if I'm releasing a YouTube video that
would be yellow in the calendar if it's
a patreon exclusive video it would be
orange in the calendar and then my
podcast would be a separate color in the
calendar every Thursday and those are
like to me and actually what's
interesting about that or not to pin the
code I mean if you watch this far you'd
probably find this boring stuff
interesting but this is also how I
planned my videos into the future so
right now I'm kind of like crazy ahead
where I have three months ahead of video
ideas for every Tuesday markdown that's
awesome yeah so it's just the concept I
don't have these videos written or
scripted out or anything but I have a
general idea of where I want to go with
it and when I'm creating these videos
have a nice balance right so it's like
alright I haven't made a video about
minimalism in a while I think it'd be a
good time to kind of workshop an idea
that would fit that maybe I can do one
of habits this year I'm doing every
month 30-day challenge so that's always
rosy yeah so that one needs to be
slotted in at some point and I try to
figure out that balance there is part of
me that always feels like I should I
should do two videos this week okay now
that I have three months of ideas I'm
like all would be great to really put
out just a couple extra videos in there
but I try to release that temptation
because I just know that's the fastest
way to lead to burnout mm-hmm have you
tried in the past yes I did about two
months of two videos every week okay and
I just noticed that one of the videos
would always suffer in quality my
personal life would certainly suffer in
quality and it just wasn't worth it yeah
I definitely had weeks where there were
tight deadlines and I've gotten three
videos out in a week and then I start to
convince myself oh I could do three
videos a week just like all these other
big youtubers you know they're so
productive why can't I be but no that's
it's a recipe for burnout for sure
that's definitely where it comes from it
definitely comes from seeing other
people and other channels people who I
admire people who I really love their
content and I'm like how the hell are
they putting out three videos a week
like this is absurd the amount of time
and energy goes to make these videos and
like one you just never know what's
actually going on behind the scenes like
they could have a big team they also
could be really stressed out and it
could be over
it could be like not the best thing for
their own health yeah so I try not to
measure myself based on other metrics
whether it's the number of videos
somebody else is creating how much money
somebody else is making or how many
views they're making and I try to just
measure it based on am I happy do I feel
and am I happy with how the videos that
I'm making am i proud of what I'm making
intrinsic versus extrinsic it's hard to
do it's easier said than done but that's
kind of what I strive for gotcha
yeah I found that people on the internet
are sort of professionally good at
making it look like it's all easy hmm
and you may I know you put your video on
anxiety and a few other people have kind
of come clean with how stressed out they
are and being at VidCon you hear a lot
of just like oh yeah it's it's you know
it's a complete you know just absolute
disaster yeah and I'm always stressed
out but they make it look easy yeah and
I think that's that's something that I'm
trying to work on because a lot of my
videos like just at least my filmmaking
style it can be a very clean cut
type a it can look like I have
everything together and I did have like
Maddie H who we were talking about
another awesome youtuber like he
commented on my anxiety video and he's
like dude I never would have known that
you were going through this because like
it just looks like you're like somebody
who's just got his together that's
like I will say that a lot of times I do
have my together
but like we all have our lows and we all
have these really challenging periods of
our lives and it doesn't matter how many
subscribers you get or how much money
you're making you're always gonna have
these really difficult things to get
through yeah and I think it's like you
just try to be more open and honest
about that in each video you make it's
like I'm not gonna do a video about
anxiety every single day I still haven't
yeah exactly but it's here right still
going on but I think it's like it's it's
helpful to be real and authentic as much
as that word is thrown around these days
I think yeah real authenticity helps
yeah there's like a pressure to put on
this I don't know strong face on the
internet but I guess you know you've
discovered this I've discovered this
from my limited you know moments of
vulnerability when you do communicate
what you're going through it actually
helps people relate yeah because I think
that you know people especially in the
help itself helps to a space can run the
risk of making it seem
like everything's too easy for them or
that like they have everything together
and then people watching or like well
you know what's wrong with me
why can't I do that why I not feeling
you know nothing but pure bliss all the
time and then they get to see like oh
the people that I'm watching they also
go through the same exact human
struggles yeah that was a turning point
for me I would say probably last year at
the beginning of the year where I felt
like I was hitting a wall in terms of
what continent could create because I I
just was only talking about what I knew
and what I was an expert in yep and then
I was like this is I I only got two
things I've got filmmaking and I've got
minimalism and like that's like and like
the minimalism I'm like am I an expert
I'm not Marie Kondo but I'm like I know
enough to talk about it mm-hm and I'm
like okay but I need to branch out and
I'm getting a little bit bored talking
about these same things yeah so I was
like what if instead of being an expert
I was an experimenter what if I didn't
hook the box and I just started playing
around with things and I do that's where
the experiments came from like cold
showers for 30 days like I'm not an
expert in cold showers I don't know who
is I'm not wim HOF right but I can
actually explore this and I can learn
about it and I think that to me has made
the process more enjoyable and it's
again taking the pressure off to be like
the expert in everything yeah you're
learning along with the audience
essentially yeah I kind of hit the same
wall you know it how many times can you
make a video about to-do lists before
you said everything you want to say and
then I kind of had this realization like
you know the power of habit was written
by a journalist and he went out and he
dug to get a story and then that turned
into a book okay well maybe I need to be
a journalist and go ask questions again
go do interviews like this series yeah
and you know yeah you just can't you
can't talk about only what you know
forever especially when your job is
professional content creator yeah
because all of your time is invested in
that instead of yeah you know forget
about that people forget about the fact
that like the actual job is making
videos and they think that the job is
just knowing stuff I'm not sure yeah you
know eight hours a day I'm getting rid
of stuff yeah I used to think about that
though - I tell my friend who's a
self-development life coach and I was
like man I'm like I envy you because
your job is to like work on yourself
and to like you know write about
self-development and always be learning
about that
and it is true that that's a great place
to be in but it's also true that that's
a hell of a lot of work yeah and there's
also twice as much work as you think
that is there yeah exactly
so I want to talk about your
organization essentially the space
you're in the files all that good stuff
and obviously the coolest thing is what
we're sitting right behind your closet
here so tell me a little bit about how
you got your camera gear organized I
love that you've got the coolest thing
as my closet dude it's like you're my
kind of guy
Natalie does not care about this at all
but I'm like this to me was a I'm super
proud of it it's a it's funny because I
don't know where all this stuff was
before I we moved into this new place we
just moved here a couple months ago and
this is the first time that I've had an
actual studio to work from that I can
have my gear organized in the way that I
want it yeah shoved under the bed shoved
in a closet somewhere and so I put a lot
of thought into it I'm like how do I
want this organized I kind of went with
this idea of what if I made my stuff be
like the decor mm-hm and it's kind of a
play on minimalism what if I just laid
out all my camera gear all my things on
a pegboard and then you know what if I
laid my lenses out pulling from
inspiration from other youtubers other
other videos that I've seen online but
also just trying to keep everything
organized and easy to go
having my battery station set up so I
can charge any battery for any device I
have yeah load it right out that saves
me a ton of time that's genius just yeah
because it's always plugged in and I'm
guessing you probably do like one of the
charger at all time so you have an extra
to go yeah so usually when I finish a
shoot I'll take all the batteries and
then I'll put them on the top shelf
there and then I'll load all the
batteries up there so be a few left over
that aren't charged I'll go through
charge all those maybe I'll come back a
couple hours later take them off put
them in where they're designated in like
the drawer below it yeah and then the
cube goes from there and I think the
batteries from the top and then I charge
those and then Ovation so then basically
no uncharged batteries go in that drawer
because that's a mess when you just look
at a stack of 20 batteries you know
which one of these is charged yeah isn't
it can be stressful and like you have to
go out and charge each one for me the
biggest thing when it comes to
organization when it comes to setting up
my workspace my desk my
space even setting my files online it's
like how can I reduce as much friction
as possible yeah so it's easy to get to
work even in setting up this desk right
here I originally had it kind of jutting
out into the room and it created a nook
behind it but I just felt myself like
this is gonna sound crazy but it's like
I was so much less likely to walk all
the way around I can walk around the
gear I had to get around the desk and
then sit down and I'm like I just want
my body because I sometimes we're just
on most of them were just on autopilot
so I'm like I just need the V straight
like or a straight line straight to my
desk and then boom I sit down and then I
get to work and I've noticed like it has
helped me out so much yeah so I try to
be thoughtful at every single thing in
the apartment to reduce that friction as
much as I can that was a big thing for
me and music when I got my new house I
built this really cool recording studio
upstairs and I realized like I'm not
going upstairs to grab the guitar and
mess around so I just moved it all
downstairs like the amp the guitars
everything is just out in the living
room yeah it's so easy just grab it play
it and that as a result like do yeah
that's one of those powerful things
about habit change is the the changing
of the environment something that I've
learned over the past year is when I
feel like I'm gonna forget a habit right
that's the hardest thing is like how am
I gonna remember every day to keep doing
this thing yeah so when I took cold
showers every day for 30 days I just
printed up a calendar and I put it right
next to the shower and I taped it there
with a permanent marker so then every
time I went to take a shower and I did
shower daily so that was an important
first step and I would just exit out and
then I would always see it I did that
for meditation for the gym I'll keep my
protein out on the counter to remember
see that oh yeah I got a really gym
today and I think those environmental
changes are yeah it's just about the
friction it's about making it easy for
yourself so do you use any kind of habit
tracking apps or anything like that I
don't know I'm envious of people who do
because I see the the bullet journals
and I'm like those things look so cool
and like you I mean I'm sure you've seen
them online like they're super artistic
and beautiful and like people have these
amazing illustrations but I'm like I
don't I don't have the time right now
to make my notebook creative like for me
that would actually be reverse
productive to like spend too much time
doing that I understand how habit
tracking can help people and I think I
might experiment with in the future and
just try to track certain things in my
life yeah when I'm doing 30-day
challenges I track things but I don't
have like a specific system for tracking
those habits in the long run I do do
something called the two day rule so
that's when I go to the basically for my
gym workout routine it's like kind of a
keystone habit for me it's one of the
most important habits because it
influences so many other things in my
life when I'm going to the gym five days
a week four days a week I am more likely
to have my protein shake I'm more likely
to drink more water I'm gonna be eating
healthier just because I feel motivated
and more energized and I don't want to
you know gain John junk food so that to
keep that gym habit is really important
to me so I enact a two day rule which is
basically I will not let myself take two
doll to two days off in a row okay so so
you could take a rest day any day yeah
but it's not planned and I got in the
next day you must go back yes and I have
multiple I could take multiple days off
in a week - okay and you know it's it's
important because like I am so much more
likely to miss a third day if I skip -
yeah I'm four and five and you should
get so far from it that's when you
forget you wait a minute was I trying to
be able to have it here but where did it
go so the two day rule has been
instrumental
I will caveat it by saying that like
it's I'm not super strict with it to the
point where I'm gonna like hurt myself
or I'm sick and I'm going to the gym I
will take a week off if I'm sick if I'm
traveling and I like feel like taking
off I might just travel for two weeks
and not work out but knowing that when I
come back to my normal routine the two
day of rolls back and it helps me get
right back and build a habit again that
helps yeah cuz like I think it's like
it's important to know that yeah it's
like you you put the two day row out
there and then people think that that's
what I'm doing
365 days a year and it's not I would
imagine that you're not doing most of
what you say all the time it's more just
like you know 90% is what we're shooting
for
yeah 100% yeah because like we're all
human and I mean we're all working and
challenging ourselves to overcome these
things to implement these systems into
our
yeah and it is like if I can do this
most the time if I'm on top of my to-do
list most of the time then I'll feel
good and yeah ninety percent of the time
is good enough for me and if you're
striving to be totally perfect I think
you're just gonna let yourself down
because nobody is yeah yeah absolutely
yeah what do you do when it's the middle
of the day and for me this is probably
two three o'clock I don't know what it
is for you mm-hmm you're just riddled
with brain fog and you can't motivate
yourself to do anything so I typically
go to the gym in the middle of the day
so you're not like a wake up go to the
gym first scene I did I did that for a
couple months this year and I liked it
okay so again it's like it might vary
and this is where I'm like not type-a
and I like I will kind of structure my
day differently at times just to see how
it feels but when I'm going to the gym
in the middle of the day I find that
like one it's a nice break like I can go
out get lunch have some Chipotle you do
a workout and then come back and I find
that especially if I'm doing cardio I'm
like getting that energy going again
yeah the one thing other than that which
gives me energy is doing different tasks
so I usually try to write first thing in
the morning okay guys that's typically
the hardest thing for me to know because
it's it's if I wait till the end of the
day like there's just a certain amount
of creative energy that I can get onto
the page that I can get into writing and
I cannot I couldn't spend eight hours
writing in a day I just couldn't I would
just I get after a couple hours I
usually get pretty tired and I get
enough done that I'm happy so I might
write for two to three hours in the
morning and then do editing I find that
editing from me is a little bit easier
to do when I'm kind of feeling a little
bit of brain fog when I'm feeling tired
I will give myself some breaks so I
won't just work for four hours straight
I'll work for an hour I might set a
timer to remind myself to stop working
an hour just to take 15 minutes off to
kind of get my eyes away from the
computer screen to take a lap around the
apartment to talk to Natalie or get a
glass of water and then come back to my
come back to my work okay
what time you wake up in the morning
do you have a specific yeah yeah I means
I know you did the was at 4:30 in the
morning about 5:30 5:30 yeah which was a
you know not far off from my normal
routine but far enough that it really
negatively affects my life and also so
strict I was like I'm gonna do it for 30
days straight yeah so that was part of
the problem is that I didn't allow
myself the flexibility of I didn't do
the 2-day rule I like it was like every
day when I'm traveling regardless time
zones tough time zone changes so that
was really difficult but typically I
wake up around 6:30 I would say on work
days okay if I if we had a late night or
something else then I'll sleep in till
7:00 I'm usually rarely in bed by 7:30
do you have a pretty strict bedtime or
as a disorder whatever you know when
Natalie had her full-time job it was
more strict because she would just be
like all right it's like 9 o'clock or
9:30 gotta get to bed cuz I gotta be up
she's not get to work and I got a
commute so yeah usually it was a little
bit a little bit more strict then now
we're still in bed by 10:00 p.m. okay so
that's so pretty early
yeah we're yeah we're pretty boring so
you're getting eight eight and a half
hours yep yeah yes pretty good amount
yeah I would say definitely eight hours
a night for sure
cool yeah well I think that might be
enough cuz we've done like 20 minutes of
footage yeah that was great dude yeah so
hopefully you guys enjoyed this
interview your channel is easy just
youtube.com slash Maddy Bella baby Bella
cool I'll have it on screen with my
After Effects magic go check his stuff
out it's better film than mine we're
using his cameras I'm lucky I love you
videos Dan thank you
and your videos are awesome as well like
interests a bunch of them this morning
breakfast burrito nice oh yes yeah
Matthew Mel and burritos that's like the
kids are doing good I'm gonna write that
down actually my to-do list
yeah dude thank you for coming on
whatever this show is and you all should
go and subscribe to Matt and start
watching his videos cool thanks brother
appreciate it
yep good stuff cool