today we are talking about Google
Calendar because I've been getting a lot
of questions about how I use my calendar
personally and Google Calendar has been
my weapon of choice for the past five
six seven years almost at this point so
today in this video we're going to go
through how I use Google Calendar some
of the tips and tricks I use both on
desktop and mobile how I use it as a
student versus uh now as an incredibly
professional businessman and hey if you
guys use a different calendar most of
the stuff is going to apply not all of
it but for the vast majority of it it's
going to apply to any calendar you use
so IAL uh Outlook calendar I don't know
like a stone tablet on the ground that
one's going to be a bit of a stretch but
this will apply to almost any system for
the most part and the first thing I need
to stress here is that Google Calendar
is part of what I call my quick capture
system now I'm going to talk about this
concept a little bit more in a future V
video but essentially the gist of it is
that quick capture means you want to get
ideas of any kind out of your head as
immediately as possible and into a
system that you trust one that has
context one that's organized and one
that will either notify you when you
need to know about it again in the
future or that you trust yourself to
check regularly so with that being said
we're going to get into how I
specifically use Google Calendar in my
daily life and I need to split this
explanation in two because the way I use
it today is very different than how I
used it as a student as a student I had
my calendar split into multiple
different calendars because the concept
essentially for me was to split my life
into different components and then be
able to look at each component
individually so I had specific calendars
for classes for work for on campus
events I also had one for uh other stuff
just kind of things that didn't fit and
then I also had a professor office hours
calendar by the way guys if I sound like
a frog right now it's because I'm sick
sorry one last thing about how I use my
calendar as a student is that at the
beginning of every semester I would put
in all the important dates uh right away
so like the date when I need to sign up
for classes for the next semester that
would go in right away uh finals week
would go in there and that way I knew it
was all set up at the beginning of the
semester I wouldn't have to be worrying
about when do I sign up for class class
when do I start studying for finals it's
all set up initially and then I can just
react to it as it comes up on a week toe
basis so that brings us to today where I
use my calendar in a very different
Manner and that's because I'm no longer
a student and my time isn't dominated
mostly by events I'm a business owner
and most of my time is kind of free form
I can choose to work on whatever I want
to work on at any time as long as it
gets done I would say probably about 90%
of my time is like that the other 10% is
scheduled meetings for the most part
because as a podcaster I'm often
interviewing people or I'm being on
other people's shows the other main use
is for travel since I'm going to schools
to speak sometimes or I go to
conferences in different cities and
different states I'm often traveling and
when I travel I create all day events in
the calendar so they're not blocking up
the hourly slots and that way I just
know oh I'm in Denver these days I'm in
New York City these days and the last
main thing I use my calendar for these
days is for exercise because a lot of my
exercise is actually event driven like
my yoga class is 6:30 p.m. on Thursdays
so I got to be there on time and for for
ice skating practice it's only a very
limited window of time every day that I
can do it so I just schedule on the
calendar and then because I'm a
completionist I put my gym time on there
as well so with those explanations out
of the way I got a few more things to
talk about first of which is mobile now
I used to use Sunrise calendar on my
iPhone to manage Google Calendar because
it was free and it was beautiful and at
the time the Google Calendar app kind of
stunk in my opinion that is not the case
anymore I think the Google Calendar app
is pretty good however I don't use it
because now I use an app called
Fantastical and the reason I use
Fantastical is number one it is the best
calendar app that I have found for use
on the Apple watch right now because
it's the one that has glances so I can
just easily look at the watch swipe up
and see what my next event is and it
also has absolutely fantastic natural
language processing which means if I use
voice dictation to create an event which
is a really seamless frictionless way to
get it out of my brain and into my phone
then it will intelligently pick out the
uh parts of the event that need to be
put in different fields and that brings
me to the last thing we need to talk
about in this video which is scheduling
stuff because email tag is the worst
trust me I've got like 50 message long
threads from a few years ago where I'm
trying to be like yeah I'm available
this day oh you're not available that
day blah blah blah you can use
technology to make this much much
simpler now the app that I use on a
regular basis is called calendly and
this is an app that lets you define
certain dates and times on your weekly
schedule when people can basically
pencil in their own appointments with
you and this is really really useful for
people like me who are podcasters and
who have to schedule interviews a lot or
maybe people like tutors anyone who has
to open up big amounts of their schedule
and limited Windows to let people
basically pencil in their own
appointments but I don't think it's
super useful for students because you
guys usually have a lot of your schedule
already spoken for by classes and you're
generally just trying to schedule things
like uh group project work time now
Google Calendar has their own like find
a Time feature but what I found is most
students don't have their calendar game
unlock so you're going to be like the
only person who has everything really
nicely scheduled and everyone else is
going to be like yeah I don't know what
I'm doing next Tuesday so doodle is what
I recommend for you guys because doodle
basically lets you define a date range
and then everyone can vote on the times
that work for them and you can easily
see the column where everyone's
available so that about does it for this
video now if you've been paying
attention you are now a scheduling ninja
though do not put that in your Twitter
bio or I will find you and if you guys
have extra tips about how to use your
calendar that I didn't cover here I
would love to hear them otherwise thank
you so much for watching if you enjoyed
this video and you found it useful give
it a like to support this Channel and if
you want to get new tips on being a more
effective student every every single
week you can click that big red
subscribe button right down there also I
wrote a free book on how to earn better
grades so if you want to get a copy of
that you can click the book and I'll
send one to you and in last week's video
we talked about skipping classes and
whether or not it's worth it so check it
out if you missed it also if you want to
get the full article for this video
along with links to all the resources we
talked about click the orange button
right there and lastly if you want to
connect I'm Tom frankley on Instagram
and Twitter or you can leave a comment
down below thanks for watching