if you want to learn and make quicker
progress in literally any skill then
grab your phone grab a tripod for that
phone and record yourself there are
three main components to progression in
any skill be it physical
mental and art form or anything else
those components are number one
good instruction number two deliberate
practice and number three
feedback when you're learning on your
own feedback is often the thing that's
lacking you're either not getting any or
you're not getting it nearly fast enough
so build yourself a better feedback loop
by recording yourself
i'm learning tennis right now and every
time i go to practice i put my phone on
a tripod and record my swings
that way i can come back later on and
check myself how was my body positioning
how was my form how was my
follow-through
and i've done this with other things as
well public speaking guitar
weightlifting when you record yourself
you're able to go back later on and look
at what you did and you can pinpoint
exactly what you need to work on and
what you need to change up
the next time around