hey what's going on friends in this
video we are going over seven books that
i think everyone should read in their
20s these are all books that i read when
i was in my 20s and they all had a
tremendous impact on my life and helped
me to improve my life in five different
categories that we're breaking this
video down into those categories are
relationships productivity personal
finance career success and health so
let's get this video started off with
the first book on my list which is
stephen covey's seven habits of highly
effective people this is the book that
more than any other book helped me to
improve the way that i both build and
deepen relationships with other people
now this isn't entirely a book about
relationships in fact about half of this
book is a book about productivity the
first three habits deal with it like
habit number two begin with the end in
mind is all about planning and
understanding your goals and habit
number three put first things first is
all about prioritization but it's habit
number five that had the greatest impact
on me seek first to understand then to
be understood see most people listen
with what covey calls an
autobiographical point of view you're
listening because you're waiting to
respond with something from your own
perspective your own experiences a lot
of people don't take the time to really
put themselves in the shoes of the other
person consider their perspective try to
see it the way the other person sees it
kevin calls this empathetic listening
and when you can listen empathetically
when you can actually do this
perspective shift you become better able
to understand the meaning and the
context behind what somebody else is
telling you about and in doing so you
build much better and deeper
relationships and you're able to make
the lives of everyone around you much
better so that is my favorite book in
the relationship category and now we're
moving on to the productivity category
now there are a ton of productivity
books out there i've talked about many
of them on this channel but if you were
only going to read one the one that i
would recommend is going to be chris
bailey's the productivity project well
this and also atomic habits by james
clear but i in fact made two videos
about that book so i'm not gonna include
it on this list and the productivity
project is a wonderful overview of
really the entire field of productivity
so if you're looking for one
concentrated book that's gonna teach you
all about time management managing your
attention your energy procrastination
all these different topics this is the
book that i would recommend and the best
idea that i want to share from this book
is his breakdown of these six different
procrastination triggers this is pulled
from procrastination research that has
been done at several different
universities where they have found that
there are indeed six different aspects
or qualities of tasks that we tend to
put off of tasks that are unpleasant so
when a task is boring when it is
frustrating difficult ambiguous lacking
and personal meaning or lacking an
intrinsic value i.e it's not fun we tend
to put it off and there are a ton of
different strategies in this book for
fighting procrastination but i want to
share this idea because once you know
these six different triggers you can now
start to think critically about your own
tasks and ask yourself if i'm
procrastinating which of these triggers
is causing me to procrastinate on this
task and once you know that you can
start to figure out some things you
could do to lessen the influence of
those triggers for example last week i
had to go into my accounting software
and do a ton of bookkeeping which is a
task that i absolutely hate so one thing
that i've realized is that because this
task is boring one thing i can do to
make it a little bit more fun is to add
a bit of a challenge to it so i set a
20-minute timer and i challenged myself
to reconcile as many transactions as i
could within that time period still kind
of boring but a little less boring
because i had now set up a challenge and
i also put out some of my favorite music
so overall those two little tweaks made
the task just a bit less unpleasant and
a bit less boring and with that we are
now moving on from the productivity
category onto the personal finance
category where i have two book
recommendations for you and the first
one is your money the missing manual by
jd roth who was one of the og personal
finance bloggers that i was reading back
when i was in high school in college and
this book was really my first
introduction to the world of personal
finance and it's really just an overview
of a ton of different topics that you
need to learn about if you want to
manage your money effectively talks
about debt it talks about budgeting
talks about credit cards talks about
investing and the big idea that i would
like to share from this book with you in
this video is the concept of automated
investing this was the book that taught
me that i should automate my finances
essentially put them on autopilot so
this means you can put your bills on
autopay but perhaps even more
importantly you can put your investments
on an auto deposit schedule which is
exactly what i did after i read this
book now on my investment platform which
at the time was vanguard i have since
moved over to m1 finance works on both
of these i have an auto deposit schedule
where every single month money will come
out of my bank account and go into my
investment account and be invested into
a set series of etfs essentially mutual
funds that i have set up beforehand and
there are two huge benefits to
automating your investing in this way
number one is the consistency of
actually investing because if you have a
robot doing your investing for you
you're almost certainly going to invest
more over the years than if you were
deliberately making the choice whether
or not to invest every single month if
you were doing it that way there are
inevitably going to be months when you
decide that i'd rather buy a jet ski or
i don't feel like i have enough money
but if it's on a schedule it just comes
out and you don't think about it until
10 or 20 or 30 years later when you have
a ton of money invested you will thank
yourself for enabling this robot
secondly doing this helps you to avoid
what jd roth calls the behavior gap
which is the difference between what the
stock market would have made if you just
left it on autopilot and what the
average investor makes because of their
decisions and the example that it gives
is at a 20-year period between 1988 and
2008 where the s p 500 which is
essentially an index that tracks the
entire u.s stock market made a little
bit less than eight and a half percent
return but the average investor made
only about 1.8
a huge gap and actually less than the
rate of inflation now some of that gap
is due to a lot of investors
diversifying their investments which
makes them a bit more secure a bit more
hardened against losses and volatility
but a lot of that gap is due to bad
decisions that were fueled by greed or
by fear or by stupidity and when you
automate your investments you don't
think about the market all the time and
you don't even give yourself the
opportunity to make these dumb decisions
our second book in the personal finance
category is one where i regrettably lost
the book jacket at some point so tony
can you please vfx the image on here for
me this is a random walk down wall
street by burton g mulkel and if you're
interested in investing at all i highly
recommend reading this book now if
you're somebody who just wants a good
investment setup you don't want to think
about it i think the general tips that
are in your money and missing manual and
the videos that i am planning for this
channel are going to be quite adequate
but if you want to understand investing
this is the number one book that i would
recommend he goes into a lot of detail
on how a lot of people even very smart
people often make a lot of mistakes in
the market that will cause them to lose
out on potential gains but the big idea
from this book that i want to share with
you it was actually kind of mind-blowing
to me is just how valuable retirement
accounts can be for growing your money
in the book he sets up a hypothetical
example where 5 000 is invested every
single year for 30 years and after that
period the money that was invested in a
retirement account in either an ira or
401k or another tax advantaged account
grew to 1.4 million dollars whereas the
money that was not invested in a
retirement account was put into a
regular old taxable account only grew to
about 900 thousand dollars so there's a
five hundred thousand dollar potential
earnings gap that is realized simply by
utilizing these retirement vehicles and
that is why personally i do my best to
max out my ira my 401k every single year
and then and only then put money into
taxable investments and why i would
highly recommend you do the exact same
thing unless maybe you're saving for a
short-term big purchase like a down
payment for a house
all right now that i have damaged my
walls from that last book we are now
moving on to the career category and
this is yet another category where i
have two different recommendations for
you and i have a very good reason for
adding two different books into this
category because they are very different
and very useful for uh independent
reasons so the first one that i'm gonna
recommend is pivot by jenny blake and
this is a fantastic book for anybody who
wants to potentially move or change
their careers and this is a super common
thing a lot of people especially after
they've been in their career for three
to five years start to realize hey i
would like to do something different i
kind of don't like what i'm doing right
now and there's these creeping feelings
of guilt right you're like well i spent
all this money and all this time in
college and i'm moving down this career
path i don't want to lose all this
career capital and everything that i've
gained but you have to realize that
wanting to change wanting to move up in
the world is actually a very healthy
thing it means that you have this drive
to learn and to adapt and to grow but
doing so is a strategic endeavor and
this book has a lot of strategy to offer
for that a lot of case studies and my
favorite uh concept in this book is her
idea of doing pilot tests so in the tv
industry executives will order a pilot
episode of a show if they're not quite
sure it's going to do really well so
they're going to get the pilot episode
see how it does and if the audiences
like it then they order an entire season
piloting is essentially a strategy to
invest a little bit of time money of
resources into a potential direction
before going all in on it and the
problem with careers is a lot of people
get fed up with where they are and then
they quit their job and then they don't
really know where to go so instead ask
yourself and jenny talks about this in
the book can i do some little pilot
tests are there little experiments that
i could run in my free time without
giving up everything i have right now
that would allow me to test out a
possible different career shift and see
if it's for me see if i can do it for
example i really like doing stuff in
notion i like teaching people how to use
notion i like to build notion templates
like my task manager template but i'm
not just gonna move on for being a
youtuber number one because i like being
a youtuber but number two because i'm
not sure if making stuff for notion is a
viable career path or for my particular
purposes a viable addition to my
business so i tried some pilot projects
first did a couple of videos on this
channel teaching notion doing some stuff
and those did well and then i started my
second channel thomasfrank explains
that's where i create notion tutorials
and template tutorials and that is now a
little bit of a side business where i've
invested a bit more than i originally
did but i've still not completely
shifted over so if you have something
that you want to do or if you're fed up
with where you currently are in your job
ask yourself how could i pilot a small
change our second book in this career
category is josh kaufman's the personal
mba and i truly do believe that everyone
in their 20s should read this book
because this is a high level overview of
many of the different concepts in
business of sales of marketing a value
creation of how to work with others and
when you understand the fundamental
concepts of business you understand the
goals and motivations of your employer
better and that makes you a higher value
employee so if you want to get a raise
if you want to get a promotion if you
want to get new and more exciting duties
at your job and take on leadership roles
reading a book like this and
understanding the fundamentals of
business can be a very useful thing to
do now the big idea that i want to share
in this video from this book is the
different types of value creation that
he goes through in the book this was
sort of a mind-opening read for me when
i went through this section because a
lot of people don't really understand
value creation if you ask the average
person what are the different methods of
creating value in business they're gonna
answer with two different categories
products and services but as josh
explains in the book there are actually
quite a few more different types of
value creation and if you're somebody
who wants to maybe start a business one
day understanding these and knowing what
they are can be very useful to you so
i'm not going to list all these i'm
going to put them up on the screen here
so you can screenshot them if you want
but i do want to highlight just a few of
them a product is a very obvious one
this book is a product my notion
templates are a product service is also
pretty useful a barber is offering a
service but what about a shared resource
something like disneyland that is
something that people can come and enjoy
but they don't buy it and it's not
really a service in itself also option
was a very interesting one for me and
here's an interesting question what is
the value that a place like planet
fitness gym is offering to its patrons
we might automatically say it's a
service and that is true but i think
that the main value that a planet
fitness especially a big box gym like
that is offering is an option you are
getting the option to do something but
you don't necessarily have to exercise
it so really they're paying for the
optionality not necessarily the service
or the shared resource and that brings
us to the health category where my one
book recommendation for you is dr john
ratey's spark the revolutionary new
science of exercise and the brain and
i'm recommending this book literally for
everyone because this book hammered into
my brain the need for exercise not just
for my body but for my mind as this book
explains an excruciating detail exercise
benefits your focus your creativity it
helps with anxiety it lessens adhd
symptoms if you can believe that it
lessens stress and depression it in
almost every way fathomable helps you
regulate your mental health and this was
very important for me because as an
ambitious entrepreneur with a pretty
computer-based career it has always been
very easy for me to justify skipping
workouts because going to the gym for an
hour or two makes me feel like i'm
putting off the things that i need to
get done but as this book makes
abundantly clear exercising isn't a
waste of time it isn't taking my work
time away from me it's actually a force
multiplier for my work time think about
it i can either choose to work 10 or 12
hours a day skipping all my workouts
probably not sleeping well probably not
eating well and in that case each hour
that i put into my work is probably only
worth about 20 minutes because i'm
spending a lot of it groggy or
procrastinating because i just don't
feel very focused or i can actually get
my workout in i can actually sleep eight
hours i can actually eat a good diet and
if i do that maybe i only have time for
six hours of good work in a day but
every single one of those hours truly is
worth an hour so if i'm taking my health
seriously in general and making sure to
exercise every day specifically the
value of my time the effectiveness of it
has essentially doubled and i don't have
to work as many hours to get the same
amount done and spark is really the book
that helped me to
really take that seriously now if
there's one more piece of advice i can
give you here it's that not all these
books may be ones that you need to read
right now even if you are in your 20s
really the main thing that you and
pretty much everything else should be
prioritizing above all other skills is
thinking critically especially with
respect to your goals so if you have a
goal that is aligned with one of these
five categories we just went through
then maybe it is worth picking up one of
these books and if you want to improve
your ability to think critically which
is incredibly important then this video
sponsor brilliant has a brand new logic
course that you should check out
learning to think logically and to do
things like analyzing worst-case
scenarios and dealing with unknown
information these are skills that will
help you in nearly every area of your
career and your life and brilliance
logic course in particular teaches you
these concepts in a completely
interactive problem-based approach that
makes the learning process a lot more
fun and a lot more effective they also
use this exact same strategy for all
their other courses as well which can
help you master math science and
computer science in the library you're
going to find a full math suite ranging
from number theory to advanced calculus
along with science and computer science
courses tackling everything from
electricity and magnetism to machine
learning so if you want to start
improving your critical thinking skills
and start learning on brilliant you can
go over to brilliant.org thomasfrank or
click that link right there to sign up
and that link is going to get you 20 off
their annual premium subscription if
you're looking for something else to
watch i've got a video right there on
james clare's atomic habits another
amazing book and that video goes through
three of the biggest lessons in it or
perhaps you're curious about how i
actually make my videos well i've got a
full breakdown on my second channel
which you can watch right there beyond
that hit the like button for the
algorithm follow me on twitter for bite
size content and i want to know in the
comments down below what is the number
one book that you recommend for people
in their 20s or for people in general
thanks for watching and i will see you
in the next one