I'm going to be honest I am not a
particular fan of sleep as a pretty
ambitious guy with a lot of ideas a
to-do list about a million miles long
and nowhere near 1 thousand hours in
OverWatch yet I get pretty frustrated
every time I realize that I have to
spend a third of every single day asleep
but just like a car needs regular oil
changes to keep running smoothly our
bodies need lots of good highquality
sleep to function properly getting good
sleep not only rebuilds muscle regulates
metabolism and helps you keep focused
but it's also an integral part of the
learning process so with that in mind
today I want to give you some tips that
can help to improve the quality of your
sleep and help you fall asleep faster to
start out we have to talk about one of
my absolute favorite substances in the
world which is coffee or more
particularly the caffeine in that coffee
because caffeine can actually disrupt
your sleep quite a bit and the important
thing to note here is that caffeine
doesn't just disrupt your sleep if you
take it right before bed in fact a 2013
study published in the journal of
clinical sleep medicine found that
caffeine can actually disrupt your sleep
even if it's taken six hours before bed
so the takeaway here is if you're going
to drink caffeine whether it's coffee or
whether it's tea if you're drinking
those Monster energy drinks you should
probably just quit those alt together
but with coffee and tea take those in
the morning let them give you a little
brain boost but then cut the caffeine
well before your bedtime if you want to
sleep well tip number two is to do your
exercising a little earlier in the day
and the reason you should do this is
that exercise both raises your core body
temperature and places a mild amount of
stress on your central nervous system
and both of these things can make it a
little more difficult to get to sleep so
if you feel like it's taking you longer
to get to sleep at night than it should
and you happen to do your workouts or
some form of exercise near bedtime try
shifting that to earlier in the day all
right for the next tip here we got to
talk about your phone and more
specifically the light that your phone
emits smartphone screens computer
screens TV screens all these different
screens that we spend all hours of the
day staring at all emit high
concentrations of what's called short
wavelength enriched light AKA blue light
and that can be a problem because that
blue light can actually play Havoc with
your sleep schedule if you're seeing it
late at night not during daylight hours
and that is because your eyes contain
what are called and brace yourself
because this is a bit of a mouthful
photoreceptive retinol ganglion cells
and when light hits these cells your
body clamps down on the secretion of a
hormone called melatonin which is
helpful in inducing sleep now this
biological mechanism works great during
the daylight hours because it keeps your
sleep schedule in sync with the day
night cycle but once the sun goes down
and then you go inside and keep looking
at all these screens to keep throwing
tons of light in your face all night it
can screw up your sleep cycle and blue
light in particular has an especially
powerful effect at clamping down on your
body's melatonin secretion so what can
you do about this problem well number
one the simplest solution is to turn
your screens off and this is something
that I've been adopting in my own life
because at 900 p.m. every single night I
make sure that this computer behind me
is turned off for the night and that's
about an hour and a half before bed now
if you just don't want to turn your
screens off or if you quite reasonably
want to watch a TV show before going to
bed or you want to check your phone
there are some apps you can use to cut
down on that amount of blue light for
both Mac and PC as well as you Linux
users there's an app called flux that
I've been using for quite a long time
which basically just Alters the color
profile of your computer screen to make
it a lot warmer and it makes it cut down
on a lot of that blue light if you have
an iPhone there's actually a built-in
feature called night shift that does
this exact same thing and you can set it
to turn on at a specific time of night
and then turn back off in the morning if
you're an Android User you don't benefit
from having that built into the OS but
there is an app called Twilight that
basically does the exact same thing the
other solution which I haven't
personally tried myself but when I think
about it seems like it would be the best
one is to buy yourself a pair of blue
light blocking glasses now these look
basically like your average
run-of-the-mill safety glasses you can
get them off Amazon for about eight
bucks but the benefit with these is they
block all blue light not just the blue
light from your screens which is
beneficial when you're looking at lots
of artificial Lighting in your house at
Night Tip number four pertains to any of
you guys who have alarm clocks in your
room that you can see from your bed and
the tip is to turn those alarm clocks
away from yourself so you can't see the
time one of the weird kind of
counterintuitive facts about sleep is
that we actually wake up several times
during the night at least to a degree
due to the nature of how the Sleep Cycle
Works we go through different stages of
deep and shallow sleep and at that first
stage a lot of us actually briefly wake
up or in a semi- woken state but some
people wake up fully and if you're one
of those people who finds themselves
awake in the middle of the night and
having trouble getting back to sleep
seeing the time you have remaining
before you actually have to wake up for
work or class or whatever can cause a
lot of stress which makes it even harder
to go back to sleep the last thing we
have to talk about is improving your
sleep environment and that evolves your
bed itself the amount of light in your
room The Sounds the odors the
temperature a lot of different factors
so we're going to briefly go through a
few of them here and while we do that
for each one ask yourself if you could
be making any improvements so first up
let's talk about your pillow couple of
things about pillows number one you want
to replace yours every couple of years
both because it breaks down over time
and gets less supportive but also
because every night you're sleeping on
it you're kind of injecting that pillow
with lots of dirt and germs and body
odor and stuff that makes it gross which
can make it harder to fall asleep
secondly and this was news to me until
just recently there are different kinds
of pillows for different kinds of
Sleepers for example I am a sid sleeper
and for years I was just using like the
most non-supportive awful pillows until
I learned that a sid sleeper probably is
going to need a firmer pillow that has
these gussets on the side of it instead
of just the two pieces of fabric that
are stapled directly together and after
sleeping on this thing for about a week
now I can tell you it is a lot better
than the stuff I was using before when
it comes to the temperature in your room
cooler is better and according to the
National sleep Foundation the optimal
temperature range for sleeping is
somewhere between 60° F and 67° F the
amount of light in your room or should I
say lack of light plays a big role as
well because pitch Darkness actually
plays a big role in melatonin secretion
so if you have a lot of ambient light
coming into your room from like a street
light outside your apartment you can
pick up a blackout curtain which will
basically eliminate that light all
together actually got one right there
that I use for filming also if you
happen to fall asleep with the TV on you
should probably try to break that habit
because well blue light now if you're
one of those people who thinks that the
TV is soothing and they just can't fall
asleep without it there are some
sound-based Alternatives and actually
silence really isn't the optimal
solution for all people because silence
is so often inconsistent there's a bump
in the night or there's a voice in the
other room or there's somebody snoring
in the same room as you so having some
sound that can block out those
inconsistencies can really help you fall
asleep one option you can check out is
ambient noise generators which can
generate both White Noise which is
basically just consistent noise that
sounds a little bit like an air
conditioner and ambient noises like rain
and thunder and for me my favorite one
is nois Le because you can add as many
as you want you can change the volume of
each one and basically create the
perfect mix for you there's also lots of
music out there that's good for falling
asleep too I've made a playlist of my
own and found several on Spotify and
I'll link to those down below but my
favorite way to fall asleep is with
audiobooks for me at least there is
nothing better to fall asleep to than
spoken word and in fact ever since I
discovered audiobooks back when I was
probably 12 or 13 all the way up until I
graduated high school and got a roommate
in college I would fall asleep every
single night to either Ender Game by
oron Scott card or The Hitchhiker's
Guide of the Galaxy by Douglas Adams and
as a result I have huge swaths of both
of those books basically memorized now
if you'd like to listen to those books
yourself the absolute best place to get
them is audible Audible has an unmatched
library of audiobooks spanning just
about every genre you could think of and
they also have have an excellent app
that does include a sleep timer I've
been using audible ever since I was a
high school student and I don't just use
it for sleep I also use it when I'm
driving when I'm cooking when I'm
folding laundry basically anytime where
I'm doing a task that doesn't involve a
whole lot of mental activity I like to
listen to an audiobook because it
basically lets me double my productivity
during those times now if you'd like to
give audible a try you can get a free
30-day trial by going to audible.com
Thomas which is linked in the
description down below and that trial
includes a free audiobook of your
choosing that's yours to keep forever
whether you decide to subscribe or not
if you're looking for a recommendation
one of the best books that I finished
recently was deep work by Cal Newport
which is all about how to resist
distractions and cultivate an ability to
work intensely for long periods of time
it is easily the book that made the
biggest impact of my life last year and
you can start listening to it today by
checking out that link in the
description down below I want to give a
big thank you to Audible for sponsoring
this video and thank you for watching
and supporting this channel if you
haven't subscribed yet you want to get
new videos and learning and working more
productively you can click right there
to do so and you can click right over
there to find a video that you'll
probably find interesting as well thanks
for watching and I'll will see you in
the next one