so my dad once taught me a lesson that i
will never forget i was probably 12 or
13 at the time and it was a saturday
morning i was down in the basement with
my brother my dad and my dad had built
an entire gym down there and he had us
work out with him most saturdays we also
had to work out a few times a week he
was kind of a strict dad and he made us
lift weights but i remember that
saturday morning i was telling him dad
i'm not really feeling into it today i
feel like i'm having an off day and
i'll never forget what he said to me he
said sometimes
you have an off day and then you hit a
personal record anyway so don't give me
that bad attitude
do your warm-up sets and let's get going
now around this time i had been lifting
for maybe a year it was pretty casual
but i was struggling with the first big
milestone that a lot of people have when
they're lifting weights which is bench
pressing 135 pounds that's the big 45
pound plate on each side of the bar i
had tried to hit it a few different
times failed each time i had this i
guess mental block really but i thought
i couldn't hit it so i was warming up i
was working up to what i thought was
gonna be my working set and my dad said
thomas i want you to go into a different
room i'm gonna put weights on the bar
and i don't want you to look at what's
on the bar so i go out of the room and
then i come back a few seconds later and
at a little glance couldn't help but
look a little bit i realized that
there's a ton of random weights in the
bar a bunch of little 2.5 5 pounders 10
pounders but i can't tell what's in the
bar i get under it he unracks it for me
i hit one rep put it right back and he
says congratulations you just hit 135
pounds on the day
that i had told my dad hey it's an off
day i don't think i'm gonna do well i
did in fact hit that personal record and
that i think is the best possible
illustration that i could have ever
gotten for the lesson he was trying to
teach me some days you think you're
having an off day and then you hit a pr
anyway and i have now reinterpreted that
to realize that some days you think
you're having an off day but you really
aren't what is happening instead is you
have not yet given your body and your
mind time to properly warm up to get
ready
for the challenge that you are throwing
yourself into and when you do you can
take what feels like an off day and turn
it into a day where you perform your
absolute peak and that is because there
is a two-way relationship between your
perception of your capabilities your
perception of how you're feeling and the
actions you actually take and
unfortunately a lot of people think that
this road is actually a one-way road
where i perceive that i have a certain
level of energy today and they let that
dictate the actions they take in reality
that road is two-way and when you spend
some time getting into the flow of
things spend some time if you're a
writer just writing gibberish on a page
that you know is going to be garbage or
if you're a lifter spend some time
actually doing warm-up sets like you're
supposed to
sometimes the actions you take
get you into a different frame of mind
and it's not just a cerebral change it's
not just oh i guess i was actually
capable of more than i thought i was
today
it's a more emotional change too you
start to feel better you feel more
capable because of the actions you took
it is a two-way road between how you
feel and how you act now some days you
really are having an off day some days
you're sick some days you just aren't
feeling it and that's okay but i truly
believe at least for me but you as well
that more than 50 of the time you think
you're having an off day it's just a day
where you have not yet warmed up enough
so let me now talk a little bit about
the art of warming up i want to share
two principles that will help you warm
up more intelligently and more
successfully for whatever it is you're
trying to do number one stop trying to
perform during your warm-ups this is
something that i have to remind myself
of all the time when i get into the gym
and right now the working set that i'm
working on right now is three reps of
275 so i've got several different
warm-up sets that i'm gonna do before i
get up to that and when i'm doing those
warm-ups i often go through this little
mental exercise where i first think why
not get a little bit of extra work while
i'm doing the warm-ups huh so i'll throw
the 135 on there and i'll be tempted to
do like 20 reps but that's not the point
of the warm-up sense the point isn't to
perform there the point is to simply get
your body warmed up and in exercise
science there's this principle of
effective reps if you do a set of 10
squats say maybe only the last three
reps are effective they are actually
challenging you and causing your body to
prompt a growth response in your muscles
the other reps are just sort of getting
you to that effective rep range you
shouldn't be using your warm-up sets to
try to generate effective reps and the
same thing applies to non-physical work
if i sit down to write and i realize
that i'm not in a writing mood and i
need to warm up i shouldn't be trying to
edit my writing right away that's a big
principle for writing or for art or any
kind of creative work when you're
warming up when you're trying to get
into the flow state turn off that
editing brain just let yourself get
whatever's in your head onto the page
even if it is complete garbage and you
know it because the point isn't to
perform during the warm-up the point is
to warm up the second principle that i
want to share for you that will make
your warmups more successful is to give
yourself the time you need to warm up a
lot of us have more off days than we
would like to because what we're doing
is shoving our day full of so many
different tasks and schedule activities
that we have this anxiety that we're not
going to be able to perform in them
because we have to do this and then go
to this and then go to this and i'm
guilty of this as well even though i've
talked about rule of three and all kinds
of principles around giving yourself the
time to do a proper job i'm still guilty
of thinking i can shove just one or two
more things onto the to-do list for the
day a little bit of compression with
your schedule is good but if there's not
time to warm up you're not going to be
able to do it you need some time to warm
up so schedule less in your day and give
each task the time it properly needs for
you to get into the flow state and then
for you to perform you need a little bit
more time to properly carry out the task
but most importantly when you feel like
you're having an off day ask yourself
have i warmed up have i given myself
that opportunity because if you haven't
then there is a high probability that
this actually isn't an off day and you
have the potential to turn it around if
today is feeling like an on day you're
looking for a creative outlet for your
energy and a way to become a more
innovative and capable problem solver
than you my friend should check out
brilliant who have kindly sponsored
today's video brilliant is learning
library for math science and computer
science if you want to increase your
expertise in any of these areas
brilliant is an absolutely amazing
resource to check out they have more
than 60 in-depth courses covering things
like number theory calculus probability
statistics algorithm fundamentals data
structures even a course on how to build
your own search engine and understand
how the big search engines like google
work and the great thing about brilliant
is that unlike sitting in a lecture or
reading a book you are engaged actively
the entire time you go through one of
their courses because active learning is
their central tenet for designing all
their materials which means that as
you're going through their courses
you're going to find yourself engaged in
interactive and challenging problems
that you have to solve you are in the
driver's seat you have to warm up a bit
and get into that learning state of mind
and if you're ready to do that you can
go over to brilliant.org thomasfrank or
click right there and be one of the
first 200 people to do so to get 20
off their annual premium subscription
thanks as always for watching thanks for
brilliant for sponsoring and being a big
supporter of my channel hopefully you
found this video helpful if you did hit
that like button for ye old algorithm
and i'll have a couple of other videos
on screen if you want to check those out
today but
if you feel like today has been an off
day so far and you feel like you haven't
warmed up yet go do that and then go do
whatever it is you're supposed to be
doing see the next one