this is a flashcard more specifically
it's a bad flashcard and by the end of
this video you're gonna understand
exactly why because today we are talking
about how to make effective flashcards
and how to study them more efficiently
now flashcards are an incredibly
powerful learning tool because they
promote active recall the process of
actively retrieving memories out of your
brain which is one of the most efficient
learning strategies there are but
flashcards are tools made by human
beings and as you probably know things
made by humans come in varying degrees
of quality for example my girlfriend's
art versus my art however when we go
into the making of a thing with the best
practices in mind we can come out with a
better product and in today's video I'm
gonna give you eight specific rules for
both making better flashcards and for
studying them more effectively now for
the purposes of this video I figured I
would need some flashcards of my own to
use as examples so I've gone ahead and
issued myself a challenge and that is to
learn and memorize the entire periodic
table of elements because believe it or
not I actually never took chemistry in
high school and a really busy schedule
with other classes at the time and just
never got to it so I've gone ahead and
started making some flashcards which I
will be using in the course of this
challenge and we're gonna use these to
demonstrate the elements of good
flashcards but first we have to start
with a more general tip which is to
simply make your own flashcards I know a
lot of people like to share their
flashcards with their friends and for
people who study flashcards on computers
or on apps there are entire online
communities where you can upload and
download pre-made decks and I think
these have their uses in certain cases
but in most cases it's gonna be much
more effective for you to make your own
flashcards one of the most integral and
important parts of learning is the
process of in taking information and
really wrangling with it on your own and
creating your own words and your own
forms out of that information that's
gonna build really strong neural
pathways and those are gonna be unique
from the neural pathways of somebody
else and if you just take pre-made cards
made by somebody else that you didn't
have to do any work to create you're
denying yourself that entire part of
learning process so now that you know
the importance of making your cards
yourself let's get into the actual
nitty-gritty of what makes a card good
and the first tip I've got for you is to
add pictures to your cards and to mix
them up with words now in cognitive
psychology there's a principle called
the picture superiority effect which
describes how people remember images and
pictures much better than they do words
and from an evolutionary standpoint this
makes sense written language is just a
system of arbitrary symbols that people
made up and when we look at things on a
grand scale it really hasn't been around
for all that long plus our brains are
adapted to be very sensitive to imagery
the locations of food the animals
they'll think your food the animals that
will take your food but it'll still
completely mess you up
etc by adding pictures to your flash
cards you can make them a lot more
memorable and personally I like to do
this by drawing on my flash cards but
you can also just print out pictures
from the internet and glue them on or if
you're using an app or a computerized
flash card program a lot of them will
allow you to easily import pictures but
you can take this one step further by
making sure those pictures are next to
words
in 1985 there's a study done in Canada
that showed that descriptive sentences
added next to pictures made those
pictures much easier for people to
recall now if you take a look at my
chemistry flashcards here you might
think they look a little bit weird but
that's actually on purpose because
they're demonstrated the third tip I've
got for you which is to use mnemonic
devices on your flashcards now a
mnemonic device is really anything that
helps you create associations between
pieces of information in your mind a
classic one is the acronym Rosie Biff
which helps you remember the order of
the colors in the visible light spectrum
but it can really be anything and I'm
using associative imagery on my
flashcards for example my flash card for
magnesium has a Magnemite asking for
more goulash which is a completely
ridiculous picture but it helps me
remember the association between mg and
magnesium because Magnemite sounds like
magnesium and more goulash is a good way
to remember mg now the more weird and
crazy and wacky these pictures are the
more easily you're gonna remember them
and remember you're making your
flashcards for yourself so it doesn't
matter what anyone else thinks of them
or whether or not those associations
would work for someone else it's just
for you so the next two tips have got
for you guys really go hand in hand and
the first one is to have only one
question or fact on each one of your
flashcards now doing this is going to
help you avoid what are called illusions
of competence basically our brains can
really easily confuse recognition with
recall when you recognize something
you're basically affirming to yourself
that yes I've seen this or I've been
exposed to it before but recall is
different recall is actively retrieving
something out of memory without again
being exposed to it and our brains can
really confuse these things if we're not
careful so here's an example say you're
taking a history of flight class because
obviously airplanes are off
and now you're studying for a test where
you need to know some information about
the first airplane the Wright Flyer so
you make yourself a flashcard you put
the first airplane on the front but then
on the back you put several different
facts and here's where you can run into
trouble because later on and you're
studying and you see first airplane you
might remember that it flew in 1903 you
might remember that it was called the
Wright Flyer and you might even remember
that it flew four times but maybe you
forgot that it used a sprocket chain
drive to drive the propellers and then
you turn it over and you say to yourself
oh yeah I do remember that and then you
put it aside so by making four
individual cards for each of these facts
you're guaranteeing that you're getting
each one either right or wrong and
that's gonna help you to study the ones
you got wrong more efficiently and avoid
those illusions of competence now on a
related note we have the fifth tip here
which is to break complex concepts or
questions down into simpler questions
and you can run into a lot of situations
like this one where say you're trying to
learn the different groupings of
elements on the periodic table and
there's lots them there's two alkali
metals the transition metals there's the
noble gases so maybe you go and make a
flash card like this where all these
groupings are a different color and you
have to name all of them well once again
this is a bad flash card because maybe
you know some of those groupings maybe
you know all but one but that one
grouping you didn't know there's gonna
be an illusion of competence and you're
gonna think that you knew it just by
looking at the listing on the back so
instead make flashcards like this that
only highlight one of those groupings
and make sure that you know it before
putting that flashcard aside so now that
you guys know some of the best practices
for making your flashcards it's now time
to move over and how to study them and
I've got three really important tips in
this section of the video for you guys
starting with the first one which is to
say your answers out loud when you're
studying your flashcards and this is
kind of just a way to mentally commit to
your answer before you actually look at
the back of the card which helps you
again avoid those illusions of
competence it helps you make sure that
you're not recognizing the answer and
mistaking that recognition for recall
make sure that you actually know the
answer now the second tip here is to
make sure you study your cards from both
sides and this is a way of creating a
neural pathways in your brain that work
in both directions so that way if you're
asked either side of a question you'll
be able to trace that neural pathway
back to the answer for example if you
only studied the chemical symbol de and
you knew that it stood for beryllium but
then you were later on asked what's the
chemical symbol for beryllium you might
not be able to get back
be if you didn't study the cards in both
directions so make sure you do and
lastly guys my final tip for you here is
to realize that flashcards are not a
silver bullet they're just one method of
reviewing material and they are
situational they're just like say a bow
and arrow right you wouldn't use a bow
and arrow in every single situation you
wouldn't use it up close no matter how
good of a Hanzo player you think you are
and flashcards are the exact same way
you have to know the right situations to
use them in a lot of information ties
into an overall visual hierarchy or an
organization and with flashcards you
kind of lose that for instance the
periodic table is a really really
powerful visual tool and if you were to
say try to memorize all the atomic
numbers the elements with flashcards
you'd really be doing your brain a
disservice because learning the periodic
table and all the visual representations
and and relationships is much more
effective also make sure that you're
learning before you're reviewing because
flashcards often aren't the best tool
for teaching you the underlying concepts
which may help you learn facts much more
efficiently so those are my eight tips
for improving the way that you make and
study flashcards and right now you might
be thinking to yourself wait a minute
Tom skip something and yes I did because
there is one additional incredibly
effective technique for learning and
studying that goes hand in hand with
flashcards and that is spaced repetition
but that's such a complex topic and I
really want to dig deep into it and
teach you guys the science behind it and
how to use it effectively both on paper
and with apps so that is gonna be the
subject of next week's video until then
guys thank you so much for watching and
if you've got additional tips about
flashcards I would love to hear them
down in the comments below also if you
enjoyed this video and you found it
helpful give it a like to support this
channel and you want to get new videos
on being a more effective student every
single week you can click that big red
subscribe button right down there if you
want to get a free copy of my book on
earning better grades you can click the
picture of the book right there and if
you missed last week's video it was on
having a more productive summer so check
it out right there to find the full
article for this video with lots of
links and resources and cool extra
details right over there and if you want
to connect with me go out into the
forest and tune into one of those creepy
number stations and listen
my lips don't actually do that