this video is sponsored by
curiositystream and nebula
so in the movie ratatouille there's the
scene where the villain chef skinner
tries to pry linguine for information
about
zarat and to do it he uses one of the
oldest and most obvious persuasion
tactics in the book
it gets them drunk and unfortunately for
chef skinner this does not work he
wastes the entire bottle of wine and
learns basically nothing
so perhaps instead of using alcohol he
should have used one of the more
successful and subtle persuasion tactics
that have been used for thousands of
years
to successfully persuade people to buy
things to go along with ideas
so that is what we're going to talk
about in this video we're going to go
over five of the most common and most
successful persuasion tactics that you
and i and basically everyone else in the
world are exposed to on a daily basis
now i've been running my own business
for 10 years so i have some personal
experience with persuasion tactics but
the insights in this video are going to
come from a much more authoritative and
thorough source
which is robert shielding his book
influence the psychology of persuasion
this has long been considered one of the
pun intended most influential books on
the science of persuasion so it's a
great read if you're looking to dig into
more detail on this topic
but in this video we're going to keep it
short and sweet we're going to go over
these five persuasion tactics and we're
also gonna talk about how to
defend against them or at least to
realize their influence
on you so when making a decision you can
divorce the merit of the message from
the persuasion tactics
that are being used so with all that
said let's get into our first one which
is called commitment
and consistency as human beings we have
this natural tendency to act
consistently with our past actions and
with what we've said in the past
and this makes perfect sense we want
people to act consistently on an
unconscious level
so we can trust them so this is really a
good thing at its core
but people can also exploit it so for
example i just got this sticker in the
mail as part of a swag package for an
online course that i'm taking and if
you've ever bought an apple product you
will know that you get an
apple sticker very similar to this one
in the box with the phone or the
computer that you've bought
and apple's not putting that sticker in
there just because they're trying to be
nice
trying to give you something for free
they're hoping that you put that sticker
on something you own i've seen people
put it on their cars on their laptops
and all kinds of stuff maybe even their
baby's forehead i don't know
but when you put a sticker on something
you own it's almost the same thing as
writing out a statement that i am an
apple person and when you've made a
public commitment like that you are much
more likely to act in accordance with
that commitment with your future
decisions this is also why you see a lot
of what are called tripwire products
these are products that are very very
cheap they're very
easy sales to make and what they do is
they turn you from
being a prospect into a customer and
it's this
little commitment you have to make maybe
it's a dollar purchase within an online
game like fortnite or a mobile app or
something like that
but it makes this mental shift happen it
changes your self-identity you go from
being a prospect
to a customer who is now more likely to
make bigger purchases
in the future so the defense here is to
realize that when somebody is offering
you a small gift or a favor or there's a
free trial or really really cheap offer
it is more likely than not going to be
something that is designed to get you to
make commitment and that commitment
is going to make you more likely to pay
big bucks for their bigger offerings
down the line
this doesn't mean you shouldn't take
these offerings but you should keep this
in mind when the next
pitch comes the second manipulation
tactic we're going to talk about
also preys upon one of our natural
tendencies and that is reciprocity
as humans we have this natural
inclination to repay
favors or repay small gifts that have
been given to us there's this great book
called debt the first five thousand
years by david graber and he argues that
basically everyone is always in debt to
each other you do a small favor for me
i do something for you and it's almost
always out of balance money actually
kind of muddies up the situation because
it allows us to sort of wipe out
the the debt and the ledger and that can
actually allow relationships to be
broken up
in pre-money societies everyone's just
kind of lending each other things
borrowing things everyone's always in
some amount of debt to one another
but we never really know where we all
stand but what we do know
is that we should reciprocate when
somebody does us a favor or gives us
a gift this is a good thing but again it
is vulnerable to exploitation by people
who have something to sell by people who
want to manipulate our emotions
for their own gain for example if you've
ever gone to a car dealership you will
know that one of the first things they
do
is offer you free coffee or free water
they are not a coffee shop but they
gladly do it
because it results in a lot more profit
when it actually comes down to the sale
and the reciprocity principle in our
minds is not
naturally uh even we don't think oh i
now owe that guy
a cup of coffee we're just gonna feel
indebted and feel like we should pay
them back
so what it's gonna make you more likely
to do is actually get in a car and take
a test drive if they offer one and if
you are ready to buy
you're going to be less likely to
negotiate hard when it comes to the
price
and more likely to just say yes when
they pitch you services like
expensive warranties and because of this
they come out way ahead
to the reciprocity principle and it
should be noted that in the ratatouille
scene chef skinner tries to use this as
well
giving him free wine and it's not
inexpensive wine either it's some pretty
great wine
unfortunately for him it doesn't work
and hopefully for the next car salesman
that you talk to
it doesn't work too well for them as
well because you want to learn how to
defend
against this and here's how you do it
number one realize that if somebody's
offering you a favor or a free gift and
it's in
a sales or a marketing context they're
probably trying to play on
our natural tendency to reciprocate so
be wary of that
and number two realize that a small gift
is often being leveraged
to get you to give something much much
bigger in return
another tactic that you really want to
learn how to defend against is the
exploitation of social
proof as humans that live in complex
societies we know
unconsciously that we often can't rely
on our animal instincts or our personal
knowledge alone to know what to do
in certain situations so we often look
at social cues we look at what other
people are doing
to guide our decisions if you've ever
been in a concert and you've looked at
where other people are lining up to get
in to figure out where you should stand
then you have benefited from social
proof but again
this is a concept that is open to
manipulation you've probably seen
commercials with
testimonial videos from people who are
just like you
but what you often don't see is very
small fine print text at the bottom of
the screen saying that they are paid
actors
and it often goes way further than that
marketers that don't have
an ethical bone in their body will often
make up fake testimonials and just put
stock photos right next to them
i know this because it's somebody who
designed websites for a long time
i often went through stock photo
websites trying to find photos for
clients
and later on in life i would see sales
pages with stock photos next to their
testimonials and i'd say hey i actually
recognized that photo
that's from a stock photo website so
people will often
straight up lie to try to engage this
social proof that we are manipulated
by and even when it's real you still
have to be skeptical
only happy customers tend to write
testimonials and in many cases customers
can be incentivized to write
testimonials so whenever you're looking
at an instance of social proof that's
trying to sway your decision making when
it comes to a product
or an idea or whatever it is ask
yourself what is the incentive for
number one this person to say what
they've said
and for number two for me to even be
able to see it in the first place why
was it placed
on this sales page it doesn't mean that
the product isn't worth your time but
again you want to force
the merit of the message the actual
factors that go into your decision that
will affect your life
from the social proof elements and in
many cases you may want to also seek out
dissenting voices or at least more
critical voices less biased sources
reviews on third-party websites that
don't use affiliate links that kind of
thing
and going back to the ratatouille
example chef skinner does use some
elements of social proof on linguine as
well here when he pours the wine he says
you
have to be an idiot of elephantine
proportions not to enjoy this particular
wine which is
mostly using the next tactic we're going
to talk about but it does have some
elements of social proof in there as
well
i like this wine everyone likes this
wine you would have to be an idiot not
to enjoy this wine
but mostly what he's engaging here is
our fourth tactic which is
authority now i live in the united
states and in western culture we have
this very individualistic nature and we
like to think
that we have contempt for authority and
we make our own decisions independently
but
the reality often couldn't be further
from the truth we defer to sources of
authority
all the time and use them to aid our
decision making
this happens from the moment we're born
we have to we have no choice
but to defer to our parental figures for
not only physical
care but also for you know helping us
make decisions and stopping us from
doing stupid stuff like putting our
fingers into outlets
and as adults we also defer to figures
of authority all the time we refer to
our doctor's authority we trust cooks at
restaurants to cook our food to a safe
temperature and not ruin it because none
of us is an expert
on everything so we have to put trust in
other people
to help us live the lives we want to
live but the problem is
authority is very easy to exploit
because we usually place trust
in the symbols of authority not in the
substance
this book has a lot of citations to
psychological research and peer-reviewed
journals to back up its claims
there's a lot of authority here but when
we make decisions on a daily basis we
often aren't looking for this substance
instead we unconsciously place trust in
the symbols
of authority and those are much easier
to fake we place trust in confidence
we place trust in labels we even place
trust in the way people dress
this outfit communicates something that
the previous one didn't so if someone's
trying to convince you that they know
how to make a lot of money or that they
have a lot of business experience
they're probably going to be wearing
something like this
maybe even filming their video inside of
a bentley because that establishes
a certain amount of authority and this
effect is even more powerful when it
comes to occupation-specific
attire take for example the classic
white lab coat
if you've ever seen a commercial for a
weight loss supplement you're almost
always going to see a doctor on screen
talking about how great that medication
is and they're wearing that lab coat
and it says they're a doctor and in many
cases yeah they're a doctor but they're
a doctor with a completely different
specialization or
they maybe have the relevant
qualifications to talk about weight loss
but they're being paid to endorse this
medication
so how can you defend against implicitly
placing trust in figures of authority
well it's really twofold number one
learn to recognize when the symbols of
authority are really doing the heavy
lifting and the substance
is not many times the symbols can be
faked they can be easily gained
qualifications are easy putting on a
suit is easy but real authority with
real substance
that takes a lot more work secondly even
when the authority source is legit
ask yourself is this person using their
authority
in my best interests or are they using
it for their own personal gain
from there you can divorce the authority
again from the merit of the actual
message and make a better decision just
like linguine did when he did not reveal
any information about
zarat to skinner i don't think this was
a conscious decision on his part he was
a little tipsy in that scene
but it is absolutely true that skinner
was trying to use authority as part of
his manipulation
this was established from the get-go in
the movie he's got this fancy office
with all these symbols of authority
in it and in this interaction he uses it
to imbue the wine that he's offering
linguine
with a bit more legitimacy but really
what he's using here is the final tactic
that we're going to talk about which is
liking in this scene skinner is trying
to get linguine to like him he is
complimenting him which is very
uncharacteristic for skinner he's giving
him free wine he's saying
let's toast to your non-idiocy
everything he's doing here
is an attempt to establish rapport to
establish a relationship because
we are more likely to comply with
requests from people
that we like but you have to recognize
that likability is another area that is
ripe
for exploitation let's go back to the
car dealership example
the moment you walk into that dealership
the car salesman is going to try to get
you
to like him he's going to shake your
hand he's going to compliment you
he's going to ask you about your
interests he may just so happen to have
the same favorite sports team or same
favorite movie
that you have this is all an attempt to
get you to like him and to build rapport
so you're more likely to buy a car from
him so to defend against this
if you notice that you're starting to
like somebody suspiciously quickly in an
interaction
especially one where there might be a
sale on the line
you need to step back and ask yourself
what are this person's incentives for
being so friendly right now
are they truly interested in my life or
are they just trying to get me to like
them so they can close a sale now this
can be
pushed too far if you're always wary of
everyone you're gonna become a
skeptical person and you might find it
hard to make friends and build good
relationships
but a healthy dose of skepticism in this
context is very very useful
now there is one other huge manipulation
tactic that is often used in conjunction
with all the others that we've talked
about in this video and that is the
principle
of scarcity the less abundant something
is the rarer it is the more we
inherently value it
and want it and marketers love
exploiting this
so if you'd like to see some examples of
scarcity tactics in action and also
learn how to defend against them you'll
find all that in the extended version of
this video on
nebula where that bonus section actually
replaces this ad
because nebula is ad-free we're calling
these extended sections nebula plus
and you're gonna see them in all my new
videos going forward there are places
where i can share
extra details that come up with the
research process but artificial scarcity
can be used to have people make
bigger decisions that often have huge
financial consequences
or make videos that are just too long
for youtube's algorithm
and that really is what nebula is all
about it's a streaming service that i
built with other creators like aaliyah
doll whenever productions
braincraft tierzoo and lots of others
and it gives us the opportunity to
experiment
to try things that just wouldn't work on
youtube or that would get demonetized
and that includes extended versions of
videos yes
but it also includes originals in fact a
great follow-up to this video
and a place where you can start applying
what you've learned here is tom scott's
original game show money which creates a
great opportunity for some creators that
you probably recognize like
mike boyd or sam from
wendoverproductions to try manipulating
each other to win some prize money and
what's even better is that we've teamed
up with curiositystream which is the
go-to resource for the best
documentaries on the internet the team
over at curiositystream absolutely loves
supporting educational content so we got
together and we formed a deal where when
you go to curiosity stream use link in
the description down below and you sign
up
you get access to nebula for free and
here's a relatively harmless example of
scarcity in action
right now curiosity stream is running a
sale for earth day where when you go to
curiositystream.com
thomas you can get a full year of both
curiosity stream and nebula
for less than 12 dollars that's a
whopping 41
off and once you're in you could have
access to some of the best documentaries
on the internet from people like david
attenborough
sigourney weaver and my home's actual
patron saint
nick offerman so again if you use that
link down in the description to sign up
you're going to get a full year of both
curiosity stream and nebula all the
ad-free videos extended sections
originals
for 41 off or you can go to
curiositystream.com
thomas to get that same landing page
doing so is a great way to support both
my channel and educational content in
general so if you do
thank you so to wrap up i do have one
question for you what is your best
real world example that you've
experienced of one of these manipulation
tactics
in action leave your answer down in the
comments below and together we can all
learn and become a little bit more
perceptive
beyond that i've got a playlist of
additional videos on decision making
that you can check out right here if you
want some extra content to watch
subscribe there or do literally none of
that and go do anything you want because
as always i'm not your dad