so you've probably heard about mnemonics
at some point in your life
if you haven't they're basically mental
devices that allow you to access hard to
remember information
in a sort of roundabout way take the
acronym roy g biv
for example this silly sounding name
allows us to easily remember the order
of the colors in the visible light
spectrum
red orange yellow green blue indigo
and violet our brains aren't really
wired in way that makes remembering the
order of arbitrary words easy
but they do easily latch onto silly
sounding names
so essentially this acronym provides a
pathway to a specific piece of
information
information that does exist in your
brain even if it's hard to access
directly but building these sorts of
mental pathways isn't just useful for
accessing information that's already up
in your head
you can also build them to easily access
information that you
don't know and in doing so you can
greatly expand your brain's capabilities
someone who understood this concept
exceptionally well was henry iv
i have row of electric push buttons on
my desk he once said
and by pushing the right button i can
summon to my aid men who can answer any
question i desire concerning the
business which i am devoting most of my
efforts
in other words ford didn't know all the
information that he needed to run his
business himself but he did know how to
quickly get any answer to any question
that
needed now today there are entire
businesses that provide the access to
experts like the ones that fore relied
upon back in his day
they're called expert networks and
actually learned all about them back in
my mis program
in college other businesses like hedge
funds especially
often pay huge sums of money for yearly
subscriptions to these types of networks
but of course we have another tool at
our fingertips which is called google
and what's more
it's free so with such a useful tool at
our fingertips
why even make a video about this well
here's the thing google is
incredibly useful yes but it does have
some limitations the main one being that
it's a search engine which means that it
can only return results based on the
terms that you feed it
and sometimes you don't really know what
you're looking for well enough to give
it
the accurate terms but there's another
problem as well it's the one that i want
to focus on in this video
it's the problem of re-access how many
times have you stumbled across a really
useful article or video only to be
unable to find it again
later it's just like putting new
information up in your brain
if you can't access it again when you
need it then what good is it
fortunately google is not the only tool
out there so today what i want to do is
share some of the other tools and
methods that i use to easily re-access
information think of them as modern day
breadcrumbs to follow except that these
breadcrumbs don't get eaten by birds so
you don't get eaten alive by a witch and
really at the end of the day isn't that
what my entire channel is all about
so since we are on youtube the first one
that i'm gonna mention is youtube
playlists if you go to my channel and
you go to the playlist tab you're gonna
see many publicly available playlists
that i've made of my own videos but
hidden underneath the surface there are
also
dozens of unlisted playlists that i make
for basically any topic that i'm
interested in and with these playlists
i'm able to easily save anything that i
want to access later on so whatever i'm
interested in be it rock climbing or
guitar pedals and signal chains or
making better videos i will make a
playlist for that topic and then i'll
save stuff to it as i come across it
now that feature is useful for anything
on youtube but what about the rest of
the internet
well for that there is pocket and pocket
is basically a browser extension and
also a set of mobile apps that allows
you to save
any web page you want for later reading
and one of the nice things about pocket
is that it's very similar to the reader
mode on the iphone
it actually strips out a lot of the
extraneous elements of the website that
you're on and just gives you a nice
article view which is very distraction
free additionally on their mobile apps
pocket gives you the option of saving
articles for
offline access so anytime i have a
flight i often go and download a lot of
the articles that i've saved for later
reading so i can access them while i'm
on the plane now i know several people
who actually delete articles out of
their pocket once they're done reading
them but that isn't the way that i use
it
essentially for me pocket is a way of
saving anything i come across on the
internet whether i've read it already or
whether i want to access it in
the future it's basically my main way of
laying out these bread crumbs and i
don't worry about keeping things
organized i don't use the tagging
feature very often i don't delete things
i just make very liberal use of that
save the pocket button
in my chrome browser and that way i know
if i find something useful i'm gonna be
able to find it again even if i forget
the search terms that might bring it to
me in a google search
now there is one place in particular on
the internet besides youtube where i
don't tend to use
pocket to save things and that is reddit
i will often save reddit comments
directly to my reddit account
over the past couple years i have found
that reddit is often a better source of
information for certain purposes
than blogs or videos and this is true
for a couple of different reasons first
and foremost reddit like many other
social media sites has a very low
barrier of entry to post people don't
need to buy a camera like they do on
youtube people don't need to learn how
to set up a blog
they just need to make an account and
they can write to their heart's content
and because of this you often get a
larger and much more diverse group of
people sharing their knowledge
plus you usually also get multiple
answers in each thread these are coming
from multiple different voices
and because it has a conversation style
setup reddit encourages discussion
encourages debate and i often find the
best answers several levels deep
nested beneath the original comment so
sometimes this debate is really really
useful now i know that i could easily
save reddit pages to pocket just like
any other article
but usually i'm interested in saving a
specific comment rather than the entire
thread that it's from
and yes i could click the permalink
button and save that in pockets but
usually saving things to my reddit
account makes things easier because
if i'm looking for something in the
future i usually at least know whether
it was from reddit comment or from a
blog post and it was from a reddit
comment i know that i could start from
my profile instead of digging through
pocket
alright so we talked about youtube
playlists pocket and reddit the next one
i want to talk about
is screenshots i take a lot of
screenshots especially when i'm watching
youtube videos
saving an entire video to one of my
playlists can be very useful but
sometimes i just want
one frame for later reference for
example i was recently watching a video
about how to set up a specific order of
guitar pedals
they had this diagram of the signal
chain in the video so i screenshotted
that
in case i need to reference it later on
now basically every computer operating
system out there has a built-in
screenshot program and i am here to tell
you that it is
not good enough that you can do better
so the program that i personally use is
called
green shot it's open source and free on
windows and incredibly full featured and
then it also exists on the mac but it
costs about two bucks and doesn't have
quite as many features though that being
said i still use it just because i like
to use the same programs on
each operating system if i can the main
thing that i like about green shot is
that allows me to set up multiple
destinations for my screenshots for
example i have mine set up to not only
save each screenshot to a specific
folder that's in my google drive so i
can access it from anywhere but it also
saves screenshots to my clipboard so i
can easily paste them into photoshop if
i need them for a video
or i could paste them into notion or
evernote for note-taking purposes
and in addition to that feature i also
like that allows me to set up different
shortcuts for taking a screenshot of the
entire screen as well as also drawing a
box around a specific region that i want
to capture
now green shot is by no means the only
screenshot program out there so if
you're looking for an alternative there
is
share x on windows sketch for mac and
then mono snap for both platforms
and that just leaves us with one more
method that i want to talk about which
is
trusty old notebooks and note taking so
in addition to taking notes on
individual books i'll often create
specific notes and evernote on things
i'm trying to learn
as well and if it's a current interest i
usually bookmark those notes and add
them to my shortcuts bar a few examples
include my japanese notes my after
effects notes which have different
scripts that i use occasionally and
different shortcuts that i like to
reference and can't always remember off
the top of my head
and my notes for my live setup which i'm
trying to build right now which has a
lot of very complicated gear that has to
go in a specific order and aside from
just typing notes i also make extensive
use
of the camera feature in evernote as
well i've got like a specific
configuration of things or anything
where just
a visual reference would make much more
sense than typing things out for a long
period of time
take a picture of it i'll shove it into
evernote and that way i can easily
access it just as i can with
text now the one odd thing about my
evernote setup is that i don't tend to
use the web clipper function which is
essentially this browser extension that
you can use
to save articles and basically anything
you want to your evernote just like you
can
with pocket and i know my friend martin
uses that all the time especially for
things like recipes
but i tend to keep articles and things
like that in pocket
and things that i kind of create myself
in evernote but you kind of have to use
what works
for you now one last way that i made
sure that i can easily re-access
information
is by building a library or rather
several libraries i have a physical one
sitting on the bookshelf behind me
a digital one in my kindle app and
another one made up of
audiobooks now you might think that it'd
be hard to re-access specific
information in an audiobook
that's hours long but that's not a
problem if you're listening through
audible since their app actually lets
you set
specific bookmarks at timestamps and
even add notes to them
audible is also simply the best place to
get audiobooks ranging from the
bestsellers to more obscure titles on
botany and music theory i use audible
almost every single day especially now
that it's warm and i can bike more often
and if you'd like to give it a try as
well you can go over to audible.com
thomas or text thomas to 500 500 on your
phone to get a 30 day free trial that
trial also comes with a free audiobook
download of your choice
and this month i'm going to recommend
bill bryson's excellent a short history
of nearly
everything this is one of my favorite
non-fiction books of all time
and even though it's not on my list of
essential books on my website since it
doesn't deal with
productivity or academics i do think
that everyone should read it it is a
fantastic
introduction to basically all fields of
science now of course you could go and
get any other audiobook that you want
and once you're a member you're going to
get one new credit every single month
for another audio book plus
access to two audible originals every
single month that you cannot get
anywhere else and a library of audio
workout and meditation programs to boot
so once again to get a free 30-day trial
of audible service along with a free
audiobook download of your choice and
two free audible originals go over to
audible.com
thomas or text thomas to 500 500 on your
phone
big thanks as always to audible for
sponsoring this video and being a
supporter of my channel
and thank you as always for watching as
well if you enjoyed this video hit that
like button and also get subscribed
right there so you don't miss new videos
when they come out
and also click right there to get a free
copy of my book on how to earn better
grades if you haven't done so already
last but not least you can check out one
more video on this channel by clicking
right over here or check out our latest
podcast
episode right over here and if you
haven't subscribed to that podcast
channel you should probably do that
as well thanks again for watching and i
will see you in the next video