hey everyone this is Thomas Frank from
college infogeek dcom and today I'm
going to show you how to build a
personal website in less than 10 minutes
using Wordpress if you're ready to get
started let's Dive Right
[Music]
In okay so in this screencast tutorial
I'm going to show you how to build your
own personal website step by step and
hopefully we're going to get this done
in less than 10 minutes now it might
take you a little bit longer to do it
since you haven't done it before like I
have but I just want to show you how
easy it is to do and how little
technology you actually need to know to
get this set up so before you get
started um watching this video I just
want to guide you towards my complete
step-by-step text tutorial that you can
use along with this video that will go
into detail about every single step so
if you go to my website college infogeek
ccom and if you go to the uh site bar
you can see that there is a box right in
the sidebar that says Ultimate Guide
build a personal website if you click on
that then you will get to my guide and
this will show you everything you need
to know in detail so if you don't get
something in the video you don't
understand what I'm doing this guide
will very thoroughly explain it to you
and if you want an even easier way to
get to this you can just go to build a
personal website.com I've registered
that domain to point directly to this
guide so if you want to remember
something you can type in later build
apersonal website.com you can tell that
to anybody else that you want to show
how to build a personal website in the
future okay so here's just a couple
examples of personal websites this is my
personal website that I use I put this
on my business card I give this to uh
employers at Career Fairs when I meet
people at networking events and they can
go see all my work my Twitter my
portfolio all that kind of stuff and
it's awesome much better than resume and
here's a couple more examples this is my
friend Martins he's got his you know
language learning things his technology
writing examples my friend Zach actually
made his website look kind of like a
resume itself which I think is really
cool so there are a lot of different
options all right so without any further
Ado let's get into the process of
creating a personal website here we go
all right so if you are on the guide
then you can just scroll down and if not
you can just listen to me the first step
to building your personal website is
getting a domain and hosting now this is
the only part of the process that costs
any money it doesn't cost cost a lot of
money but um right up front it will cost
you a little bit if you use my method
and as I say right here full disclaimer
I do get a little bit of a commission if
you use my link and my coupon code for
your hosting you definitely don't have
to there are definitely tons of other
good options out there but these are the
services I've been using myself for
years and since I spend a lot of my time
making tutorials like this I just use it
as a way to make a little bit of money
so I can afford to keep doing this so if
you do use my link thank you so much it
helps out a lot and let's continue so
right here is link to HostGator which is
the website that I recommend for hosting
if you click this picture right here or
just go to hostgator.com
then you'll be about to this page you're
going to go to view hosting plans and
the plan you will want to select is this
hatchling plan which is their simplest
and cheapest and all you need so click
order now and what you're going to do is
register a new domain name here you're
going to want to pick something very
close to your name and something that is
easy to say in conversation so my name
is Thomas Frank and the most optimal
domain for me would be thomasr
docomo for me in my case I needed to get
Thomas JF frank.com with my middle name
my middle initial in there um some
people might need to do a dash or
something I don't recommend using
numbers at all and I don't recommend
ever using like a DOT Biz orino if you
have to use net orme that's fine so I'm
just going to register something simple
for um the purposes of this video so
let's just go with
Thomas Frank
test.com and then down here in the
coupon code area if you enter the code
College infogeek
this code will get you 35% off of your
order so it's actually quite a bit
better than the default code that they
give you continue to step two and as you
can see here 35% off so the way that the
hosting is set up and all hosting
companies do this is the more you pay
for up front the less per month it's
going to be um however the more you pay
for up front the higher your initial
purchase will be just because it's more
months um I would recommend doing at
least a year that gives you time to have
it for any Career Fairs coming up and
things like that you will probably want
to renew after that but I would at least
do a year so you don't run out of space
and accidentally have your website go
down when you need it the most um since
this is a tutorial video and I don't
need this website I'm going to go with
one month and then you're going to
create a
username I'll just say Thomas test I
guess I can't do test Thomas
F I just Thomas yeah there we go and a
pin we'll just go with that
now obviously these things will be
blurred out because
person okay and once you have your
information filled in then you'll go
down here to the hosting add-on section
and as you can see they have pre-checked
a couple of these hosting add-ons I
recommend that you uncheck them because
they are more money per year than you
may want to spend so sight lock I'll
show you some other ways to secure your
website in the actual tutorial so you
won't need selck and then as for domain
privacy prote protection this basically
hides your name and your address and
your phone number in who is searches so
everyone that owns a website has their
name listed in a who is database and
anybody can go look that up so if
somebody should want to go look up your
information your name and your phone
number in the who has database they can
if you want to protect this and have it
just say who is guarded you can have
this on I'm not going to have it since
my contact information will already be
on my website it seems pointless to me
okay so here's where your total will be
it may be more for you if you got more
hosting time uh either way let's
continue we'll hit create
account okay and then you should get an
email to whatever email you specified
earlier with all your login information
so let's head over to
that okay there it is if you go in here
you get all your information including
your link to your control panel and your
username domain and your password so I'm
just going to copy this password
remember my username and then head over
to my control panel okay so throw that
in
there okay this is your C panel click no
I'm fine no no no and you're going to go
down to under software and services
Fantastico Deluxe this is a script
installing uh piece of software that
will let you install WordPress very very
easily so just click WordPress
and hit new
installation and we'll go through this
so install in domain here you go install
directory leave this blank for this use
something other than admin admin is very
insecure because everyone uses it so use
something different your name is just
fine give it a
password and other than that you're good
to
go okay and then hit finish installation
and now that this is done you can head
over to your email and click the link
for your
domain and you'll see that you now have
a working WordPress site which is pretty
plain but it is up so let's figure out
how to get some content in here
customize a little bit and then we'll be
ready to go so on your site you'll have
a login page but you're going to want to
get rid of that later so I'm going to
tell you the URL now to log in it's just
your website.com WP
[Music]
in and then you will log in with the
credentials you set up in
Fantastico and this is the WordPress
Dash dashboard so first thing you're
going to want to do if you have an
update message at the top like I do
you're going to want to update so let's
do that
now boom boom boom there we go you
always want to keep WordPress updated to
the latest version in order to keep
yourself secure Okay so so here's a
couple settings that I think are
important to do before you start with
anything else and as I said before all
this stuff is in the tutorial so if you
don't catch it here you can easily find
it step by
step so first thing Premier links we're
want to want to set our Premier link
structure to post name this basically
just makes Pages go your domain.com
whatever the Page's name is instead of
just a number which is much more
readable we'll do
that General check that everything is
fine here
and then
for reading later you're going to come
here and you're going to set a static
page as your front page so let's go
create a page first and since this is a
personal website you're probably going
to want your homepage to be in kind of
about me thing so we'll call it about
me and on my personal site this is how I
have it set up and you know this is my
personal
website you can obviously add more
things here later hit publish and then
back to settings
reading set your front page as a static
page about me and there you go now with
this setup you will have a Blog on your
website if you do want to have a Blog on
your website then you can easily create
a new
page call anything I'll just call it
blog keep it
blank and then you can set your post
page as that blog and any blog posts you
write in the post section will show up
there so let's check out our site now
now we have about me as the homepage we
have the blog where your posts will show
up and then the only things we have left
to do besides getting your content in
there which I'll leave up to you are
installing themes and plugins so if you
want to get a new theme you don't like
this one then you can go to install
themes and if you found a theme
elsewhere there are a few places that I
link to in my guide that show where you
can find some cool theme you can always
go to upload and upload the zip file
that you've downloaded or you can simply
search you can look at the feature
themes just see what you like a lot of
these are free so let's just go with
this
one and with all themes you will have to
read the documentation and figure out
how the author set the theme
up but as you can see the moment you
apply buy a new theme and activate it it
will show up on your website and all
your content will change and then lastly
I'll show you how to do
plugins so plugins are just pieces of
code that add new functionality to your
website so a really good one I like is
called limit login
attempts and this basically stops any
hackers or Bots from endlessly trying to
guess your username and password
combination it will limit it to a spe
specified number that you
specify so if we install and make sure
that's active then in settings we'll
have here and here you can set how long
it will up someone out if they get the
username and password combination wrong
a certain amount of times if you want to
be emailed when it happens blah blah
blah and now you have a more secure site
so in this tutorial I've showed you how
to get your domain and hosting setup how
to install WordPress on your server turn
it into your personal website set a
static page as your homepage and then
apply some themes and plugins this is
not all you're definitely going to want
to get all your content in there and
customize your site make it look the way
you want so once again builda personal
website.com will redirect you to my
tutorial where I go over all that in
much more detail check it out and if you
do have any questions be sure to hit me
up on Twitter I'm @tomfrankly on Twitter
or you can simply use the contact form
on College infogeek just ask me a
question I'm always there to help and I
would love to see your finished personal
website when you're done so show it to
me and other than that have an awesome
day