Thanks to Notion for sponsoring this
video and supporting my channel. When
most people think of Steve Jobs, they
naturally think of Apple. But there's a
story about Jobs that's always stuck in
my head, and it has nothing to do with
Apple. Well, almost nothing. In 1985,
Jobs was forced out of Apple after a
long power struggle with John Scully,
who was the CEO at the time. In
response, Jobs left Apple and took a
handful of the employees with him to
start a brand new company, which would
develop what was called the Next
Computer. This was going to be a much
more powerful workstation style computer
meant for colleges. And it was housed in
this black cube- shaped case. And in
Walter Isacson's biography of Jobs, he
recounts how Jobs insisted that the
black paint that covered the outside of
this case also be applied to the inside
at extra cost, even though almost no
customer would ever open it up and see
the paint for themselves. And this story
illustrates one of Jobs's most famous
qualities, his perfectionism. Jobs
demanded absolute perfection of all the
hardware and software that he and his
teams developed. And it's one of the
reasons why he was notoriously hard to
work for. It's one of the reasons that
pushed him to be so cruel to his
employees at times. And yet, the legacy
left behind by Jobs and by other famous
perfectionists often makes perfectionism
seem like something worth striving for.
Some people even wear it as a badge of
pride. That's why I'm a perfectionist is
one of the classic copout answers to
that age-old interview question, tell me
your greatest weaknesses, along with
really brilliant ones like, I just work
too hard, man, or I care too much, or
the classic,
I have no weaknesses.
But as you're going to find out in the
rest of this video, perfectionism really
is a weakness. Sure, it can have its
benefits, and the stories from people
like Jobs can make it seem like a
strength, but overall, the drawbacks
really do outweigh those benefits. In
2018, a research review surveyed all the
perfectionism research that had been
done over the past decades. And they
found that while perfectionism was
aligned with being more motivated at
work and putting in more hours, it was
also aligned with stress, with burnout,
with anxiety, with overwork, and with
depression. And to add some anecdotal
evidence to that research review, I've
been a perfectionist for a very long
time, and I found some additional
drawbacks. often focus way too intently
on a small part of a project that
ultimately doesn't really matter at the
end of the day. And it will cause me to
waste a lot of time. Earlier this year,
I made a video called How to Think More
Strategically. And if you saw it, you'll
know that we did a lot of chess B-roll
in that video. And I had one shot in
particular that I really wanted to get.
I had envisioned having the camera
suspended over a chessboard, slowly
moving back as different chess positions
sort of flashed by. So essentially, I
had to play out a game of chess on the
board. And I could have gotten the shot
a lot quicker just by randomly moving
the pieces, taking one away every once
in a while and then, you know, taking
some stills from that sequence and
creating out of that. But in my mind,
the only way to do that sequence
properly was to play an actual game on
the chessboard.
So here, Tom is playing against himself.
So that way when people saw those chess
pieces moving in the shot, they would be
moving in real positions that actually
made sense. And no one has ever
commented on that. I doubt anybody has
ever noticed that they were moving in a
realistic way. And that took me way
longer than it should have, but I just
couldn't let it go. And in addition to
just wasting time on things that I
really don't need to be fixating on,
I'll sometimes be paralyzed and unable
to start until I get right up against
the deadline for a project. I'll get
ideas. I'll start writing something down
and then my brain goes, "That's not good
enough. Your audience has better
expectations than that of you. That's
not going to fly." So, personally, I
would like it if perfectionism had a
little bit less influence in my life.
And if you identify as a perfectionist
as well, you might want the same things.
So, I want to talk about some ways to
get over this perfectionism or start
moving past it in this video. And to do
that, I think it's important to tell you
what a perfectionist really is because
it isn't just somebody who has high
standards for themselves. As the
psychologist David Burns describes it, a
perfectionist is a person whose
standards are high beyond reach or
reason and who strains compulsively and
unremittingly towards impossible goals
and this part's very important measures
their own worth entirely in terms of
productivity and accomplishment. Having
high standards for yourself is a great
thing, but perfectionists tend to take
it a bit too far. They set the bar
impossibly high and then they tie their
self-worth to it. Now, classically,
perfectionism has been divided into two
camps. Adaptive and maladaptive
perfectionism. These have also been
called excellence-seeking perfectionism
and failure avoiding perfectionism. The
excellence- seeeking perfectionists are
the people with ultra high standards for
their work. They're constantly trying to
make their work as good as it can be.
And they apply that perfectionism to
people working under them and sometimes
even their significant others and
friends as well. Meanwhile, the failure
avoiding perfectionists are the people
who are more fixated on not failing.
They're worried that other people don't
think their work is good enough and by
extension that they aren't good enough
either. And this can be split up even
further. In 1991, a pair of Canadian
psychologists developed their own model
with three different types.
Self-oriented perfectionism where you
have your own ultra high standards for
yourself. Other oriented perfectionism,
where you have unrealistic standards for
other people. And then socially
prescribed perfectionism, where again
you feel like other people have super
high standards for you and that you
can't live up to them. And when I look
at my own perfectionism, I can see that
it doesn't neatly fall into any one of
these categories. Yes, I have my own
high standards for my own work. I want
to see things be as good as they can be.
But I also feel like the people that I
know, both in the real world, my
personal relationships, but also my
audience online has super high
expectations for me and for my work.
That creates a lot of pressure, which
can lead to that paralysis and that
fixation on the things that don't really
matter at the end of the day. And while
we're talking about these different
types of perfectionism, I will note that
that research review found that the big
drawbacks of perfectionism, the
depression, the anxiety, the stress, the
burnout, these were more aligned with
the failure avoidance type of
perfectionism. But they were also
aligned with the excellence seeking type
if to a lesser degree. They still were
there. And crucially, they also found
that neither type of perfectionism was
aligned with better overall work
performance. So even though we may have
people like Jobs as the storied counter
example, the broader research has shown
that being a perfectionist doesn't make
you better at your job. So the question
now is what can we do about this? If we
are perfectionists, how can we move past
it and let perfectionism be less of an
influence in our life and on our work?
Well, the first thing is to work on
setting more realistic expectations for
yourself. As the author Martin Anthony
writes in his book, When Perfect Isn't
Good Enough, although standards and
beliefs are subjective, people usually
take for granted that their
interpretations, their beliefs, their
predictions, and standards are true. So,
becoming less perfectionistic will
involve relaxing your standards and
changing your perfectionistic beliefs.
It'll involve treating your standards
and beliefs as possibilities or guesses
about the way the world should be rather
than as hard facts. And if you like me
have that socially prescribed
perfectionism, I think the best way to
start doing this is to talk to people.
Ask them, "What do you really expect of
me?" Because I cannot tell you how many
times I've had conversations with people
that I work with or with people in my
audience and find out that what they
expect from me is still high, but not to
that astronomical level that I've built
up in my head. Next, if you're going to
perfect something, then perfect how you
allocate your efforts. In other words,
get to know the 8020 rule. This rule
states that 80% of the results often
come from just 20% of the efforts, the
vital few. And we as perfectionists are
often pretty bad identifying those vital
few things, both as individuals, but
also sometimes as entire organizations.
As I was researching this video, my
editor Tony gave me a great story from
the book Creativity Inc., which is
written by Ed Catmill, the co-founder of
Pixar, where he writes, "There is a
phenomenon that producers at Pixar call
the beautifully shaded penny. It refers
to the fact that the artists who work on
our films care so much about every
detail that they will sometimes spend
days or weeks crafting the equivalent of
a penny on a nightstand that you'll
never see." There's a great example of
this in Monsters, Inc., where Mike and
Sully bring Buu back to their apartment
for the first time. There's this
3-second shot of a stack of CDs that Buu
knocks over. And even though it's only 3
seconds long, and even though you only
see a few of the CD covers, the artists
at Pixar took the time to create art for
every single one of those CDs. There are
more than 90 of them. In telling that
story, CMO was mainly making a point
about the production process of the
company, writing that because of the way
production unfolded, our people had to
work on scenes without knowing the
context for them. So, they just
overbuilt them to be safe. But there's
another insight here as well. He goes on
to write that to make things worse, our
standards of excellent are extremely
high, leading them to conclude that more
is always more. This is something that
perfectionists really deal with. And the
truth is often the opposite. Often less
is more. Taking away is more. So get
critical about your work. Try to
identify that crucial 20%, that vital
few and spend a little bit less time
fixating on the 80% that doesn't matter.
Finally, be imperfect on purpose. One of
the most common ways to get over fear is
called exposure therapy. Essentially,
you expose yourself to the thing you
fear over and over and over again at
slightly increasing levels of intensity
until eventually you're just kind of
over it. And to apply this principle of
exposure therapy to this problem, you
need to be imperfect on purpose. One of
my favorite examples of this in action
comes from the YouTuber Andrew Hang, who
makes a ton of music. And I cannot for
the life of me find the video where he
said this, but I saw a video where he
said that he'll often limit himself to
four takes when recording parts for a
song. So if there's a specific guitar
lick he's got to record, he does four
takes, takes the best one, and that's
it. And fittingly, Andrew has published
hundreds of songs on his Spotify. And
meanwhile, I've published three. So,
there's a thing or two that I could
learn from Andrew. Uh, quantity
challenges are also a great thing.
Jennifer DeWalt made 180 small websites
in 180 days and learned a ton doing it.
My friend Martin, who helped me write
the script for this video, and who is
even worse at perfectionism than I am by
his own admission, said that he did a
daily Instagram challenge where he
posted daily photos for over 200 days.
as a way to be imperfect on purpose. And
as a side note, he told me that he
recently constructed a portfolio of his
best photography work. There are 24
photos there, and he found out that 15
of the photos he picked came from that
daily challenge. So, even though he
didn't have a whole lot of time to make
perfect work, he ended up with work he
was proud of. And there's a reason for
this. Not only do these deadlines give
you very little time to fixate and act
on perfectionist tendencies, but they
also give you a ton of feedback. You're
making and publishing things and getting
feedback on them and coming back and
reviewing them. And this helps you get
better. Perfectionists don't get a ton
of feedback. That research review I
mentioned at the beginning of the video
concluded that perfectionists don't do
any better at work than
non-perfectionists, but they didn't know
why. And I think this is the reason
perfectionists don't get as many at
bats. they don't get that feedback that
is crucial to growth. So, be imperfect
on purpose. Not only are you going to
get that feedback, but each time that
you act in an imperfect way, you're
going to prove to your brain that
imperfection is not the disaster that it
thought it would be. Imperfect chair
turn. Oh, hey there, other camera angle.
So, I'd like to wrap this video up by
giving you a quick look at how we made
it using Notion. So, first there is the
idea stage. Martin came up with the idea
for this particular video. So, he added
to this cool content ideas area that we
built, which can be separated by our
channels, or if you switch the view, by
topic. Once we knew that we were going
to make the video, we used the template
to create the video project area. Martin
and I both added a ton of research and
outlines to our research area, pasted
tons of links, and then I did a bunch of
writing and turned that all into a
script in the script area. Now, while
filming, I pulled up that script on my
iPad, which sits on a music stand next
to me, so I can look at the lines and
then say them into the camera. Then once
I've done the initial cuts and know
roughly how long the video is going to
be, I add all my B-roll ideas to a tool
called Frame.io, which gives each one of
them a timestamp. I then export those
and bring them into this pre-made
database in my video project. And
because I have the timestamps, I can
sort them all chronologically, but I can
also tag them, film, overhead, screen
recording, whatever it is, and switch my
view so I can more efficiently batch
them as I gather them. Once the video is
done, I create an editing checklist from
a template that reminds me to do all the
little things like bordering captions
and adding end cards. And finally, I add
the URL back into notion. And I mark the
video published so that it shows up in
this special archive view we built. So
that is idea generation. That is
research, scripting, project planning,
to-do lists, and an archive all in one
tool. And we're able to do this because
Notion isn't just a note-taking tool or
a to-do list app. It's really a set of
building blocks that allows you to
create the exact tools you need for the
work that you want to do. It can be as
simple as you want or as complex as you
need it to be. And now is a great time
to try Notion out using the link below
because their personal plan is now
completely free. So check out that link
below if you want to get started. And
after that, check out my new channel,
Thomas Frank Explains, for some
tutorials and even some free templates
that can help you get up and running
more quickly. Thanks as always for
watching this video. Hopefully you found
it helpful. Hopefully you liked it. This
is the last one for 2020. So, if you did
like it, hit that like button as always
to show the YouTube algorithm what's up
and get subscribed if you haven't
already. I'll have a subscribe button
somewhere on screen along with other
couple videos you can check out. And uh
once again, I'll have that Thomas Freick
Explains channel linked here as well, so
you can check that out if you are
interested in uh upgrading your Notion
knowledge and workspace. See you in the
next one.