studying is boring right every time you
have to open up a textbook or tackle a
homework assignment million things go
through your mind it would be more fun
to do like skydiving or watching paint
dry or typing a youtube comment about
how the fact that I'm holding a pitch is
spinning right now it makes you want to
puke yeah I can see you warming up your
fingers Derek
of course studying is something that you
just sometimes have to do which leads to
the obvious question if you have to do
it is there at least a way to make it
more fun or at least less boring well
that's what I want to talk about today
I'm going to get this out here right up
front there is no way to make studying
always fun after all part of learning
process is to have to sometimes go
through challenging and difficult
material and that's not always going to
be a walk in the park
but there are things you can do to make
studying more fun more of the time and
that's what I want to talk about in this
video so let's dive right in first and
foremost if you want to make studying
fun you need to get interested in your
topic all the way back in 1913 Frances
Lockwood wrote in his book the freshman
at his college in the long run the
secret of study resides in our ability
to bathe our thought our task our lesson
in the stream of interest but how
exactly do you gain that interest
well you certainly don't do it by
jumping straight into my new details to
gain interest that's truly strong enough
to power you through the hours of
rigorous study you need to expose
yourself to the truly exciting facets of
the topic first nobody reads the history
of middle-earth before reading the Lord
of the Rings or at least watching the
movies first and nobody goes digging
through c-sharp documentation unless
they're interested in building something
in c-sharp like a video game
that's why Bill Nye made Bill Nye the
Science Guy like Carl Sagan made cosmos
my David Attenborough helped to make
Planet Earth these three men are known
first and foremost as science
popularizers because they knew what it
took to get the public interested in
science they knew that showing
electricity in action or showing a shark
hunting its prey is far better at
generating that needed initial spark of
interest than talking immediately about
Ohm's law or talking about how to dorsal
fin effects fluid dynamics and the best
teachers in the world understand this
innately they know that they need to get
their students initially excited about
the topic before they jump right into
the rigorous my new details but if your
teachers not good that you can do that
yourself one great way to do this is to
find a book or a movie or a podcast or
even a video game that can give you an
initial high-level introduction to the
topic and entertain
way or that somehow connected to it I'll
use my girlfriend Ana as an example Ana
is somebody who really doesn't like to
read a whole lot of nonfiction but last
year we took a trip to st. Louis to go
to City Museum and on the way we
listened to a podcast called hardcore
history and if you have a listen to this
podcast before it is one of the
downright most entertaining podcasts in
the world is my personal favorite
podcast and the particular episode we
were listening to was talking about
ancient Persia after we listened that
episode Ana actually got interested in
the topic and she went and bought the
book Persian fire by the historian Tom
Holland and this is a good book but as
you can see right here it's a pretty
thick history book and it's not an as
usual affair but despite that she
finished the entire book because the
podcast gave her that initial spark of
interest and I remember while she was
reading it she'd come to me several
times and say hey I remember when he
talked about that in the podcast so she
was building an interest link a second
tip that will help you become more
interested in anything you're studying
is to adopt a growth mindset Carol
Dweck's book mindset the new psychology
of success contrasts people with fixed
mindsets people who essentially believe
that talent or intelligence is fixed and
doesn't change with people who have
growth mindsets people who believe
anything can be changed and improved
upon early on in the book direct
demonstrates how the mindset that you
have also plays a huge role in how
interested you'll be in your studies
especially when the going gets difficult
during her research for the book she
followed pre-med students who are taking
an initial chemistry course during their
freshman year of college and in this
course the average exam grade was a
c-plus it was one of those weed out
courses that's basically designed to be
difficult so weeds out people who are
not a good fit for the medicine program
right at the start in the book she
reported that most students started out
pretty interested in chemistry yet over
the semester
something happened students with the
fixed mindset stayed only interested
when they did well right away those
kinda difficult showed a big drop in
their interest and enjoyment if it
wasn't a testimony to their intelligence
they couldn't enjoy it in contrast
students with the growth mindset
continue to show the same high level of
interest even when they found the work
very challenging challenge and interest
went hand-in-hand so try to reframe the
way you think about your classes not as
tests or evaluations to show everyone
how intelligent or unintelligent you are
but as continual learning opportunities
opportunities to learn grow and yes
sometimes fail but to come back and
improve upon those failures and to win
eventually this is a glow
mindset if you can do this you're going
to find that your studies across any
subject you tackle are going to be more
enjoyable and more interesting another
great way to make studying more fun and
interesting is to do it with a partner
but studying with a partner is a
double-edged sword that can go wrong
really easily and I find there are two
main pitfalls that you fall into when
you do this first and foremost if you
study with the wrong partner they're
going to distract you and you're never
going to get any work done and I've
definitely been here during my freshman
year I tried to study with the people in
my dorm and all we ended up doing was
opening up Duke Nukem sound boards and
wasting all of our time but just as
easily you can find a partner who goes
through the work so quickly and does so
much of it that you end up glossing over
the problems in the concepts and never
end up really learning them yourself so
if you're going to do this you need to
not only find a partner who is focused
and stays on task the whole time but who
also ensures that you understand the
problem solution and that they
understand it as well before both of you
move on the next tip is to change your
environment in non-distracting ways that
make studying more enjoyable and there
are a lot of ways you can do this one of
the best ways to find a study playlist
that you enjoy listening to that doesn't
distract you and I've been making a
playlist here on YouTube called the
ultimate study music playlist for a few
years that works really well when I need
to get some work done it can also help
to find a study spot that you really
enjoy being in like your favorite spot
in the library or good coffee shop or
maybe study with the cat and having a
good drink next to you while you study
definitely helps as well pretty much
every single morning I make a pot of
cinnamon clove tea which is basically my
favorite kind of tea and I drink that
while I do some writing and it might
sound weird to you but the ritual of
having that pot of tea and being able to
pour multiple glasses while I write
makes the process of writing more
enjoyable so I do it
[Music]
and that brings us to our final tip on
lists you want to make studying more fun
and more enjoyable and create many
rewards that you get for doing that
studying see your motivation to compare
task is defined partly by the reward
you're going to get for doing it and
with studying there's a pretty obvious
main reward you'll get a good grades
you'll graduate from college and you
won't have to live in a van down by the
river
but that doesn't have to be the only
reward you give yourself you can also
create many rewards that can be an
incentive for finishing assignment or
even just putting an amount of time in
now you've probably all seen the gummy
bear trick on Facebook and that might
work for some people I think I would
just eat all the gummi bears and close
my book right away but for the most part
these rewards should be high-density fun
letting yourself go out with friends or
letting yourself play overwatch for a
while something that isn't stupid like
scrolling through Facebook for five
minutes it's also important to plan out
the details of these many rewards in
advance as the author Pierre still talks
about this book the procrastination
equation boards are a lot more
motivating when they're pre-planned
because they build anticipation you know
in the back of your mind that once you
finish studying you're going to get to
do something fun and that's going to
further increase your motivation to
power through that study session this
video is made possible in part by
Skillshare now earlier I talked about
how important it is to get interested in
the things you're studying and that's
especially important for required
classes you have to take but there are
also things that you've probably always
wanted to learn things you already have
an interested like maybe playing the
guitar like I am or learning digital
illustration or maybe just learning how
to cook so you don't to keep living off
of Hot Pockets everyday if that's the
case then you should definitely give
Skillshare a try with over 16,000
courses and a ton different topics
there's something for almost everybody
and almost all the courses include
challenges and projects that you can
tackle to start putting what you're
learning into action right away Premium
Membership on Skillshare will run you
about ten bucks a month which basically
makes it a Netflix subscription that
will actually make you smarter but the
first 500 people that click the link in
the description below and sign up will
get a free two month trial of unlimited
learning and trust me in two months you
can learn a lot so if you're interested
definitely go give that link a try I
want to give a big thanks to Skillshare
for sponsoring this video and supporting
this channel and thank you so much for
watching if you found this video helpful
give it a like if you have additional
tips that I didn't mention here
definitely go down in the comments and
share them so other students can benefit
you can also hit that subscribe button
right there to get new videos every
single week and if you
free copy of my book on how to earn
better grades click right there
initially you should definitely go check
out this week's podcast episode where we
discuss a book called essentialism which
is one of the best books I've read this
year so click right there if you want to
check it out or click right there for
another video on this channel thank you
so much for watching and I'll see you
guys next week