thanks to brilliant for sponsoring this
video and supporting my channel a few
years ago i made a video about something
called the feynman technique this is a
simple but highly effective study
technique where you deepen your own
understanding of a concept by attempting
to simplify it and explain it to someone
else in other words you teach to learn
in this video i want to present a
modified version of that original
findment technique that i've been using
in my own independent learning projects
as of late conceptually it is very
similar to the original finding
technique but in execution it is quite
different so i'm going to give it its
own name to keep things distinct and
that name is the lpc method which stands
for learn present critique and i've been
using this lpc method in my own studies
of anatomy biomechanics and
bioenergetics as part of my goal to earn
both cscs and pbc certifications which
if you're curious are certifications in
the strength training and coaching
industry and i've learned through using
this that this technique has a very high
roi on helping me retain lots of
information without having to spend a
lot of time actually studying it so in
this video i'm going to walk you through
exactly how to use the lpc method along
with some examples and i'm also going to
compare it to the original feynman
technique you can see in the timestamps
below exactly where those sections are
but first if you haven't seen my
original video or if it's been a while i
want to give you a very quick refresher
on what the feynman technique is the
heart of this technique can be found in
a quote that is often attributed to
albert einstein though he probably
didn't actually say it but it goes like
this if you can't explain it simply then
you don't understand it well enough the
idea behind the fieman technique is to
break down a concept and simplify it to
the point where you could easily explain
it to a lay person if you can't do that
then you don't understand it well enough
yourself and in going through this
exercise actually trying to explain it
on a piece of paper you expose gaps in
your understanding which you can then go
and try to shore up so again
conceptually the lpc method is very
similar to the feynman technique we're
trying to achieve the same goal except
for replacing the act of writing on
paper drawing diagrams with actually
presenting to a camera here is the tldr
version of the lpc method first you go
out and learn go to the lecture material
watch a video read a book take your
notes as normal second present a concept
present something you've learned to your
phone camera as if you were explaining
it to a friend or explaining it to a
classroom like a speech and third upload
that video paste it into your notes and
finally watch it and critique it and in
your critique you're looking for three
different things number one any errors
factual errors that you need to correct
number two any areas where you are vague
where you can add clarification and
number three any questions that your
critique brings up after the fact you
can then go and learn about through
supplemental material or through
revisiting the actual material you're
learning from so here's a real world
example from my own study of human
anatomy if you look through my notes
here on notion you'll see lots of
different videos where i'm explaining
lots of concepts but the one that i want
to show you here is my explanation of
the different moving joints in the human
body which are called synovial joints so
first i went through that learning
process in this case the material that
i'm working through is barbell logic's
principles course which goes through
pretty much everything you need to learn
to become a beginner strength coach so
biomechanics bioenergenics the basics of
human anatomy as well as how to coach
the four main power lifting lifts so i'm
going through this course and i'm taking
my notes on the different joints in the
body and how they move and i use a
pretty typical outline style note taking
technique here in notion with the one
exception that i often will clip a lot
of screenshots and add a lot of
multimedia elements into my notes to
take advantage of multimodal learning
and i'll touch on that a little bit
later but now it's time to move on to
step two which is present at this point
i want to put my phone on a tripod and
pick a concept or a set of facts to
present and explain to my phone as if i
were explaining it to you or to a friend
so in this case i picked these six
different diarthrodial joints in the
body and explain how they work in the
video so the way to imagine a saddle
type joint and how it moves is if you
took your knuckles here and took the
other knuckles here and sort of
sandwiched them together now this is my
own analogy they did not teach this in
the course but it sort of is analogous
to how you'll see illustration once i'm
done recording i use the youtube app to
upload an unlisted copy of this video to
a second youtube channel i have
specifically for my own learning and for
this lpc technique and because it's on
youtube i can then go ahead and paste it
into my notion which will embed it and
that brings us to step three critique at
this point i'm going to watch through
the video and i'm gonna look for again
three things number one factual errors
so for example at one point in the video
i mentioned the carpels of the hand and
the carpels of the feet those are the
tarsals i'm gonna also look for anything
where i could be a little bit more clear
or more correct in my explanation so at
one point i mentioned the joint between
the metacarpal and the uh phalangeal
bones here in the thumb well that is a
joint but it's called the
metacarpophalangeal joint so i should
actually use the name of the joint and
finally number three if i have any
questions that come up in this critique
process and i almost always do i want to
go out and get answers to those
questions and this is just another way
that encourages me to deepen my
understanding often by using
supplemental resources so how is this
method better than the original feinman
technique well i am not going to stand
by that claim for every subject or every
concept out there but i do think that
for certain types of information certain
concepts this is much better than the
feynman technique in terms of roi and
it's because you're using a different
mode of learning or mode of active
learning specifically to deepen your
understanding of the subject material
going back to my example of the synovial
joints in the body if i get on camera
and i verbally explain how these joints
work but also use body language to
demonstrate how they work and point out
where they are on my own anatomy i am
using multimodal learning to deepen my
own understanding if i wanted to do that
with the feynman technique i would have
two different options i would either
have to write out in text how these
things work that's a very abstract way
of learning it's gonna take me a lot
longer or i would have to draw them that
is a more iconic type of learning using
iconography it's much better in terms of
me being able to visually see how
something works but drawing takes a lot
more time than just pointing out and
moving my arm to show how a hinge joint
works so in terms of time spent studying
versus retention of information for
certain kinds of topics this is going to
be superior though i think the real
improvement to the finding technique
here is to combine your use of both of
these techniques either separately based
on the type of concept you're studying
or maybe even lumping them all into one
big technique there is nothing stopping
you from breaking out a whiteboard and
actually writing out or diagramming
while you film yourself but that extra
step of critiquing yourself afterwards
is another thing that's going to help
deepen your understanding in general you
want to pursue a multi-modal learning
strategy because no one way of learning
is better than any other you may have
seen this often cited learning pyramid
floating around the internet where
people will say things like you only
retain 10 percent of what you hear 20 of
what you read etc well as it turns out
the original version of that pyramid
number one wasn't even called a pyramid
it was a cone it's about the cones but
number two did not include those
percentages at all and as far as
research has been able to find those
percentages are completely made up the
original version of the cone was called
the cone of experience it was created by
edgar dale who was a very well respected
education researcher and his whole point
in creating this cone was to just create
a model that showed visually the
differences and levels of abstraction
between different methods of learning be
it verbal or text based or audio visual
and his whole point was that mixing up
different methods of learning is more
powerful than using anyone in fact back
in 1969 he wrote that direct hands-on
experience what we often think of as the
gold standard for learning anything is
often not the best way to learn
something and more recent cognitive
research has confirmed this and shown
that for basic concepts a more abstract
learning model is actually better and
once you get into higher order learning
concepts then hands-on experience is
better so as far as cognitive research
is found a multimodal approach truly is
the best so talk about what you're
learning demonstrate it with body
language draw it find a way to get a new
perspective and a new view on what
you're learning and you're going to find
your long-term memory your long-term
ability to retain and recall that
information and master it truly
understand it is going to improve as
well before i end this video i want to
let you know about one more resource
that i'm using in this independent
learning project of mine and that is
brilliant specifically their chemistry
course because believe it or not i never
took chemistry in college and in my
current study of bioenergetics i am
learning that a little bit of chemistry
knowledge is actually very useful so i'm
currently going through brilliant
chemistry course and i'm finding it very
helpful for understanding how chemical
reactions work i'm also using some more
passive supplemental resources lecture
materials videos but brilliant is built
with active learning in mind which means
while i'm going through their course i'm
constantly being quizzed i'm constantly
being asked to solve problems and if you
know anything about the cognitive
science behind active learning you will
know that this is a much more effective
efficient and interesting way to learn
and it is the methodology they use to
build all the courses in their library
of which there are more than 60. so if
you want to get better at math at
science at computer science you're going
to want to check out brilliant in all
their courses you're gonna find
logically sequenced bite-sized quizzes
and interactive puzzles that keep you
actively engaged and help you to master
the material more effectively and by
solving problems more frequently you
become a better problem solver overall
so if you want to get started learning
today go over to brilliant.org
thomasfrank to sign up and to support
this channel hopefully you found this
video helpful i'm finding this very
helpful in my own study so hopefully you
will as well if you enjoyed this video
likes and comments definitely help the
algorithm and i'll have one more video
right here and another one right here if
you want to keep watching stuff on this
channel thanks as always for watching
and i'll see you in the next video