Hello friends and welcome to my final
accelerated Japanese learning challenge
review video uh we're in a small town
smallish called Iwakuni near Hiroshima
and uh I just wanted to briefly talk
about the um expectations I set for the
challenge and I guess the failure as I
could call it in quotes uh so basically
I kind of challenged myself to make this
like an epic Challenge and I really
wanted to put about 20 to 30 hours of
study uh into Japanese before we got to
Japan now going off of toggle which is a
Time tracking app I used I only put in
about 7 hours actually and this is a
result of the amount of things I had to
do and the underestimations I made uh in
planning things so I only got less than
a third of the actual studying that I
wanted to do done but uh on the bright
side I actually studied Japanese and I
actually was able to relearn a lot of
what I'd forgotten and actually going
through this trip we've been here for
what 10 days now an right I think
um I've been able to speak more Japanese
and understand more Japanese than I ever
have before so I guess the um result in
my mind of this challenge is that even
though I bailed my own expectations the
act of setting a big challenge for
myself actually spurred me to take
action that I wasn't taking before and
when I get back from Japan I'm planning
on continuing my studies and actually
hiring a tutor every single week so if
you want to do something and you find
yourself not doing it maybe try setting
a big challenge
even if you fail then you might find
that the progress you do make is enough
to make a dent in your goals oh and one
last thing there will be no video next
week as I will be massively jetl lagged
and you'd basically probably get a video
of me sleeping so take a breather as I'm
going to do and the next week we'll be
back to regularly scheduled videos about
studying and productivity and all that
cool stuff so see you till
then
[Music]
[Applause]