let's talk about Theodore Roosevelt for
a second back in 1876 before he was
president of the United States before he
grew his epic mustache that I sadly will
never be able to equal he was just a
freshman at Harvard University and as
Edmund Morris points out in his
biography Roosevelt had a ton of
interest at the time boxing dance
lessons bodybuilding naturalism and many
many more so many in fact that he had
barely any time to spend studying
compared to his peers and yet Roosevelt
excelled at Harvard during his freshman
year he took seven courses and out of
those he earned honor grades in five of
them so how exactly did he do that in
the book deep work the author Cal
Newport explains that Roosevelt would
begin his scheduling by considering the
eight hours from 8:30 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.
he would then remove the time spent and
recitation and classes his athletic
training which was once a day and lunch
the fragments that remained were then
considered time dedicated exclusively to
study as noted these fragments didn't
usually add up to a large number of
total hours but he would get the most
out of them by working only on
schoolwork during these periods and
doing so with a blistering intensity to
put that another way Roosevelt used the
time pressure caused by his busy
schedule to amplify his concentration
and as a result he spent far fewer hours
to make studying and homework than his
peers but he still did really well in
his classes and that's the overall goal
here you clicked this video because you
want to do homework faster but you also
want to do a good job of it you don't
want to phone it in or just skip it all
together
of course building an intense work ethic
like Teddy Roosevelt will definitely get
you part of the way there but there are
also some more tactical decisions and
changes that you can make to the way you
work that are gonna help you crush those
homework assignments more quickly that's
what I want to focus on in this video to
begin we're gonna look at something
called the hard start jump to easy
technique which is a test taking
strategy talked about in the book a mine
for numbers by Barbara Oakley to use
this technique essentially you look over
your tests before you start and identify
which problems are difficult and which
problems are easy then you jump straight
into one of the difficult ones but
crucially once you get stuck on that
difficult problem you have to disengage
and go to one of the easy ones then
after you've solved a few of the easy
ones you can jump back and more often
than not you're gonna find the insights
that weren't there
four are gonna come to the forefront of
your mind and you're gonna be able to
solve that problem this technique works
so well because it engages both of your
main modes of thinking your focus mode
and your diffused mode and mine frame
number spends a lot of time talking
about both of these modes and explaining
why using both of them is crucial for
solving tough problems to go through
really quickly the focused mode is what
you use when you directly concentrate on
a problem and you try to work through it
logically and this is the state of mind
that you start in with pretty much any
problem whether it's solving a calculus
equation or trying to flank your enemy
team and overwatch my comment rust
oakley says that diffuse mode of
thinking is what happens when you relax
your attention and just let your mind
wander this relaxation can allow
different areas of the brain to hook up
and return valuable insights and she
goes on the note that diffuse mode in
sites often flow from preliminary
thinking that's been done in the focused
mode so really it's this back-and-forth
interplay between the focus mode and the
diffuse mode that makes this technique
so powerful for solving tough problems
but it also comes with an additional
benefit in that it helps you use your
time effectively which is really
important in a test when you have a
limited amount of time but it also can
apply to your homework yes you don't
have a limited amount of time per se
with your homework assignments but you
do want to get them done faster and this
technique can do that for you I do have
one little caveat though with your
homework spend a little bit more time
trying to solve a tough problem once you
get stuck don't disengage after one or
two minutes my reason for this is that
with a test you should ideally have
those concepts buried somewhere in the
back of your mind but with your homework
that's really the training ground where
you're gonna build that initial
understanding of those core concepts so
in that situation spend a little bit
more time wrestling with those problems
before stepping away and letting the
diffuse mode take over my next tip is
something that you should apply while
you're in class it's gonna be especially
useful for when you're taking math
classes or physics classes or really any
kind of class where you're applying
concepts and trying to solve complex
problems when your professor or your
teacher is going through an example
problem on the board or guiding you
through the process make sure that
you're writing down every single step of
that example problem this is incredibly
important to do because there is a huge
gap between being able to follow along
with what someone else is doing and
understand it and being able to do it on
your own and you probably could think of
many times in the past where you've gone
through example problems in class your
professor is guiding you through them
and you understand everything but then
you come to your homework later on it's
using the same exact concept but then
you're stuck now I know that I used to
get really frustrated in these kind of
situations but it's just a reality of
the skill building process it's just
like watching somebody do a skateboard
trick and trying to do it on your own
you have to build that muscle memory and
it takes a long time and a lot of
deliberate practice so think of those
example problems in your notes as the
equivalent to having like a YouTube
video of someone doing a kickflip the
more camera angles you have that person
doing the kickflip the more easily
you'll be able to see what's going on
and what you're doing wrong it's the
same story with your notes if you have a
one-for-one representation of exactly
what the professor did on the board
you're gonna be able to go line by line
through it and see exactly where you're
confused and don't just offer those
example problems themselves while you're
in class for each step in the problem
ask yourself do I truly understand
what's going on here and if you don't
simply draw a little arrow and make a
little note in the margins that explains
it so you'll know later while you're
trying to implement it finally one
additional tip for finishing those
homework assignments more quickly is to
try doing your homework at school when I
was in college I would occasionally have
semesters over there was like a one to
two hour gap between my last class the
day and the class that came before it
and this actually turned out to be a
pretty good situation because I was
basically gonna stay on campus for those
two hours I wasn't gonna go home and
really the only thing to do was my
homework now having that gap of time
where I had to be at a class within two
hours created a little bit of time
pressure that made me work more
efficiently but also being on campus I
was in the right context to do the work
because I don't know about you but when
I come home the last thing I want to do
is work this is the complete wrong con
next for it this is where my bed is for
my video games are where my kitchen is
there's all sorts of different things
that I want to be doing but at school
it's a totally different story now maybe
you are different maybe you do like to
work at home and if that's the case I do
have one additional tip for you instead
of doing your entire homework assignment
at school take some time as soon as you
can after class to simply preview your
assignments when I was writing the
script for this video I talked with my
friend Martin I asked him what caused
you to spend more time on homework than
you would have liked and he said the
main thing was that he had to spend a
ton of time trying to reefa Milly as
himself with the requirements of the
assignment figuring out all the places
in his textbooks and notes that he had a
reference and just took a lot of time to
setup and it would demotivate him now if
you want to cut down in that lag time
then as soon as you can after class
spend just a few minutes going through
the details of the assignment mentally
note the concepts are gonna be covered
and then note where your textbook and
your notes that you're going to need to
reference and if you want to take this a
step further you can actually get these
little plastic sticky book notes and you
can go to those spots in your notes mark
them so that way when you come home and
start working on your assignment you can
easily turn right to the exact page now
once you've mastered the art of
finishing your homework assignments
quickly the next challenge is deciding
what to do with all the time you've
gained and of course you could spend
some of that time playing Mario Plus
rabbits Kingdom battle which is exactly
what I'm gonna go do after I finish
filming this video but you might also
dedicate a portion that time to building
a skill that you've always wanted to
learn like learning how to edit videos
or design graphics or build iPhone apps
and if you want to build that skill
quickly just like you finished those
homework assignments quickly that a
great place to start learning is over
app skills this week I want to highlight
one of the newest courses on Skillshare
which is phil Abner's complete beginners
course on Dobby Photoshop now I am not
much of a photographer but as a youtuber
I've had to learn the ins and outs of
Photoshop to create my thumbnails and
you might think that making the
thumbnail is pretty easy but for me at
least it's actually a pretty complicated
process to get something that really
stands out on the youtube homepage after
I've got the picture I want to use I
have to cut myself out of the background
and cleanly using the selection of
masking tools I have to add a colored
background and set its blending mode and
then I have to add shapes and text and
these are all skills that took me quite
a while to learn but they are also all
skills that are covered comprehensively
in Phil's course so if you're a budding
youtuber and you want to improve the
graphic design on your channel which I
can tell you from personal experience
matters a lot or if you're just a
photographer and you want to learn how
to correctly color grade your photos you
can take that course and
your skills really quickly and there's
something else you want to learn the
skill shares library of over 17,000
hands-on practical courses is almost
guaranteed to have you covered
membership on Skillshare starts at about
ten bucks a month which is right around
the cost of two lattes though I have
checked and said that they don't take
payment in lattes but the first 500
people that go down the description
below and click that link will get a two
month free trial of unlimited learning
so definitely go check it out
big thanks to skill share for sponsoring
this video and helping to support this
channel and as always thank you guys so
much for watching now if you have
something I didn't mention in this video
that would be helpful to other people
definitely go leave it in the comments
below and give this video a like if you
liked it you didn't you know what to do
otherwise you can subscribe right there
for new videos every single week or you
can go right there to get a free copy of
my book on earning better grades you
should also check out this week's
podcast episode where we talk about ten
essential life skills that every student
should know some of my favorite recent
episodes so definitely go give it a
listen or you can find another video on
this channel by clicking right there
thanks so much for watching and I will
see you next week