this video is brought to you by Snorlax
crunk and that one chicken from the
movie Surfs Up three dudes who never let
the stress of adversity get to them too
much actually Snorlax just kind of
sleeps through adversity anyway test
anxiety let's talk about it and then
let's do our best to destroy it the time
leading up to a test is so Laden with
Stress and Anxiety because tests are
high pressure situations and high
pressure situations can actually deplete
your working memory and reduce your
performance this is commonly called
choking and it's common to all types of
high pressure situations not just
academic ones now it's important to note
that a little bit of stress and a little
bit of fear can actually be a good thing
stress heightens our senses and brings
out our best like the famous radio
broadcaster Edward R Murrow once said
the best speakers know enough to be
scared the only difference between the
pros and the novices is that the pros
have trained the butterflies to fly
information without any stress at all
we'd just be apathetic stress means you
care too much though and your health and
your performance start to suffer so
today I want to help you mitigate some
of the stress and fear that's caused by
your exams and specifically I want to
focus in on three main fears that I
think all students have when exams are
around the corner number one the fear of
the unknown number two the fear of
inadequacy the feeling that you're
unprepared and not ready for the
challenge ahead and number three the
fear of the stakes the feeling that
everything is riding on this test and
that your life will basically be over if
you fail and actually now that I think
about it there are a couple of other
worries that I think most students
probably face but I want to wait until
the end of the video to briefly touch on
those first let's talk about these three
big ones and then go over some specific
things you can do to reduce the stress
caused by each of them so let's talk
about our first fear skeletons or I mean
uh the fear of the unknown so really the
best way to conquer the fear of the
unknown is to make the test as much of a
known quantity as possible do your best
to make that test feel like a familiar
old friend when you walk into the class
and face it down on test day now there
are three main ways to do this that I
want to go over in this video and the
first one is to Simply recreate the test
conditions as best you can when you're
studying this means actually going to
the location in which you'll be tested
and if it's your classroom I don't
really think sitting in class every day
really counts because it doesn't really
recreate the high pressure situation of
the test so go there during the off
hours even if the room's empty take a
desk sit down and try to do some active
studying while you're in the actual room
you'll be tested in don't stop at
location either try to recreate the time
constraints and maybe even the type of
questions you'll be quizzed over and
basically make it a dry run that doesn't
really have the high stakes of the
actual test so that when you actually do
take that test it's as if you've already
done it but you might be asking me how
do I actually recreate these test
conditions if I don't know what's going
to be on the test and that leads into my
second tip ask your professor a lot of
students make the mistake of assuming
that if the professor didn't readily
give out information in class about the
test that they're unwilling to give it
out if asked this isn't always the case
so if there are aspects of your exam
that you're unclear on ask your
professor you can ask them about the
format what types of questions you'll be
asked true false multiple choice essay
style how long you'll actually have to
complete the test and what sort of
materials are allowed in the testing
room and my final tip for getting to
know the test ahead of time is to look
for old tests a lot of fraternities
sororities and other student
organizations maintain test banks that
you might be able to look through and if
you don't have access to anything like
that there's sites like koofers.com
which maintain their own databases our
second big fear to conquer is the
feeling of inadequacy the feeling that
you're unprepared for the challenge that
the test presents and honestly the best
thing you can do here is simply to
prepare like the famous Marathon or Juma
ianga once said that the will to win is
nothing without the will to prepare so
use the other tactics in Your Arsenal
the discipline hacks the planning
techniques and make sure that throughout
the semester you're working diligently
so that way when you get to the weeks
leading up to the test you don't have a
whole lot of catching up to do you've
been preparing the whole time like if
you've ever seen a Rocky movie my
favorite part is actually the training
montage because that's the stuff he has
to do in order to win the fight your
entire semester is your training montage
and if you don't use it correctly then
the test is not going to go well for you
it's just that simple but let's talk
about those couple of weeks going up to
the test whatever you did during the
semester revision is really important
and there's a couple of things you can
do to make it go more smoothly number
one is to go through your notes and the
other materials got throughout the
semester and see what areas of the
material that you're not really clear on
know your gaps that will allow you to
focus most efficiently on the facts and
Concepts you really need to solidify in
your mind and not waste too much time
going over stuff you're already pretty
clear on Additionally you can create
something that the author Walter Pac
calls a home stretch schedule this is a
more detailed schedule that you probably
don't need to break out during the
earlier days in the semester but in the
couple of weeks leading up to a test it
can be really useful so on this schedule
you want to make sure you block out time
for your set obligations like class and
work and also for the more mundane
things you take for granted like eating
and sleeping because these are very
important when you're studying for
finals but then you actually want to
block out time for studying that way
when you create that list of gaps and
the the material you need to go through
you know when you're going to actually
study it also when you're revising for
tests it's doubly important that you
study actively like if you're just
passively going through your notes and
textbooks you're wasting a lot of
precious time so make quizzes for
yourself and make sure you're having to
actively recall information and pull it
out of your brain now what if you tried
your hardest to prepare throughout the
semester and efficiently and you still
just don't feel confident about your
ability to do the test well well I've
got a couple of suggestions to ease that
fear and the first one is to Simply act
confident tell yourself that you're
going to do well in the test whenever I
go into a new situation where I feel a
little bit unprepared I just tell myself
that I'm going to do well I might not
but there's no reason to worry about it
so I just give myself the confidence you
can do this too and there's also one
other thing you can do to ease your
worries before a test and this is
actually backed up by science so a study
done by the University of Chicago
actually showed that students with test
anxiet were able to raise their test
grades by simply taking 10 minutes
before the exam to write out their
worries to air them out so if you're
feeling anxious about a test try this
show up a little bit early for the test
pull out a piece of scrap paper and
write out why exactly you're worried
this pulls it out of your brain puts it
on paper puts it aside and lets your
brain focus on the actual test science
and the final worry we're going to go
over in this video is the fear of the
stakes the fear that this test is the be
all end all the determining factor and
who you're going to be and where you're
going to get in life and I just wanted
to tell you it's not one test does not
define you and in fact your grades don't
Define you if you've ever read my blog
post on the Student Success triangle
you'll know that academic performance is
really just one point of the triangle
the other ones are value creation and
relationship building and if you're
putting in effort in these areas as well
as your academic performance one test is
not going to ruin you you can think of
your test in the same way that I think
of job interviews when I've gone into
interviews in the past I don't think of
it as an audience with this all powerful
Arbiter who decides whether or not I get
to stay in my mom's basement for the
rest of my life life no it's just a
conversation between two individuals who
want to figure out if they can provide
value for each other think of your test
the same way it's just one examination
of a small body of knowledge you've
learned over a set period of time that's
it but also feed off of some of that
pressure find your Center generate some
confidence and let that pressure hone
your senses let it make you stronger
rather than weaker now let's briefly
touch on those two final worries that I
alluded to earlier the first one is
perfectionism a lot of students feel
like they have to do absolutely perfect
on an exam and I just want to tell you
you don't the writer and speaker scottt
Burkin once said I don't want to be
perfect I want to be useful I want to be
good and I want to sound like myself
this should be your mindset going into a
test know your goals work as hard as you
can but don't expect absolute perfection
from yourself it's unhealthy and the
last worry is past failures if we fail
one time we tend to see a trend forming
and we think we're going to fail again
this is due to something called the
negativity bias which I'll talk about
more in depth in a future video but
basically we tend to put more weight on
negative experiences the thing to
realize here though is that the out come
of any particular situation is
determined by the factors that went into
it so if you change the factors you can
change the result change the way you
study and prepare you'll change the
grade you get on a test so that's it for
this video and once again I have to
leave you with a quote from the Roman
poet Horus who said in adversity
remember to keep an even mind hopefully
the tips here have helped to quell some
of the anxiety you're feeling about your
tests and if you're looking for more
tips on how to do better in your exams
well I have a couple of suggestions
number one I made a video at the end of
last semester on how to Ace your exams
and you can click right there to watch
it and also if you're looking for some
specific techniques to use during the
actual test my friend Simon Clark who's
a YouTuber from the UK made his own
video and you should check it out right
there also you should probably just
subscribe to him he makes good stuff
that's all I've got and if you have
additional tips that I didn't cover here
feel free to leave them down in the
comments for other students to see and
thanks so much for watching this
video hey guys thanks for checking out
my video on test anxiety if you enjoyed
it you can leave a like so other
students can find it more easily and
also you can get new videos on being a
more efficient student every single week
by hitting the big red subscribe button
right there if you want to improve your
grades I wrote an entire book on the
subject and it's actually free so if you
want to get your copy just click the
picture of the book you can find a
summary and links to anything I
mentioned in the companion blog post for
this video which you'll find by going to
the orange logo right there if you
missed last week's video there's a clip
of it playing so definitely check it out
and also if you want to connect or have
questions or ideas for new videos you
can leave a comment below or connect
with me on Twitter and speaking of
Twitter here's one final bonus tip for
test anxiety that I posted on my Twitter
page yesterday thanks for watching