hey what is up guys so I have got some
book recommendations for you today and I
am doing these in the middle of the
summer so for those of you who want to
get ahead before the school semester
starts you'll have at least a month and
a half right Martin about two months
maybe so I've got 10 books why am I
holding up two fingers that's not 10 10
books that I think every student should
read starting with my favorite book from
last year which is deep work by Cal
Newport this book is at the top of my
list because it tackles the number one
problem that I get emails tweets and
comments about which is I can't focus I
can't uh stop procrastinating I can't
get into the flow of my work and this is
something that I struggle with just as
much as most students and I think this
book really helped to point out the fact
that when we get these cravings for
novelty Cravings to check our Snapchat
or our Instagram or just distract
ourselves from our work and we act on
them we're actually ingraining a habit
and we're weakening that Focus muscle in
our heads and by contrast by avoiding
those distractions and by sticking with
our work we actually become more able to
focus and when that was explicitly
stated to me I took it more seriously
and I found it really really helpful in
my work book number two on my list is a
mind for numbers by Barbara Oakley now
this is the learning how tolearn book in
fact there's a course over on
coursera.org that you can take for free
called learning how to learn and it's
created by the same person and this book
is basically the companion to it and
even though the subtitle here is how to
excel at math and science this really is
a book about General learning skills now
this book has a lot to offer so I can't
really summarize the whole thing here
but a couple of the key lessons I took
away from from the book were number one
the process of memory formation how bits
become chunks which are essentially
Loosely grouped bundles of information
that are connected through meaning and
it talks about how to efficiently form
those chunks and it also talks about the
difference between the focused mode of
thinking and the diffused mode of
thinking now these are two complimentary
forms of thinking a focused mode is what
happens when you sit down and you focus
on a problem with intensity and you're
mainly using your prefrontal cortex when
you do this but the diffused mode of
thinking is just as important and uses a
lot more of your brain and it's kind of
what happens when you background process
a problem by taking a break or sleeping
on it and a good example is if you ever
try to think of a word it's on the tip
of your tongue but just can't get it and
then you take a break or you go for a
walk or you wake up from a nap later and
it comes to you so these two modes of
thinking help you to solve problems in a
compliment way and this book highlights
the importance of taking breaks so you
can use that diffused mode just as much
as the focused mode third book on my
list is getting from college to Career
by Lindsay Pollock and I think this is a
great introduction to a lot of the
career skills that you're going to need
to be able to get a job or the job that
you want after you graduate from college
now I was going to put so good they
can't ignore you by Cal Newport at this
spot in the list but I've already talked
about that book in the past and while
that talks about that big overarching
passion hypothesis question you know
what do I do with my life this book
really gets into the details and into
the trenches of how to get a job and how
to stand out amongst the competition it
talks about interviewing how to build a
resume how to build your online web
presence all the skills you need to
learn to be able to get that job that
you want fourth book book on the list
some of you definitely guess that it
would be on here The Power of Habit by
Charles doig and yes I've talked about
this book before but I really think that
you should give it a read if you haven't
done so already and the reason for that
is that habits form so much of our
behavior and when you know how to
intelligently build strong ones and
break the ones that you don't want to
have that are hurting you then you're
going to be so much more successful and
you're not going to be wasting as much
of your limited willpower on the things
you want to get done book number five on
my list is spark the Revolutionary new
science of exercise and the Brain by Dr
John R and I'm recommending this book
for two different reasons number one it
is a surprisingly detailed introduction
to how your brain works on a biological
level and I found that very interesting
but also for a certain subset of you out
there the scientific explanation of how
exercise affects the way that you learn
and can improve your overall brain
health can be a powerful motivator to
get into the habit of exercising more
often and I know from experience that as
a student or when you're just busy in
general it can be really tempting to put
off exerc izing in lie of giving
yourself more time to get your work done
but just like Cal newart talks about in
deep work the intensity of your focus
times the time you put in equals your
productivity and when you don't exercise
you're robbing your brain's ability to
focus intensely and work efficiently at
all book
5.5 Anime Club cuz there can be no
higher aspiration for a student than to
run their own Anime Club very serious
recommendation all right so the sixth
book on my list is the productivity
project by Chris Bailey and this book is
my favorite General introduction to the
concept of productivity now when most
people think of productivity they think
of time management but in this book
Chris is very careful to stress that not
all hours are created equal and
productivity is the product of your time
attention and energy So to that end the
book goes through a ton of different
productivity topics including
procrastination how to focus on your
tasks without getting distracted how to
avoid multitasking how to batch tasks
plan your day intelligently and gets
into things like meditation I also like
how every chapter ends with the
challenge so if you want to start
putting things into action he gives you
a lot of direction to do so the seventh
book on my list is the happiness
equation by Neil pasricha and I put this
book on my list because a lot of us
aren't actually very good at knowing
what's going to make us truly happy when
we're planning out our career goals or
other life goals we might look at what
Society seems to value or we might trick
ourselves in different ways but as
Neil's research points out in this book
A lot of people who are rich or in
positions of power Executives of big
companies they're not actually happy now
this book goes through a lot of
different things and there's a lot to
think about but one of the biggest
lessons that I took away personally from
this book is that Milestones don't
actually make us happy and this is
something that I've had to deal with
quite a bit in my life I mean if you
look right down there at that subscriber
count that's something that I use as
sort of a marker for my success in my
YouTube career but I remember the day
when I hit 100,000 subscribers it didn't
feel any different the bar just kind of
moved to a million and it didn't make me
any happier so I realized that happiness
actually comes from the Fulfillment in
the work itself not in the external
reward wordss and when you can
internalize that and accept it you're
going to be a lot happier on a
day-to-day basis all right so we are now
to book number eight in the list and
that book is steel The Show by Michael
Port which is a book all about
communication now a lot of this book
deals with how to give a great speech
how to prepare for it how to master your
body language how to get an ovation from
the audience at the end but it also
deals a lot with interpersonal
communication networking job interviews
negotiation tactics and for that reason
I think it's a great all-around
communication skills book that you
should read book number nine is your
money the missing manual by JD Roth
which is a great introduction to
personal finance now there are a ton of
personal finance books out there and I
actually run a personal finance podcast
myself so I can't tell you that this is
the best introduction to Personal
Finance in the world but it's the one
that I read and I found it very helpful
for learning how to manage my money how
to pay off my debt faster and had to
start investing smartly and that brings
us to my final pick on this list my
ultimate book recommendation for you
which is not actually any specific book
at all at this point in the video I want
to encourage you to go out and indulge
your interests productivity for
productivity sake is useless so you need
to be able to do something with all
these personal development tips that
you're learning from all these books I'm
recommending you the problem is a lot of
people who get interested in
self-development in productivity they go
too narrow they stick to the recommended
lists by online gurus and they never
actually Branch out and become experts
in something unique so if you have an
interest indulging go read a book about
the history of the Telegraph and at the
next party you're at you'll be able to
tell a cool story that nobody else will
know so hopefully you're not too
disappointed that I only really had nine
books on the list but I did think it was
important to mention that at the end and
I'm going to have links to all those
books down in the description below so
definitely check them out and on that
note of indulging your interests and
going and learning new and unique things
I want to recommend a channel that I
really like to you guys and that channel
is wise crack now there are a lot of
Education channels on YouTube but wise
crack is one of my favorites for the way
that they seamlessly blend nerd culture
and education they do it in a lot of
different ways with a lot of different
series including the philosophy of
series which takes anime and movies and
video games TV shows and it looks at the
philosophy that underpins their stories
so I'm going to put one of my favorite
recent videos from that Series right
there the philosophy of one punch man
along with their Thug Notes analysis of
my absolute favorite book of all time
the hitchers guide of the Galaxy right
there definitely check those out and go
give them a subscription if you like
their Channel and thank you guys so much
for watching hopefully you found this
video helpful give it a like if you did
and I will see you next week