I going to be 100% honest with you guys
here I am an absolute sucker for Roundup
lists of app recommendations and I know
I'm not the only one because I get asked
by you guys for app recommendations all
the time so here we are now my intention
this week was to sit down and make a
list of app recommendations for the
iPhone and then I was going to come back
next week and make a companion video for
the Android people but what I found out
when I started making my list is that
the majority of my picks are actually
crossplatform these days with very few
exceptions so instead of making two very
redundant videos I decided just to take
the IOS and Android halves and smash
them together into one delicious peanut
butter and jelly sandwich of a video and
in this video I'm going to be giving you
10 specific productivity app
recommendations you should check out and
fittingly we are going to be starting
with my to-do list recommendation now
when it comes to to-do list apps I
personally use a very powerful app
called Asana and I absolutely love it
however Asana is built mainly for teams
and it's got a lot of features you
probably won't need if you're just
managing your personal tasks so if
you're not managing a team like I am I
recommend wonderlist it's elegantly
designed it has apps on iOS Android and
lots of other platforms and it doesn't
lock essential features behind a paid
version like some other to-do managers
do now every good task management app
needs a calendar app as a companion and
while Google Calendar and IAL are both
good Fantastical is my calendar app of
choice the design is great it's one of
the few calendar apps that features
complication support on my Apple watch
but the killer feature for me is the
natural language processing instead of
typing out events I can speak them and
the app will intelligently parse what I
say and fill in event details
automatically Fantastical does not have
an Android version and the only Android
app I could find that has a similar
natural language feature is today
calendar which is around $5 after a free
trial now if you don't want to pay that
much and you can live without the
language processing feature I'd
recommend checking out S calendar for a
free full featured alternative habit
tracking is another practice that helps
me stay productive and my favorite app
for that is habitica along with a full
featured web app habitica has IOS and
Android apps that you turn tracking your
habits into a video game you can level
up a character you can buy gear and you
can join up with other people to go on
quests and keep each other accountable
you'll also find a college info geek
Guild within habitica that has over
7,000 members now if those video game
features aren't your cup of tea but you
still want to track your habits I'd
recommend checking out an app on iOS
called momentum which lets you simply
open the app check a box and move on
with your life you can also check off
habits within ios's today VI which is a
really cool feature on Android check out
habit bow for something that has similar
features for managing notes my app of
choice has always been Evernote this app
is pretty much my second brain I write
all my scripts in it I take notes in it
and I shove all sorts of information in
it that I want to remember now Evernote
is crossplatform but if you own more
than two devices which is the limit on
evernote's free tier you may want to
give Microsoft's OneNote a look as a
possible alternative I prefer Evernote
personally but I am a premium user and
the apps are pretty comparable and I
think one note does offer more on the
free tier than Evernote does anyway
while Evernote is keeping my notes
managed and synced to keep fil synced
and backed up across all my devices I
use dropbox it integrates amazingly with
a sauna which lets me attach files to
tasks in the blink of an eye and overall
I consider it to be one of the most
crucial Tools in my work setup next up
we've got scannable and app that lets
you automatically scan documents and
send them straight to Evernote other
than my idea notebook and Sketchbook I
try to keep my life as paperless as
possible and scanable lets me do that
really really easily now if you're not
nevern note user though I would check
out scanbot which offers a lot of
different export options additionally
it's also the app you should check out
if you're on Android since scannable is
an iPhone exclusive now if you often
find yourself getting distracted by your
smartphone while you're working you've
got a couple of different options number
one turn it off but number two if that
doesn't work you can download Forest
which is an app that rewards you for
leaving your phone alone by growing a
virtual tree now if you touch your phone
before a session is up the tree dies you
also get a record of your progress and
the positive reinforcement that provides
may be just the thing you need to
improve your focus speaking of focus one
of my favorite ways of getting focused
on a particular task is by using the
Pomodoro Technique and there are a ton
of Pomodoro style timer apps out there
feel free to check out as many as you
like but on the iPhone I'd recommend
going with Focus keeper while those of
you on Android should check out clear
Focus lastly one practice that helps me
stay productive throughout the entire
day is exercising which is why I use an
app called the 7-minute workout pretty
much every single day and this just
helps me make sure that even on the days
I don't go to the gym I'm still getting
some exercise in so guys that is my list
at least for this particular video now I
definitely have more apps on this bad
boy that I use and want to share with
you so I'm going to do more app Roundup
videos in the future and if you got app
picks of your own you can share them
down in the comments below before I wrap
this video up I did want to let you guys
in on one more thing and that is that
college infog geek t-shirts are now in
stock over at dftba.com and if I can
stand on my tiptoes enough you can kind
of see the shirt cuz I'm wearing it
right now but you can see the full
picture at the link in the description
and if you click that link you can also
buy a shirt if you want if you do get
one and you want to send me a picture of
it you can tweet me over at tomf
frankley and you can also use my to ask
me questions which I'll use for future
videos and future Q&A rapid fire
lightning style round video things and
that about does it for this week's video
guys so if you enjoyed it you want to
get new videos every single week on
being a more effective student you can
click that subscribe button right over
there and if you want to get a free copy
of my book on earning better grades you
can click the picture right there click
there to find another video you might
enjoy and you'll find more helpful
resource links in the description below
the like button which you can hit to
support this channel see you