so there's this fact of life that I
think about pretty often every single
one of us you me everyone else we are
all skeletons wearing meat suits
hurtling through space on a rocket
thousands of miles an hour and when you
really think about this fact it's
humbling but it's also totally rad and
it's a good reason for why we should
probably wear sunglasses indoors more
often but in addition to all that it
also means that we shouldn't really feel
nervous when we're meeting new people
after all they too are just shambling
stacks of collagen hurtling through
space at ludicrous speeds still a lot of
us get that tight feeling in the gut
when faced with the prospect of meeting
a new person and there are a lot of
deep-rooted reasons for this maybe you
fear being judged maybe if you're being
rejected or something that I struggle
with big time maybe you're just afraid
that you're gonna have nothing to save
the other person after you introduce
yourself and shake their hand and things
are gonna get awkward luckily there are
strategies that you can use to deal with
all of these problems and today we're
gonna go over some of the ones that
don't include ingesting fermented sugar
or limiting all of your interactions to
two-dimensional characters number one
detach your sense of self-worth from the
outcome of the meeting realize that
rejection doesn't matter in the long run
whether it's someone that you want to
ask out on a date or a potential
business contact or just somebody that
you admire the way that they respond has
no effect on your self-worth now if the
meeting goes poorly you're gonna feel
some embarrassment in the short term yes
that is unavoidable but once you get
over that feeling of embarrassment the
long-term effects are nothing but
positive that rejection and the survival
of that rejection just is another data
point that proves you can get through a
rocky meeting and come out the other
side intact and adopting this mindset
actually makes you a more attractive
person right off the bat because when
you're not preoccupied with the outcome
of the meeting you're gonna act more
naturally now a great way of getting
better at adopting this mindset every
time you go into an interaction is to
work on building a strong internal sense
of self confidence and that is a topic
for another video this one actually but
when you know that you're awesome you're
not constantly looking for external
validation to prop up your sense of
self-confidence whether it comes from
people praising you or people agreeing
with your tastes when you have that
strong core of self confidence you're
going to be much more able to make
through a situation where there's
potential rejection number two remember
that the meeting is a two-way street and
this means that the person you're
meeting is often just as nervous as you
are even if you feel that you're on the
wrong side of a power imbalance such as
meeting a famous person or trying to
talk to somebody who you feel is out of
your league people who are in the
limelight people who are constantly
showered with compliments they often
feel like they don't deserve them or
that they're being put on a pedestal and
they don't know how to react well and in
many cases it's not their social
confidence that has put them in the
limelight it's something else like their
talent as a writer or as a musician and
those things don't automatically
translate to being confident in social
situations a lot of celebrities and
famous people have attested to this many
of them have come out saying that
they're shy that they're uncomfortable
around new people including people like
Lady gaga number three do your research
on the other person sometimes now this
is not a tip that's going to apply to
spontaneous interactions if you meet
somebody at an event you shake their
hand and then you say one moment you go
into the bathroom to stalk them on
Facebook things are probably gonna get a
little bit awkward so in those cases
probably ignore this one but if you know
you're gonna meet somebody beforehand it
can be useful to take a few minutes glad
for their social profiles and try to get
a quick indication of what their
interests might be for example if you're
gonna be Elon Musk you might want to
know the current state of the Falcon
rocket projects and also that he likes
bees with top hats number four the next
tip is to practice visualization which
is essentially the practice of mentally
picturing a successful interaction
happening before you actually go into it
or in a more general sense visualization
just means picturing success in your
mind Confucius said it best he who says
he can and he who says he can't are both
usually right it comes right back down
to the internal sense of self confidence
when you are confident that you're going
to win or have a great interaction
you're much more likely to make that a
reality and many many athletes Olympians
movie stars famous people of all types
have used this technique to great effect
I think my favorite example is Jim
Carrey who actually wrote himself a fake
check for ten million dollars that was
dated three years in the future and then
kept that in his wallet I wrote myself a
check for ten million dollars for acting
services rendered and I put it in my
wallet and I kept it there and it
deteriorated and deteriorated and stuff
and just before
Thanksgiving 1995 I found out that I was
gonna make ten million dollars on
dumb and dumber yeah lots of athletes
use this technique as well the most
famous example probably being Michael
Phelps who when he was working with his
coach would go home every single night
and be instructed to watch the videotape
which wasn't actually a physical
videotape but it was a mental projection
of having a perfect race and well you
know how well he did number five
remember that you do not look as nervous
as you feel and this is something that I
have to remind myself of every single
time that I speak publicly when I first
started speaking publicly I was sure
that the nervousness I felt at shaking
in my hands that sort of static feeling
in my head was translating to the way
that I looked on stage but after I got
some video footage of my first few times
speaking I realized that that wasn't the
case at all maybe my emotions were a bit
robotic maybe I looked a bit unpolished
but the way that I felt was not
reflected in the way that I looked I
looked a lot calmer and when you realise
this you're actually gonna feel a lot
calmer as well numb about six take
deeper and slower breaths before you go
into an interaction where you're nervous
now all of us know that our body
language is affected by the way that
we're feeling and by what we're thinking
but this too is a two-way street and by
deliberately taking slower breaths
breathing in more deeply these things
can actually calm you down and lower
feelings of anxiety similarly changing
your posture or to do with your hands
can literally make you feel more
confident and even choosing to smile can
release chemicals that make you feel
happier so realize that the brain-body
connection is a two-way street and you
can deliberately affect it positively in
both ways number seven let the other
person do most of the talking this is a
great way to get over that fear of
having nothing to say which is my
biggest struggle in meeting new people
especially when I'm in a context where
there was not a whole lot that I can go
off of to strike up a conversation like
I'm at a wedding or something you know I
often feel like I don't have anything to
say but what I've learned is that people
love to talk about themselves and their
interests especially if you've
demonstrated that you're willing to
listen and be engaged so if you're
worried that you're gonna have nothing
to say let them take the lead listen
actively ask questions and if there are
opportunities for you to contribute well
you can finally I want to share a mantra
that I've tried to live by for a long
time an interest ed person is an
interesting person this applies not only
to showing interest in the other person
during a conversation but also to the
breadth and depth of your own interests
if you spend time learning widely then
you'll be able to speak knowledgeably
and passionately about a lot of
different things and that makes it so
much more likely you'll make connection
with anyone you meet and if you want to
start broadening your basic knowledge in
areas like nature and science and
history check out curiosity stream they
have over 2400 high-quality
documentaries and topics ranging from
artificial intelligence to funghi do the
history behind pompeii and lots lots
more and you can stream all these
documentaries to almost any device you
want as they have apps for iOS Android
Roku and lots more and you can do it
without paying a whole lot since the
subscription to curiosity stream is just
$2.99 per month and if you're looking
for a place to start I'd recommend david
attenborough's light on earth which
explores bioluminescence and you can
actually watch it for free because if
you go to link in the description down
below and use the code thomas when you
sign up you'll get a one-month free
trial huge thanks as always goes out to
curiosity stream for sponsoring this
episode being supporter of my channel
and thank you as well for watching if
you enjoy this episode maybe consider
hitting that like button and also get
subscribed right there so you don't miss
future videos when they come out of
course you can also grab a free copy of
my book and how to earn better grades
right there which might be relevant to
you since back-to-school is right around
the corner otherwise you can find a
couple more videos on this channel right
over here and here thanks for watching
and I will see you in the next one