what getting back here is not easy
all right ladies and gentlemen it is
time
for another what's in my backpack video
oh my gosh this thing's so heavy
now i haven't done one of these in over
two years i think and uh
even though i get a request probably at
least once a month for an updated what's
on my backpack video i held off because
quite honestly before now i really
didn't change my setup since 2017.
i got a new macbook but really nothing
else changed but
all things must come to an end all
things must change all things must take
a new
form and that is exactly what my
backpack is doing now
so basically i've been doing a lot of
traveling lately and while my
macbook pro is powerful it's not quite
the setup that i wanted it to be
so i have built what i consider to be
the
ultimate no compromises portable
workstation now what do i mean by no
compromises well when i'm
at home i've got access to my dual
monitor dual 4k
monitor is actually gaming workstation
which has a powerful cpu
a lot of ram a very good graphics card
and it also runs windows so i can play
games
and even though i've been using mac os
and windows for over 10 years
concurrently on a daily basis
i actually prefer windows so i have
decided
to take the leap and switch over to
windows and
not just switch to windows on the laptop
side but try to build
an equivalent experience or to get as
close as i can
to that desktop holy grail so that is
what i'm going to show you today we're
going to go through my backpack which
now contains the ultimate portable
workstation along with a few other
doodads that you might find
interesting but before we get inside the
bag let's talk
a little bit about the bag itself now if
you saw my 2017 video
the bag itself has not changed this is
the
e-bags professional slim laptop backpack
and it is
still my favorite backpack for everyday
work use
and also for traveling i've got all my
clothes in a suitcase i bring this on
the plane it's everything that i want it
to be not least of which because you get
this
bottom pocket here that is just perfect
for your laptop brick your charging cord
maybe a couple of other things but it's
nice and separated from everything else
in the bag
and it makes that charge cord really
really accessible
the other thing that i like a lot is the
flip out
organizational kind of flap here i have
never seen another backpack
do this it kind of lets you get access
to all these pockets the little pen
holders everything
without having to dig in and that is one
of the main reasons i like this pack
so that being said let's talk about
the ultimate portable gaming slash
productivity workstation all right
so the brains of the operation is
a pretty new laptop this is the asus
rog i guess republic of gamers zephyrus
gx701
it's a 17 inch gaming laptop but it's
actually
pretty thin and light um it's it's no
macbook pro it's no macbook air but it's
for a 17 inch gaming laptop quite
thin and pretty portable actually i
think the way they've done this is
number one they've made the bezels of
the screen just
much thinner than i've seen on previous
gaming laptops they also cut out the
webcam which
some people on the internet are kind of
mad about i could really care less
personally
another cool thing is when you open the
laptop it literally
raises itself up with this cool like
hinge thing that comes out of the bottom
to add extra cooling capacity so this
thing can run adobe premiere i can do my
editing
much better than any other laptop that
i've used in the past it can run games
at ridiculous frame rates
and it's honestly pretty great to work
with the only quirk that i've noticed
is well the keyboard is at the bottom
so if you have like a little tiny
counter to work at
like a coffee shop or something it's not
the ideal laptop because it's coming
right up to the edge
and i personally kind of like to have a
little bit of room to you know put my
wrists down or at least have some room
for my arms
but if there's a big enough table
wherever i'm going this thing works
just fine now my desktop is dual monitor
and you're thinking this thing
you know 17 inch screen it's pretty good
but it's not dual monitor tom it's not
the ultimate no compromises
portable gaming setup if you don't have
a second monitor and to that i say
i do so this is a pretty cool little new
addition
this is a usbc
portable full hd 1080p monitor and it
actually plugs into the laptop with just
a single usbc cord and it's got this
cool smart case which allows you to
kind of fold it into different
configurations so that one works
for just your standard landscape
orientation
and then you can actually fold these
down
and put it into portrait mode if you're
like a coder or something like that you
can
get all your code on there i guess man
like 100 lines of code so those two
taken together
enable me to have a perfect dual screen
setup wherever i am as long as i have a
big enough table
i use the keyboard on the laptop but
another kind of compromise with laptop
is the trackpad is really small
honestly the gestures are amazing the
drivers they have put into this thing
make it
nearly as good as a macbook pros track
pad in terms of how smooth it feels
which i found
very surprising but it's just kind of
tiny and it's not the easiest thing in
the world to use
so instead i've got a corsair i believe
this is the dark
core wireless gaming mouse and i've also
got a mouse pad in here
so these together i mean this is this is
it guys
this is basically no compromises the cpu
and a laptop is never really going to
match what you get in a desktop so
video render times are longer you can't
do quite as insane of animations in a
program like after effects as you can on
the desktop
but this is pretty much as close as
you're gonna get unless you wanna lug
around one of those truly
huge laptops with like a desktop grade
graphics card
and at that point you're getting a
different backpack and you're going to
have to do
a lot of squats and need a lot of boats
which you know i do
but i don't want to have to do that many
squats all right so getting into the
rest of the backpacks contents here
where you guys are probably actually
curious about
uh here in the bottom pocket here like i
said this is great for storing charge
cords and the you know computer
brick for your laptop and then up here
we've got a couple of other things one
we got a single
folder for papers now stay tuned for
next
week's video because i'm doing a whole
guide on file organization i've got some
alternative options for people who get a
lot of papers
but if you're like me if you digitize
almost everything that you get
and you're also not in school and don't
get a whole lot of handouts i think a
single folder
is perfectly adequate for storing papers
temporarily
and then you know coming home later on
and getting them either digitized or
into an actual filing cabinet
okay so for the next item i want to go
back to one of the drawbacks i mentioned
for this gaming laptop
the battery life is not the greatest
thing in the world and
if i have easy access to a plug that
isn't an issue
but on occasion i'm gonna go to a place
where i just don't have an
outlet and i might need to do a lot of
work so if i'm doing heavy duty you know
video editing gaming all kinds of stuff
like that it's going to happen on the
laptop but if i'm just doing
a really simple task like a writing i
don't necessarily need this
so if i'm traveling somewhere i don't
want to bring two laptops
i can just bring this ipad mini and with
the case here it can easily stand up
and then i can pair it with a bluetooth
keyboard
now this is not the apple bluetooth
keyboard this is a logitech
k811 but i find this to be a lot better
than apple's bluetooth keyboard the
key travel just it feels nicer it feels
more substantial
and the other nice thing is it can
actually switch between three different
bluetooth
devices so if you've got an ipad and
maybe like a desktop computer or a phone
you could easily switch
between them but put those two things
together and you have a really nice
portable writing setup that lasts
for 10-12 hours hours oh one little
other feature that i didn't mention
about this backpack it does have this
nice
padded and shallow pocket in the top
here that's perfect for an ipad mini
or for a little notebook again just like
with the folders i don't do a whole lot
with paper i don't take a whole lot of
notes by hand but
occasionally i do want to draw something
out or i want to write some notes by
hand
so i've just got this little free
notebook that i got from a co-working
space
in there and i can make to-do lists and
all kinds of other stuff and that brings
us to
the i guess the main pocket of the
backpack this is like the laptop pocket
but there's more room in here
the first thing that i have here this
isn't something that i keep in my
backpack all the time
but when i'm traveling i put this sword
along
three prong that's the most important
part three prong extension cord in the
backpack
that way if i need to sit somewhere
that's not very close to an outlet
i have a little bit of extra length that
i can use to plug in
the other thing is this cord has three
plugs on there
so number one if i need to charge
multiple devices i can do that
but if i'm at an airport or i'm at a
very busy coffee shop where all the
outlets have been dominated by other
people
i can make new friends i can split one
outlet into two
and i'm good to go also in this main
pocket we've got
the headphones these are the same
headphones i've been using for two years
they're the bose
they're the bose qc35s they're wireless
bluetooth
noise canceling headphones and the noise
cancelling aspect
is the game changer i was unconvinced
about
active noise cancelling until my friend
martin let me try his
i think there were beats noise canceling
headphones a couple of years ago
right away i was sold on the benefits
because
when you have that active noise
canceling it essentially
opens up a whole plethora of different
study spaces and workspaces to you
because where places were too noisy
before
they are now perfectly workable so if
you've got a coffee shop where they've
blasted music too loud or people are
always talking
you can just pop these on and you are
not going to hear any of what is going
on around you and you can actually focus
on what you got to do
and last thing in this pocket is uh just
a big novel i would usually read books
on the kindle app but
i just really wanted the physical
version of this because i saw it sitting
on a bookstore shelf
and uh children of ruin is it's a sequel
to a sci-fi novel that i read last year
and it's
absolutely fantastic so far that brings
us to all like the knickknacks stuff
right all the tiny little things in here
so
got a couple of things a marker um like
various
little knickknacks in here but this is a
just a little business card case
and i always recommend just carrying
around a couple of business cards
you know if you are trying to find
clients trying to find potential
colleagues to work with if you're
looking for a job
just having a couple of business cards
in your backpack will allow you to
you know hand someone one and let them
remember you in a pretty classy way
what else oh yeah we got all our cords
every single kind of cord that you could
want so micro usb mini usb usbc
apple lightning is in there also we've
got dongles
because you know i went to that new
macbook pro last year so i'm living that
dongle life
and uh it's not all that necessary on
the big windows laptop the i o is pretty
good on that thing
but it does have uh hdmi and the sd card
reader slot that's one thing that almost
all laptops i see nowadays have been
jettisoning so
as a content creator as a youtuber with
a sd card and that camera right there
kind of need the dongle presentation
remote so if you do speeches anywhere a
presentation remote that plugs into your
laptop and lets you
advance slides can be really really
handy and a pair of cheap sunglasses
i don't buy expensive sunglasses because
i break or lose them all the time so i
just buy like packs of three or five on
amazon for a dollar
and uh you know ironically i haven't
lost a pair in quite a while but these
also didn't cost me much and they worked
perfectly fine for me and lastly we've
just got a few things in here
flash drive i still actually use a flash
drive even though i'm a devotee of
google drive and
in the past dropbox sometimes you need
to transfer big files quickly for
example i will be giving all the footage
for this video to
my editor and even though we could
transfer it online it's going to be
quicker for him to just take this flash
drive home and then immediately
transfer the footage to his computer
because there's going to be gigabytes of
it
oh how could i forget my john wick coin
just in case i get ex communicado
sometime i'm gonna need this to buy
i don't know various weaponry or a suit
or a dog
yeah the webcam that comes with laptop
one thing i will note about this is even
though some people are kind of annoyed
that they didn't build the laptop
with a webcam in the chassis the webcam
that they
include in the box is actually a lot
better than most laptops have built in
so for my money this is actually a
better solution because when i want to
use a webcam i would rather
it be higher quality than be built into
my laptop and finally
rounding things out we have a little usb
thing for the wireless mouse and a
couple of iphone bricks and that's
about it so that is it that is basically
everything in my bag
though one thing that i do want to
mention before we end this video
is this book that i mentioned earlier
children of
ruin i'm about 135 pages into it so far
and i'm gonna make a prediction now that
this will be my favorite sci-fi novel of
and i say that with confidence because
the first book in this series children
of time
was indeed my favorite sci-fi novel of
2018. it was absolutely fantastic
listen actually because i listened to it
while i was on a 10-hour trip from
denver to iowa for christmas
and if you want to dig into that book as
well now is a great time to do it
because you can get it on
audible and if you are an amazon prime
member you can actually get three months
of audible for just 4.95
per month by going over to audible.com
thomas or by texting thomas to 500 500
on your phone and that is an excellent
deal because you're basically getting
three months for the price of one
but you're going to want to do it soon
because that offer ends july 31st now
for my part audible is one of my most
used apps on a daily basis because
whenever i'm commuting somewhere or
going for a long bike ride or cooking
dinner
i love to listen to audiobooks and
audible is the best place on the
internet to get your hands on audiobooks
they have the largest library of
audiobook titles that you're going to
find anywhere including all the best
sellers
and both of my recommendations for this
month because in addition to children of
time i'm also going to recommend
the productivity project by chris bailey
and the reason i'm recommending this one
is because we are getting really close
to a new semester and the productivity
project is
an excellent productivity overview if
you want to learn how to manage your
time
your attention and your energy more
efficiently it is a
great book to dig through now with
audible you get one credit every single
month that is good for any audiobook in
their library
plus two audible originals that you
cannot get anywhere else and
hundreds of audio workout and meditation
and fitness programs
so if you are an amazon prime member you
can go over to audible.com
thomas or text thomas to 500 500 on your
phone to get
three months of audible for just 4.95
for each of those months big thanks as
always goes out to audible for
sponsoring this video and being a big
supporter of my channel and thank you
for watching as
well if you enjoyed this video
definitely hit that like button get
subscribed right there and also download
a free copy of my book on how to earn
better grades over
there last but not least you can find a
couple more videos on this channel right
over here and here and i will see you
in next week's video