today I'm gonna share seven quick
general workflow tips that I use to
boost my productivity on a daily basis
and the commonality between all these
workflow tips is that they are focused
on shaving time off of repeated
processes these are things that I do
every single day often multiple times a
day now none of these tips are specific
to any one job or profession of them are
even specific to any one computer
application though most of them do
target things that happen within your
computer in the computer so if the work
that you do happens on a computer than
this video is primarily for you though
with one of these tips we are going to
venture out into the real world alright
let's get into it
tip number one use text expansion to
bind long strings of text that you have
to type often to small key words for
example I'm using a program called
autohotkey on my PC to bind my home
address to the keyword h8 dr now at
least on windows autohotkey is probably
the best way to do this number one it is
absolutely free and number two it is
incredibly powerful it has a lot more
can do besides just text expansion on
the Mac side use a program called a text
which is about 5 bucks it's not free but
it does have a lot of customization
options and it's really easy to use and
if you want to do this on Android or iOS
there are text expansion options for
both of those platforms as well and I'll
have some links in the description below
if you're interested in that tip number
2 start using your computer's quick
access areas more often whether you're
on Mac or PC the file explorer program
that comes stock with your computer has
a little sidebar or you can put
shortcuts to the folders that you use
most often for my workflow I keep
persistent links to Google Drive to a
lot of my businesses folders and to the
folder where screenshots or
automatically saved on my computer and
in addition to all those folders I also
keep temporary shortcuts to all the
videos that I'm working on until they're
done tip number 3 spend some time
learning the keyboard shortcuts for the
programs that you use most often back
when I was in college I spent a lot of
time learning the keyboard shortcuts for
Evernote which made me a much faster
note-taker and in recent years I spent a
lot of time learning the ones for
Photoshop After Effects and Premiere all
of which make my video editing process a
lot more efficient now in addition to
the specific programs that you use for
your work be it Logic Pro or be it
blender or whatever it is I would also
suggest going and learning the shortcuts
for your email program because simply
learning that in Gmail at least hitting
II can archive a message
hitting pound can delete a message these
can make your email processing time a
lot
shorter and one good thing to note is
that for most popular programs there are
cheat sheets out there that you can find
for the most important keyboard
shortcuts though if you do use a really
complex program like logic or like After
Effects I would also recommend having a
personal reference the keyboard
shortcuts that you use most often and on
the off chance that keyboard shortcuts
are actually interesting to you that you
can go even further down the rabbit hole
and start learning about the wide world
of macros these are buttons on your
keyboard or sometimes on external
devices that you can program to do
basically whatever you want and if you
want your head to spin in a good way
then a good place to start would be any
of Teheran fan humorous videos on
keyboard macros over at the Linus tech
tips channel alright so we are now on to
tip number four and for this step we are
going to briefly venture out of the
computer and into the real world because
I'm going to suggest that you put any of
your commonly used physical tools within
arm's reach of your workspace now to do
this for myself I'm using a swivel
drawer that screws into the bottom of my
desk and I did just discover there is
now like clamp on version so that's even
more accessible but within mine I've got
scissors I've got SD cards in case I
need more camera memory space I've got a
little pin for resetting different
devices got a box cutter pens pencils
highlighters sticky notes all kinds of
stuff that I find myself frequently
reaching for tip number five use a
launcher tool a launcher tool is a
little utility in your computer that
essentially lets you hit a very quick
key combination that brings up a little
window or you can type and then lets you
easily launch websites programs files
all kinds of other stuff now the best
launcher tool that exists in the entire
world is called Alfred and it is
unfortunately Mac only but by hitting
command and space on my Mac I can forget
this nice little typing window that lets
me launch any website any folder I want
and do lots of other things ranging from
really simple stuff like doing
calculations to lots of complex and
really deep user generated workflows
like this one which deeply links into my
password manager dashlane and lets me
find a password or username without
having to actually go over to the
application and search using its window
now unfortunately nothing quite as good
as alfred exists on windows but there is
an open-source program called walks
which is free and does a lot of what
alfred does except for some of that
really complex workflow stuff tip number
six I guess I need a second hand this
time use
clipboard manager now whether you're
using a Mac or a PC your computer has a
clipboard where you can copy text or
copy images and then paste them
elsewhere the problem is that computers
by default only remember the very last
thing that you copied so if you've
copied something awhile ago and then you
copied something later on that thing you
copied first it's just gone and I don't
know about you but I want my clipboard
to remember more than just one thing and
it can with the clipboard manager now on
Windows the absolute best one that I
found is called clipboard Health Plus
spell and it can do a lot more than just
saving your clipboard history you can
have favorites you can do all kinds of
different stuff and on the Mac side
there are tons of dedicated clipboard
managers as well but wouldn't you know
it Alfred also has a built-in clipboard
manager I just love Alfred so use that
unless you really really want something
dedicated for some reason that brings us
to our final tip in the video lucky
number seven try using virtual desktops
so here's the thing I love using dual
monitors but not everyone can afford a
second monitor and not everyone has the
space for a second monitor even if they
do have the money to buy one but if you
find yourself in either of those
situations you don't have to have tons
of things crowding up your desktop all
the time because all major OS platforms
Windows Mac and Linux have virtual
desktops which basically means you can
switch from one desktop to another
really really easily and you can put
different programs on different desktops
so for me when I'm working at a coffee
shop from my Mac I don't have a big
monitor like this behind me I like to
put my email and my Spotify my password
manager on my second desktop that way my
first desktop can be completely
dedicated to my browser additionally on
the Mac when you fullscreen an app it
gives its own virtual desktop and I
often use that when I'm writing an
Evernote or in type Ora so to do a quick
recap here number one use text expansion
to bind long string to text that you
often have to type two very short key
words to start using your computer's
quick access area to create shortcuts to
come in folders we learn the keyboard
shortcuts for the apps that you use most
often or find a way to put commonly use
tools within arm's reach of your
workspace maybe use a swivel drawer five
use a laundry tool like Alfred or walks
six start using a clipboard manager and
finally number seven clean up your
desktop by using multiple virtual
desktops now starting to use any one of
these seven tips can definitely make a
marginal improvement to your workflow on
a day-to-day
but if you also want to make sure that
the foundations of your productivity are
solid ones then you may also want to go
and take my productivity systems course
over on Skillshare in less than an hour
of this course will guide you through
the process of properly setting up your
task manager your calendar your file
organization system and more and along
the way you'll also learn how to make
sure these systems stay organized over
the long term and since this course is
on Skillshare you can actually go and
take it for free by being one of the
first 500 people to use link in
description down below to sign up for a
two month free trial once you've got
that you'll also have access to more
than 27,000 other courses on Skillshare
they can help you boost your skills in
graphic design and video production in
marketing and many many other areas
including an area that I'm personally
interested in right now which is music
production and if you have the same
interest then I'll also recommend you
check out young gurus course on mixing
music or dig into Martin Svendsen's
14-hour mega course on editing with
Logic Pro a Premium Membership on
Skillshare is super affordable less than
ten bucks a month and like I said
earlier if you were one of the first 500
people to use that link in the
description down below to sign up you're
also gonna get two month unlimited free
trial of their service big thanks to
Skillshare for sponsoring this video and
being a big supporter of my channel and
as always guys thank you so much for
watching if you enjoyed this video hit
that like button get subscribed for new
videos every single week and maybe click
right there to get a free copy of my
book on how to earn better grades you
can also check out one more video on
this channel right here and if you
haven't checked out my podcast yet you
might want to check it out right here
especially because in a couple of days
we have an entire episode coming out all
about how to improve your workspace
you're gonna want to keep your eyes
peeled for that thanks once again for
listening and as always I will see you
in the next video