if there is one thing that we
productivity guru rock starred mogul
ninja samurais love to go on and on
about it is our schedules how utterly
customized and tailored they are towards
our optimal working conditions our
prototypes and our secret Wow rating
addictions but every single time we
write another blog post or make another
video about our scheduling hacks I know
there are many of you out there who are
simply tearing your hair out how
unhelpful they are for you because you
are dealing with an inconsistent and
chaotic schedule that is out of your
control whether it's due to your class
schedule or a job you simply don't have
time for three-hour morning routines
with FEHB asana meditations or to our
forest bathing sessions in the middle of
the workday to say nothing of
consistently cooking dinner on a regular
basis or getting to the gym as many
times a week as you want so what can be
done for people in this situation what
do you do if you have an inconsistent in
chaotic schedule that seems to hamper
the development of new habits and block
your progression towards your goals well
I've actually got a few suggestions for
you in this video today because I have
been in this situation in the past yes
now as an entrepreneur I'm able to set
my own schedule but that wasn't always
the case all throughout high school I
have part-time jobs at grocery stores
and Target and lots of other places
where my manager basically set my
schedule I had pretty much no say in the
matter and even in college I worked at a
job where I had different hours almost
every single week so from those
experiences as well as a lot of online
research that I did in preparation for
this video I want to give you some
suggestions for making the most of an
inconsistent schedule and still making
progress on your goals despite it and
the first thing that I'm going to share
here is lesson that I learned very early
on when I started my first job in
college at the campus IT Center which
was that I had to get my schedule into
my own personal calendar as soon as I
possibly could see my first job in
college was working at the tech support
center answering calls and helping
people fix their computers and the cool
thing about that job is that you could
basically choose your own hours every
single week but there was a catch every
week at a specific day and a specific
time a giant calendar of our slots would
become open to every employee in the
company which means that it was a
first-come first-served thing if you
were there first you basically had the
best pick of hours you could get exactly
what you wanted but if you were there
even say five minutes late
times you could be looking at slim
pickings and there were certainly some
weeks early on in my first semester at
that job before I had really learned how
important it was to get there early
where this happened to me so after a few
harsh weeks trying to fill my our quota
with a bunch of little random half an
hour sessions here and there between
classes I learned two important lessons
number one be sitting at that calendar
refreshing it over and over and over
again right when those hours opened and
number two which is the less I want to
share here the moment I understood what
my schedule was on that work calendar I
needed to transfer it over to my Google
Calendar my personal calendar now you
know this is important for knowing when
you're supposed to go to work but this
is also important for being able to
develop healthy habits and work on your
independent projects as well what we're
trying to avoid here is derailment the
railing on your goals the railing on
your habits and yes ultimately the thing
that's going to cause this to happen is
a lack of motivation and a lack of a
self-discipline
but the catalyst for those things can
often be that inconsistent schedule we
kind of run on schedules we run on
consistency and when external factors
are really kind of destroying that for
us it can be hard to actually
self-regulate so the way that I combated
that the way that I lessened its impact
on my life was by getting very good at
managing my own personal schedule and at
getting things into my calendar as early
as possible what this did was allowed me
to sit down at the beginning of the week
and look at my calendar from a bird's
eye view yes it was an inconsistent
schedule but I was able to identify lots
of little blocks of time that were free
to me so maybe I couldn't say go to the
gym every single morning or have time to
cook dinner at the same time every
single night but I could look and say
all right I've got Monday and Wednesday
free so I'm going to schedule gym time
during those free blocks Tuesday
mornings taking up my work in class but
I do have a tiny block Tuesday afternoon
free so maybe I'll go for a run then and
when I found over the years is that when
I plan things in advance I feel sort of
beholden to my past self so it's more
likely that I'm going to actually do
them it's definitely not foolproof it's
not like I got a combat boot wearing
fairy about ready to kick me in the butt
if I don't do what I set out to do but
it's much better than trying to decide
in the moment that I'm going to do
something because I've got a couple of
free hours so when you've got an
inconsistent schedule make sure you're
getting things into your personal
calendar as early as you possibly can
and then sitting down once a week over
your calendar and picking out those free
hours that aren't already taken up by
something and deciding what you're going
to do with them ahead of time now one
thing that I fortunately didn't have to
deal with during my years of part-time
job work was night shift work having an
inconsistent sleep schedule dictated by
my job but I know that this is something
that a lot of people do deal with
including a couple of friends of mine
who work at a hospital so I wanted to
include a few tips for if you're in this
situation as well first and foremost if
the consistency of your sleep is under
attack by an inconsistent schedule then
what you need to prioritize getting is
enough sleep you may not be able to get
it at the same time every single night
but you can at least make sure you're
getting enough now one of the things
that can really hamper this goal for a
lot of shift workers is the fact that
they're trying to get sleep during the
day and they're under assault by light
coming in through their windows by noise
being made by their roommates or t-rex's
in the other room if you work a drastic
park all kinds of stuff so what do you
do in that situation well tip number one
you get what I have hanging right over
there in this studio a pair of good
blackout curtains see your body's
circadian rhythm the synchronization
with the day and night schedule and part
of the biological process that regulates
your sleep is heavily influenced by the
amount of light that you are perceiving
to give you a really quick refresher
from ninth grade biology class in your
eye you have in addition to cones and
rods that sense things like detail and
color and movement something called a
photosensitive retinal ganglion cells
and these cells perceive light and send
signals to a part of the brain called
the suprachiasmatic nucleus now this
little piece of brain hardware sends
instructions to other parts of the body
which regulate the production of
hormones like melatonin and cortisol and
these affect your sleep in your sleep
drive so long story short if you have a
bunch of light coming in through your
window where you're trying to get some
sleep because it's 7 a.m. and you just
got done with a shift you're gonna have
a harder time actually falling asleep
your body doesn't think it's the time
for sleep but if you have a pair of
blackout curtains then that basically
solves the problem your room is dark and
your body can think that it's nighttime
of course light isn't the only problem
you have to deal with if you're trying
to sleep during the day because you also
have to contend with noise whether it's
your roommates in the other room or
literally the band dragonforce if you
are a particularly sleepy roadie so to
deal with all that noise make an
investment in a good pair of earplugs
and buy investment I mean like $2
because earplugs are super cheap now one
thing that I do want to mention before
we move
on from this issue of dealing with your
sleep schedule is that you could
actually change that sleep schedule most
people sleep in what's called a mono
phasic sleep schedule which means they
sleep in one long seven to eight hour
block of time each night but there are
also polyphasic sleep schedules now a
lot of these are ineffective and result
in not sleeping enough hours total but
the one that I want to suggest here
which can be effective is the simple
biphasic sleep schedule this is a
schedule where you have a four to five
hour core block of sleep each night
followed by a two to three hour longer
nap during the middle of the day or at
some other time and there was actually a
nasa-funded study that looked at the
effectiveness of this sleep schedule for
astronauts and they came to the
conclusion that split sleep schedules
are feasible and can be used to enhance
the flexibility of sleep work schedules
for space operations involving
restricted nocturnal sleep due to
mission critical task scheduling dim
run-on sentences it goes on to say that
these results are generally applicable
to any continuous industrial operation
that involves sleep restriction night
operations and shift work so given those
results this might be something to look
into if you don't have time for a mono
phasing schedule now one thing to note
is that all the tips we've gone over so
far are meant to help you deal with a
chaotic schedule but ultimately the goal
should be to actually escape it yes for
people with certain career goals like
EMTs or surgeons inconsistent schedule
might just come with the territory but
for most of us having a chaotic schedule
is just kind of part of paying our dues
it's a byproduct of the jobs and
obligations we have to take on over in
school or otherwise to climb up the
ladder so if you eventually want to have
a more consistent and manageable
schedule and be able to have those
three-hour morning routines then be on
lookout for jobs and opportunities that
would get you closer to it or negotiate
with your manager or your current job
once you've proven yourself to see if
you can start moving towards more
consistent hours there and of course use
some your free time to bolster your
career skills so you can put yourself in
a better negotiating position work on
your soft skills like communication and
organization but also work on becoming a
better creative problem-solvers someone
who can tackle the more challenging
complex problems that every business
deals with and if you want a resource
that you can use to start building those
problem-solving abilities check out
brilliant brilliant is a math and
science learning tool that focuses in
helping you learn actively and become a
truly capable problem solver of course
or you immediately in the challenging
problems
not only help you learn about subjects
like calculus and machine learning
really effectively but also help you
become universally better at dealing
with the type of complex problems you'll
face in your future career brilliants
library has courses on probability on
math quantitative finance physics and
astronomy and computer science topics
like algorithms and memory and in
addition to being able to learn right on
their website you'll also find mobile
apps allow you to work on your courses
wherever you are
so to start learning for free headin
over to brilliant org slash Thomas Frank
and if you wanted the first 83 people to
click that link in the description down
below and sign up you're also gonna get
20% off your annual premium subscription
I want to give a big thanks to brilliant
for sponsoring this video of being a
supporter of this channel and as always
guys thank you so much for watching if
you enjoyed this video maybe think about
hitting that like button and also
subscribe right there if you don't want
to miss future videos when they come out
every single week you can also get a
free copy of my book and how to earn
better grades by clicking right there
follow me on instagram at tom frankly
and last but not least you can get one
more video on this channel by clicking
right here thanks for watching and I'll
see you guys in the next video