hey what's up guys so last week we did a
video about whether or not music is an
effective study Aid or if it's just a
distraction and at the end of that video
I said I wanted to follow it up with a
video on music that's intentionally
designed to increase Focus or
concentration or some other cognitive
function and well to be honest that
video's research isn't ready yet I've
been researching all week and I'm going
to put a comment down below this video
if you want some more explanation on it
but in short I'm G to have that video
coming out next week so I have a little
bit more time to polish it and make it
as good as you guys deserve but I didn't
want to just not publish anything this
week so I went looking in the College
inuki Community which has been up for a
few weeks now and there was a really
good question by a student who said uh
often I'm paired up with group members
that refuse to do any work uh no matter
how many times I attempt a conversation
or email them or uh phone them or even
just talk to them face to face I don't
know if they lack motivation or if
there's just something wrong with me
that they refuse to work with me help so
the question really here is how do I
deal with group members that aren't
contributing to the group project and I
have had to deal with this before I know
like personally friends of mine who have
been sitting up at almost like 11:59
p.m. waiting for a group member to email
the last part of a group project so they
can submit it when it's due at midnight
like this is a common problem so in this
video I've got five quick tips for you
to deal with unresponsive or Co
uncooperative or lazy group members and
the first tip is to consider that maybe
it's not a laziness issue maybe it isn't
that they are simply not doing any work
and rather it's actually a communication
problem with your group there could be
just inefficiencies in how you guys
communicate or share files or get things
done so when the group project is set up
and you're able to communicate for the
first time in class after all the
details are given I think you should
really take stock of everything that
needs to be done divvy up all the work
and assign roles and assign tasks and
have everyone in the group verbally
affirm what they're going to do that way
everyone else knows what they said
they're going to do they're a little bit
more beholden to it and they are
accountable to everyone else also during
that first meeting it is critical that
you get as much communication
information from each group member as
they are comfortable giving so email
address or phone number or whatever it
is just in case something comes up but
tip number two I think it's much better
to use a tool that is specifically
designed for group work rather than
trying to communicate through email or
something in the past I've used things
like Google Docs or base camp or Trello
but the one I'm using right now is
called Asana and I'm going to recommend
it because I am loving this tool and I'm
using it for all the work that I do with
both of the people who regularly help me
with work on College infogeek it's
totally free for groups of up to 10
people so you'll never have to pay for
it and it's just really good for
assigning tasks and keeping projects
really well organized you can sync up
Dropbox so it's really easy to attach
files and overall I just absolutely love
it so tip number three is to pay very
close attention to deadlines and
structure the project so that there are
many deadlines along the way so say you
have a group project and there's five of
you and it's due in two weeks so instead
of being like all right this is your
role this is your role and you guys go
do it and get it all done by the due
date you need to build uh basically
checkpoints along the way for each
person to send work to an editor or a
project manager and I'm going to say
like if you're worried about group
members not pulling their weight or the
group project not getting done in
general it's probably a good idea for
you yourself to take on the project
management role because if you're
worried about this you're likely to be
one of the more responsible members in
the group but with these manyi deadlines
you can make sure things are along
schedule you can make sure people aren't
procrastinating and I think it is
absolutely essential for one deadline in
particular to be created and that is a
deadline for everyone to get everything
they need to contribute to to the editor
of the project at least one day before
the deadline preferably two that way the
editor has time to get everything in
order and actually submit it before the
deadline so now we've moved on to tip
number four which is emailing the
professor so maybe the communication is
not an issue maybe the tools are not an
issue and you really just have somebody
who is unresponsive or who's just not
getting their work done and they're
dragging the entire group down you feel
you need to bring the issue to your
professor well you can do that but you
need to think very carefully before you
do and make sure you do it in the right
way because it's it's very possible that
your professor is trying to structure
this group project as a simulation for
the real world where there is a project
manager who is responsible for the group
and if you're that project manager or if
somebody else at the pro is the project
manager it's their responsibility to do
what they can to make sure the project
is on track before you escalate it to a
supervisor which is in this case your
professor so if you haven't already
emailed that member who's not doing what
they're supposed to do if you haven't
already escalated that to a face face
Toof face conversation in class your
professor might well ask you why you
didn't do that before bugging them with
the problem also if you're going to go
to the professor you want to do it early
on in the project right when the when
the problem re your its head and you've
already tried things out rather than
waiting because they're going to ask you
why did you wait until now to bring this
problem to me rather than nipping it in
the bud right when it was uh actually a
problem and that brings us to the last
and most inconvenient tip which is that
you might just need to suck it up do the
work for them and let them ride your
coattails it sucks it's awful totally
unfair but but it's great training for
the real world there was actually
somebody in the subreddit who expressed
a lot of surprise when I said that they
were like wait a minute people in the
real world aren't more responsible than
people in college and I would say on the
whole people do mature they grow up they
become more responsible than they were
as teenagers or college students but
there's always going to be people in
almost any organization you work in in
the future that aren't going to pull
their weight or they're going to be
disorganized or they're just not going
to communicate well and you're going to
have to deal with that and professors
know that that's why they build group
projects part of the intention here is
to help you work in a group and deal
with those kind of issues and they know
that some people are not cut out for
group work and they're just not
responsible so hopefully this video has
been helpful to you in some way I know
dealing with unresponsive group members
is absolutely awful and that's why in
college when I had the option to I often
elected to do group projects by myself
instead of with a group but sometimes
you have to deal with a unfortunate
situation so if you have additional tips
or you want to discuss this video there
will be an official discussion thread in
the College inek Community linked down
below Below in the description and as
always thank you so much for watching
and I will see you next
week hey there guys thanks so much for
watching this video If you want to get
new videos every single week on being a
more effective student you can click
that big red subscribe button right
there I also wrote a book on how to earn
better grades which has an entire
chapter on group projects so if you'd
like to get a free copy of it you can
click a picture of the book and if you
want to read the article for this video
click the orange logo right there and
last week's video we talked about the
relationship between music and studying
so if you missed that video and you want
to dig into it click the thumbnail and
if you want to connect with me I'm on
Instagram and Twitter at tomf Frankle or
you can leave a comment down below or in
the discussion
[Music]