what's up guys welcome to the second
video in my little series on speed
reading now if you missed the first
video you can watch it right there but
that one went over the science of how
the reading process actually works both
how our eyes move and fixate on text and
how our brain constantly pauses to
process that incoming information now
for this video I want to take a look at
three commonly touted speed reading
techniques that all claim they can
circumvent or augment some part of this
process in order to increase your
reading speeds and these three
techniques include number one enlarging
the area of your fixations essentially
allowing yourself to read text in your
peripheral vision number two eliminating
sub vocalization suppressing that voice
inside your head that speaks when you're
reading and number three what's called
rapid serial visual processing showing
each word in succession in the same
exact spot the question is do any of
these techniques actually work let's
start with the claim that some speed
readers can fixate on larger areas of
the page there's actually some speed
readers who even claim that they can
take a single mental snapshot of a page
and process the entire Page's text
inside their head all at once similarly
a 1962 study CED somebody who could read
it 10,000 words per minute by making
only six fixations per page and the
weird part here is this person claimed
they made the fixations in a
counterclockwise motion going around the
edges of the page they didn't follow the
lines of the text at all however the
problem with that study is there was no
formal measure of comprehension so it
wasn't really clear what this person was
remembering from their reading at all
additionally further Studies have shown
that good reading comprehension can only
be had when people follow the lines go
figure and here's the kicker you can't
read text and understand it if it's in
your peripheral vision it has to be
within that fval range or just outside
of it in fact a 1987 research paper on
speed reading reported only one correct
answer out of 30 test cases where a
reader was tested on information that
was three letter spaces or more from an
area they had fixated on add these
findings to what we already know about
the I fial range and the results are
clear fixations are very small and we
can't comprehend text that doesn't fall
within or very very near them but what
about eliminating subvocalization some
speed reading courses agree that you do
need to fixate on text in order to
comprehend it but they also o claim that
subvocalization essentially your brain
speaking the things you're reading aloud
inside of your head is slowing you down
if you could jettison that
subvocalization or suppress it in some
way could you increase your reading
speeds again research shows that this is
a tactic that's unlikely to work
according to Elizabeth shter who is the
author of some of the most recent
research on speed reading there's a lot
of evidence that when people recognize
words visually they access the sounds of
those words to understand them even if
you're not reading aloud your brain
sends signals to your vocal cords as you
read Nas scientists even developed a
computer program to detect these signals
and measure them scientists have done
studies where they try to have readers
suppress subvocalization in some by
playing a tone whenever these signals
are detected by the computer program and
in others by having readers try to hum
aloud while they read in each case
comprehension went way down it seems
that reading is inextricably tied to our
auditory language processing
capabilities and trying to separate the
two does more harm than good so let's
move on to our third method and this is
the one that you guys requested I talk
about the most it's the technique
utilized by apps like Spritz spreer read
quick on the iPad and others and the
name for it is rapid serial visual
processing these apps work by showing
each word in a reading by itself and
Rapid succession the words are fixed in
place which eliminates the need for sads
because your eyes can remain fixed in
the same spot as the words change that's
where the words you see on the screen
right now are doing though since they're
following the pace of my voice they're
going very very slowly as a
demonstration here's the next segment of
the script going at 500 words per minute
[Music]
now in case you didn't catch any of that
let me go ahead and restate it the RSVP
technique Finds Its origins in a device
called a tachistoscope which uses a
slide projector to flash images in Rapid
succession which is supposed to help
people improve their recognition speeds
teist Scopes were used during World War
II to train fighter pilots to recognize
other aircraft as Friend or Foe more
quick L and then in the 1960s some
schools started using them to try to
increase the reading speeds of their
students many modern RSVP apps have
their own unique features for example
spreer lets you set multiple words to be
flashed instead of just one at a time
and Spritz tries to move the position of
each word in order to help your eye more
quickly reach its optimal recognition
point for all these cool features though
research shows that RSVP systems in
general don't really work that well one
of the main problems with RSVP systems
is that they present every single word
in a reading requiring your brain to try
to process them all as we learned in the
first video in the series people don't
fixate on every single word in a reading
they tend to skip a lot of the content
and they do it in intelligent way they
tend to fixate more on content words and
less on the function words in fact that
1987 speed reading study revealed
something pretty interesting for normal
readers it's not just the length of the
words that explains why content words
are fixated upon more often even in
Reading tests where all the content
words were only three letters long for
normal readers they were able to fixate
more often on those content words for
skimmers and speed readers however the
proportion of content words fixated upon
to function words was about even this
reveals that at least at normal reading
speeds our brains are able to
intelligently fixate upon the most
important words in the text but with
RSVP we don't get this ability because
every single word is presented one after
another this makes your working memory
the bottleneck it strains to keep up
while all the text is flooding in at one
constant rate my own informal test using
these apps confirms this I find it
really exhausting to read this way and
after about 30 seconds of doing so I
find that it's really hard to remember
the detail of what I just read an
additional strike against RSVP apps is
that they don't allow for regressions
going back to reread over sections that
you've already read before Elizabeth
shter conducted another study that
looked at RSVP systems in detail back in
2014 and the conclusion of this study
was that this is a big problem as it
turns out the ability to make
regressions is integral to having high
comprehension levels when you read and
the problem with this software is it
can't accurately predict at what points
your brain needs to go back and read
something again so in my eyes at least
for the case of reading for Learning and
comprehens attention all three of these
systems have been thoroughly debunked
does that mean they're entirely useless
well maybe not some of them could be
useful for scanning over text quickly
maybe reading a text message or an email
or trying to find the gist of something
but if you're doing an in-depth reading
of a textbook or you're trying to read a
book to learn something I don't think
they're really that useful to be using
now there are definitely other speed
reading techniques out there that I
didn't mention in this video one in
particular that I'm currently interested
in is called beine there's not a whole
lot of research on it so if you know
something please tell me and I'm sure
people will let me know about other
techniques down in the comments comments
also in the interest of time I had to
leave a lot of the nuance and detail
about these techniques in particular out
of the video but I did link to all the
studies and articles that I use to
research this video in the companion
blog post so you can click the card
right now or the link down in the
description to read them so that's it
for this video in the next one we'll
wrap up this little miniseries on speed
reading with a discussion on how you can
actually increase your reading
speeds hey guys thanks so much for
watching this video If you enjoyed it
giving it a like will help support this
Channel and if you'd like to get new
tips on how to be a more effective
student every every single week click
that big red subscribe button right
there also if you'd like to get a free
copy of my book on earning better grades
click the picture of the book and I will
get one to you and like I said links to
all the research resources that I use
for this video can be found in the
companion blog post which you can access
by clicking the orange logo right there
last week's video went over how I set up
my iPhone to be more productive so check
that out if you haven't seen it and if
you'd like to connect I'm on Twitter at
tomf Frankle or you can leave a comment
below thanks for watching