hey guys so it finally happened I
finally moved into a new house and don't
let this backdrop deceive you my room
actually looks like this right now uh
things are definitely still in flux I'm
not even near finished setting up this
room so this week I wanted to bring you
a quick video where I recommend three of
the books that really helped me become a
more effective student and I'm going to
go ahead and say that each of these
three books is something that you should
read if you're a student so my first
book recommendation is the Power of
Habit by Charles doig and as I've said
before and if you're on my mailing list
you know that I think habits are one of
the core things that form your ability
to become a successful student your
habits and the patterns that are
ingrained up in your head are largely
what Define what you do on a day-to-day
basis and as time goes on the
accumulations of those actions really
define whether or not you achieve your
goals the reason I love The Power of
Habit is because it explains how habits
are formed it goes over something called
The Habit Loop and shows how routines
are formed in your head they're
triggered by certain things and they end
up leading to certain rewards it also
shows shows you how you can start
changing your habits with the knowledge
of this habit Loop how you can break bad
habits or start building good habits
that you don't have yet my second book
recommendation is one I mentioned last
week the personal MBA by Josh Kaufman
now the personal MBA is the author's
attempt at building a education in a
book that can sort of replace actually
going back to graduate school for an MBA
and uh while he's not very serious about
that claim he obviously isn't saying
that two years of intense graduate level
education is going to be replaced by
this book what he wants you to uh
realize is that there are certain
foundational Concepts to each aspect of
business accounting working with others
sales marketing value creation and in my
opinion all of these aspects of business
are useful to know no matter what your
major is and the reason for this is that
you probably want a job after you
graduate no matter what your major is
you're looking to get hired by a company
that has to conduct business so if you
understand the fundamentals of business
if you understand Val creation value
delivery if you understand how marketing
works if you understand how your brain
works how to work with others and how to
work with yourself all Concepts that are
gone over in this book then you're going
to be a better candidate it's going to
complement the actual in-class
information you get that's specific to
your major and my final book
recommendation is debt fore You by Zach
biset now this book I think is the most
essential book for anyone looking to go
to college in the US I can't really say
that it's essential for people in other
countries because I know that the
financial situation with education is
different but for us students at least
read this book it can save you thousands
and thousands of dollars the book
contains a wealth of information about
student loans the cost of debt and how
hard it might actually be to pay off and
most importantly whether or not you
actually need to take debt to get a good
education he breaks down a lot of the
flaws in the college rankings that drive
a lot of students College decisions and
shows how you can get a really good
education at an in-state Public
University or even a community college
he also shows in actual detail how you
can can afford that education without
taking on debt now so far this channel
has been mostly about studying and
productivity but that's only one of the
focuses I have with my website College
infogeek I also want to teach students
how to become better job candidates and
how to become financially stable and the
first step is helping them stay out of
student debt or pay it off as quickly as
possible that's why debt for you is
probably my favorite student Focus book
of all time and if you've ever seen my
Essential reads for students list which
you can read by clicking the card right
now you'll see it right at the top above
my own book so that's it for this video
hope you find these books useful and
you'll find other recommendations over
on my Essential reads page you can also
get my book 10 steps to earning awesome
grades while studying less for free and
while I'm not going to list my own book
as essential for students I do think
you'll find it useful so I'm going to
get back to cleaning this house up and
building a proper backdrop for next
week's video so I will see you in that
video and also if you're waiting on the
10,000 subscriber bonus video it is
coming these past few weeks have been
really hectic and I haven't had time to
film it but I will be getting it out as
soon as I can and I'll show you how I
actually shoot these videos so look
forward to that
hey everybody thanks for watching this
video on my book recommendations if you
want to get new videos every single week
on being a more effective student then
you can click that big red subscribe
button right there you want to get links
to these books and also see the other
books I recommend for students then go
to the companion blog post for this
video by clicking the orange logo right
there if you also want a copy of my book
on improving your grades just click the
picture and I'll send you a copy you can
also check out last week's video on
building your ability to focus if you
missed it and lastly if you got ideas
for new videos or just want to connect
I'm Tom Frankle on Twitter or or you can
leave a comment thanks