we live in a culture where it's
basically the norm to be constantly busy
to have a million things going on is
basically the mark of an ambitious
person so how in the heck can you get a
ton of work done while also being lazy
seems like a paradox right well it's
actually not a paradox because being
lazy is something you can do
strategically and you do that by taking
regular breaks throughout your day
taking breaks is an absolutely vital
part of keeping your brain healthy and
able to produce great work they're like
the Yang to hard Works Yin like the
necessary white space that enables great
Pros to be read on a printed Page by
being a little bit lazy at regular
intervals throughout your day you enable
yourself to work far more intensely and
effectively during your actual work
hours as the writer Cal Newport put it
in his excellent book deep work
productivity really breaks down into a
simple formula highquality work produced
is the product of time spent and
intensity of focus but when you don't
use a little bit of this time for these
pockets of laziness you rob yourself of
the ability to focus intensely at all we
often like to think of our brains as
similar to computers but this is one
area where the two are vastly different
see computers are designed from the
ground up to be able to run a steady
supply of power of electricity and in
return they can work pretty much
ceaselessly and tirelessly aside from
the occasional update or crash a
computer can work like a certain battery
powered bunny for hours and hours and
keep on going without a break and we
can't you and I are both products of
millions of years of evolution that is
always dependent on a cycle of work and
rest stressful exertion and relaxation
and this applies just as much to our
brains as it does to our muscles and all
the other parts of our bodies as as the
writer Joe Robinson put it the brain is
usually seen as an ethereal realm that
exists apart from the body and the laws
of physiology yet gray matter tires well
before the body does since almost all of
us are doing mental work these days
managing cognitive resources is not a
nice thing to be able to do it's
essential and to make sure you're
managing those cognitive resources well
you need to build two types of breaks
into your work schedule tiny breaks and
long breaks now tiny breakes are those
little 5 to 10 minute breather sessions
that just give you a chance to step back
from your work for a little bit and get
mentally refreshed Fred whereas long
breaks just like they sound are much
longer periods of time maybe 30 minutes
or an hour where you can completely
disengage from your work and do
basically whatever you want and like I
said if you want to work with the utmost
intensity when you're actually working
both of these types of braks deserve
slots in your work schedule and the
following five tips will help you get
the most out of both my first tip has to
do with your long breaks and it's to
predetermine when they're going to
happen at the outset of your day when
you're planning out everything you have
to do and this has a lot of benefits
that comes with it number one when
you're pre planning your breaks there's
no ambiguity or guilt about when you
should be working you know exactly when
you should be working and you know
exactly when you should be on a break
and you and I both know we've had these
times where we're on YouTube maybe or on
Reddit or Twitter or just doing
something that we know isn't work and in
the back of our minds we're thinking I
should probably be working right now
right or you have this guilty feeling
well when you pre-plan your breaks you
basically know what you should be doing
at all times and this guilt becomes
erased in addition to that you're also
going to be more motivated and work more
intensely during your actual work hours
because the existence of a pre-planned
break coming up in your near future is
going to create a little bit of time
pressure you know that your current work
session is going to end according to
your plan so you're probably going to
work a little bit harder to try to
finish whatever you're doing up before
it actually does end my second tip for
you guys is consider your tiny breaks to
be breathers little mental respites away
from your work and in fact away from all
work and in fact I think you should
actually physically get up and get away
from your workspace all your books your
computers your notebooks and walk around
go get a drink of water go get a healthy
snack if you're hungry you know do some
stretches basically move about amble
about a little bit talk to a friend and
get some mental Clarity just basically
disengage from all the work that you're
doing and that leads right into my third
tip which is what you should not do
during your tiny breaks I really truly
believe that you should not go on social
media you should not go on distracting
websites and you should not check email
or engage in other lower value work
during your tiny breaks and there are a
couple of different reasons to not do
these things the first one is to avoid
acre what a 2009 paper at the University
of Minnesota coined attentional residue
and this concept describes what happens
when people switch from one big task to
another and then try to switch back to
that main task basically by switching to
another task like your email or some
other kind of work you bring new ideas
and new problems that weigh on your
attention and take up working memory and
when you try to switch back to that main
task the really important one those new
ideas and new problems don't really go
away they kind of Gunk up your working
memory and they create this attentional
residue and that can really lower your
productivity and impede your ability to
get back into the Flow State secondly
and this is something I probably don't
have to tell you because you know just
as well as I do from personal experience
social media and distracting websites
can turn a 5-minute break into a
30-minute break I mean these sites are
absolutely engineered designed honed and
tested to suck up as much of your
attention and time as possible that's
what the entire YouTube algorithm is
designed to do so if you expose your
attention to these kind of sites during
a 5 minute break it's probably not going
to be 5 minutes okay I'm going to stop
telling you what not to do and we're
going to get into the fourth tip now
which is to go for walks outside and
this is something that helps me more
than almost anything else when I'm
feeling mentally drained or when I'm
feeling you know very unmotivated and I
just can't get into the flow of my work
without fail going outside and going for
a walk always lifts my mood and helps me
get back into the flow of work like
nothing else can the fact of the matter
is our bodies and our brains are built
from the ground up to move a lot and
we're not adapted to sitting in chairs
for8 hours and looking at squiggly lines
and sheets of paper all day so when you
need a break get up and go out side and
take a walk and I am far from the first
person to Advocate this in fact almost
2,000 years ago the Roman philosopher
Seno once said it does good also to take
walks out of doors that our Spirits may
be raised and refreshed by the open air
and fresh Breeze and he didn't know this
at the time but also you get vitamin D
furthermore as Barbara Oakley points out
in her book A M for numbers taking walks
is a great way to get your brain out of
that focused mode of thinking and into
that just as important diffused mode of
thinking where you can enlist a lot more
of your subconscious resources to solve
problems in ways that the focused mode
can't lots of great scientists and
thinkers and adventur over the years are
famous for using this technique to make
their breakthroughs in fact Charles
Darwin would use a huge chunk of his
workday to walk all around his property
to mle over large problems that he
couldn't solve while he was at his desk
so to sum up this particular tip and to
put a bow on it I think at least one of
your breaks every single day should
involve a walk that takes at a minimum
10 minutes to do if it's outside that's
awesome but even if it's not it's really
cold like it is for me doing it inside
has a lot of benefits and that brings me
to my final tip for you guys which is to
experiment with the time intervals
between your work sessions and your tiny
breaks because there are a lot of
systems out there that try to suggest
the quote unquote best ones I mean
there's the Pomodoro Technique which
says you should work for 25 minutes and
then take a break for 5 minutes there's
the be- minder talk system which is a 45
minute work session and a 15minute break
and then there's the research done by
the desktime time tracking app which
says that 52 minutes and then a
17-minute break is the optimal solution
but I really think that it's variable
your ability to concentrate and focus on
your work is like a muscle it's like
something that must be trained like a
skill so if you find yourself easily
bored or easily distracted start with
something small like the Pomodoro
Technique but if you are you know a
productivity Master then maybe you could
work for a full hour and then take a
15-minute break it's totally variable so
if you found this video helpful I would
love it if you gave it a like to support
this Channel and if you have additional
suggestions or other ideas for taking
effective breaks that I didn't cover
here I would love to hear about them
down in the comments and I'm sure a lot
of other people would as well beyond
that if you're not already subscribed to
this Channel and you want to get new
videos every single week on being a more
effective student you can click right
there to subscribe and you can also
click right there if you want to get a
free copy of my book on earning better
grades you can also click your mouse
button right around there if you want to
watch another video and other than that
I'm going on break see you next week