handson sacred books of your choice
right now because I need you to be
completely honest with both me and
yourself is the act of you watching this
very video on how to stop wasting time
on the internet part of a distraction
Loop you've gotten yourself caught into
are you procrastinating by watching a
video on how to stop procrastinating it
had to be said cuz I know after this
video a bunch of people are going to go
down to the comments and point out the
delicious irony and it all and hey I
just wanted to be the first one but
seriously though if you want to stop
wasting so much time on the internet and
get back to work and cut down your
procras ination that is what we are
going to get into today cuz I have
learned a lot over the years on how to
be more productive and resist the
Temptations of online distractions and I
have a lot of different tools and apps
that I can point you to which will help
you in that Crusade so to start this out
let's just talk about the tools that are
probably going to be the most
immediately helpful to you which are
website blocking apps and extensions
basically tools that simply don't let
you go to those distracting websites
that your brain likes to meander over to
when it doesn't want to write its paper
and the one that I use is called cold
turkey and you may be familiar with this
because in the last video I made I
talked about an app called cold turkey
Rider now cold turkey ryer is a really
Draconian app that basically turns your
computer into a typewriter lets you do
absolutely nothing except write until
you've hit a word count goal and I think
that's really really useful for when
you're hammering out a first draft for
an essay or a research paper but
sometimes you need greater access to
your computer maybe you need the
Internet for research and in those cases
the original cold turkey is really
really useful the things that I really
like about cold turkey are number one it
is crossplatform it's got Mac and PC
versions and as a Mac and PC guy it
means I can use it across both of my
systems and number two well there is a
paid version that costs about $25 and
has some Advanced features there is also
a free version which is more than
adequate for most people's needs the
process of using cterie is really really
simple first you define a list of
websites that you want to block and then
you create a Time window in which you
want to block them and once you hit go
on that timer between now and the end
time you selected you absolutely cannot
visit any of the website you selected
and this is the reason I really like
cold turkey because it is really really
difficult to circumvent I mean yeah if
you know pseudo Nano ety hosts or
something like you can probably figure
it out but for the most part you're not
going to be able to turn off the blocker
and distract yourself during your work
time and this is where it shines over
extensions like stay focused or distract
off these things are kind of hard to
disable but for the most part you could
pretty much figure it out if you really
really wanted to now cold turkey is
definitely not the only option out there
for website block software there's also
things like hay Focus focal filter
Freedom self-control and many others and
you can compare their features to figure
out which one works best for you but I
will say if you're having problems with
getting distracted and wasting a lot of
time online I think this is the first
thing you should do it's just like
somebody who is trying to go on a diet
and stop eating junk food the first
thing that person should do is get the
junk food out of their house remove
access to the Temptation so that way you
just literally can't go for it right and
speaking of Temptations I know that some
of you and you know exactly who you are
don't stop at just websites when it
comes to finding ways to distract
yourself maybe you have a steam account
with hundreds and hundreds of games you
can jump into maybe you're addicted to
the Pokemon online trading card game
whatever it is sometimes you need a way
to lock down more parts of your computer
than just the browser if you count
yourself among that group then you have
several different options for fixing
that problem and the first one is to
upgrade to the premium version of cold
turkey because it can actually block
full applications in addition to
websites and that's a really useful
feature but you don't have to get
turkeys premium version to do this
because there are other options and I'm
going to list three here in varying
degrees of extremity the first one is to
Simply create a work account on your
computer which you use when you're
working and this will be an account
where you don't have access to your
games you don't have access to any fun
programs you only have access to your
work software if that's not enough of a
barrier and you find yourself logging
back into your personal account to
distract yourself well number one you
could let a trusted friend set a random
password to your personal account and
only type it in when you're allowed to
take a break or you could simply use a
different computer for your work if
you're on a college campus or you have
access to a computer lab or a library
computer lab you could do your work
there on a different computer that
literally doesn't have any of your
favorite software on it if even that
isn't enough then it's time to come to
my final solution which is to Simply ask
yourself do you even need to use a
computer you know if you're writing a
paper you're doing some research maybe
go hit the books in the library or go
back to pen and paper and just sketch
some stuff out do some handwriting and
then come to the computer only when you
need it so now you know about some tools
that can prevent you from getting
distracted in the first place but what
do you do when you're currently
distracted and you realize that you're
procrastinating well here's exactly what
I do and it really boils down to a
simple step-by-step mental process that
goes on in my brain first I basically
acknowledge that yes I'm distracted I'm
procrastinating I'm doing something that
I shouldn't be doing then I ask myself
okay what is the exact next step I need
to take on whatever I'm supposed to be
working on once I have that in my brain
I commit to get getting rid of
everything in my environment browser
tabs computer programs stuff on my desk
everything that isn't related to that
one task and once I've done that it's
time for a pomodora session I set a
timer for 25 minutes I tell myself I'm
going to work on only that exact next
step for 25 minutes and if I finish it
I'll move on to the next one after that
and then I hit go and get back to work
and I found that the Pomodoro Technique
is really really useful for disengaging
from distracted web browsing sessions
because sometimes I'm just unmotivated
and that's the reason that I'm wasting
time online so if I can motivate Myself
by defining a very concrete specific
task and then defining an exact amount
of time I work on it then that's really
really helpful for me now there is one
more really important thing that I want
to say before I close this video out yes
the internet is an incredibly powerful
distracting force and there are
thousands of companies that are pouring
zillions of dollars and man-hours into
building platforms and systems designed
to exploit your short-term sensibilities
and distract you I mean you're watching
this video on one of them and by
consequence it can be pretty help ful to
basically arm your brain with weapons
against these systems the roadblocks the
website blocking applications these are
all tools that can be really helpful for
increasing your brain's ability to push
out these distractions and temptations
and to focus but remember this isn't
just about blocking distractions out
this is about building a stronger brain
because your ability to focus and pay
attention to block out these
distractions that ability is like a
muscle and it has to be trained and when
you throw it into just this complete
distracting environment where all
websites that distract you or just a
click away it doesn't have the ability
to get trained so these tools should be
thought of as training wheels they're
tailoring an environment in which your
brain actually has the ability to grow
stronger but someday your brain can
actually cast off these tools and
operate within the greater environment
while still pushing out distractions and
getting great work done and that should
be your overall goal so now that you
have your mission in mind and the tools
with which to achieve it the next step
is simple get to work don't click any of
the related videos to the side down
below or wherever they are just simply
get into your next task now if you do
happen to be on a break right now and
you have a little bit of extra time you
can click subscribe right there if you
want to get some new videos every single
week I'm being a more effective student
and you can also click right there to
get a copy of my free book on how to
earn better grades I am going to put a
video right there but it's going to be a
very specific video it's only 30 seconds
long and well you can see what it says