do you ever wonder like what the ratio
is between luck and hard work for people
who have been wildly wildly successful
in their lives What proportion of their
success comes from being in the right
place at the right time and what comes
from actual really hard work so I came
across this guy's Blog the other day his
named Sebastian Marshall and he has a
post about this Theory called the equal
odds Rule and I'm going to get to the
details of this rule how it affects your
success both as a student and a
professional in a few seconds but first
I need to talk about Ira Glass now you
may or may not be familiar with Ira
Glass maybe you've listened to this
American life before but either way
there's something he said once that has
stuck with me for a long long time and I
want to share it with you and the quote
is pretty long so I'm just going to give
you the gist of it and basically Iris
says that people who get into creative
Fields do it because they have really
really killer taste but when you're
getting into it and you're just starting
the ability to create work that you have
doesn't really match up to The Taste and
the point of what he was trying to say
is that the only way to start closing
this gap between your taste and your
ability to create things that you
actually like is to do a ridiculous huge
massive load of work create a giant body
of work and over time you'll start
learning how to create work that matches
up to your taste now when you do have
good taste you have this tendency to be
a perfectionist right you want to create
something that's absolutely perfect the
first time and I had this exact same
problem when I wanted to make videos I
sat down in front of the camera the
first time and I thought I'm going to
make this perfect it's going to be
amazing and now I realize that you can't
do that with your first piece of work
there are going to be things that you
don't see there are going to be
techniques you didn't even know about
and the only way you can start getting
better and moving that ability closer
and closer to that taste uh level you're
at is to do a lot of work and what Ira
says is to put yourself on a schedule to
make sure that you get something out
every single week and what I want to add
to that is kill the perfectionism get
your project to 90% or 95% or whatever
you can do Under the time pressure and
then publish so this gets us over to the
equal odds rule the equal odds rule says
the average publication of any
particular scientist does not have any
statistically different chance of having
more of an impact than any other
scientist's average publication in other
words those scientists who create
Publications with the most impact also
create Publications with the least
impact and when great Publications that
make a huge impact are created it's just
a result of trying enough times now
that's an excerpt of an Amazon review
for the book that first put this Theory
out there and I'll link to that review
in the show notes for this video but
essentially what he's trying to say is
that scientists who create amazing work
also create crappy work sometimes and
the reason they do both is because they
create a lot of work so really what it
is is they're getting a lot of at bats
they are putting a lot of things out
there some of them are golden eggs and
some of them are bad a lot of it is is
just mediocre I've actually heard this
called the 70201 rule as well where 70%
of your work is mediocre 20% is
absolutely terrible and 10% of it is the
cream of the crop that rises to the top
and becomes really really successful so
the take away from the equal odds rule
goes right back to what Ira Glass said
you have to make a lot of things and the
good thing here is that in most cases
you're going to be judged on your best
work unless you're Rebecca Black there's
a quote from somebody I really admire
named Corbett bar and he says write for
the body of work you want to have in 5
years and this is actually one of the
things that drives me sometimes I'll
look at my blog or I'll look at what I'm
creating on YouTube and think this is
really hard um maybe I should just go
get a job then I stop myself and think
what do I want to do you know what do I
want to see in 5 years when I look back
do I want to be able to see that I made
something every single week or do I want
to see that I stopped halfway through uh
decided I wasn't very good and then just
quit and did something else for a while
ask yourself that same question what do
you want to see when you look back in 5
years on your own body of work so the
lesson from the equal odds Rule and I
glasses advice leads into a question
that I get asked a lot and it's how do
you get massive amounts of work done in
a short amount of time so I'm going to
tackle that topic in next week's video
and you can subscribe using the button
below or The annotation in a few seconds
to do that otherwise thanks for watching
this video and I will see you next
week well hello there and thank you so
much for watching my video on the equal
odds ratio now if you're ready to start
building your own body of work and you
want to to go about it in a more
efficient way then I've got a free book
called 10 steps to earning awesome
grades and you can get your own copy of
it by clicking The annotation around the
picture of it right there otherwise if
you want to get new videos every single
week on being awesome at College then
hit that subscribe button right there
and if you want to get the companion
blog post to this video with links to
anything I talked about in the video
then click the orange button which you
can find right there lastly you can
follow me on Twitter at tomf frankley or
leave a comment on this video if you
have new video ideas or want to connect
and if you missed last week's video
there's a clip of it playing right there
so click that and head over there if you
missed it