hey guys so if you've been watching any
of my recent videos you may have seen me
teasing this book I've been writing
called 10 steps to earning awesome
grades while studying less and this is
an announcement video just a short
little one to tell you that uh two
things it's done finally and it's also
free so if you want to click The
annotation that's right around the book
picture here um you can go over to my
website college infog gig.com and get
your hands on the book it's about a 100
Pages after I got everything written and
it goes through everything that I think
you might uh be able to use to earn
better grades and become a more
efficient study year so that the book
covers um how to pay better attention in
class how to take better notes and get
more out of your textbooks it covers
planning strategies how to build a study
environment that has less distractions
how to organize your files and keep
everything organized fight that entropy
that uh messiness that just seems to
creep into our semesters every single
time we start them later on in the book
I tackle procrastination and how to
study more efficiently and the stud
chapter is really cool because I added
in sections on both learning lots of
facts quickly and also studying tougher
subjects like math so if you're looking
to study either one of those it's
covered there and it also has some tips
on how to beat test anxiety so if you
find yourself uh kind of choking up when
you go into a test even after you've
studied that chapter will cover what you
can do to uh mitigate that the book
rounds out with a chapter on how to
write better papers and one on how to
tackle group projects and make them suck
less because yes they do suck so if that
sounds interesting to you then just
click The annotation grab the book and
just as an apology um I didn't have time
to make the video that I promised last
week on how to get lots of work done
because I was ironically getting lots of
work done on this book but the book is
there it's about 100 Pages as I said
it's free so check it out you should be
able to read it pretty quickly I made it
a pretty Snappy read and I will be there
next week with a video on how to get
huge massive workloads done I promise it
next Thursday so keep me accountable to
my word if you want to leave a comment
and say you're watching me that's
totally cool it's not crazy at all
anyway so yeah go grab the book oh yeah
and I forgot to mention the book is not
all just Theory and techniques I also
mentioned a lot of tools that I use and
that other students that I know use to
stay more productive so if you're
looking for Tool recommendations you
will find them in the
[Music]
book o