this video is sponsored by skillshare
every second we're awake
we're taking in unfathomably large
amounts of information
together our five senses process 11
million bits of it
every second but while the unconscious
mind continuously gathers these millions
of bits the conscious mind can only
handle about 40 of them
at any given moment just a tiny fraction
of what we take in
this is just one of the reasons that we
so often find it difficult to
concentrate on our work
there are severe limits to how much
we're able to focus on at once
and keeping the spotlight on the 40 most
important bits is hard
when the other 10.9 million usually
contain more than a few temptations
so in my constant quest to improve my
own ability to focus on my work
i recently picked up the book hyperfocus
by chris bailey to see if it had any new
focus boosting tricks that i could hide
up my sleeves
which are honestly kind of short so i'm
not sure how many tricks are going to
fit up there
but for me this book was a great deep
dive into many topics surrounding focus
and concentration
i took really really detailed notes in
this book and i've got them in a new
book summaries and notes section on my
website so i'll link that in the
description down below
but in this video i want to share and
summarize three of the most important
ideas that i took away
from the book let's start with the skill
of meta awareness the state of knowing
what you're thinking about our minds
love to wander and they do it a lot
by some estimates half the time we're
awake and when your mind is wandering
you're not really aware of what it's
focused on and sometimes
this is okay but when you're trying to
focus on your work you want to reduce
the time your mind spends wandering
and meta awareness is the tool you use
to do that
when you're aware of where your mind is
you can consciously guide it back to
where it needs to be
after you catch it wandering hyperfocus
spends a lot of time talking about ways
you can improve this meta awareness
skill
but here's one of the most important
tips that i took away from the book
create some kind of regular reminder to
simply check in on the state
of your thoughts on the state of your
mind bailey's suggestion is to create
what he calls an
hourly awareness chime using a timer or
maybe an alarm on your phone
when it goes off you ask yourself where
is my mind right now
over the past hour have i been focused
or has my mind been
wandering freely have i been working
with intention or maybe just jumping
from task to task on autopilot
as i get bored of one task and then
another and
over the last hour have i been working
on the most important thing
that i should have been working on and
by using this external chime
an external system to help govern your
internal self-discipline
by using this over time you get better
and better at continuously exercising
this meta awareness
as you work however sometimes it's
actually a good thing to let your mind
wander
throughout the book bailey makes
reference to two opposing states
hyperfocus and scatter focus as you can
probably guess
during hyper focus you block out
everything except for one singular
object of attention
right now since you're watching this
video that should be my face and not the
twitter feed and your other monitor
yes i can see what you're doing derek
during hyperfocus that gets blocked out
along with everything else so you can
slip into a state of flow
and actually execute on your intentions
but as you're probably well aware
hyperfocus is a difficult state to
maintain over a long period of time
especially if you're feeling bored or
stressed or in a distracting environment
which is why it's very important to try
to go into your work sessions in a
positive state of mind but also to
create a distraction-free work
environment by pushing out everything
else that could be a distraction
you enable yourself to focus on those
most important 40 bits
and if you're curious about how to set
up an environment like that i've got a
whole video
on it i'll link that down in the
description below so you can check it
out after you watch
this video but hyperfocus isn't the best
state for every purpose
not only is it taxing after a while but
because it leans so heavily on your
brain's prefrontal cortex
it's also a state where you're less
creative so to get the most from it you
need to slip
out of it from time to time in exchange
for its exact opposite
scatter focus a state where you
intentionally let your mind wander
this mode of thought is often terrible
for what we tend to narrowly define
as productivity immediate work output
but it's great for creativity and if we
look at a longer time scale than the
five seconds your boss catches you not
typing on your keyboard
we can probably agree that creativity
and productivity go hand in hand
you can't have one without the other and
scatter focus lets your mind
wander around different thoughts in a
more creative fashion finding new
connections
between them in the book bailey is very
clear about one thing
scatter focus is not the same thing as
unconscious mind wandering the type of
mind wandering that we usually engage in
the key difference here is
intentionality in scatter focus you
intentionally let your mind wander in
one of three
different modes first there's capture
mode in this mode bailey says you get
out a
piece of paper or you open up a new note
on your computer and then you just let
your mind wander freely for
10 or 15 minutes writing down
observations and thoughts as they come
and by the end of a capture mode session
you might find yourself with a list of
projects you want to check in on or
people you want to reconnect with or
maybe just a list of random ideas
i know personally when i do this i
always end up with more than a few
different video ideas
secondly there is problem crunching mode
in this mode instead of letting your
mind wander completely free
you pick an object of focus maybe a
problem that you're stuck on
and you let your mind wander around that
in a sort of non-linear relaxed fashion
as you maybe go for a walk or a bike
ride which i try to do
pretty much every day this is actually
very similar to the walking meditations
that kyle newport talks about in his
book deep work
or the diffused mode style of thinking
and problem solving that barbara oakley
talks about in her book a mind for
numbers there's sort of a lot of common
threads around here
and what's really great about this mode
is you are thinking about the problem
that you're working on during hyper
focus
but you're thinking about it in a much
more relaxed state allowing your entire
brain to sort of mull over the problem
the illustration that barbara oakley
gives into mind for numbers is of a
pinball table
if you're using that hyper focus mode
it's almost like a tightly gripped
cluster of those bouncers that keeps the
ball bouncing around in one very
specific area of the table
whereas in the diffused mode or in
scatter focus you're using the entire
table it's like a very
loosely grouped spaced out group of
those bouncers
so the ball can go basically wherever it
needs to go
and in these modes you'll often find
that new insights come that wouldn't
have come
during hyper focus finally there's
habitual mode
where you again let your mind wander
freely but you do so while doing the
dishes or doing something that doesn't
take a whole lot of mental effort
and personally on a pretty much daily
basis i tend to combine
capture mode and habitual mode often go
for a walk or i'll go for a bike ride
not really doing problem country mode
and only thinking about a specific thing
most the time
but when thoughts come to me i've got
the voice memos app on my watch or on my
phone so i can record the thoughts and
insights
that come to me and i find that again
when i'm out on these walks and i'm on
these bike rides
i often get ideas that i would have
never gotten if i was just sitting at my
desk trying to write
and that's really the purpose of this
scatter focus state
because you're more relaxed you think in
a less linear fashion
and you get more ideas as a result and
then when you switch back to hyperfocus
you can take action on those ideas
especially if you can learn how to set
stronger intentions at the outset of a
hyperfocus session
this is my third big takeaway from this
book just as my friend charles cornell
stressed that
intentionality is the most important
element to deliberate practice setting
strong
and specific intentions is also a key
element to actually getting
well really any work done so what makes
an intention
a good one well for me there is one key
question to ask here
when you sit down to work ask yourself
if the intention that you've set
is specific enough to make your next
action an obvious one
here are a few examples write a video
script i literally did this just this
morning
well it's actually not a very good
intention because it leaves a lot of
room for interpretation
and writing a video script might be a
multi-day process
so instead i could rephrase that as
write a rough draft of the first
main body point of this script again
it's a multi-day process so if i know
i'm writing on one point
i'm much more likely to get started
quickly and additionally this might even
be more important
i know that i'm writing a rough draft
that's my intention and that's going to
stop me from making edits which will
slow down
the initial writing process edits are
much better made during a second
pass-through after i've already gotten
the rough draft
onto the page a second example go to the
gym again
a lot of room for interpretation there
so things are gonna be a lot better
if i know what i'm gonna do when i get
to the gym i know which exercises i'm
gonna do
what order i'm gonna do them in how many
sets and how many intended reps
this is actually part of the reason why
i work with an online coach who sets
that programming for me
ahead of time but even if i wasn't i
would always make sure to go into the
gym
with a plan now for me the absolute
most important element to getting my
work done is still interest
care wanting to do the work that is in
front of me
but the reality is all of us have things
that we sometimes have to do
that we don't want to do and this
applies to people who overall love their
job
personally i love being a youtuber i
love being a content creator there's a
lot of freedom involved
there's a lot of creativity involved but
still there are small parts of the job
that i still
just don't want to do sometimes or
sometimes my brain wants to put my main
job on the back burner because of some
other
current obsession and this this is where
intentionality really shines because
when you get specific
when you make your next actions
completely obvious and when you tailor
your environment for focus
that's when your self-discipline comes
in and allows you to get your work done
even if it's not exactly what you want
to do in the moment and that
is the crux the main part of this lesson
that i took from this book
now one thing that can really help you
to set these intentions when you're
working is having a well-maintained
productivity system as david allen
famously put it our brains are for
having ideas
not for holding them which is why you
want to have a well-maintained
organized external system a single
source of truth if you will
for recording the details of all of your
tasks your events and
your ideas it's the system that allows
you to make sure nothing ever slips
through the cracks
in your life i call this a productivity
system and over on skillshare i created
a class that will teach you exactly how
to build one or to improve yours if you
have one already
in the class we go over several
different categories of apps your task
manager
your calendar your note-taking app plus
file management methods for both digital
and physical documents we talk about how
to set these apps up so they're
organized
so that they work together in harmony
and so that you reduce the friction
involved
in getting things into them additionally
we talk about some methods and some
interesting meta skills
for making sure this system doesn't
become a jumbled mess over time which
would challenge its status as that
single source of truth
more than 88 000 people have already
taken this class with one recent review
saying it was one of the best online
classes they've ever taken
and if you want to take it for yourself
if you want to give it a try you can
actually do so for free by being one of
the first 1 000 people to sign up for a
free trial on skillshare at the link
down below
when you get that free trial you're
gonna have unlimited access to
skillshare's entire platform which means
you can take my class then go take my
other classes on skillshare
or take any of the thousands of
additional classes that can teach you
practical skills like audio engineering
video editing marketing and tons more
after that skillshare is still a very
affordable platform with their annual
plans spreading less than 10 bucks
a month which is just one of the many
reasons why i really like skillshare
why i have three classes on the platform
already and why i have a fourth class
coming out in january of next year which
is really going to help my fellow
creatives youtubers
entrepreneurs and content creators so
check it out and link down below and as
always thank you to skillshare for
sponsoring this episode
and being a supporter of my show if you
enjoyed this video definitely hit that
like button to show the youtube
algorithm what's up
and make sure you're subscribed to this
channel if you haven't done so already
so you can get more videos like this
when they come out
in the near future something that i'm
committing to for 2021 just to give you
a heads up is fewer videos but more
production quality more writing time so
my schedule is going to get a little bit
more sparse and you're going to want to
have that notification belt on so you
don't miss out on videos
when they come out in the future i'm
very excited for the stuff that we're
cooking up in 2021
both here and on my new channel thomas
frank explains right now there's a lot
of notion tutorials on there and we may
branch out into additional productivity
software if
my interest goes in those directions so
check out that channel if you're curious
otherwise i'll have a couple of
additional videos here and here which
you can smash your face under your phone
screen to
check out for extra style points or if
you don't want to do that
don't go punch windows or i don't know
like eat a bunch of cake or whatever it
is i didn't write a joke for the end of
this video but as always
i'm not your dad