there's this pretty well-known quote
that gets thrown around a lot and it's
often attributed to Albert Einstein and
it goes if you can't explain it simply
then you don't understand it well enough
now whether or not Einstein was the
person who actually said this let's be
real he probably wasn't it's still
really insightful and reversing it
reveals a pretty powerful piece of study
advice if you want to understand
something well explain it now this idea
is something I touched on briefly back
in my video summary of the study L study
smart lecture by Dr Marty lbell because
in that lecture he talked about one of
the most effective study techniques
being to teach what you're learning to
someone else so in this video I want to
dig deeper into that idea and share with
you a step-by-step process for doing
this which has been called the Fineman
technique now this technique is named
after the physicist Richard Fineman who
was in his own right a great scientist
in fact back in 1965 he won a Nobel
Prize for his work in Quantum
electrodynamics which is something I had
to practice saying a couple of different
times and he contributed to science in a
number of different ways including the
development of what are called findan
diagrams which are are basically
graphical representations of the math
behind how subatomic particles work but
in addition to being a great scientist
he was also a great teacher and a great
explainer and in fact one of his
nicknames was the great explainer
because he was able to boil down
incredibly complex Concepts and put them
in simple language that other people
could understand and that's why he's one
of those great scientists who is also
known as a very good teacher and in fact
even in his own learning feeman was
famous for tirelessly working through
equations until the concept he was
wrangling with was intuitively easy to
understand in his mind so that's why
this technique is named after him but
you don't have to be a physicist or you
don't have to be working on math or
science problems to use this technique
because explaining a concept Works to
improve your understanding of that
Concept in basically any area be it
history or be it math or be it web
development doesn't matter and it also
works for multiple different purposes if
you're shaky on a concept and you want
to quickly improve your understanding
you can use it but if you already have
have a pretty confident grasp of a
subject and say you've got a test coming
up soon you can also use it to test your
understanding and challenge your
assumptions as fan himself said the
first principle is that you must not
fool yourself and you are the easiest
person to fool the ultimate way to
ensure that you actually understand all
the little nitty-gritty details of a
concept in your head is to explain it to
someone else or to at least pretend
you're doing so and that is the Crux of
the fan technique so let's get into it
it's a process of four steps in the
first step is to Simply get out a piece
of paper and write the name of the
technique down at the top and in the
example I filmed here we're going to use
the Pythagorean theorem because it is
simple and it won't get in the way of
the actual steps we're going to go
through step two is to explain the
concept and to do it in simple plain
English or French or really whatever
language you happen to speak but the
idea here is to do it in a way that's
easy to understand as if you were
teaching someone else and don't just
settle with defining the concept either
also work through examples and make sure
that you're able to use the concept in
practice as well for for step three
identify any of the areas that you're
shaky on after your explanation or
identify areas that you got stuck on
which halted your explanation and go
back to the source material or go back
to your notes or work through examples
until your understanding of these sub
areas is just as solid as all the other
areas and finally step four is to look
at your explanation and try to identify
any areas where you've resorted to using
technical terms or convoluted language
and then challenge yourself to break
down those terms and explain them in
simplified easy to understand words
remember the key here is Simplicity the
act of explaining a topic as if you were
teaching it to somebody who didn't have
the same base assumptions and base
knowledge that you have is the ultimate
test of your own knowledge in that
subject and that's pretty much it that's
all there is to the fan technique Now
using this technique is incredibly
helpful because it number one helps you
to quickly overview the concept and see
where your knowledge is solid but number
two it helps you to instantly pinpoint
the areas where you're shaky and where
you need to do extra work and that makes
this technique a great first step in in
reviewing a concept because it's very
efficient and it helps you waste less
time I did want to give you guys one
extra suggestion though and it relates
to how you frame your mind going into
step four instead of just thinking how
can I make this simple how can I put it
in plain English also think how would I
explain this to a kid why well besides
asking questions like can I have another
Oreo or can I go watch Dragon Ball Z a
kid's going to ask why why does that
work and that's going to help to
challenge your assumptions for instance
going back to our Pythagorean theorem
example maybe you know the formula but a
kid would ask you why does that formula
work why does the Pythagorean theorem
hold as a rule for all right triangles
and yeah maybe you understand that
intuitively maybe you can bust out the
proof by rearrangement but maybe you
can't maybe you've always just looked at
the formula and taken in at face value
in which case you have some more
learning to do now speaking of the
Pythagorean theorem maybe that was a bit
too simple of an example for you and
you'd like to see this technique appli
to something more complex or something
that has nothing to do with math at all
if if that's you in the companion
article for this video I've included a
couple of different examples one going
through base rule which is a concept in
probability Theory and statistics and
one going over the CSS Box model which
is related to web development and not
related to math at all that you can
check out so if you want to see those
you can click the card on screen right
now to get over to the article or you
can find the link down in the
description below beyond that if you
enjoyed this video and found it helpful
definitely give it a like to support
this Channel and if you have additional
tips or ways that you use this technique
personally I would love to hear from you
down in the comments below additionally
if you're not subscribed to this channel
yet and you want to get new tips on how
to be a more productive student you can
click right there to subscribe and you
can also click right there if you want
to get a free copy of my book on how to
earn better grades otherwise you can
click right around there to find another
video which you'll probably find
interesting thanks for watching and I
will see you in the next
one