so a couple of weeks ago i lost all of
my friends you probably remember i put
out this video on seven different money
mistakes people often make and in that
video i publicly declared very stupidly
that i actually enjoy looking at
financial spreadsheets and ever since
then none of my friends have texted me
back and weirdly every time i go out in
public i just hear people yelling nerd
at me i don't know why anyway since then
i have been trying to make some new
friends and in that process i have made
a discovery which is that making friends
really isn't as easy as it was back when
i was a kid
but that doesn't matter i actually i do
have some friends still there's bing
bong there's gary there's tyler eduardo
see i got tons of friends still i would
like to make some more and i would not
be surprised if you feel the exact same
way that i do about making friends
because this is a very very common
problem a lot of people find it
difficult to make friends especially as
they get older or when they say move to
a new city so as somebody who is in fact
getting older and who moved to a new
city in the past year and a half i want
to share some tips and strategies for
making new friends and we're going to do
something that i haven't done in quite a
while which is make a two-part video so
in this video we're going to focus on
the process of making new friends we're
going to talk about how to meet new
people and also break the ice so you can
actually have great conversations and
then later this week i'm going to
release a second video which will be all
about how to take those casual
acquaintances and casual friendships and
turn them into deeper more meaningful
friendships now today's video is going
to include six different tips but before
we get into those i do want to share a
quote from the author and speaker zig
ziglar if you go looking for a friend
you're gonna find they're very scarce if
you go out to be a friend you'll find
them everywhere keep this in mind when
you're trying to put the tips in this
video into action if you can remember
that making friends is about giving more
than receiving about putting in a lot of
effort and about helping people then
you're gonna have no problem whatsoever
making friends and with that let's move
on to the tips starting with tip number
one which is to go out and do active
things now this tip stems from a
question i got from a student years ago
and that has been repeated by many other
people who have messaged me in the
intervening years which was where do i
go to meet people who could become my
friends and this person the first person
who asked me this question didn't really
know where to go because they had really
only made friends by proximity whether
it be in their neighborhood when they
were a kid or in their dorm in college
and what i told them was if you want to
meet friends who actually do cool things
who are active then you have to go to
where active things are happening you
can't just sit around in your dorm room
waiting for somebody to walk in and say
hey dude you want to play ultimate
frisbee no you need to look at maybe
your campuses activities directory or
like a meetup group in your city that
actually meets for ultimate frisbee show
up and you're going to start meeting
people who are into that activity now if
you're wondering how to actually find
these sorts of activities i do have a
few suggestions for you one look in your
local community for example i go to a
gym that's just a few blocks away from
my apartment and every single time i'm
there i see bulletin boards with
advertisements for intramural sports and
other groups that i could easily join if
i wanted to in addition to that there
are sites like meetup.com which has
hundreds if not thousands of different
groups for all different types of
interests that are gonna be listed for
your area so definitely check out that
one and you can also look at facebook
now you should probably stay off the
news feed on facebook if you don't want
to absolutely destroy your productivity
but the groups feature on facebook and
the events feature on facebook these two
are gold mines for finding events where
you could find potential friends and
that leads us into tip number two don't
be afraid to try new things you might be
tempted to look at meet up to look at
facebook and to only look at things
you're already into but remember the
human brain is very good at adapting and
you don't know what you're going to like
until you try it so try something new
for example just this week i tried out
rock climbing and mountain biking for
the first time and i found no surprise
that both of those things are extremely
fun if i only stuck to skateboarding and
rollerblading which are the things i did
ever since i was a kid then i'd be
limiting myself quite a bit
but i don't i actively try to do new
things all the time because i know that
i'm probably going to like them and even
if i don't i can just move on to
something else remember the only thing
you lose if you try something out and
end up not liking it is say an afternoon
worth of your time which isn't that bad
of a price to pay now if you want a few
activity suggestions i will reiterate
mountain biking and rock climbing are
both insanely fun and if you live in a
big city i'm starting to see dirt jump
parks pop up for mountain biking so you
don't even have to go out into the
forest and find a trail and there are
also lots of climbing gyms and if you're
looking for something a little less
extreme a little less active one thing
that i really enjoy doing is playing
magic the gathering and most towns have
a local game shop that hosts events like
friday night magic and commander nights
where you can show up play that game and
meet lots of new people now to reiterate
these are just ideas you don't have to
go have a day of mountain biking and
climbing and magic the gathering if
something else piques your interest go
out and try it and you just might find a
new hobby and some new friends now that
prospect is very exciting but i do want
to remind you tip number three here
don't ignore proximity friends you know
proximity friends the people who live
near you and you had a lot of these when
you were a kid right you kind of went
out to the neighborhood and just played
with whoever happened to be near you and
this is probably also the case for
school and college and when people get
to be adults i think they kind of forget
that proximity based friendships can
actually be very good they're only
looking for the meetups they're only
looking for people who share their
current interests but the thing about
proximity based friendships is that
these are friendships with people who
might expand your horizons because they
like different things than you like keep
in mind that you don't have to have the
exact same set of interests to be
friends with somebody and a great
analogy for this is your relationship if
you have one i've been with my
girlfriend for six years and while we do
share certain interests we also have a
lot of interests that the other person
doesn't really like but that doesn't
stop us from being great friends in
addition to being in a relationship so
wherever you live if you find the
opportunity to strike up a conversation
with a neighbor take that opportunity
that could just as easily lead to a
friendship as an interest-based meetup
group alright so i've given you a few
places where you can go out and meet new
people but that leaves one question
unanswered which is how do you actually
break the ice how do you get those
conversations going that actually lead
to friendships well that is what the
next few tips are going to cover
including tip number four which is to
use the three second rule and now that
i'm thinking about it i kind of wish i
had made that tip number three but too
late now so here's the crux of the three
second rule if you're at an event and
you see somebody who you want to talk to
decide within three seconds whether or
not you're going to actually walk up and
strike up a conversation if you wait any
longer than that your brain's going to
start concocting all sorts of reasons
why you shouldn't right you're gonna
think they look busy you're gonna look
silly and then you're gonna talk
yourself out of doing it so instead
within the first three seconds tell
yourself either yes i'm gonna walk up
and talk to that person or no i'm going
to walk away and then act on it and on a
related note work to become comfortable
with the fact that some conversations
are simply going to fizzle out or become
awkward this is probably the most common
fear people have about striking up
conversations deep down we know the
other person probably isn't going to
walk away or say something ridiculous
like how dare you even think to talk to
me reginald peevington lancaster the
third why do you even know how far my
family lineage could be traced back what
what but what people are afraid of
realistically is the conversation
fizzling out or getting awkward and
truthfully this is gonna happen
sometimes it even happens to total
extroverts some people just don't click
but if you can get over this fear and
become okay with the fact that it's
going to happen sometimes that's gonna
lead to more interactions which makes it
more likely that you're going to meet
people who you actually do click with
and finally if you want to keep your
conversations going then make sure you
take an interest in the other person and
ask a lot of questions this is a tip for
all the people out there who don't
really know what to say in conversations
with new people they know they can come
up and say hi then they can talk about
the weather if they want but then again
they're afraid of things fizzling out if
you don't want them to fizzle out well
maybe the other person will ask you a
question and then you're kind of off the
hook but a lot of times they're not
going to do that so you have to be the
person to ask the first question now i
know what you're asking yourself tom
what do i ask them about do i ask them
about where they got their shoelaces
from or like how many hairs are on their
head no you use the context of the
situation for your initial questions and
here's a great example yesterday i went
to a dirt jump park here in denver with
my mountain bike and i spent about an
hour just jumping by myself but
eventually i saw other people jumping
and i wanted to strike up conversations
with them so i started out my
conversations by asking them hey how
long have you been coming to this park
or what other parks in denver do you
like going to i really want to know
where else i can go where do you like to
ride that's trail riding that's actual
technical rock gardens and stuff like
that or what kind of bike hardware are
you running why are you using a hardtail
instead of a full suspension bike there
are all kinds of questions based around
the context of the activity you're doing
and again this is another great reason
to go out and actually do active
activity-based things rather than just
sitting around and having casual
friendships based on really nothing
except for watching netflix i guess
having an activity that you're both
participating in gives you context for
conversation now there is one final
quote that i want to share with you here
which is actually one of my personal
favorites and it comes from the film
critic gene youngblood an interested
person is an interesting person whenever
i hear this quote i think of the concept
of a renaissance man or heck a
renaissance woman somebody who knows a
lot about lots of different topics so
they can strike up conversations with
anybody and i'm always reminded of the
scene from one of my favorite movies
limitless where eddie's at this party
and he's talking to all these different
groups of people and no matter who he
talks to he's able to converse
intelligently with them that's the kind
of person that i have always wanted to
be and i'd bet that you would say the
exact same thing and if you want to be
that kind of a person well the only way
you're going to do it is by intaking
information from a huge variety of
different sources regularly and one of
my favorite ways to do that is by
listening to audiobooks i love
audiobooks because they let me learn
while i'm cooking or while i'm riding my
bike or finally folding my laundry after
leaving in the dryer for three days
they're just a great way to intake
information while i'm doing things that
don't require a ton of my attention and
if you're looking for a great place to
find audiobooks the best place in the
world to get them is audible audible has
an unmatched library of audiobook titles
in a ton of different genres they've got
all the best sellers and lots of obscure
books so whatever's on your to be read
list whatever is gunking up your good
reads they probably have it for you and
audible's membership has a ton of great
features as well including the fact that
if you don't like a book that you get
with your credits or that you buy you
can return it and exchange it for
another book with no questions asked and
one of the best things about audible is
that you can get a free 30-day trial and
a free audiobook download of your
choosing by going over to audible.com
thomas or texting thomas on your phone
to 500 500. now you guys probably know
by now that i always recommend a book in
these audible spots and i am very
excited for the book recommendation i
have for you guys this week because
spoilers it is my own book yes 10 steps
to earning awesome grades is now an
official audiobook and it is read by
yours truly and what's best as i said
just a couple of seconds ago you can get
it absolutely free by going over to
audible.com thomas or texting thomas to
500 500 on your phone you can get that
book or again you can get any other book
of your choosing anyway i want to give a
big thanks to audible for sponsoring
this video and being a supporter of this
channel and as always thank you guys so
much for watching thank you for so much
support over the years thank you for
everything basically uh if you enjoyed
this video you can hit that like and
i'll thank you for that as well you can
also subscribe right there if you want
to get new videos every single week when
they come out also you can get a free
ebook copy of my book 10 steps to
earning awesome grades by clicking right
there or you can get the free audio book
with audible description link below or
you can get one more video on this
channel by clicking right over here
thank you guys so much for watching
don't forget to come back in three days
for the follow up to this video on how
to build stronger friendships and until
then stay cute