hey what's going on guys so today we are
tackling how you can learn new skills
incredibly quickly and over the course
of this video I'm going to share a
four-step process that you can use to
take any skill whether it's related to
school or your future career or whether
it's just a fun one like guitar or
cooking and break that skill down so
that you can learn as much as you need
to about the most important parts and
then start practicing them effectively
so you can gain basic proficiency really
really fast now this process we're going
to talk about applies to any skill
because at its core skill development
whether it's really physical like
basketball or whether it's really mental
like mathematics it's all learning as
you intake information about the skill
and as you practice it you're forging
new neural Pathways in your brain you're
connecting them with other neural
Pathways and you're strengthening them
over time as you do this you move
through What's called the three-stage
model of skill acquisition which starts
with the cognitive stage where you're
just learning about the skill and you're
just forming those neural Pathways then
moves into the associative stage where
you're doing a lot more practice and now
you're able to sort of self-reflect and
pick out mistakes and change things
based on those mistakes and eventually
you move into the autonomous stage and
at that point you have mastered the
skill and it's basically able to be done
automatically and this autonomous phase
takes a really long time to get to
Mastery takes a lot of hours of practice
but that doesn't mean you're doomed to
spend dozens of hours in the beginning
phases because if you know how to
structure the learning and the practice
processes the right way you can make a
surprising amount of progress in a very
very short period of time in fact in his
book the first 20 hours author Josh
coffin argues that you can learn basic
Proficiency in almost any skill that
exists in under 20 hours of dedicated
practice and his process for doing this
breaks down into a series of four
distinct steps and in a second we're
going to go over those steps but first I
want to issue you a bit of a challenge
if you're sitting there watching this
video and you have a skill you've been
wanting to learn use this framework to
create a plan for doing that once the
video is over take out a piece of paper
and create a plan going through each of
the steps and then start putting it into
action so the first step in cofins
process is to deconstruct the skill
basically you break it down into its
component parts and then you prioritize
those parts based on your particular
goals within that skill area now to give
you an example let's talk about playing
the guitar a lot of people want to play
the guitar but there are lots of
different ways to play the guitar
there's tons of different musical genres
you might want to just play a few
different songs or maybe you want to be
like slash or like Dragon Force
guitarist and be ripping solos all day
long right these are very different
skills so by breaking it down into
individual subskills chords scales
picking technique reading tabs
understanding musical intervals you end
up with a list of building blocks that
you can then prioritize and take action
on the second step in confence process
is the education step basically at this
point you want to take each subskill
that you've prioritized and learn enough
about it that you can practice well and
identify your mistakes and self correct
now notice I said enough about each
subskill not as much as you can about
each subskill because I know personally
I'm the kind of guy who will walk into
Barnes & Noble and look at every single
book on the Shelf related to what I'm
interested in and think I should buy
every single one here and read them all
before getting started and that's just
not how good skill development Works
especially if you want to do it quickly
you need to learn just enough about each
sub skill so that you can start
practicing getting your hands dirty and
making mistakes because then you're
going to know what you should correct
all right step number three in the
process is to eliminate any potential
barriers to success or barriers to your
progress in your practice and in my mind
the most likely thing that's going to
get in the way of your practice is a
lack of motivation in the long term so
find a way to motivate yourself on a
constant basis maybe it's having an
accountability partner maybe it's
joining a forum where you can talk about
your interest or maybe it's just making
a record of every single day you
practice so you can see a chain
developing that you don't want to break
all right so skill has been
deconstructed learning has been done and
barriers have been sliced in half with a
samurai sword we are now on the fourth
and final step of the process which is
simply to practice deliberately in the
first 20 hours Josh koffman's rule is
that you should practice deliberately
until you've achieved achieved your
goals for each subskill that you
prioritized or until you've hit 20 hours
of dedicated practice and what he
recommends is that you actually practice
by using a timer or a clock and track
the amount of hours you put in because
when you're practicing something
difficult it can be really really easy
to overestimate how much time you spent
practicing now that we've gotten through
that four-step process I want to give
you a few additional tips you can use to
make your skill development Journey even
more successful and the first one is to
identify the work of somebody who is a
master or somebody who is where you want
to be analyze that work as best as you
can and then try to imitate it now a lot
of people are going to say this is
copying this is ripping people off but
actually as long as you're not passing
off this work as your own this is how a
lot of people learn their skills and in
fact in Japanese martial arts there's a
concept called shua that is exactly this
and in music it's the same the famous
jazz trumpet player Clark Terry believed
that imitation was in fact an essential
part of becoming a great musician and he
told his students that music learning
happens in a three stage process which
he called imitate assimilate and
innovate here's what he said about the
role of imitation by imitating the
players you love you'll begin to
understand the music on a deeper level
and begin to see a personal sound
develop in your own approach to
improvisation questions that can't be
answered by music theory or toe books
like how to play longer lines or how to
articulate and swing will reveal
themselves as you start to imitate the
Masters part of the reason this tactic
works so well is it gives you a method
to go way way beyond your comfort zone
and your current level of skill because
if you can take something that a master
are made you can analyze it from every
angle you can probably recreate certain
aspects of it even if you don't know
exactly what you're doing or why you're
doing it then later on as you're kind of
backfilling your knowledge by learning
the theory and all the fundamentals
you're going to be able to say oh that's
why I did that or that's how I did that
I didn't understand it at first but now
I get it and I kind of had like a rung
to pull myself up because I did that
work in the first place the stand for
mathematics professor Ravi Vil called it
backfilling and here's how he described
it in terms of mathematics mathematics
is so rich and infinite that it is
impossible to learn it systematically
and if you wait to Master One topic
before moving on to the next you'll
never get anywhere instead you'll have
tendrils of knowledge extending far from
your comfort zone then you can later
backfill from these tendrils and extend
your comfort zone of course another way
to learn from the Masters is to simply
be taught by them which is why another
way you can really accelerate your skill
development process is by finding a
teacher or a coach or a course that you
can take now I know from personal
experience having a coach or somebody
who can tell you your mistakes is
probably the most valuable thing in the
world but you don't have to let
geography be a limiting factor in your
access to teachers because there are
hundreds of thousands of tutorials and
online courses that you can use for
basically any skill that you're trying
to learn and one place where you can
find those courses that I want to let
you know about is skillshare who's
actually the sponsor of this video now
skillshare is an online learning
community that has over 12,000 courses
in a ton of different subjects and I've
actually been taking a few of those in
After Effects animation but they also
have coures in photography graphic
design logo design and things like
cooking guitar presentation skills in
fact they have a presentation skills
class from Simon s who gave probably my
favorite Ted Talk of all time but one of
the reasons I really like skillshare is
that it gives you the ability to get
feedback from both your teacher and from
other people who are taking the same
course there's two ways it does this
number one below the videos in any
course you're taking there's a comment
section and if you ask a question you
can get an answer from the course
instructor but also most of the courses
on skillshare have a participation
component basically there is a project
section of the course where you can
upload your own work for feedback now a
membership to skillshare is normally
around eight bucks a month which is
right around the same price as Netflix
and potentially a lot more useful but if
you want to get 3 months of completely
unlimited use on skillshare you can get
it for 99 Cents by using the link in the
description below and I'll have a few
more details about that at the end of
the video before we end this video
though I've got three additional tips
for you and all three of them relate to
making your practice practice sessions
more effective and more useful and the
first one is to find a way to record
some of the practice you do now you
don't have to record all of it but
recording some of it is going to allow
you to analyze your performance see the
mistakes you're making and make
improvements and this is something my
skating coach actually told me to do she
said bring your iPhone to the rink set
it up on a tripod and film yourself
practicing the moves you have to
practice for the competition because if
you can't see what you're doing you
don't really know how to make
improvements my friend Martin also does
this with Spanish practice one thing he
does is have an impromptu speech in
Spanish with his webcam so that way he
can go back and analyze his accent his
rate of speech if you made any
grammatical errors Etc secondly if you
want to accelerate your development
process and actually get good you need
to make time for hyperfocused and
honestly lengthy practice sessions now I
was going to say when I was writing the
script that you could just do 20 minutes
a day or 10 minutes a day of practice as
long as it was consistent but when I got
to thinking I couldn't think of a single
skill that I have that I'm proud of that
I think I'm truly good at where I just
put in 10 minutes a day or 20 minutes a
day of practice I mean after effects
public speaking skateboarding figure
skating all the things I think I'm
pretty good at I spent hours and hours
of practice on and each individual
session was honestly quite lengthy and
lastly as you practice you want to vary
up the stakes when you're learning a new
subskill you want to start with low
stakes where you're in a very low stress
situation there's not much of a threat
of consequence and then move to higher
stake situations where there is some
pressure and video game design is a
perfect example of this because if you
analyze almost any video game as it
teaches the player a new skill it
usually gives them a space where there's
some isolated practice where you can
basically practice the skill with not
much else going on very little threats
the opponents aren't hitting back and
then once you've gotten it down there
you move it into an actual situation
where the opponents do hit back or when
things are happening faster and when
there's very low margin for error or
there's some consequences if you look at
real world skills this principle applies
just as well I mean look at learning a
new language when you know absolutely
nothing you need some low stress periods
to drill flashcards or learn vocabulary
but then to really up your skills and
solidify what you've learned you might
do something like scheduling a
conversation with somebody on Skype or
even going to a foreign country and
talking with people face to face now I
know we went over a ton of different
tips in this video and because of that
there might be a Temptation for you to
wait for a perfect moment to start
building your skill when you can plan
everything out when you can integrate
every single tip but if you take nothing
else away from this video just take this
away the best time to start learning a
skill is now even if you have an
imperfect implementation plan even if
you start really slowly if you can start
making some mistakes start learning some
initial foundational pieces of that
skill that's going to help you build it
into the future so whatever it is
whatever you want to learn something
career focused something totally fun
make a plan for implementing it use that
four-step process and then just get
started once again I want to give a big
thank you to skillshare for sponsoring
this video this is actually my first
sponsored video so let me know what you
thought about it in the comments down
below but I'm a big fan of skillshare
personally so it was a no-brainer for me
and if you want to try it once again you
can try that link in the description
below for 3 months of unlimited use for
just 99 Cents or if you're on the site
you can use the promo code beard when
you sign up because hey it's me beyond
that if you enjoyed this video I'd love
to hear what you thought about it in the
comments down below definitely ask me
questions if you have them and I'll try
to get them answered in future videos or
in the comments themselves and also if
you enjoyed this video give it a like to
support this channel you can subscribe
right there if you want to get new
videos every single week I'm being more
productive and improving your learning
capabilities or you can click right down
there if you want to watch another video
see you in the next one