hey what is up guys so in today's video
we're gonna be taking a look at one of
my favorite types of apps in the entire
world
the humble habit tracker this very
simple type of app helps you to build
strong habits or break bad ones by
leveraging what's been called the don't
break the chain strategy for some reason
when our brains see that we have done
something for a long period of time or
haven't done something for the same long
period of time we don't want to break
the chain we don't want to break the
pattern so essentially a habit tracker
just lets you check off whether or not
you've done something every single day
and over time you get a visual
indication of your progress and that
keeps you motivated to keep progressing
in the right direction
now since habit trackers are very simple
they're also not that difficult to make
in comparison to other apps and as a
result there are a ton of them out there
whether you're on iOS Android or just
looking for a web app version so what
we're gonna do today is I'm gonna share
my picks for the top eight habit
trackers that deserve your attention
here in 2019 and for an app to make my
list it has to do something beat onto
just letting you check off whether or
not you did a habit has to bring
something unique to the table and
without further ado let's just jump into
the number eight pick on my list which
is called habitable if I makes my list
because it is very well designed in fact
across all the apps that I tested for
this video I found have benefice
combination of simplicity and really
nice UI to be at least the most
attractive to my eyes and in addition to
that it is also cross-platform you're
gonna find it on Android iOS iPad and
there's even a Mac app as well
additionally you're gonna find features
like a dark mode lots of fancy charts
and graphs to track your progress and if
you are an iOS person you're gonna find
Apple watch apps a widget for your
iPhone homescreen even I miss a as
well which I have not seen in any other
app that I've looked at next up on my
list is an app called a habit hub which
gains the distinction of being the only
Android exclusive app to make this list
now a lot of the other apps I'm going to
talk about in a little bit have Android
versions but this is the only Android
exclusive so if you're an Android person
and you want to lord it over your iPhone
friends that you got an app that they
can't use well this is probably the one
that you're gonna want to pick habit hub
also has a really nice design it has a
couple of other features that I really
enjoy it as well including the ability
to have goals for your habit streaks so
you can do things like having a 30 day
challenge and the ability to mark a
habit as
instead of just failed so if you had a
business trip or you found yourself sick
for some reason you could mark something
as skipped you could add a note to it to
explain why you had to skip it and
you're gonna get a visual indication of
it being skipped rather than just failed
or not marked altogether that brings us
to number six on the list which is tick
tick and tick tick isn't really a
purpose-built habit tracker it's
actually a full-fledged
task management / to-do app that is very
similar to todoist
and actually talked about it my video on
the best task management app since 2019
which you'll find linked in description
down below if you haven't seen it that
but now they have actually integrated a
habit tracker into the app and for a
real long time I begin questions from
all kinds of people asking me Tom is
there a task management app out there
that also integrates a habit tracker and
for the longest time I answer that
question has been no or at least I don't
know of one but now tick tick has filled
that void so if you want to have your
task management and your habit tracking
living in one place in the same app on
the same screen
tick tick is gonna be what you probably
want to go with for both of those
purposes now if you are one of those
people who wants a little bit more
complexity and your habit tracking then
you might want to pay attention to
number 5 on my list which is b-minor and
yes I've talked about being minder many
many times in this channel it was most
recently profiled in my video on apps
that force you to work so I'm not gonna
talk too much about bee minder but in
case you haven't heard of it it is an
app that allows you to essentially put
money on the line to ensure that you do
your habits and in addition to that
financial incentive part of the app
there is just a lot of data and
beeminder you can look at all these
crazy charts and graphs you can see all
of your data points you can get really
really nerdy with this app and it also
holds the distinction of being the app
that can pull in data from the largest
amount of sources that I've ever seen
they can pull an Apple health data it
can pull on data from all kinds of other
quantified self apps and it can even
connect up to IFTTT which can basically
let you pull data from literally any
other service in the world that you can
probably think of through some weird
combination of home automation Python
scripts and whatever it is you
programming there it's like to build out
there you can probably use it to shove
data into beeminder
but let's say for a second that all that
data is not the top priority for you
because you are a person of culture you
are a person who prides and values
aesthetics over
everything else well if that is the case
and if you have an iPhone because the
one we're going to talk about here is an
iOS exclusive then you may want to look
at number four on the list which is
called today today is a beautiful app in
fact it might even be a little bit too
beautiful for my taste in fact the
reason that it's not a little bit higher
on this list is because I feel some of
the aesthetics get in the way of using
the app really quickly and efficiently
that being said it is a very capable
have a tracker under the hood in
addition to all the nice design and UI
and it even packs in some features for
free that other apps charging monthly
subscription fee for now of course you
can do all the basics you can add habits
you can check them off you can do
multiple check-ins per day but you can
also set specific covers for your habits
so you get that nice little splash
screen for each one and one thing that
I'd really like is that for each habit
you can add what are called custom cards
to the data area for the habit and well
it can't pull in your Apple health data
to actually hold your feet to the fire
like beeminder can so you can't do
something like having a walking goal and
then pulling in your steps data to check
it off or not check it off you can add
in Apple health data for some extra
context for your habits which is really
nice touch plus today is just pretty did
I mention that all right I will stop
gushing about today's design let's move
on to number three on list which is
coach dot to me and I didn't put it on
there because it rhymes though that is a
nice little coincidence so coach taught
me is actually the first habit tracker
that I ever used back when I was using
it was called lift notice since
rebranded to coach dot me and as you
might imagine there is now a coaching
component to the app and that is
actually what makes it pretty unique now
at its core coach taught me is a very
capable habit tracker you can add in
your habits you can check them off
there's nice high-five animations
sometimes but there's also a big
community element to the app as well
both in the form of coaching and in the
form of a simple community with
discussions so for any habit that you
add to your list if it is a common habit
there's probably to be questions and
discussion threads for those questions
from other users you can use it to get
tips and additional motivation if that
discussion area isn't enough for you you
can also go over to the coaching section
of the app which is where it gets its
namesake and for a lot less money than
I've seen in almost any other coaching
venue that I've come across online you
can get personalized check-ins with
coaches for basically any habit that
you're trying to build or goal that
you're trying to achieve now
if I had to guess I would say you
probably get a little less personalized
attention a little less time than you
get with an actual coach but a lot of
people don't need a ton of personalized
attention a lot of people don't need to
pay $60 for an hour of a coaches time
some people just need to be able to
check in with somebody a couple of times
a week and just have someone there to
keep them on track and that's the need
of this at Phil's
all right homestretch baby we are on to
number two on the list and it is what
has been my favorite tab at tracker
might have a tracker of choice for a
very long time it's called strides and
it is unfortunately an iOS exclusive
once again but hey the Android people
got habit hub so you can't complain too
much right so at least on the surface I
would say the strides is pretty similar
to high bidify both have really clean
professional you eyes both are very fast
or snappy they are a joy to use
but we're have been if I is a little bit
more rigid in the types of goals that
you can set up and track strides is more
flexible it has some additional options
for the types of habits that you can set
up within it for one you can set up
street goals which are great for things
like 30-day challenges and you can also
set goals to be either yes or no did you
do them to do not or based on a certain
quantity of things so if you want to
take like 10,000 steps a day you could
actually type in that number if you
really wanted to but the feature that I
like the most about strides and this is
something that I have not seen in any
other habit tracker that I've tested is
the ability to track an average for a
specific habit so if you want to make
sure you're not playing too many hours
of video games each week or you want to
just track the number of times you go to
the gym which you do have a specific
goal for it this is a great feature and
I love it but not as much as I love the
number one app on this list which is of
course habiddig a-- in my humble opinion
habiddig agos beyond all other habit
trackers out there because instead of
just letting you track your habits it
lets you turn your life into a bonafide
video game medaka is basically an RPG
with habit tracking elements built in
and instead of just working on yourself
you're working on yourself while also
building up a character in the game that
can go on quests and party up a people
and get mounts and all kinds of gear and
all kinds of fun stuff now I will
readily admit that I am a nerd and
not everyone out there is a nerd maybe
you're not a nerd so habiddig a-- is not
for everyone there's a lot going on in
that game there's all kinds of stats and
buffs and all kinds of crazy stuff which
is why I made this list there's seven
other pics on the list that you could go
for if you want something a little bit
more simple but in my experience all of
the gamification elements that are built
in to have etiqa are really really
motivating if you get into the game then
you really don't want to fail on your
habits because you're trying to build up
some gold to get a new piece of gear or
you're trying to level up so you can
actually cast more powerful spells or
and I think this is the most genius part
of haveta kheh
you can actually party up with other
people real-life humans and you can go
on quests and fight bosses together and
when you are fighting a boss at the end
of each day that boss is going to attack
you and it will never damage you unless
somebody in your party fails to do their
habits or if they mark off a negative
habit like smoking a cigarette or eating
junk food if people don't stick to what
they're supposed to be doing everyone in
the group gets hurt and if you run out
of Health and die you actually lose a
piece of gear so there's this great
accountability element to have it occur
that a lot of other habit trackers just
don't have plus in contrast to a lot of
the other habit tracking apps out there
all the core habit tracking
functionality in hebediah is free if you
get really into the game you can buy
gems for certain purposes or you can
actually donate directly to the team if
you want but all of the habit tracking
features those don't cost anything to
use and this is in the meta I really
respect about have it occur that and the
fact that I can put a pair of steampunk
goggles at a top hat on my character now
no matter which habit tracker you do
choose to go with one habit that should
probably be on it it's taking some time
to do some independent learning each day
and that's something that you can easily
do with the daily challenges feature on
brilliant each day new challenges are
posted that can test and stretch your
problem-solving skills in areas like
calculus physics computer science
statistics astronomy and much more and
if a particular problem piques your
interest you'll also find dozens of
full-fledged in-depth courses in
brilliants course library that can
improve your knowledge even further each
course use the principle of active
learning to help you learn as
effectively as possible while keeping
your level of interest high at the same
time so if you want to start boosting
your problem-solving skills on a daily
basis which can help
prove your job prospects and even help
you become more creative then head over
to brilliant org slash Thomas Frank and
sign up for free free account gets you
access to new daily challenges every
single day and if you do decide to go
for their premium subscription you're
gonna get access to their entire daily
challenges archive with lots more
problems to sink your teeth into and all
their in-depth courses as well plus if
you're one of the first 200 people to
sign up using that link which you'll
find down the description below you're
also gonna get 20% off that annual
premium subscription huge thanks as
always goes out to brilliant for
sponsoring this video and being a big
supporter of my channel and thank you to
you as well for watching if you enjoyed
this video hit that like button to get
subscribed right there so you don't miss
out on future ones when they come out
you can also click right there to get a
free copy of my book on how to earn
better grades if you haven't done so
already
or if you are perhaps in the mood to
watch more videos here on YouTube you
can find one more video on this channel
right over here or listen to our latest
podcast episode right over here thanks
again for watching and I will see you as
always in the next one