what's up guys so I know you've asked me
how to create a study space in the past
and today I was going to show you my
room but I'm going to switch it up
because literally last night my roommate
Martin who's back there yo changed his
room around and I think uh his idea for
a study pce is actually better than mine
so I'm going to have him show it to you
and walk you through it in this quick
[Music]
video
here just like be in the frame I'll just
I do an interview like obviously I need
to say more than it's basically two
tables with a shi screen yeah what's up
that's it actually you could literally
do that all right well before I had
actually tried to separate this out so
there was a gaming table and a work
table also but they were on opposing
walls mhm the problem then was that I
still
like I knew that I was in the same room
it felt like one room and I wanted it to
feel like it was a completely separate
space so there was a bit of mental
separation between work and play so you
got one desk here all the gaming stuff
what else is over on this side over on
this side we've got all my books we've
got a guitar in the closet some Pokémon
stuff and thing basically all sorts of
non-focused nonproductive things so this
is like a completely separate room
almost yeah and like it feels like a
separate room when you get in here the
show you screen in the middle really
makes a big difference I think I I
legitimately feel like I'm entering a
different room in the house even though
I know I'm just a foot away from my
other things where didd you get that
thing I did I stole it from my friend
Clyde yeah you did but you can get it on
Amazon as well for 50 bucks I think all
right so this is the roost stand mhm it
is meant to raise the screen because
ergonomically you want the top of your
monitor to be at your eye level okay now
what's cool about this is that it's
extremely portable it's freaking
cool so you can bring it with you
anywhere to a cafe to a library to your
friend's house if you need to do work or
a hotel I've done work in a hotel and
then we've got this keyboard stand which
is basically just a keyboard stand but
it's got these Grill rubber parts so it
won't slide on your pants and you can
pull out a slidable mouse pad so that
you can work with the screen at the
correct level and your keyboard at the
correct level for your arms as well so
basically like you're not even using the
table to work on at all no you could you
could take this off of the table and put
it on something literally just a little
square in front of me and it would work
just the same and because this has
adjustable height it's incredibly
flexible I can work anywhere so what
else I have on the desk I've got my
noise cancell and wireless headphones
over there this Moes notebook which I've
just got a daily schedule that I wrote
out this morning so that I could pay
attention I used to do that in Google
Calendar but I found that checking my
phone every 3 seconds to check Google
Calendar was really distracting which is
why my phone's way over there not being
touched so I've got this whiteboard up
on an easel and I basically use this
right now I've got some simple habits
and things that are sort of a template
for my daily schedule that I'm writing
out like put somewhere to read put
somewhere to study Spanish and on this
one here I write down ideas if I think
of I need to do laundry I need to run
this errand but I haven't scheduled it
in today instead of letting it
completely throw off today's work I put
it here and then schedule it in tomorrow
morning why whiteboards on whiteboards
because like are you exhibit or
something because I can take this off
and go plan things somewhere else if I
need to occasionally I use this for if
I'm drawing in the other room I'm
planning out like a web thing and I
don't want to be in here oh that's cool
so it doesn't need to be on here but
it's a good place to store it and you
clearly have a message that does like
never leaves your whiteboard so what is
the story behind this thing I had my
girlfriend write don't overthink it on
there because overthinking it is
probably my biggest weakness because I
will spend just hours and hours trying
to solve something and I could have done
something that worked within the first
10 minutes if I get caught up say I'm
editing a podcast and I get caught up on
a single vocal pause that I can't remove
like a uh I will just remember don't
overthink it nobody's even going to
notice that vocal pause just leave it if
you can't get rid of it that's smart so
I get I get the the markers I get the
Eraser yeah what are the bead things the
bead things have been useful several
times the most recent use of them was I
tore up a piece of printer paper into a
bunch of pieces wrote down ideas
attached them with magnets so that I
could slide them around the board and
rearrange them any way I wanted that way
I could determine what order to do
things in what I you can connect them
drawing lines between them and writing
things it's just good for brainstorming
we've got a couple more things we've got
a I've got a zafu here for meditation
I've got a glass teapot and some teacups
because I'm super Zen but that's pretty
much it I just did this because I've
been craving that mental separation
between work and play and I don't have
enough to pay for an office right now
outside of my house so guys that about
does it for this video just wanted to
give you a quick look at Martin's room
which I think is set up in a pretty cool
way and additionally if you don't know
Martin is my co-host over on the college
infogeek podcast where every single
Monday we take three of your questions
and answer them in a half an hour Q&A
Style Show so if you want to subscribe
and if you haven't done so already cig
podcast.com is the URL you can go to but
I'll also have it linked down in the
description below and if you want to
subscribe to this Channel and you
haven't done so you can click right
there to get new videos every single
week both on desk tour stuff we're going
to do one in my room pretty soon and on
productivity tips and other tips that
can help you be a more effective student
you can also click right there to get a
free copy of my book if you want and you
can smash your face onto your phone
screen right there or click either one
works to see another video thanks for
watching I'll see you next week