you might not want to believe this but
the place that you're sitting right now
is filled with things that are quietly
destroying your productivity this is
especially true if you're currently
sitting here but also true even if
you're sitting here today we are going
over four ways in which your workspace
your environment is probably harming
your ability to stay focused on your
work these are issues that can be so
distracting that some people will go to
extreme lengths to escape them and one
of those people is peter shankman an
author who has publicly talked about his
struggles with adhd and a few years ago
peter bought a 5 000 round trip ticket
from his hometown in new jersey to tokyo
japan and after spending 14 hours flying
to tokyo he got right back on the exact
same plane and flew all the way back
home he didn't even stop to see the
life-size gundam which is a missed
opportunity if i've ever seen one so why
would someone spend five thousand
dollars in 26 hours of their life just
to fly halfway across the world and
right back home well as peter tells it
he was working on a book and he was
coming dangerously close to his
publisher's deadline he couldn't get
himself to focus at home so he decided
to put himself in the one place where he
would have no access to his phone to the
internet or to any distractions
whatsoever a tiny cramped airplane cabin
and it worked he wrote chapters one
through five on the way to tokyo and
6-10 on his way back landing with a
finished first draft and this even
though it is completely ridiculous is my
favorite example of what a good
environment can do for your focus and on
the flip side what a bad environment can
do to rob you of your potential so let's
meet our four workplace productivity
destroyers or the four horsemen of the
productivityocalypse and see what we can
do to fix them preferably without buying
a 5 000 plane ticket and we'll start
with one that i personally have the most
trouble with paths of lesser resistance
see most work worth doing is difficult
which means you're almost always going
to encounter resistance when you try to
do it your brain doesn't want to go
through the difficulty involved so it
looks for an escape route and it's easy
to identify the usual suspects here
right tik tok twitter that game on your
phone all offer up these bite-sized hits
of dopamine that are available at a
moment's notice but i think there's an
even more insidious form of distraction
that's even harder to deal with other
work the 50 unanswered emails in your
inbox that unpaid toll bill that you got
to pay at some point these all have to
get done as well so it's easy to justify
switching over to them when you feel a
little bit stuck on your main task but
here's the problem every time you switch
from one task to another you deal with
something called attention residue part
of your attention remains the unfinished
task that you switched away from making
it harder to fully concentrate on your
current task as cal newport points out
in his book deep work this residue gets
especially thick if you work on task a
was unbounded and of low intensity
before you switched and these are
perfect descriptors for those little
tasks like checking your email so it's
no wonder that it's so difficult to get
back into the flow state when you switch
back to your main task and this is why
peter shankman's flight to tokyo was so
useful sitting up in that cramped
airplane cabin with no internet he had
little to do but write his book now you
don't have to go blow your life savings
on a trans-pacific plane ticket to get
the same benefit and honestly i think
part of his reason for doing it was to
get a good story out of it and hey here
i am telling it to you but all you need
to do is follow a simple rule clear
everything out of your workspace that
doesn't have to do with the task at hand
the closer all these other things are
the easier it's going to be for your
brain to want to switch to them start by
clearing off your desk put any loose
papers in an inbox get any visual
clutter out of the way and consider a
small set of drawers so you can keep
things out of sight and out of mind
until you actually need them i've got
this nice little one from ikea that also
doubles as a charging station for my
camera batteries once that's done it's
time to look at something even more
important which is your computer as
chris bailey points out in his book
hyperfocus on average we work for only
40 seconds when working on a computer
before either being interrupted or
distracted a huge reason for this is
that we love to leave tabs in windows
open that are completely unrelated to
the work that we're trying to do so one
way that i combat this is during that
five-minute prep i talked about in the
last video i take the time to close
anything that is completely unrelated to
my task and if i don't want to lose
something i'll paste research links into
notion now if that's not enough for you
you can also opt for the nuclear option
distraction blockers apps like cold
turkey and freedom these let you define
a list of apps and websites that are
going to be blocked during your work
sessions and then either during specific
hours or when you tell it that you're
starting a work session you're not going
to be able to access those at all and
that is actually helpful for our second
horsemen of the productivity apocalypse
which are active distractions now these
typically break down into two different
categories notifications on your devices
and distractions in your immediate
physical environment so let's first
start with notifications and i'll just
tell you what i do here i disable pretty
much every notification that could
possibly reach me except for messages on
my phone sms text messages and certain
people dming me in slack and when i
really need to focus i double down on
this by enabling do not disturb mode on
my phone that way nothing can break
through so i can really concentrate
especially when i'm doing research or
writing video scripts another idea that
your brain is probably going to throw up
some resistance to is hey maybe turn off
your phone or put it in another room and
if you are feeling resistant to this
simply ask yourself when you need to
work do i need my phone for the next 45
minutes the answer is probably no the
other source of active distractions are
in your immediate physical environment
can include things like people
interrupting you or cats interrupting
you loud noises and the arrival of
galactus and the end times surprise
[ __ ] whatever it is try to
predict what those distractions could be
and then see what you can do to get rid
of them or keep them from happening in
the first place for example telling your
friends or your family that you need an
hour of uninterrupted time is a great
way to prevent interruptions and for
loud noises a good pair of headphones is
really really nice especially if they
are noise cancelling now for the arrival
of galactus breaking your concentration
i haven't quite figured out a solution
but i do think i'm close to cracking the
code while i'm finishing that up let's
talk about our third horseman of the
productivityocalypse which is ergonomics
or rather poor ergonomics now ergonomics
is the study and science of fitting the
workplace to the individual making you
more comfortable while you work and it
is here that i will assert peter
shankman's airplane workspace wasn't so
good i fly for work a few times a month
and i find airplane seats to be
horrendously uncomfortable now maybe
this is due to the fact that i'm over
six feet tall but i think most people
would agree with me here now there are
definitely some things that you can do
to tailor your workspace for better
ergonomics which will make you more
comfortable and also help you to avoid
some chronic injuries over time which
can definitely destroy your productivity
but we have to talk about the most
important aspect of ergonomics first
which is movement and exercise i can't
tell you about any fancy desks or chairs
before we talk about this because i have
literally seen people who i know go out
and buy super fancy expensive thousand
dollar ergonomic office chairs and then
be lulled into a false sense of security
thinking the chair is all they need to
prevent injuries that is not the case
the chair might help but alone it is
inadequate and i have experience with
this a few years ago i did a whole bunch
of research and i went out and i bought
a fancy ergonomic chair for my studio
workstation and a few years ago i also
went through a period of constant
chronic back pain sitting in that fancy
chair so the chair did not fix it in
fact no single tweak to my workspace
fixed my chronic back pain what fixed it
was exercise and flexibility training
specifically some yoga moves that helped
to increase the flexibility and mobility
in my hamstrings and leg muscles but
even more importantly squats and
deadlifts weight training that
strengthened both my core and my back
muscles so they can actually support my
spinal column take this seriously and
prevent your future self chronic pain if
you don't have it already get up at
least once an hour move around go for a
walk and ideally go to the gym sometimes
or have some kind of resistance training
program so you're strengthening your
body and not letting it atrophy in a
thousand dollar computer chair and
speaking of those chairs how important
is it to get a super fancy ergonomic
chair in the first place well if you ask
the marketing departments the companies
that make them they will say it's very
important indeed but personally i'm a
bit more skeptical i think movement is
the number one factor and beyond that
i'm not convinced about all the science
and fancy research that's gone into
every aspect of these chairs and how
they contour to your body but what i do
think is important is to get a chair
that can adjust its height and if you
can do the same with your desk that's
useful as well i've got a sit stand desk
that lets me make my new adjustments to
the height but even if you can't afford
that there are cheaper desks like at
ikea that have adjustable height legs so
you can make your desk the right height
for you and what is that right height
well actually if i switch back over to
this camera i can physically demonstrate
it so first chair height should be set
so that your feet are flat on the ground
or barring that on a foot stool don't
have them dangling second set your desk
height or adjust the chair height so
that your elbows are about a 90 degree
angle you don't want to be reaching up
with your fingers and lastly with your
monitor you want to at about eye level
the top of the monitor should be right
with your eyes and laptops actually
present a problem there because you put
them on the table and now you're staring
down the laptop craning your neck which
can cause pain after a while so ideally
if you're going to work on a laptop you
want to get a laptop stand that you can
put the laptop on and then get an
external keyboard and mouse so you're
not reaching up to that stand so now we
have perfected your ergonomics we have
turned off notifications and we've dealt
with those paths of lesser resistance
but still at this point your workspace
might be missing something it might be
uninspiring i think this is important to
talk about because the environment you
put yourself in has a huge effect on
your mindset when i'm in an area that
makes me feel muted bored uncreative i
can't do my best work and i think you
would agree here so let's talk about
some changes we can make to our
workplaces and our environments to make
them just a bit more inspiring now this
is absolutely something that varies from
person to person so what i want to do
here is simply share some things that
i've done with my own workspace that
make me feel a lot better about doing my
work first and foremost i love bright
open spaces ideally with sunlight and
also i like having a workspace with
plants this is a fake plant it would die
down here in this studio if it was real
but real plants are a great addition to
your workspace i think and there's
actually some research to show that
nature exposure and i think bringing
some nature into your workspace has some
cognitive benefits so maybe go out and
add a plan to your workspace and see
what that does i also love working with
tools that let me work as close to the
speed of my thoughts as possible now
this varies based on the task if i'm
writing a script really all i need is my
laptop but if i'm editing a video or
designing a new template in notion i
love having my dual monitor workstation
so i can see everything all at once and
i also swear by gaming mice because the
high dpi sensors make them much easier
and more comfortable to use even when
i'm doing regular work tasks so those
are just some suggestions that work for
me but they might work for you as well
and overall ask yourself is my workspace
inspiring to me is it a place where i
actually want to get my work done and if
it's not what can i do to change that so
now that we've tackled your workspace
and fixed that let's talk about
something much bigger that needs fixing
as well so this is where i would
normally tell you about my video sponsor
curiosity stream but they have been kind
enough to actually donate this sponsor
spot to let me tell you about team c's
remember last year when mr beast and a
ton of other content creators got
together to raise 20 million dollars and
plant 20 million trees well this year we
are doing something very similar but we
are also raising the stakes team seizes
a global campaign to raise 30 million
dollars and remove 30 million pounds of
trash from our planet's oceans rivers
and beaches for every dollar that's
raised one full pound of trash will be
removed and we partnered with two
different organizations to accomplish
this the ocean conservancy will be
tackling the oceans and the beaches and
the ocean cleanup will be cleaning up
the rivers with their interceptor units
preventing trash from ever reaching the
oceans in the first place personally i
was incredibly impressed with team trees
last year especially since they actually
reached their goal and this year i love
the precedent that team sees is now
setting the patterned setting that every
year content creators like myself and my
friends can come together with our
audiences with you guys to band together
and do something truly big and truly
good for the environment so personally
i'll be making a donation and if you'd
like to help the cause as well there's
going to be a link in the description
down below or in the pinned comment
beyond that now that you're finished
watching this video check out this one
right here on a three-step process you
can easily follow to more reliably get
yourself into the flow state or if
you're curious about how i'm currently
doing my task management i've got a
video right here on my second channel on
my notion task management system which
is actually a free template as well so
check that out follow me on twitter for
bite-sized content if you haven't
already make sure you're subscribed and
thanks for watching hit the like button
for the algorithm and i'll see you in
the next one