hey what's up guys my name is Thomas
Frank and today I'm actually wearing
this shirt that I've worn in many other
videos for a good reason because it is
high time we talked about the impossible
list so I've been in several classes and
situations before where students are
asked to give their goals and all too
often I hear this really limited answer
where a student will say they simply
want to graduate and get a good paying
job and yeah that's an honorable goal
but I think it's really limiting
yourself if you only want to get a
high-paying job and you think about
nothing else then what happens when you
graduate get that job and find yourself
in a life situation you really can't
stand I think situations like this are
easily avoidable if you take the time to
think about each individual aspect of
your life outside of your career when
you're setting your goals so that brings
me to my impossible list this is a tool
that I've been using for the past 3 or
four years to specifically and publicly
set down my goals and then show when
I've achieved them now I didn't come up
with this idea on my own I actually got
it from a guy named Joel runan who runs
a site called impossible hq.com and he
built his impossible list when he had
graduated from college and couldn't find
a job and today he's used it to run
ultramarathons help build schools in
other countries and do all sorts of
awesome stuff and when I found it I knew
I had to make my own so essentially my
impossible list is just the list of all
the things I want to do with my life
categorized by type I have health goals
I have financial goals I have
professional goals charity goals skill
goals all sorts of goals and I have them
specifically written down and public on
my website now you might look at my
impossible list and think it looks like
a bucket list and it has some similar
ilities but it also has some key
differences that I want to go over right
now for one a bucket list doesn't really
inspire you to take action right now
it's kind of a list of things you'd like
to do and like to be able to look back
and say you did before you die but the
impossible list is more active it
demands action right now it Demands a
plan and it's also iterative so if you
look at my impossible list you'll see
goals on there with lines through them
but you'll also see sub bullet points
beneath them with goals that are similar
but even more challenging when I achieve
something more often than not I'll find
something that's even harder and
iteration on that previous goal and
write it down this makes the impossi
list concept fundamentally different
from a bucket list because a bucket list
is static and it gets smaller as you go
on you cross things off and there are a
limited amount of things left on it on
the other hand the impossible list
encourages you to evolve it encourages
you to think about the journey and keep
progressing keep getting better now like
I said I can't take credit for this idea
Joel's the one who came up with it and
I'm incredibly thankful I came across
his blog and kind of stole the idea for
myself but I have added a couple of
extra features that I think make it even
more useful if you look at the top of my
impossible list you'll see two extra
sections that aren't on Joel's list
number one is the last five completed
goals and I added that there because as
a student I was always really afraid
that I would graduate and get in a
comfortable life situation where I was
making enough money and then stop
progressing I was really afraid that I
would rest on my Laurels stop getting
outside of my comfort zone stop learning
and I really didn't want this to happen
so the last five completed goals section
lets me look at the things I've done and
how recently I've done the last one if
there's been a long time since I've
completed something then I know I need
to get myself back into gear having that
section there and having it public keeps
me accountable and keeps me progressing
keeps me staying uncomfortable the other
addition is the top section of my
impossible list and it's my current
focuses there I list the three to four
things that I'm really focusing on
because I know as somebody who wants to
achieve a lot of different things it can
be hard to pick one or two to really
focus on at one time and when you're
juggling a lot of different things at
once not very much progress is going to
be made so by listing my current focuses
I can always look at my impossible list
and say this is what I have committed to
achieving right now and if I want to
work on something else I need to
physically edit the list take the old
thing off and put the new thing on there
so that's an overview of my own
impossible list and to round this video
out I actually want to challenge you to
create your own so if you want to get
started on making your own list and want
to do it in a really simple way just
grab a piece of paper create your goal
categories write your goals down and
then make sure you put it up in a place
that you're going to see often the one
thing I'll say with putting it on paper
though is that you want to leave room to
iterate when you cross off a goal you
want to have someplace where you can
write another goal that's an extend of
that first one you can also choose to
make it in a digital format which does
make it easier to edit and if you want
to do what I did and put it on your own
website where it's more public and
you're held more accountable then I've
got a guide on how you can build your
own blog on my website which
incidentally is the longest blog post
I've ever written but you can find it by
going right there or clicking the link
in the description as a side note I've
also had employers bring up my list
during interviews in the past and
whether or not it helped me get a job it
definitely made the conversation more
memorable if you don't want to build
your own custom website you can easily
use like a free blogging platform like
Tumblr or you can even put it in a
public Evernote document I think the two
most most important considerations when
building your list though are that it's
in a place where you see it very often
whether that's public or not and also
that it's easily changeable so keep
those in mind when building your list if
you want to check out my list so you can
get some inspiration then click The
annotation right there or the link in
the description and feel free to steal
any of the features and goals that I
have on there if you do end up making
your own list and you make it public
then I'd love to see it and you can
tweet me the link over at Tom frankley
or just leave a comment down below
that's it for this video so thanks for
watching and I will see you next
week hey everybody thanks so much for
watching my video on the Poss list if
you want to get new videos every single
week on being an awesome college student
then click that big red subscribe button
right there I also wrote an entire book
on earning better grades and if you want
to get a free copy of it click the
picture of the book and I'll send you
one if you want to get links to anything
I mentioned in this video and also some
extra impossible list examples then
click the orange logo right there to go
to the companion blog post if you missed
the last video there's a clip of it
playing right there you can click and
lastly if you have any suggestions for
other videos or just want to connect I'm
Tom frankley on Twitter or you can leave
a comment below
thanks