Sherlock Holmes is undoubtedly one of
fictions most popular characters having
been portrayed by over 200 actors on the
screen over the years and having served
as the inspiration for other characters
such as Batman and Adrian Monk and it's
no wonder why we're so fascinated with
him
yes his stories contain lots of mystery
and adventure but he's also a character
who can make logical deductions from the
most scant evidence and we find that
inherently fascinating we find
characters who are hyper intelligent to
be really interesting and what's better
about Sherlock Holmes he's not
superhuman he is human which leads me to
the point of this video because if
you're anything like me you've probably
gone beyond simple fascination with the
character at one point or another and
thought to yourself how can I think like
Sherlock Holmes
you know without all the sociopathic
tendencies and the substance abuses just
the good parts well that is what I want
to explore in this video and by the end
of it you're gonna understand three of
the core mental strategies that Holmes
brought to his cases deep observation
skepticism and probabilistic thinking
the first strategy on my list is also
probably the most famous one Holmes is a
keen observer of his environment he
doesn't just casually see or perceive
his environment like the rest of us he
observes it with scrutiny taking it all
in and storing away details that other
people would miss entirely or forget
really quickly this well trained power
of observation allows him to tie
together all those small details in
order to make conclusions and this is a
skill it's useful not just in detective
work but in almost any field so here's
how you can build the skill for yourself
first be an active participant in
whatever is going on in your life try to
be as present minded as you can when
you're having a conversation with
somebody else try to listen actively try
to formulate questions in your head to
dig into what they're saying and when
you're travelling around or going about
your business
don't be staring at your phone or
otherwise dividing up your attention try
to be present minded and observe your
environment like many other cognitive
skills observation is a habit that can
be strengthened over time the author WIB
beverage puts it really well in his book
the art of scientific investigation
training and observation follows the
same principles as training in any
activity at first one must do things
consciously and laborious Lee but with
practice the activities gradually become
automatic and unconscious and a habit is
established right now most of us aren't
very
all trained in the art of observation we
divide up our attention we multitask so
again if you want to get better at this
be as present minded as you can and to
get specific I do want to give you one
little challenge to take away from this
video next time you sit down to eat next
time you sit down to the table don't
take out your phone at all not only will
this force you to be present minded not
dividing your attention with your phone
whoever's at the table but it'll also
force you to make conversation so you'll
be building your social skills as well
now aside from mindfulness there's one
other critical piece to building those
observational skills and that's to gain
experience in whatever field that you
want to be really perceptive and
observational in experts naturally pick
out details that are relevant to them in
situations and environments that the
average person just isn't going to see
think about how it actually I can't say
this word what is it plus ooh yeah that
somebody who practices the art of
parkour would look at the average urban
environment versus how a normal Pradesh
stream would look at it well you and I
would just see roads and sidewalks and
buildings and other people somebody
who's an expert in parkour is gonna see
a lot more naturally they're gonna see
the most efficient way to get from point
A to point B whether it's ducking under
a railing or vaulting over something
climbing up a wall and you and I are
just not gonna see that now this tip is
pretty related to another quality that
Sherlock Holmes emphasizes a lot a
background knowledge across many
different fields that's both deep and
most importantly according to Holmes
himself well curated this is a concept
that Holmes calls the brain attic and
here's how it describes it in a study in
scarlet I consider that a man's brain
originally is like a little empty attic
and you have to stock it with such
furniture as you choose a fool takes a
novel umber of every sort that he comes
across so that the knowledge which might
be useful to him gets crowded out or at
best is jumbled up with a lot of other
things so that he has difficulty in
laying his hands upon it now the skilful
workman is very careful indeed as to
what he takes into his brain addict now
I don't think you need to be paranoid
about taking in the wrong thing since
the brain is pre elastic and you're
really not going to fill it up as such
but you do want to make sure that you're
focusing on the most important things
for the majority of your time most of us
have that one person or life that's a
master of useless trivia but hasn't
really put a whole lot of time into
developing a useful skill don't be that
person
but the majority of your time and energy
and focus into gaining useful
information and when you do learn
actively take notes summarize
you learn and try to put it into
practice as soon as you can additionally
you want to be exploring lots of other
subjects that are somehow related to
your main subject doing this will form
lots of additional neural connections
and build a really deep web of
information in your brain and memories
that have lots of different connections
are both more likely to be retrieved and
more likely to be combined with the
problem at hand to come up with a
creative solution as the famous investor
and partner of Warren Buffett Charlie
Munger said the first rule is that you
can't really know anything if you just
remember isolated facts and try and bang
them back if the facts don't hang
together on a latticework of theory you
don't have them in a useable form the
second mental strategy of Sherlock
Holmes that were gonna cover today is
skepticism the Athenian playwright
Euripides once wrote that man's most
valuable trait is a judicious sense of
what not to believe and Sherlock Holmes
brings a natural skepticism to every
case that he faces he listens to his
clients or observes the details of a
case or crime scene deeply and
scientifically but he also compares what
he's seen and observed to his current
model of reality and all of his
background knowledge but on the other
hand as studies have found most of us
can't help but instinctively believe
what we hear right when we hear it
especially if we're put in stressful
situations or put under time pressure
not only that but our brains also rely
on lots of different little cognitive
biases and heuristics mental shortcuts
that are very useful in many different
situations especially as the human
species evolved but that can also lead
to incorrect decision-making and bad
thinking for instance we tend to wait
the information that is available to us
much too heavily that's called the
availability heuristic we also tend to
believe things if we know a lot of other
people believe them the bandwagon effect
and we also rely heavily on stereotypes
in fact a recent study in the journal
criminology which I think Holmes
probably would have read found that
certain physical traits are correlated
with sentencing decisions this being
despite the fact that logically we all
know that our physical appearance has
nothing to do with whether or not we
committed a crime and that isn't even
half of it environmental factors that
you wouldn't expect also have the
ability to really influence our decision
making
for instance prospective students that
visit a college campus on a cloudy day
are more likely to enroll in that
College than if they did on a sunny day
and people who are affected by seasonal
affective disorder tend to make more
risk-averse decisions with their money
during the winter
than they do during the summer months
not with all these natural flaws in our
thinking how can we actually think
objectively but one powerful strategy
comes from the author Maria konnikova
wrote the book mastermind how to think
like Sherlock Holmes which was as you
might guess one of the big inspirations
for this video her advice is to actively
work on noticing what is priming your
thoughts and influencing your decisions
as she states in the book a prime stops
being a prime once we're aware of its
existence bring any attention at all to
the priming mechanism and you'll likely
find the effect go down to zero when we
are aware of the reason for our action
it stops
influencing us and as a little add-on to
that piece of advice make sure that when
you come to a conclusion you can point
to the logical deduction or the
observable evidence that caused it if
you can't it's a good sign you're
relying on one of those cognitive biases
and you should probably work through the
problem a little bit more deliberately
again finally Sherlock Holmes ability to
make deductions and solve cases hinges
on his ability to think in terms of
probabilities what is most likely to
happen when Holmes is working on a case
he thinks like a scientist and uses the
scientific method forming hypotheses as
he goes along and testing them against
new data as its discovered and since
that data is almost never 100%
conclusive he generates many different
hypotheses and then he tries to figure
out which one is the most likely
candidate now this probabilistic
thinking is also called inductive
reasoning while deductive reasoning uses
certainty and sound logic to reach
conclusions that are 100% true inductive
reasoning asks what is the most likely
answer given the facts and again since
most complex problems in life usually
rely on incomplete information you need
to be able to use inductive reasoning
just as much as you need to be able to
use deductive reasoning now if you want
to see this probabilistic thinking in
action one of the home stories the sign
of four has a great example it starts
when dr. Watson hands Holmes a pocket
watch and asks what he can deduce from
it after looking to watch over for a few
seconds Holmes replies with quite a lot
of information actually that the watch
was originally owned by Watson's father
then passed down to his elder brother
also that his older brother had certain
periods of his life that were prosperous
but spent most of it in poverty and
probably ended up dying of alcoholism
now this deduction turns out to be
extremely accurate and at first Watson
is offended thinking that Holmes had
actually dug into his personal life that
he was being a Charlotte
but Holmes insists that he didn't even
know Watson had a brother until looking
at the watch all of his deductions were
based on the observations he gained from
the watch and probabilistic thinking now
if you're curious about all these
details I highly recommend going and
reading the story since it is public
domain you can read it for free but for
an example he does note that the
alcoholism deduction came from the fact
that there were scratches around the
keyhole and a sober man would I've never
put scratches in the keyhole because he
wouldn't have missed the keyhole and
trying to open the watch and moving away
from the realm of fiction if you want a
more practical example I found that
probabilistic thinking can actually help
you find things that you've lost a lot
more quickly than the most commonly
recommended solution which is to
mentally retrace your steps now that can
work pretty well but it encourages
linear thinking which can waste time if
you think probabilistically and you ask
yourself what is the most likely place I
would have say taking out my wallet what
is the most likely place I was really
distracted and might have set it down
you may end up finding it faster and
that could be the difference between
somebody picking it up and making off
with it and you actually getting it back
now there are lots of other techniques
that Sherlock Holmes used which we could
do tons of different videos on but one
of them which Sherlock would have surely
used in his investigations and which is
very closely related to probability is
game theory and if you'd like to find
out what game theory is and how you can
use it as an extremely effective
decision-making tool for solving
problems you should definitely check out
this video that I made with my friend
Jade over at her channel up in Adam not
only will the video teach you about game
theory in general but because it uses
multiple-choice questions as a case
study you're also gonna learn a
technique that'll help you potentially
get fewer wrong answers on your own
tests in the future and by the way it is
not something I talked about in my
multiple-choice video so you're
definitely gonna want to check it out
also you might notice that there is not
an ad at the end of this video that's
because I made this video as part of
skill shares of spotlight program where
they use their time and ad budget to
help highlight small creators who are
doing great things
Jade's channels in the spotlight this
month and focuses on topics like physics
and math and cryptography and lots of
other cool stuff so if you enjoyed this
video on game theory definitely
subscribe to her Channel in fact I'm not
gonna put any of the other
call-to-action things like you usually
put my videos here because I want you to
just go watch this video and subscribe
to Jade other than that guys thank you
so much for watching hopefully you found
this video helpful and I will see you in
the
one