my latest video got 400,000 views how
much money can you get for me on another
video that would get 400,000
views it depends since 2017 I've earned
over $1.2 million from sponsorships on
this YouTube channel this video is a
long form conversation with the man who
deserves probably the biggest share of
the credit for that my agent and also
the CEO in the company that I co-own
nebula Dave whisk Dave and his team have
booked over 100 m million dollars in
sponsorships for over 200 creators over
the last 10 years that includes me as
well as a lot of my friends like legal
eagle tiar zooo Mary spender philosophy
tube and a whole lot more so my goal
with this conversation is to create a
hopefully comprehensive guide for both
getting sponsors interested in your
channel if you're a Creator and also for
negotiating better deals with rates that
you deserve specifically we're going to
talk about how to know when your channel
is ready for sponsors how to attract
Brands how to price your early spots
when you're not really sure what your
content is worth and how to negotiate
higher rates over time so you're
actually getting paid what you deserve
over the Long Haul at what point can I
work with Brands if you look at views
from subscribers and it's 5% you don't
have an audience yet we'll also talk
about whether or not you should sign
with an agency and what to consider what
to ask them if one reaches out to you
now those are just the broad Strokes as
you can see this is a pretty lengthy
conversation there are a lot of other
insights and topics that we cover and I
wanted to talk with Dave specifically
about this because as far as I know
nebula Talent is the the only Creator
agency out there that actively pushes
hard for data from sponsors to actually
tell creators how well they're
performing and help them negotiate rates
that are fair over time before I started
working with Dave and with nebula Talent
when I got my first few brand deals way
back in 2017 all I knew was what the
agency representing the brand was
offering me I had no idea what their cut
was I had no idea how well my spots
performed for the brand over time which
meant I had no idea if I was getting
paid fairly additionally those agencies
didn't actively represent me which meant
they had no obligation to bring me deals
and I had no idea when my next brand
deal would come once I started working
with nebula talent in late 2017 that all
changed Not only was every single video
that I wanted sponsored actually
sponsored but I got performance data
which meant I was able to see which
videos were performing well which videos
could be improved and whether or not I
was getting paid fairly which meant that
my rates started rising over time pretty
quickly for example because I'm pretty
transparent with my sponsorship pric
when I started working with skillshare
back in 2017 I was getting $2,000 per
video now I get $115,000 per video and
in this conversation you're going to
learn how that pricing actually works
because spoilers it is not based on
views it is not based on subscribers and
it's not based on a lot of the metrics a
lot of other people and gurus on Twitter
and here on YouTube will say you need to
pay attention to it's all about value
and you're going to understand what
constitutes that value in this
conversation one more thing worth noting
is that our actual product the nebula
streaming service over at
nebula.com which means that as the CEO
of nebula Dave has the rare distinction
of having deep experience both as a
talent agent representing creators
negotiating with dozens of different
brands over the years but also as a CEO
of a company that sponsors creators he
has deep understanding of the metrics
that these companies actually look at
and care about so you're going to be
able to benefit from the insights that
come from both of those experiences so
without further Ado here's my
conversation with Dave wiscus all right
I'm going to jump right into it my
latest video got 400,000 views over on
the Thomas Frank explains Channel how
much money can you get for me to put a
sponsor on another video that would get
400,000
views it
depends okay on what uh million things
uh it's your channel okay so we know
something about you we know something
about your audience we know something
about how
people respond to you uh this is on wait
which channel the Thomas Frank explains
Channel okay the second Channel big old
notion Channel slightly different
audience in the main channel so we know
nothing other than these are people who
like you probably we don't know how many
of those viewers are return viewers
right now in this conversation we don't
know how many of those views are from
subscribers we don't know on average how
many views come from subscribers we
don't know what monthly views look like
we don't have any past sponsor data to
work from so the answer is how much do
you want well I'll go ask for that can I
have $400,000 I'll ask okay I'll I'll go
to the the sponsor Factory and I'll say
can Tom have $400,000 this what a dollar
per view that's I'll take a dollar per
view that's ambitious I don't think
that's ever been done the truth is that
we know a little bit about your audience
we have some sense of things you're a
handsome bearded white guy giving life
and productivity advice the audience
responds to that in a different way than
they would to a voiceover Channel if
you're if you made the same video same
script but you weren't on camera that
would play differently the audience
wouldn't attach to you in the same way a
lot of what your sponsor rate comes down
to is how attached is the audience to
you in your case fairly attached uh
we've seen from mutual friends and from
folks out in the world people who I know
who uh when they realize that we work
together they'll they'll talk about oh I
watch all of his no videos we know that
there's like an association there for
you but that's context that I have
because I know you if you were just to
come to me and say I have a video that's
likely to get 400,000 views how much
money the answer is like I so views do
not correlate to Dollars directly there
can be a correlation but it's not a
direct correlation and if there is a
correlation on a channel which there
often will be like the way one channel
performs relative to its views on you
know on a normalized scale it will look
as if there is some correlation between
the dollar amount or some causal
relationship between the dollar amount
and the view count uh that's misleading
most likely what's happening is you've
just got normalized views over like your
your sponsor performance was here and
your views happened to be here and then
later both of those numbers went up that
doesn't mean that one caused the other
it just meant that they both happened to
go up at the same rate at the same pace
so basically for a given set of other
factors audience affinity and connection
to the Creator the product being
promoted the topic the format views can
correlate with sponsor rate some
sponsors are going to work better for a
viral view video and other sponsors are
going to lean heavily for parasocial if
we if we think in terms of you something
like a skillshare you are there in your
videos primarily telling people not how
to do things but you're a little bit
like there's productivity advice there's
context there's I wouldn't call it how
to but there's a lot of like how to
think about how to because people are
coming to you as a an either subject
matter expert or um like sort of a
spiritual guide for productivity uh it's
really easy to assume that that audience
is an audience who wants to better
themselves in some way and that is an
audience that lines up pretty well with
skillshare uh at the end if you segue
into and another great way to learn
about camp placement or lighting or
whatever is to watch this great class I
found on skillshare blah blah blah then
the audience who sat through that even
if it's their first video of yours
they've seen they're kind of primed up
right and they might be much more
willing to follow that thread one step
further and click through uh so a viral
audience might play for you if that
video really blows up if it catches fire
well look at why it caught fire that
video might have gotten big because it
did a really good job of capturing uh an
answer to the question that the person
was asking when they found it and then
if that spreads and the algorithm robot
puppy puts it in front of more people
who have similar questions and even not
knowing you they feel satisfied with how
their questions were answered in the end
it's going to spread out it's going to
spread out and the end messaging segue
the virality of that video can be a plus
for you and for the sponsor right but if
you're pushing something like nebula if
the call to action and the primary
selling point of the sponsor nebula is
come sign up for more of me
Early Access to me leaning more into the
parasocial then a viral audience isn't
really going to Care they don't know you
they don't know you enough to care about
you they don't know that they should
care about you or even something like
let's say brilliant maybe the the video
the topic of the video doesn't line up
so perfectly still a great sponsor in
general but maybe it doesn't line up
perfectly with going and learning about
stem because you're talking about
cameras and making videos as a a side
hustle and then you're like well and you
can learn about physics that's not
really what I was here for so some
section of your audience might be really
into that but the largest chunk of your
audience the audience for that
particular video may not be I guess
before we get into everything else I do
want to draw a parallel there because
when I made the video for my paid notion
template ultimate brain when it hit a
100,000 views we estimated that it had
driven 65k in
sales wow getting close to that dollar
per viiew Mark but the way I look at it
is very similar to what you just said
about uh if we you know are talking
about something that the audience is
already very primed for they could they
could come into one video have never
seen me before and still convert for a
sponsor because they are already
interested in the thing that the sponsor
represents and I see that reflected in
the template video too because anybody
who's clicking on that video sees you
know in notion in the title they're
already primed to want to use notion and
ideally to want to improve how they use
notion so even if they don't know who I
am they're like well I'm already primed
for this tool so I'm primed to convert
here yeah that's an audience where you
got to think about what is The Logical
Next Step you have to imagine when the
audience sees this sponsor read or when
they get to the end of this video what
is their logical next up what do they
want to do next right at the end of a
video about uh making videos as a side
hustle what is The Logical next step for
for the person who finished that video
mhm well a pretty strong case for
logical next step is learn more about
making videos you're obviously
interested in the topic go learn more
you watch a video about notion and how
to do amazing things in your life with
notion templates you get to the end of
that video The Logical Next Step might
be to get some uh notion templates from
the expert who just made the the video
that you
watched that is how you get a a bigger
chunk of the people who finish the thing
uh to click on the the sponsor link and
and make a purchase increasing the the
conversion count if the logical next
step
is go learn more about notion but what
you present them with is let's learn
about physics or subscription coffee
yeah uh then it's like some subset of
those people will be interested in
subscription coffee because they just
were or maybe you mention coffee
somewhere in the video or maybe you have
a really great segue like yeah if you're
making as a side hustle you still have
your day job right and it takes a lot of
time to put these things together and
you might have some long nights I always
did and that's why I drink whatever
coffee and you should buy some like
that's kind of a way to fake a logical
Next Step the smooth segue thing is
about creating a logical Next Step
sometimes it works really well sometimes
it doesn't but the uh the name of the
game is often just like making sure that
the thing that you're promoting has some
actual relevance to the audience
something I would like to touch on a bit
later is how you do that in a a way that
doesn't compromise the Integrity of the
content uh because that was something
that I was always worried about back
when I first started working you in like
2017 uh I was worried like if I put
brilliant on a video on how to do better
in math it's going to compromise the
Integrity of the video because the
sponsor is too close to the video right
and I'm sort of cooled on that but I
think a lot of people also are going to
have the same question uh ideally the
kind of people that I would want
watching this video who have their
audience in mind first yeah uh when you
think Integrity a lot of it comes down
to the Integrity of the Creator and so
much of what a sponsorship is is uh just
trust you're not selling airtime on your
video right there's a cheaper way to get
airtime on your video It's called
AdSense if somebody just wanted airtime
they would do that what the sponsor is
buying is trust they are buying access
to the trust relationship that you have
with your audience so when you at the
end of the video say I really like this
brand of subscription C coffee it wakes
me up in the morning I feel great and I
have lots of Genius brain ideas uh they
believe that that is true and that you
mean what you say and over time if
you're promoting ways for them to
improve their mental acuity if you're
promoting tools that they can use to
improve their lives if you're promoting
services that help them enhance their
skills and develop professionally you
build a rhythm of trust with your
audience that you are only here to
promote things that that bring them
benefit so when you get to sponsor
number 60 sponsor number 70 uh there's a
couple of ways that can go right one is
you promote uh a service that uh
dubiously purchases maybe a plot of land
in a foreign country to get you a fake
title that nobody will ever care about
that sounds on the face of it like
either a dumb novelty that is harmless
or a scam even if it's just a dumb
novelty do you want to be the dumb
novelty guy or do you want to be quality
products and services guy yep like
you've built up this trust and now
you've just done done something that can
erode it a little bit the other side if
you get to sponsor number 60 70 whatever
it is and you make a video
about making videos and at the end
you're promoting the new Canon C
something or other because Canon saw
your previous video about making videos
they decided to sponsor you then the
audience isn't thinking this guy is a
sellout shill who's just going to take
money and put whatever random [ __ ]
he wants to in front of me they're
thinking this is high quality sponsor
that benefits me guy and if he did a
deal with Canon this must be pretty cool
yeah you need to be seen as being
selective about that that buys you out
of the ethical question of why is this
kind of sponsor sponsoring this video
the other side of that though was like
if if you are a Creator who only makes
videos about Canon or about cameras and
about reviewing cameras and then you do
a Canon sponsorship your credibility for
everything else is shot yeah so the
difference would be like here's a
channel where I review cameras and then
I take a sponsorship it sort of erodes
my non-biased opinion whereas if it's
just like I'm going to teach you
lighting setups I'm going to teach you
sound like I'm going to teach you the
craft of film making and I take a
sponsorship from Canon it's different
because it doesn't uh erode the
Integrity of editorially what what I'm
doing yeah because at no point will
somebody need to worry if if they're
coming to you for a question of which
camera should I get and sometimes you
are saying Sony when they're paying and
sometimes you're saying Canon when
they're paying it's like
well which one actually is better will
he lie to me for money right that's
weird if you've always said or if you've
made videos in the past talking about
your camera setup and then you get to
this video the one time you're promoting
an actual camera and you say here's my
setup this is what I've alwaysed use
this video is sponsored by Canon uh they
want me to talk about this great new
camera it's got these features it does
these things uh and this is what I've
always used myself that sincerity
matters right because that's really is
what you use and that's going to carry
through to the audience but it's going
to be a combination of time and
relationship maturity and how much trust
there is between you and the audience
and you got to be really careful not to
sacrifice that for a paycheck so what I
want this to be is ideally like the
One-Stop shop guide for the Creator who
either wants to work with Brands
eventually or is starting to get
approached by Brands maybe even works
you I'm going to put a lot of
expectations on your
plate and obviously it can't be you
can't be all of that um but I want I
want to at least cover a lot of the
questions that creators are going to
have well I think the I'll just call it
out there's going to be a lot of it
depends and and I should disclaim UPF
front that I work with uh a collection
of creators who work within a collection
of genres and there's plenty of genres
out there like uh beauty or vloggers or
comedy channels there's a bunch of of of
genres that I've never touched and they
might have their own rules in their
universe and I acknowledge that nothing
that I'm going to say here is
necessarily a universal truth so as long
as we're okay with that I'm happy to
answer any yes and I I I will put my
favorite quote in the universe out there
UPF front Bruce Lee once said adapt
what's useful reject what's useless
adapt what is specifically your own
uh use that as your North Star for
anything you hear here because yeah like
you've worked with going on 100 80 190
creators uh total I've ever worked with
probably probably over 200 at that point
yeah so over 200 creators um 10 years of
booking sponsorships for creators you've
worked as a Creator yourself in multiple
genres and now being CEO of nebula uh
we're one of the biggest sponsors on
YouTube at this point would you say like
500k spend per month yeah yeah uh and
Sky's limit on that because of how
quickly the the revenue returns so it's
like everything is everything is built
by numbers everything is built on data
so like get more data spend more money
get more data spend more money it's uh
yeah it's weird to have seen so many
different facets of it I've sat in so
many of the different chairs um and not
just as a content creator for video but
across medium a podcast or professional
musician so kind of getting a sense of
how different uh sharks and different
Waters operate um I've I've I've
certainly become skeptical yes and and
I've uh firsthand seen a lot of these
sharks um have worked with some of the
Sharks uh and then met you in 2017 so
you know just to cover the bonafides
here I think like since meeting you in
2017 um I've made 1.2 million in
sponsorships you're welcome that's all
yeah I mean it is it is through you and
standard so thank you well mean we're
we're uh that that's money you earned I
do yeah I do understand that I did earn
it the sponsors wanted to work with me
but like uh you and standard and all the
team you know behind standard are in
part responsible for that and in part I
think responsible for uh helping me to
navigate the path and make it
sustainable over a course of five years
um until I you know at least temporarily
stopped working with Brands last year
temporarily you say yeah I mean this is
going on the main Channel it might might
be sponsored by something we'll see so
anyway you've been working with me for 6
years now we have 180 creators currently
being represented um something like that
think you're the person that I would
want to talk to if I was building a
resource for creators coming up wanting
to know how to navigate these Waters it
would be so weird if you didn't want to
talk to me after everything you just
said if you're like you're third on my
list i' be like oh [ __ ] okay so I I sort
of divided my mental outline into
chapters of the Creator's journey and
the first one is obviously like I want
to work with Brands yeah at what point
can I work with Brands like how big do I
need to be on YouTube or or whatever it
is yeah this is this is one of those
early days questions um it depends okay
there's no there's no single answer to
this generally speaking if if somebody
recommends a channel to me and I I take
a look at it and I
see six months of posting history and
they're getting 20,000 views per video
my reaction is internally is they're not
there yet if I see 50,000 it's maybe if
I see 100,000 like okay we're about
there but even then the view counts
views don't really matter the view
counts aren't super representative
they're just like a you
got answer this question like there's
this collection of creators like how
many have this okay that shrinks the
pool okay how many have this shrinks the
pool the shrinks the pool shrinks the
pool so those concentric circles the
first filter is average views per video
a couple things you can get out of that
if I see that you've got 10,000 views
and then 100,000 views and then 2,000
views and then 500 views and then a
million views you're not a million view
Channel you're a 500 view Channel and
and some other stuff happened along the
way so you're saying the lowest view
count of a recent videos is
representative of what you think they're
likely to get future ones I would say
if I see a wide range I'm going to be
wondering why okay and if I see that
you've got one or two videos with a
couple hundred views and then one or two
videos with a couple million views but
you've got a couple hundred
subscribers that leads me to believe
that
maybe uh the million plus view videos
were either a fluke or you're just
starting to break out which matters they
could be perfectly this could be your
new normal but if it's your brand new
normal
you might still not quite be ready for
sponsorships yet there's a difference
between the audience and your audience
the audience belongs to YouTube and you
can already buy access to that through
AdSense your audience is the
relationships the trust relationships
that you have fostered you have grown
over time people who will listen to what
you say and take your advice on things
who the people who will stick through to
the end of the sponsor read and are more
likely to buy something or to sign up
for something yeah in part because they
trust you and in part because they want
to support you that desire to to be a
part of your story
paraso uh involved in your success let's
not discount that that is your audience
the audience the you know a couple
million views that's the audience that's
YouTube's audience how many of those are
yours well if you've got six videos only
the two most recent have a million plus
and you've only got 500 subscribers then
I'm going to guess probably about 500 of
those people are actually your audience
right so it's not a question of what
what is it worth how much is a
sponsorship for a couple million views
the answer the the question is how much
is a sponsorship for a couple hundred
views
and the these things if if we don't know
much more than just those numbers we
have to go by the numbers but if you dig
in and you see um that on these latest
two videos that have over a million
views a lot of them are return viewers
or uh watch time is really high that
might tilt things or it might indicate
that good things are happing but there's
I don't know there's so many data points
behind the scenes that you would need to
look at to really understand it um but
that first that first filter that first
litness test is do I see a consistency
and a trajectory okay so consistency
trajectory going upward building that
core audience that comes back for you
has trust in your channel if we're
looking at the back end and we're on
YouTube so we're going to use YouTube as
the example here what are the metrics
that a Creator should be tracking and
looking at most closely to determine you
know this is starting to pick up steam
I'm starting to become attractive to
Brands whether as uh you know me
reaching out to them or you know looking
forward to the time when they might be
com be coming to me views from
subscribers okay uh take a look at the
channel views from subscribers over the
last 30 days and this may even answer an
upcoming question like when am I ready
right if you look at views from
subscribers let's say you're getting
half a million views per video and then
you go into views uh percentage of views
from subscribers over the last 30 days
not percentage of watchtime percentage
of views from subscribers over the last
30 days and it's 5% you don't have an
audience yet okay you're building one
you're in build mode and that's awesome
to an extent you'll always be in build
mode get used to that live there but if
you don't if you've not built your
audience yet 5% or can we say more
precisely that is your audience like if
it's 5% views from subscribers maybe you
do have an audience like maybe you had
two million views in a 30-day period
like 5% is a decent number there yeah
you're going to you want to look at uh
percentage of views from subscribers you
want to look at how many views came from
the subscriber tab MH uh and you want to
take a look at how many return visitors
you have the the that'll give you a sort
of General sense of how many people are
coming in for you okay uh versus if it's
all from browse features or from search
God it's all from search you got nothing
uh really yeah well I mean I might want
to debate on that one it well anything
can vary by genre okay and productivity
might be different or how-to content
might be different uh but generally if
somebody goes into search they're
looking for an answer to something they
get to you if you've got tons of search
traffic but no return visitors what's
your audience you might have uh
something magical uh uh a really great
answer to the question about logical
Next Step that a certain kind of sponsor
would be really really grateful to be a
part of but you don't have your audience
okay if nobody watches more than one of
your videos that is not your audience
you can still capitalize like I say you
if you have uh
how-to uh guides on woodworking or
something
um uh do-it-yourself homeowner repair
type stuff people come in for that they
get their question answered if the
logical next step is go to Home Depot
and you have an ad for Home Depot at the
end that might be really effective uh
but it doesn't necessarily mean that
that person is going to buy a Thomas
Frank fix it t-shirt right so it seems
like you're almost building a
distinction between when a channel is
ready for for very specific kind of
sponsors which I think is and correct me
if I'm wrong but is a much harder
question to answer generally well even
if you're doing the the Home Depot ad
you still need views right and if you're
getting a couple hundred views per video
like why would Home Depot want to
sponsor you ever yeah and that one makes
sense like if it's 200 views a video
you're probably not going to get hardly
anything yeah and that's why the the
trick with any of this like it's such a
complicated flowchart and like what I'm
talking about here is handwavy and
specific to certain genres and I don't I
don't want to mislead anybody into
thinking that there's a single clear
answer there just there isn't one um
there can be for certain genres kind of
but then there's like are you on camera
are you not on camera do you have high
camera production value or does it look
like it was shot on an iPhone and poorly
edited all of these things will
influence sometimes in surprising
directions you would assume that this is
the better in every category but
sometimes shooting something on your
iPhone makes it feel more relatable
right or like we saw um like Linds Ellis
used to do very ironic ad reads right
and then they would do quite well
sometimes yeah like she was the one she
did where there was like a a big rant in
there or an entire video I think about
Squarespace I think there was yeah and
then uh it ends with and then go sign up
for Squarespace which uh did really well
and the audience loved it so great
everyone wins yeah so to come back to
the point there's like I guess there
might be a distinction we can we can
make between uh a channel that is ready
for let's say let's call it a general
slate of sponsors like back in my
channels Heyday if you want to call it
that it was a sponsor in every video and
we had a decent rotation and they were
all sort of something different versus
now um I feel like Thomas ring explains
might have broken past this at this
point but say six months ago anything
that wasn't notion or a notion tool
probably wouldn't perform that well
right because it's like we did have uh a
huge percentage of our views from search
before yes uh now it's mostly browse but
it was like I think it was the the top
thing was search for a while probably
because people are looking for answers
to specific questions they come in they
discover you that as a discovery
mechanism is fine the question is not
how did how did the viewers get to you
today it's how many of those people are
getting to you for the second time the
third time the fifth time and I don't
know if can see that level of
granularity but there's certainly what
was the content of those videos I mean
it's all how to everything's how to
right right uh how to what how to build
a habit tracker how to open links with a
different URL Handler like from very
broad to very very technically
technically Niche and then the the end
of that video who's the sponsor me
always me right yeah there's there's
never been a sponsor here's how to do
these things here's how here I am an
expert here are the systems you need to
solve problem MH you have problem you
will find this video people search they
find this video because they have that
problem they watch because they have
that problem and in the end logical Next
Step here's a tool you can use that
helps you solve this problem of course
that's going to do well they're already
there for notion or or habit trackers or
whatever they
here's here's a handsome bearded white
dude uh who who seems like he knows what
he's talking about he's confident and he
says these things and he's got a really
wellth thought out system I want to be
like that guy I want to be that uh put
together I want to be that thoughtful
about how I comport myself go through
life build my systems then at the end
you're saying and here's a tool I'm
going to sell you on how to build a
system like
hell yeah I'm signing up for that so
that makes sense logical Next Step so
there there's a useful insight there
people find me because they're searching
for I want to be able to have a track or
a notion they don't care that it's me
they don't know who I am half the time
right and then basically you're saying
they're watching the video initially to
get that answer but then you know by
virtue of the way I look the way I speak
the way my set looks how professional
everything looks there starts to I start
to build a connection there you win
their trust quickly this is sales right
like you go into a a car dealership and
the guy who's got the uh schlubby
ill-fitting suit and the the the bad
combover is probably not going to be as
compelling a figure to you as like a
really cool handsome guy like a James
Bond Vibes this guy knows what's what
and he's probably going to all the cool
clubs and whatever uh you're going to
kind of favor his opinion on which car
is right for you right this guy over
here it's like I don't know I read the
the car buying guide and I I went on the
internet and it said I should get this
Honda Accord so I'd like the Honda
Accord please whereas this guy might
talk you into a sports car because he's
that makes sense actually my my wife
recently went to a tailor to get a suit
jacket she bought tailored and she came
back and she was just gushing about the
person who helped her and she's like I
just want to be this guy's best friend
so very good example I feel like um he
probably could have sold her a
skillshare membership pretty easily
maybe he should have maybe he should
have okay so coming back to the sort of
view thresholds that you were saying
like 20K average is probably not going
to do it 50k
maybe this is this is super generalized
heris and it seems like it is primarily
for your benefit as an agent that has
very limited time and resources in terms
of like your ability to go out and find
brand deals for 180 creators there's
Instinct I think that comes with
experience okay where I can look at a
channel I can see high quality
thumbnails uh view count is trending up
uh might be early days but they're
clearly putting in the work and the
audience is is definitely starting to
catch on um but average 50,000 views
okay that's interesting if I go in and
the channel is five years old and
they've been putting out a video every
week and the thumbnails look like [ __ ]
bad typography bad composition uh they
just keep cranking stuff out huge
fluctuations in view counts but the
average
50k me gotcha because one of these
people is on a trajectory one of these
people is putting in the work the other
one thinks that they' found success
because the number is just big enough to
make them think that right but they're
not doing anything to build it they're
in like maintenance mode on their view
count that makes and so like uh they're
probably cycling through audience or
they have exactly Their audience but
they're not attracting anybody else in
MH so they're not going to be from a
sponsor perspective you want like you
want to Turning reservoir of core
audience because like on any given video
there's a reservoir of people who could
potentially sign up for the sponsor they
could con uh potentially be convinced to
sign up for that service and then of
that there's a smaller group of people
who will sign up for the service but you
go all the way out it's like the people
people who watch the video the people
who watch it to the end the people who
actually watch the sponsor read the
people who think the sponsor read is
interesting the people who click the
people who buy or you know some version
of that what you
want is for with every video you are
pouring more potential in at every stage
of that even down to the the people who
watch all the way to the end it should
be to some degree a different group of
people and you can have a situation
where 200,000 people watch every video
you
make but you get uh a thousand
conversions for a sponsor every single
time MH you would think conventional
wisdom would be if it's 200,000 people
and you're getting a thousand
conversions you got 2,000 of those right
at best you can do that uh two two uh
200 200 times you could do that yeah you
can do that 200 times and you've run out
of people right uh or more likely you're
going to hit a point of diminishing
returns along the way mhm this time it's
a thousand next time
it's 950 and then it's like 920 and then
and then and then that doesn't happen
what is YouTube if not a machine that
goes out and finds you more audience
right this is what the algorithm does
what doesn't find you an audience that
finds your video for the viewers who
would like it but from a practical
perspective
Ive how many new subscribers do you gain
when you post a new video you would
expect that the number of new
subscribers gained on a 200,000 view
video that that that could be any number
it could be a few hundred it could be a
a few thousand depending on the channel
so a couple of things are happening
there one is that the pool is constantly
being replenished it's not the same
200,000 people watching every video yeah
that's absurd it's a different group of
200,000 people every time right and
there's going to be some people who
watch every one and there's going to be
a larger group of people who watch every
other video y or an even larger group
who have missed the last five but then
the algorithm put this in their their
recommended feed and the thumbnail
looked good and they recognized it was
you so they
clicked of that most of your subscribers
don't watch every video and most of your
views don't come from subscribers so
what is your audience your audience is
sort of a rotating cast of people who
have seen some of your stuff right you
are not Game of Thrones you are not
destination viewing for a large number
of people and it's better off for
everybody if you don't fool yourself
into thinking that every one of your
subscribers is sitting down the moment
you post a video with a bag of popcorn
and clearing their schedule to watch
whatever you just posted right it's
YouTube videos are a crime of
opportunity in a lot of ways so some
things are destination viewing I'll stop
what I'm doing for a Patrick Williams
video I'll stop what I'm doing for I
don't know an ALT shift x video speaking
of Game of Thrones but there's plenty of
other creators who I love their stuff
but I might miss a video or two and then
maybe later I'll go back and I'll do a
little binge and these things are all
valid these things are all perfectly
good ways for audience to uh discover
the things you make but very few people
are like so in love with you that
they're going to sit down the second you
post and watch it nobody is uh I say
nobody but largely the audience is not
full of complete s who have to go
through all of that so if the cast is
rotating the cast of of the audience is
rotating if the waters are constantly
churning then you don't have 200,000
people and that's the limit of that
200,000 some of them are never going to
hear of you again M some of those people
have no idea who you were they just
watched a thing and they moved on with
their lives because who cares this
wasn't for them or it wasn't such an
important and compelling thing that they
feel they need another one right for
whatever
reason there are other groups there some
some subset of that is people who are
seeing you for the first time and will
want to see the next one but they're not
in the group that's ready to buy on the
next video or the next video or the next
video they might be MH so we can Define
the audience not and I think this is
important not as your subscriber count
super not that uh I would say out of my
3 million subscribers in this channel
probably 2 million of them have have
been gone like you know they graduated
college they don't want the college tips
anymore they don't care about
productivity anymore um so you know
there's a pool of people that are just
kind of out of my life how many times
have we been together and you've been
recognized and somebody says I watched
your videos all the time in college I
mean literally two nights ago at the
restaurant the waiter was like yeah I
watched your videos in my freshman year
I really liked them and I'm graduating
now so I don't need them anymore right
right not a bad thing he he sort of
graduated out of the audience and then
it's up to you do you want to keep
appealing to this demographic or do you
want to broaden it out and those are
decisions that you'll make as a Creator
but his feedback wasn't negative it
wasn't I liked you and then he started
to suck so I'm out it was this served
the thing that this served the purpose
that I needed it to serve and I'm
grateful to you for that even if you're
not currently a part of my viewing
habits so I I think this is important
like we should Define like your audience
is this very nebulous group of people
who are familiar with you and who are to
some degree willing to watch your
content that's coming out now right so
you know between the people who watch
every video religiously the ones who
watch here and there the ones who just
like see a video pop up and they
recommended every six months that's your
audience I would say I I would distill
it to your audience is the group of
people who watch your videos on purpose
we can handwave it at that there's going
to be asterisks and footnotes all over
the place but roughly speaking people
who who watch your videos because they
meant to that is your audience and so on
YouTube you're saying the way to get a
rough picture of that is to go into your
analytics and look at views from like
returning viewers yeah look at returning
viewers look at views from subscribers
anything that is a metric that hints
this person watched me on purpose okay
not found this video and watched this
video on purpose but watched my video on
purpose people who came back are a
pretty good example of that gotcha at
least as a Point subscribers obviously
there are people who watching on on
purpose but trouble with subscriber
count now or views from subscribers now
is that uh the the like recommended feed
is front and center even me a hardcore
sub feed user I don't use it anymore I
looked at my views like from the sub
feed on Thomas Frank explains and it
was.
2% that sounds about right and if I went
to my entire Channel's history not the
last 28 days I think it was one % so wow
so I think views from the sub feed
doesn't really say much anymore but the
number of returning views you get I
think that's much more compelling yeah
yeah and uh all of this is a little bit
mystical right we're we're trying to
read tea leaves yep and and so like no
one data point is the thing no one item
in analytics is the thing views from
subscribers is pretty good right uh
return viewers pretty good return
viewers is pretty good for establishing
like how much audience do you have uh
percentage of views from Subs over the
last 30 days tends to be a pretty good
metric for figuring out like whether
you're ready for sponsorships or not
anything under about 20% maybe not okay
uh 20% to 50% is The Sweet Spot mm the
closer you get to 50 the better your
sponsor rate is probably going to be um
once you hit 50 and above it's hard to
go over 50 because if you're at about 50
if half of your views are coming from
people who were subscribed that's a lot
of subscribers giving positive signals
to the algorithm so it will reward those
signals by going out and finding more
people I see so that 50% number keeps
growing keeps growing keeps growing so
the algorithm fills up the other 50% if
you've got this growing but the
algorithm brings you nothing it means
that only subscribers like this video
and nobody else cares and that's a
problem right so 20 to 50 % is about the
target range uh over 50 55 maybe percent
and you start to have troubles if like
100% of your views are subscri uh
subscribers it means that the algorithm
was showing your videos to people and
nobody cared gotcha so on on to pricing
oh boy the even harder topic um this is
the most common question I get yeah how
much can you get me yep how much can you
get me for a video so I want to I want
to dig into the question of how much do
you charge when you're just getting into
this uh but I first want to jump forward
and sort of like set the stage when I
was doing sponsors regularly I had to
sponsor in every video which was between
two and four videos a month every
sponsor rate was $10 to
122,000 like extremely consistent that's
pretty good and I mean and and you you
booked these how what were the view
counts like right around 50k on my
channel
know we're like 150 to 300K okay
probably I I'm remembering I think when
we first started working together your
view counts were lower yes they were a
little low I think I was probably
breaking a 100 or getting close to it
when we first started working together
and we first started working together um
this will be a a question to come back
to but the first sponsor rate you booked
me was actually lower than when I had
first worked with that brand directly
and there's a reason for that but but I
want to First establish like why was my
sponsor rate so consistent for years
like $10,000 $10,000 $10,000 every video
even though the view counts would
fluctuate like crazy and I imagine the
conversions would fluctuate like crazy
too well the view counts uh who cares
like there's there's an audience your
audience who will watch your videos the
people who watch on purpose that's
probably not fluctuating very much the
collection of viral views that the
algorithm will bring you that so here's
here's here's your audience and here's
the audience and the audience will
fluctuate wildly your audience is
probably going to be fairly steady MH to
within a margin of error uh we see this
all the time where a Creator will panic
because they think well this probably
bombed for the sponsor because the video
way underperformed then we'll look at
the data and we're like no actually did
a little better than usual and it's like
wait how is that possible like well
let's go into the analytics okay well
your views from subscribers was higher
than usual so while it didn't catch
algorithmic fire uh your audience really
liked it like your audience clicked
through your audience saw the thumbnail
and watched the thing others didn't so
you're not really growing your audience
on this video very much but like your
audience did see it and they click
through and they signed up at roughly
the same rate I'm always amused and
fascinated at the consistency from video
to video to video you would think that
the number of people want to sign up for
nebula or whatever uh from this video to
this video would be a wildly different
number of people right it isn't it's
super consistent I've also been really
fascinated with that on the sales side
like sales of our products are usually
pretty even from day to day MH and I'm
just like how is it the same number of
people decide they want to buy a
template today as they did yesterday y
like I don't get it but it just somehow
works out that way and and web traffic
seems to work the same it's like you
look at your analytics and maybe
sometimes you get a viral Spike or you
have seasonality but dayto day it's
usually like within a fairly tight range
yeah like we look at nebula signups just
like just the analytics for nebula
signups and I know that a wind over
video I can expect roughly this many
signups per day um with you know it's
day one this and day two day three day
four uh and then uh maybe a cinema winds
video goes out and a Neo video or a uh
Lindsay Ellis video was released and
like I I kind of know per Creator what
what those chunks look like and so I can
look
at the like a one Monon span of signups
and I can see with with remarkable
consistency like oh here's where more
creators posted videos and then here's
where people were like just as a
collective everybody was working on
their scripts or like trying to get
something out the door and then suddenly
at the end of the month it spikes back
up again because everybody finally
rushed their video out because they knew
that they had a deadline uh you can see
the EB and the flow of it and it's not
because like oh like on these days these
people perform particularly well it's
like no just you put the money into the
machine sponsoring the thing um and this
is the perspective as a sponsor you put
the money into the machine and you know
roughly how the creators are going to
perform so seeing the spikes and the
dips really come down to how many
sponsorships ran that day right not did
this Creator nail it or did this Creator
underperform CU there there will be
variances sometimes there's a dud and
sometimes you just knock it way out of
the park uh but those tend to balance
each other out and so from a sponsor's
perspective it's about normalizing the
data as much as you can think about like
a portfolio you're not booking one video
from one Creator you're booking a
collection of creators you're booking a
a a tranch of videos from a collection
of creators and you're doing that uh
repeatedly because you want to we're
playing baseball here right we want as
many at bats as possible we want to play
as many games as possible and over that
you can see where the trends are you can
predict better and you can get a better
understanding of what a given player's
performance is and you can optimize for
that you can build that you can try to
find the markers that would help you
identify who another great player might
be but it's not about I'm a sponsor I
give you the money you go out it's a dud
therefore never work with you again it
might affect how much I pay you for the
next one and C certainly will
um but at the beginning of the
relationship it certainly will uh but it
doesn't mean I'm blacklisting you okay
it doesn't mean this guy sucks we never
want to go there again unless the answer
is just zero or um comically lower than
what you would expect for margin of
error and this is this is another point
of confusion I think where creators will
will go in asking for astronomically
High rates to your question like why was
it so consistent but but also like the
like 10 what was it 10 to it's like10 to
122,000 was almost always the rate so 10
to
12K uh but the first one we did lower
yeah I mean when we started working
together I think the first spot we ever
did was 2K that's not and then it went
4K 7K 10K like up pretty quickly not
uncommon uh and
for a handful of reasons but uh one I'll
address here in this moment is that if
you go in at 2K and
overperform the sky is the limit for you
in how much that sponsor is going to
love and trust and be excited to work
with you again that doesn't mean you
should intentionally discount um like we
made a best guess based on data and
there's other stuff uh but generally
speaking uh what you want to do is make
sure you're not going in too high right
don't go in too low but if you have to
choose between too high and too low pick
too low because low is going to Dazzle
and create a great first impression that
makes them want to work with you again
yeah you're building a relationship and
I mean this is if you're if you're doing
it right this person is somebody you'll
work with again and again and again
because you want them to keep giving you
money right do you want $10,000 once or
do you want $8,000 a month forever mhm
right like this is the the balance you
could probably go in and convince
somebody to give you 20 grand even if
you're only worth three but if you know
you're worth three and you say 20 and
they pay you 20 you didn't get a good
deal you sold your own future right at a
discount don't do that so it's more
about don't don't go in with too high a
rate that you're you're ensuring that
they don't want to come back and work
with you you're building a relationship
you want to make the marketing person
look good in front of their boss you
should be the easiest decision they ever
made next month and the month after that
and the month after that because they
know that whatever their target is
whatever their kpis are uh key
performance indicators typically cost
per acquisition how much they pay to
acquire a new customer let's say it's
$25 they want to spend $25 to acquire a
new customer there's going to be some
influencer out there who has a giant ego
and uh a Hardball team and they convince
the brand
it's got to be some crazy number and
they say worth testing and they pay that
money performs at $300 per conversion
sponsors like all right not doing that
again right uh and then they just don't
make the call they don't call up and say
well you did you way underperformed
let's do one cheaper because they
probably know that the response to that
is going to be no yeah uh like why waste
the time why waste the energy and the
Creator is probably not calling up and
saying how well did that one do and if
they do the answer they're going to get
is it underperformed and to them that
means oh I'd have to take less money
never mind I'll just go talk to somebody
else and quote my astronomically High
rate again and for some creators they
can do that they can move from bridge to
bridge to bridge lighting fires and they
think that that's success they think
that because they got 10 people to pay
them $20,000 for a $3,000 video that
they are now sitting on a mountain of
evidence that they're worth $20,000
they're not when in reality they're just
sort of tricking brand after brand after
brand into thinking that this is going
to be worth it right so no value is
really delivered right and what's going
to happen in the end is when they
complete that cycle and they're looking
for another sponsor suddenly they're not
going to have one right or you can keep
finding new sponsors I guess or doing
Outreach to other types of Brands and
making something happen or maybe after a
year of sitting there that first video
finally had caught up to per performance
and maybe it's worth testing again maybe
from the sponsor perspective like it's
within test range so we'll try and maybe
the audience has grown they do it again
same results like oh burn that bridge
and so uh it's really easy to to mistake
a view count for audience size and then
let that trick you into thinking that
you're worth more than you are or people
paying you that much it's easy to think
that because somebody paid you that that
you're worth that MH maybe maybe not not
so going back to the question of
consistency the the answer basically is
even though there's variance in
performance on each individual spot the
brand is looking at it as in as you know
this is within standard deviation this
spot didn't so horribly underperformed
that we think the next bet is not worth
it and they're basically just looking to
normalize over the long term as long as
the relationship seems like a good one
and has long-term prospects yeah and
there's there's secondary factors like
one of the things that we look at now
when we're booking creators to promote
nebula we like yeah obviously we're
looking at CPA we want to spend this
much money and we want to have this much
money come in from those new customers
otherwise we're just setting money on
fire that's not a good way to run a
business but there are sometimes
creators who they underperform a little
bit but their videos get so much watch
time on nebula that we understand that
the value of this Creator might not just
be in how many signups they get but in
how long the retention curve is for the
customers who stay if somebody signs up
for Thomas Frank and then you keep
promoting and they stay for four years
so we have a lifetime value of four
years that is good for us the value of a
customer went up so the CPA can kind of
go up okay if somebody comes in and
signs up for you and then no matter what
we do your lifetime value is two
months it's not just so things get even
more complicated because you can look at
your average lifetime value of a
customer but if the people I bring in
stay a lot longer right that that CPA
number the cost per acquisition CPA that
is how much I want to spend to get a new
customer uh kpi key performance
indicator which are like here is what
drives us here's how we build our
campaigns these are the numbers that we
care about so if my kpi is cost per
acquisition and I want to spend $25 how
do I get to that $25 number what magic
formula tells me that $25 is the right
answer is it because the service costs
more than $25 that'd be a dumb way to do
it yeah uh it could beemp and overhead
everything right right right uh for us
you take a look at how much the service
costs and we uh so if somebody signs up
nebula.com Frank uh if they sign up for
a year they're paying $30 if they sign
up on the monthly plan they're paying $5
a month mhm so if they stay for a year
on the annual plan we get 30 bucks if
they stay for a year on the monthly plan
we get 60 bucks
yep so you would think we want you on
the monthly plan because we make twice
as much money except they don't except
people who come in uh people who come in
monthly don't typically stay as long as
people who come in annually right uh
those
people you know you can't cancel for a
year you keep checking back in as you're
reminded of it even if you don't watch
every week or every video um so you get
reminded of the service that the service
exists you come back you check something
out and over time it sort of becomes
routine and then when it's time to renew
it's like yeah let's keep that going
you've had more time to kind of uh get
invested or get bought in as this part
uh being part of your routine and for a
service like us you get to see the ways
in which we grow and change and expand
over time for the monthly folks doesn't
quite work that way they might decide
well they watch the thing they wanted to
see they'll cancel the next month so
they can save money that's perfectly
fine but what we know know is that the
annual customer is worth more on average
even though they pay us half as much
money we take the average lifespan of a
customer what is the lifetime value the
lifespan of a customer times how much
money they'd pay us the lifetime average
lifetime value LTV another three-letter
initialism conventional wisdom industry
standard you want your CPA Target to be
onethird of the average lifetime value
so if I make 45 bucks lifetime of a
customer I want to spend 15 conventional
wisdom say sure or you could extrapolate
that because our Target would be $25
let's say um that the the average
lifetime value would be $75 or um if our
our Target CPA is $50 you would
extrapolate that our lifetime value must
be50 well then you look at how long does
it take to get that
$150 that's also a right because there's
time value money but there's also how
quick does it come in and hence how
quick can you resend it redeploy it for
more marketing or more building or
whatever right so I might be able to
recognize the revenue this year but if I
don't have the cash until the end of the
year monthly is on paper twice as much
money but annual means I have the money
in my pocket today and I can turn around
and I can spend it right so if you say
average uh the CPA Target $25 and we
pull in from an annual subscriber 30 I
IM immediately have $5 in my pocket and
then $25 to to pay somebody to go get
someone to sign up again yeah so there's
a cyclical nature to it and there's math
the point here is that for me it's the
number uh the the lifetime value of a
customer is really important and that's
a thing that I can say generally
lifetime value is $75 I should spend 25
to acquire a new customer if that is the
math I've settled on and you leave
affordance for VAR things and you've got
room for overhead and whatever but for a
subscription service one3 right so let's
say $25 easy math I know because you use
a tracking link
nebula.com value your average lifetime
value is twice as high should I still
pay $25
right you should more or is it worth
well I mean more but is it worth paying
twice as much if it's still if it takes
twice as long to get the return on the
money probably not twice as much because
you take it takes so long to get right
the revenue to redeploy right but it
does tell me if your if customers who
come in through
you are worth more money even if you
underperform a little bit I can let that
slide because I understand that the
Delta between the total and your value
is different so the way I look at CPA
targets and how well you're hitting them
can be different between you and you
know standard median whatever uh and
we're I'm using handwavy numbers for
Math and I couldn't tell you with a gun
to my head what your numbers look like
for conversions but my point is that
like as a sponsor when you come back or
if I want to work with you again the the
the data the targets that I care about
might change a little bit based on other
factors so while you should be getting
as much conversion data as you can from
the sponsor it's also important to
understand how effective you are for
that sponsor in other ways if you can
get conversion data good if you can get
retention data even better knowing that
that you can pull in uh a thousand
customers at a $25 Target CPA you could
say well I'm worth
$25,000 but that's a General Target CPA
if you know that your retention is twice
as high you can argue for more per
acquisition mhm so generally speaking uh
a
sponsor uh a marketing person at a given
sponsor will have these targets and
there's a
range there's uh all of the different
creators they work with and then they
have the the overall numbers they want
to hit so they're looking at a portfolio
and across all of this
they know that the marketing department
maybe them or somebody else on their
team or their boss has set this is the
goal this is the budget so they're not
even necessarily looking very very uh
specifically at you like you the Creator
as long as they're hitting their target
and making their boss happy like it's
kind of good right right what you don't
want to be is the creator who's so cheap
that it offsets the expensive failure
mhm what you want to be is the person
who has cleaned down the middle okay you
are the best money they spend you nail
the numbers right on the line think of
it like tuning a guitar you don't want
to be sharp you don't want to be flat
you want to be right on the Note okay if
you can be that then they're going to
throw money at you every time because
you're going to help normalize their
numbers I I was going to ask you like
for a sponsor like um say brilliant are
there other factors that would cause
them to keep sponsoring say me at the
same rate like is it just Tom's LTV for
his customers he brings us is higher or
are there like reputational aspects they
look at are there like you know it's a
good look for us to work with this
Creator so this spot didn't do so well
let's let's keep doing it yeah not as
much as we'd like to think okay uh
because there's so much data being
associated with you good mhm but how
good we tend to imagine as YouTubers
that we are celebrities that to this
audience we are famous because we look
at 300,000 views per video and it's like
300,000 people love me
right maybe a few thousand people love
you and the rest just were kind of there
I assume most of them are like falling
asleep right and I just happened to come
on the TV you
were yeah you were a pretty face in a
thumbnail as they were scrolling by you
are not headlining Coachella calm down
not this year yet the and that's not
even a bad thing it's just that we we
look in the sky and we see two Circles
of roughly the same size we must assume
that they are the same size right but
one is the moon and the other is the Sun
and these things are very very very
different and when um I don't know Ben
Affleck is promoting a product versus
when you're promoting a product we could
say that uh Mr BEAST's uh squid game
video got more views than Netflix has
subs subscribers but if you were to go
around asking people which they watch
more Mr Beast or Netflix like Mr Beast
videos are free to watch Netflix you
have to pay there's a difference there
immediately right the uh uh cultural
awareness of this thing and the cultural
awareness of this thing are very
different and it's easy for us to think
as creators as influencers as YouTubers
that because I have this audience this
many people love me this many people
listen to me and therefore you must pay
me because I am a select cele I have the
Staggering star power where when I say
thing just the association is a positive
look for you it can be to that tiny
fraction of audience who's actually your
audience right but what is that really
worth yeah I'm reminded painfully of
this every time I share music I like on
Twitter it be like one like from someone
who already listens to that band yeah
nobody else cares the algorithm doesn't
push it out no no one you know they
don't care what I listen to yeah they're
like shut up even though my music taste
is amazing sure uh but you know I talk
about a new notion feature and
everything goes bananas because my
audience cares about me to a degree but
what they mostly care about is what they
come to me for right like what have I
become representative of in their head
yeah what is The Logical Next Step
somebody sees your Tweet why are they
looking at your Tweet are they in love
with you and they want to know
everything about Tom and you're a
celebrity or do you just post a lot of
like numbered list tweet threads with
productivity tips and they want those
productivity tips and then when you say
something about music they're like I
don't [ __ ] care what you listen to
give me more productivity tips y not
even in a grumpy or entitled way that's
just not what they're there for yeah
it's like uh in the music world like
there's a band they're not your favorite
band but you like a few of their songs
you go to their show when they start
playing a song you don't know you go get
a drink yep that's fine it's part of the
arrangement not everyone who comes to
the show needs to know every word to
every song right yeah so the the um
brand association thing we're not
celebrities so much more dependent on
the data much more there I mean there's
certainly again asterisks on all of this
there are certainly types of creators
who are like the top of a genre or the
top of a field or they're uh they're
associated with a certain kind of thing
I think of like Peter mcon with a cannon
or something Peter mcon with can a
camera or Marquez brownley with uh any
tech product Casey neistat uh there are
creators who are so widely associated
with a certain kind of quality and I
don't mean like production quality but
like uh an aspect a quality to
themselves that that goes beyond
parasocial it goes beyond aspirational
it's kind of its own thing and for those
types of creators yeah uh there might be
having this person 's name uh associated
with you could be a good look MH and
you'll see sometimes Brands will ask
Brands sponsors will'll ask about um can
we get a license to use the sponsor
thing in like can we can we get that
clip and we'll run it as ads elsewhere I
was about to ask like is that a a good
litmus test that you are that kind of
creator that the brand that wants to put
you in ads it's not okay like anything
there's good people and bad people
there's I'd say more often there there
are good people who are doing bad things
without realizing they're bad okay like
there's some industry practices that are
very Sharky that maybe it's not a
person's fault maybe it's a process
problem right so let's assume positive
intent for a second somebody sends you a
contract we're going to pay you $10,000
to sponsor your video and you're like
awesome let's go love the product and
they say cool uh we want it to be 60c
integration we wanted to be at the front
of the video and we want to be able to
you we want a clean cut of just the
sponsored section because we're going to
run that on our socials you might go no
you should say no to that why do they
want at the beginning of the video
that's weird logical Next Step put the
sponsor at the end of the video because
the logical next step after seeing an ad
at the beginning of a video is to hit
the skip button till the video starts
not go by product put it at the end
where the logical next step is to hear
what the person has to say and if it's a
good fit the logical next step is to
listen and then if it's a good product
and the person is interested The Logical
next step is to go purchase you put it
in the middle of the video The Logical
next step is to skip put at the
beginning logical Next Step skip yep I
think that that's an artifact of
sponsors thinking that eyeballs equals
conversions views equals conversions
because they'll they'll say things like
well how much retention is there at the
end of the video yes it's like well
obviously there's going to be less mhm
but the number number of people who
would actually click and purchase is the
same if not higher mhm nobody wants to
leave your video in the middle of your
video to go buy a product and if they do
that's also bad for you are they going
to come back are they going to remember
to finish the video honestly probably
not this is kind of an aside but I I
think of like the jobs to be done
framework a lot and like if you put a
video out there the job for the video to
do is to have people watch it right so
if you immediately put an ad there and
you're telling people click off my video
and go buy this thing like you've
sabotaged the job to be done of your
entire video right away right like
imagine you put on a concert and halfway
through you tell the audience I want you
all to leave right now and go to
7-Eleven and buy a Snickers bar and then
come back and I'll finish the show right
how many people come back yep how many
people leave in the first place probably
not that many people leave and of the of
the ones who do very small percentage
are coming back with the candy bar ready
to rock yep and that's that's what we're
talking about here but when they say and
give us the Clean Cut uh give us give it
let us post that what they want is a
free commercial so breakdown for me like
why that's a bad thing it used to be
that if I had a product or a service and
I wanted to promote it I would have to
go and hire a production company and uh
a marketing team and the marketing
people would put a camp Campaign
together uh a proposal they'd put it in
front of me I'd sign off on it they'd
hire in the production company the
production company hires in or brings in
lighting people camera people Motion
Graphics people editors uh audio people
they would do music clearance they'd
hire actors they'd build sets the whole
thing and we'd make a commercial and
then I would take that commercial and I
would go to TV networks and I would pay
them money to show my commercial so so
we're talking hundreds of thousands if
not millions of dollars just to produce
the commercial and then depending on
when and where and uh whatever um the TV
commercial is shown I have to pay every
single time it's shown to anybody and
that can be tens of thousands to
millions of dollars to have my
commercial shown that's to show that
commercial to an audience of a couple
hundred thousand people maybe a million
maybe a couple million if it's a popular
show
or now I can go to an influencer and I
can give you $110,000 and you'll do all
of it for me an excellent value for meh
no wonder influencer marketing is so
popular it is so much cheaper I can
trick you into producing a free
commercial and then giving me an extreme
discount on airtime to reach the same
number of people I would have reached on
TV except now I have the brand
Association
of being integrated into the TV show
that somebody was watching I'm not I'm
getting product placement I'm getting
Don Draper turning to the Cameron and
saying by the way sign up for skillshare
at the end of Madmen for 10 grand hell
yeah I'm going to do that no wonder it's
effective right uh so when they when
they say I want I want a clean cut or I
want the the rights to be able to run it
on our social what they're saying is
you're going to produce a commercial for
us for pennies and you're going to run
it as basically product placement on
your show where you the main character
in your show are going to look the
audience in the eye and promote this
it's not a commercial anymore that is a
parasocial advertisement right not only
that I'm also going to take your
likeness in perpetuity and run it as a
commercial on my own because you've
produced this commercial for me for
basically nothing I want to milk it
forever am I going to pay you extra for
that no probably not so the first part
of this like this is what we're talking
about running a sponsorship yeah yeah uh
so the the likeness thing is there is
there like a right way to do it should
you always say no should you say like
you get a year and it's an extra five
grand like how do you even negotiate
that kind of thing you definitely want a
time limit on it okay uh for a bunch of
reasons if we were to do this let's say
right now Squarespace came to us and
they wanted you to do this okay let's
say we would want to make
sure that there's a term limit on it
right we don't want it to be that two
years from now there's still ads with
your face promoting Squarespace and
Squarespace has stopped sponsoring you
and that relationship went sour but
they're still using your likeness out
there to promote them and you now don't
get to work with Wix or Shopify because
you've got this weird indorsement deal
with with Squarespace that you don't get
paid for so I've signed away my ability
to work with any other Creator or any
other brand of the space yeah yeah like
your ability to ever work with a
competitor shot that's what they're
really tricking you into they get a free
commercial that they can run whenever
they want and you never get to work with
a competitor M CU why would they want
you to so if we're going to do this
there's got to be a limit on it so we
could say a year okay and that seems
like that's fair right okay you can do
this for a year you pay a little bit
extra done right well I guess I now have
a year where I can't work with right any
of those Brands and Squarespace doesn't
want to sponsor me again I've just given
up 12 months of income in that vertical
yeah so maybe what we should do if if
this were to happen then the move would
be to to put a like a one-year limit on
it and then have them guarantee bookings
across that time gotcha so almost like
an endorsement deal where it's like
right like we're in business let's yeah
we're in business let's be in business
let's not half ass this [ __ ] like let's
actually do it if this is a partnership
and you get to put my face up on your
[ __ ] then like we're in business like
this is a real thing uh what I worry
about whenever I see creators saying
like oh yeah I don't mind it was a
couple extra thousand dollars like I
needed the money it's
like we're poisoning the well for
everybody here aren't we right because
then it becomes an industry Norm right
and YouTubers by and large are people
who are younger and don't have extensive
business experience or contract
negotiation experience so what we end up
with is people who think like well they
showed me a list of other influencers
they worked with and those people all
worked with this brand and they they
didn't complain and they probably did
similar deals sure or I really want this
deal I think it's GNA be great the money
is good just take it yes and now they've
normalized something now they've helped
to set something as uh they they they
continue to set precedent and they
normalize bad behavior and then the next
Creator comes along and somebody like me
says you probably shouldn't do that and
they say why not all of these other
creators do it what what's the problem
mhm like the problem is none of you
should have done it you're all getting
paid less now because you sold
yourselves out right so there something
you just mentioned that I wanted to ask
about for a long time I have a theory on
it I have no proof maybe you do you said
a lot of influencers will go to a
particular brand or a particular agency
and they want to work with that agency
or brand because another influencer has
worked with them so I have this Theory
um as far as I know standard is one of
the only agencies that actually get
conversion data for campaigns weirdly
yeah maybe the only one and it actually
goes and tells the Creator like hey you
drove this many sales and they were
looking for this CPA and that's why your
rate is this um you know most other
agencies don't do that so I've had a
theory for a long time that if you go to
agency X and they're advertising that
hey we work with this big YouTuber over
here that YouTuber is almost like a
magnet for other creators to come in and
so even if that YouTuber doesn't convert
very well or perform very well for their
brand deals it kind of doesn't matter
because the agency can sort of just like
take from the smaller crators that get
attracted to come work with them yeah
we've seen this a ton so back in the day
in the MCN era the multi- Channel
network era where it was lots of
predatory deals where basically as a
Creator you would sign with an MCN and
they would get you a better deal on
AdSense in
exchange they would take a percentage of
your AdSense Revenue so they they might
tell you your AdSense cpms will double
and we take 10% and you might think well
I'll take that deal be part of the thing
uh and they would occasionally show up
and offer you a sponsorship yep and
you're thinking sometimes I even get
brand deals and my AdSense rate is
higher all I have to give them is 10% of
everything forever what a wonderful
value creators kind of figured out along
the way that that's not really how that
works and not a good deal mhm and the
mcns uh because they could just take 10%
of all of the AdSense Revenue they would
sign every channel they could find I
mean it's like a horrible incentive
because they're incentivized to go get
more channels not to help you right and
the they were dumping a lot of their
revenue into the biggest creators
because they would attract smaller
creators in but even worse than that you
you had people abusing the system by
like going out and creating a bunch of
[ __ ] content Farm channels straight
up just ripping copyrighted content and
reposting it uh but because the the
threshold to to get AdSense Revenue was
so low and the rules weren't super
strict you could start a 100 channels
reposting literally just reposting other
people's videos and until you got caught
that AdSense money was flowing in and
you get caught you just start a new one
start the whole cycle over again and so
you've got a bunch of these these
channels out there that are producing no
value but siphoning off off AdSense
money because ads were shown YouTube got
smart and creators got really exhausted
so from YouTube's perspective they said
this is a huge drain on the
psychological benefits to advertisers if
advertisers know that we're putting this
many ads on videos that aren't real
videos or on uh channels that aren't
real channels and are going to be taken
down it's a bad look and Advertiser were
were not super happy they created new
thresholds for how how long before you
could uh be eligible for the YouTube
Partner program the other thing they did
is they said if a channel gets a
copyright strike the MCN gets a
copyright strike so just existential
threat to all the MCN overnight and yeah
and those channels you know if you're an
MCN with 10,000 channels and you're one
of them is getting a copyright strike
every 15 minutes and suddenly like
you've got a three strike you're out
policy you're like [ __ ] you're you're
done in 15 minutes yeah yeah like what
are you going to do so suddenly the MCN
shut all of those channels down the
money stopped flowing in the MCN dry up
to one extent or another that's why
they're not really a thing anymore they
never really added value they were just
a big um parasite and so that's the
reason for the 4,000 watch time hour
rule then too right mhm yeah you have to
have a real channel that is watched by
people over a period of time and and
enough subscribers to indicate that
there might actually be something here
right not a perfect system I've got
plenty of frustrations with it I think
especially for musicians who don't do
highfrequency content but they're making
art or filmmakers and musicians people
who make lowf frequency high quality art
it really sucks that YouTube can put ads
on my movie or on my uh music videos and
they can put ads on those things and
collect that revenue and I will buy
definition never see a penny of it
that's a bummer but uh generally
speaking it's good because it it means
there are fewer of those just content
Farm [ __ ] setups so when we moved
away from that it created a a
psychological Dynamic where creators
felt like the problem with MCN was lock
in you had to sign these contracts you
were locked in so when agencies showed
up they all did the same thing they
would say we're going to bring you a
deal would you like to work with audible
would you like to work with Squarespace
would you like to work with skillshare
we'll set that up for you no contract
needed we we'll do this one
deal and you know we we'll just bring
you stuff sometimes you don't owe us
anything beyond the commission on this
deal and creators thought what a breath
of fresh air no more lockin I know where
this is going though because this was my
first brand deal right right uh so where
this goes is now you've got agencies out
there
who uh will show up and offer you an
audible deal and somebody might come in
and say hey Tom audible wants to work
with you would you like to work with
Audible for
$3,000 and you might think I'd love to
build a relationship with audible that
sounds great let's do it then they go to
audible who they they have audible's
phone number or email address they go to
Audible and they say we got this guy
Thomas Frank he's awesome only $10,000
for the video so Audible doesn't even
know they have no idea they come to me
first yeah and for various reasons
and all kinds of weird behind the-scenes
stuff Audible for a long time God what
am I allowed to say there were people
who were in charge of campaigns for
certain sponsors who
were buddies with people who worked for
sponsor booking agencies like old
buddies and so what they would do is
they'd say yeah we have to fill our
quota for these sponsors like keep
bringing us stuff we'll leave it to you
go find the creators bring them to us
and so agency would say great and they
would flood YouTuber inboxes
with would you would you like to work
with sponsor would you like to work with
Audible for $1,000 would you like to
work with Squarespace for $1,000 they'd
make up num send them out any return
email any
responses well that's you've just
generated a lead and you now take you
now have a product on the hook that you
can take back to the agency representing
these sponsors and sell it to them and
they're like yeah sure let's test all of
these things we'll see what works what
doesn't when you look at as a portfolio
play some will be winners some will be
losers the ones that that performed well
get rebooked the ones that don't perform
well don't get rebooked the problem is
that the Creator you have no idea what
the sponsor has been charged you only
know what you're getting paid so you
don't know what their cut is but more
importantly you don't know what they
were expecting you to perform at right
right so you you come in and say uh yes
to
3000 and then the audible or whatever
spot runs and they see the performance
and they're like now we paid 10 grand
for that it was only worth seven like
we're not rebooking that no thank you
you never get another call even though
you were more than double the value of
what you were paid right because
somebody in the middle charged so much
extra that you weren't worth and had no
responsibility to that relationship
you're now going to get nothing you have
no relationship with the sponsor the
reason the data is so important the
reason the trans uh transparency is so
important is because if you had known
that you were worth seven and if these
people in the middle this agency had a
fiduciary responsibility to you to make
to build and maintain this relationship
as best they can then you would know
what they commission was mhm you would
know what you were worth and then when
performance came back in and they said
it wasn't worth 10 it would be worth
seven these guys come back to you and
say it would have been worth seven you
would know that you're worth seven and
then the next sponsor you talk to and
the next sponsor you talk to you can
take that data and say well I'm worth
this there's no more guessing or trying
to estimate or reading the tea leaves to
figure out what you should charge the
sponsor you would know you would have a
data point of proof you were worth this
much to this sponsor on this date M the
middleman here has all of the
information and has no obligation to you
and really no obligation to the sponsor
except they want to keep bringing good
stuff to the sponsor they're not going
to bring you back you failed so they'll
just churn through more creators right
or they'll come back and and offer you
an absurdly low rate later where they're
taking 50 60% commission they don't
represent you they don't technically
represent the sponsor who do they
represent themselves I guess yeah yeah
yeah no joke so explain to me how lock
in is bad explain to me how a contract
is bad because what you'd get out of a
contract with these guys is definition
of their roles and responsibilities and
you'd get transparency and if you don't
get transparency in the contract don't
sign the contract there's also worse
than that for me so when when this
agency who will will remain unnamed I
guess for me not getting in trouble we
should definitely not say it out loud um
when they came to me they were like hey
audible wants to work with you I think
it was actually three grand or maybe two
uh but the contract you know there's no
agency lock in but the contract says for
six months after this spot runs you
can't work with audible through anyone
else so I'm not locked into the agency
but I can't go work with audible any
other way right and if they don't come
back to me which they didn't I just
don't get to work with Audible and I
remember this this was 2017 VidCon I met
you uh I think I it was like two months
after I had done my audible spot you
couldn't book Audible for me for four
months yeah uh I think it's also
probably prudent to say that like our
commission is 20% across the board
doesn't fluctuate for any Creator it's
just literally 20% yeah I think pretty
common every single Creator signs the
exact same contract it's really
important thing for us yeah 20% is
industry standard M because of the type
of thing that we do for a 360 talent
agent like in the entertainment industry
10% is normal but they're getting 10% of
everything you do and I am starting to
see YouTube managers who take 10% of
everything and I'm like so that's that
includes patreon what are you doing yeah
so like let's break down what are the
pitfalls there if you get somebody who's
just like hey I want to be your manager
I get 10% actually a you was about a
year ago a YouTuber came to me uh not a
good fit for us and I think both sides
we knew that but you know friendly came
to me and said I'm thinking about
signing uh this manager who would be
pretty dedicated to me and it's going to
be really great it's a oneperson shop so
I'd have his full attention it' be a 10%
of everything and I said do not do it
and he's like why not so what is this
person going to do beyond the sponsor
like what 10% of what like how far does
that extend and he said it's 10% of
sponsor bookings so great deal there 10%
of
AdSense go on how are they earning that
um 10% of
patreon all right 10% of potential
Equity deals and I'm like what does that
mean and I pulled that thread and the
example I was given was like if I did
one of these things like spotter or
jelly smack where they give me money to
buy the AdSense value over the next this
period of time uh then then he would get
10% of what they paid me MH and I'm like
you should never do one of those deals
yeah never you there's there's no
situation in which the today money is
going to be worth more than the
accumulation of the AdSense that's a
payday loan for the Creator economy you
should absolutely not do it and now
you've created it a
dynamic where this manager will
absolutely tell you you should yeah
because he's incentivized right he's
going to get more money now MH he
doesn't like oh he cares about your
future for sure but also yep why not get
some money now I mean who knows if
you're even going to still be a YouTuber
in five years let's you know let's stack
the deck here and make sure he should be
this manager should be the angel on your
shoulder in this situation and you're
now creating a scenario where he is only
incentivized to be the devil on your
shoulder kind of a similar situation
some friends of mine recently got
pitched by a copywriter who said I don't
have rates uh just pay me a percentage
of the additional sales I
generate and so he writes this copy and
they're like it's it's awful but it's
like very much built to just juice sales
as hard as possible right now at the
expense of trashing the relationship
with the audience so it's it's a twisted
incentive there because if you agree to
that you're basically incentive iing
them to get as much money of you out of
you right now because they're not
signing on to become a partner long term
they're just you know I get a percentage
of whatever I generate for you over the
life of this campaign so let me trash
the relationship with your audience now
in order to maximize my profit and then
leave and this is a YouTuber yeah uh the
other problem with that is let's say the
video goes massively viral oh this
wasn't for a video this was like it was
a copywriter for for a landing page for
a product they were selling okay well
let's say that they do some other
promotion and again like maybe they do a
sponsorship or something there's the
point is there's a lot of things that
could lead to that page suddenly getting
a big burst that has nothing to do with
the copy and now you're you're
disincentivizing yourself away from
changing anything else MH because if you
change anything else and there's a big
spike well now you're paying this person
for money that they didn't help you earn
uh like what nothing about that makes
any sense yeah so a big role for me uh
both working with managers in terms of
YouTube sponsorships but anything is I
want to work with people who have to
work to earn what they're earning so no
cuts of AdSense no cuts of whatever uh
but additionally who are invested in my
long-term success and want to make it a
partnership there's a video that I point
to all the time Link in the description
probably uh Steve Jobs talking about
consultants and it basically comes down
to the problem with Consultants is the
lack of scar tissue unless you've really
been in it and had ownership of this
thing what you have is a a a thin
perhaps colorful two-dimensional veneer
of what the reality uh and the pain of
building something looks like when you
can say as a strategy consultant or or
whatever that look my clients have have
gone on to do these big big big things
like cool show me the the list of your
clients everyone you've ever worked with
does this group represent 100% of your
client list or one% of your Client List
how long did you work with these people
was it over a period of years or did you
come in and consult for a week and they
were going to succeed with or without
you there's just no way to know in a I
work with these people or these people
have written a nice pull quote for my
website because we're friendly that
doesn't tell me anything I Am Naturally
skeptical on the verge of distrustful of
of Consultants especially in this
business because it is really easy to
sell a younger and less business
experienced crowd of people
who really want to succeed in a Fame
driven influence driven
industry it can be very easy to sell
them the idea that Mr Beast did this
if you just do this you'll get here
right and look at all of these success
stories everywhere you go on YouTube you
can't throw a rock without hitting a
YouTube success story therefore it must
actually be easy if only you knew the
right guy and when somebody like God
bless him Jimmy Mr Beast will will talk
he'll take a call from every one of
these consultants and like pick their
brain right like he wants to learn
everything he can from everybody nom nom
nom he likes to eat of all the
information uh that's kind of what makes
him cool is that he's over over the
years collected uh uh like a managerie
of friends who are uh experienced and
who have done a bunch of things and
he'll he you know he'll he'll have a
conversation with just about anybody but
then when every one of these Consultants
will now say that I've worked with Mr
Beast yeah is he now validating are
people now going to think that his
success was somehow because of them
we've seen people publicly take credit
for Jimmy's success y when we can tell
on the face of it that that's [ __ ]
so the number of people who will uh come
in without any real responsibility to
you the the sharks who don't owe you
anything there's no contract they they
will make their money whether you make
more or not uh the incentive for them is
to get in extract as much value as
possible without burning the
relationship
get out and put you uh on a list on
their website saying I worked with you
that's do you think that's the only
incentive no but if you
are uh if you're out there looking for
people to work with and and who who are
you paying to manage your relationships
and help manage your money how how
comfortable would you feel trusting that
to somebody whose primary incentive is
themselves and to juice the cash today
there's lots of today money out there
you can sell the future of your channel
for a check today absolutely you can
more than ever there's plenty of payday
loan companies that will take the future
of your AdSense which could be worth
millions and give you a $20,000 check
and make you think that it's a good deal
and there are plenty of bigname
influencers who have done deals with
those companies that they'll point to
and say look he did it but you have to
think about what are the incentives does
this person work for me or do they work
for themselves right you made a good
point earlier about
when there's a consultant bragging about
their Client List you don't know if it's
100% of their Client List or or 1% uh
reminded me of a story that is a good
illustration I think very old timey scam
I think it goes back to the 1800s a guy
would take out a thing in a newspaper uh
or he sent letters this is what it was
he'd send letters to you know a thousand
people over here saying hey this Stock's
going to go down and then send letters
to another thousand people and say hey
the Stock's going up uh well then
whichever one is right you now have a
pool of a thousand people who were like
oh he got one prediction right and you
just keep doing that so 500 500 you make
another prediction 250 250 you make
another prediction until eventually you
have a group of say 50 people who are
like dang this guy got the last 10 Stock
predictions right and now you should
listen to him now you send him a you
know now you send him another mailer
saying hey invest with me and I'll grow
your fortune yeah and you know all you
did was just flip a coin 10 times but
you you told this group of 50 people the
right answer AG 10 times and they didn't
know that you were mailing a hundred
times more people than that there's
numbers games you can play there's
obfuscation of reality that you can do
and there's um cold reading like being
able to go in talk to somebody about
where their channel is and if you can
see based on things that this person is
saying that their trajectory is probably
definitely up uh like oh yeah we should
work together here's some things that
you should do and then when those things
work because anything would work you
were going to blow up regardless uh they
look like a genius so I guess we should
be fair and say like these are the
incentives that exist in this area sure
not necessarily that everyone operating
in this area is trying to just burn
through relationships no like I think
there are people who genuinely do care
but you do have a point that the
incentives can easily get twisted yeah I
don't I I wouldn't even uh despite my
skepticism and and uh you and I have
debated this a ton I would not say that
my default position is that these are
bad people who are looking to scam you I
would say that by and large these are
probably good people who think they're
giving good advice and they're
implementing toxic business practices as
a way to grow their stable of creators
and advertise themselves there are
people like you who you really like the
the Twitter format of listicle full of
advice that's a thing you enjoy doing
and you're pretty good at it but you're
giving away advice like you're just
sharing tips and sharing thoughts you're
not really selling anything not really
somebody could funnel down to find your
notion tutorials or like it sets you up
as a subject matter expert or whatever
there's nothing inherently toxic about
it when somebody goes out and there's
like 10 secrets to uh booking uh higher
sponsor rates and I'll read through them
like this is all either dead
obvious completely wrong fabricated in
intentionally or uh fabricated
intentionally to fit some bigger
narrative that pushes people to the next
phase of the
funnel people want to establish
themselves as subject matter experts
because it leads to he and I don't think
it's because they're evil I think that
they believe everything they wrote here
in their book or in their course they
believe everything that they're going to
teach you in their uh their
coaching they believe that stuff but
then the things they do to get you there
in their mind the ends will always be
justified the ends will always justify
the means uh so when they're out there
tweeting and it's like everything's a
funnel everything's a funnel but at no
point along the way is there any real
value but there will be a couple of
people somewhere in there who say oh no
I talked to this guy he made a good
point about this it's like
well cool he made a good point or he's
really nice I spent a ton of time
talking to him good guy but is this
right is this the best way to do this
and what I worry about is if we're
getting all of our information in the
sort of infant stage Salad Days of the
Creator economy if it's all tribal
knowledge if everything we have uh we've
learned from Consultants or coaches um
who may or may not have ever worked with
a successful Creator what are we filling
our heads with what is the tribal
knowledge I've talked to creators who
just among themselves were sharing like
their accumulated knowledge and they
would send me spreadsheets of like
here's here's what we've seen in my
community for what sponsor rate should
be and it was stuff like oh yeah a
sponsor should always pay a $30 CPM and
I'm like what the [ __ ] are you talking
about right you think every view is
equal in value that's insane that's not
a real thing that's never been a real
thing why would you think that and it's
because six or seven people who had an
experience and they triangulated in on
what they thought were the centerpieces
of an experience right and they treated
that as fact yep RIT large you get
creators Again by and large younger
people who don't have a ton of business
experience who are very earnestly trying
to find their way through an industry
that only barely exists and there's not
a ton of great resources yet and there
are many many sharks in the water and
there are many well-intentioned people
who will use Sharky business practices
to sell what they think is a good
product people falling into the Sharky
business practice trap only confirm Ms
for them that what they're doing is
correct we don't have a system we we
don't have regulation we don't have a
system of of governance or uh fact
checking there's no Central bodies that
that can help understand these things
and maybe there shouldn't be but there's
also not as much as I'd like critical
thinking about what are the Dynamics of
this relationship that's why I want to
make this like I don't have anything to
sell around booking sponsorships and I
you know let's call it a bias
call a bias you're to an extent you're
selling me or selling the organization I
am and I was going to get to that okay
like I personally don't have a a course
or I don't do coaching or none of that I
have no desire I want to make notion
tutorials and program all day uh I've
just done this a lot uh my bias is that
I'm a part owner in standard and you run
standard however I do not feel that that
is a compromising bias because I get the
feeling the majority of the people
watching this like you're not trying to
get them as clients right now in fact
I'm probably going to fill your inbox
with a bunch of hopefuls that is is
going to you're going to have to go
through and I'm sorry for that in
advance um but I wanted to put something
out there that was like good information
from someone who was doing it day in and
day out for a roster of clients that you
exclusively represent so you're kind of
on the line for making sure that they
are taking care of long term I wanted
that to exist in the world yeah and I'll
I'll defend my position here uh against
the straw man that we're we're inventing
as being skeptical of us the the the
contract that our creators sign
including you and me you and I have both
signed the exact same contract as
everyone else who is a part of this
organization um I'm a Creator you are a
Creator this is a an organization of
creators uh for creators by creators
Etc flowery language um 100% of the
ownership of standard is creators mhm we
really did build this um every one of
the owners had to sign the same damn
contract yep and all of the contracts
are the same and all the contracts are
good and all of the contracts are on a
30-day rolling basis so now I and my
team of 94 people uh have a Perpetual
incentive to do the best we can at all
times y we need to we are on the hook to
be constantly providing and Demon rating
our value because if not if we don't you
can leave mhm this is an exclusive
relationship and if at any point in this
exclusive relationship you're not
satisfied you can come talk to us about
it you can complain we can work stuff
out or you can go MH and sometimes
people will go for any number of reasons
not very often and when that happens
it's like what can we learn from that
was it a bad relationship fit did could
we have done something better better and
that's just part of life yep if you're
never in a relationship it's hard to
build and if the beginning of every
relationship is a marriage it's hard to
get to the point where you're willing to
do that and so you end up not having
relationships um so this notion of a
sponsor booking agency with no real
responsibility to you I mean no strings
attached sounds nice right except they
have yeah they have no incentive to help
you beyond right getting their
Commission on the last deal yeah and now
there's traditional uh talent agencies
who will do uh influencer marketing
sponsor booking stuff for certain types
of talent uh and those will be like 360
deals that you sign and you're just with
that agency and they'll occasionally
bring you sponsorships and in some cases
even if you get your own you still owe
them a commission which is but you know
it's worth it because you're signed with
that agency and they'll get you all
kinds of stuff they'll get you uh The
Rock will be a guest in your video but
it's I've actually heard I've actually
heard somebody
uh they were told that that if they
signed with this agency The Rock would
appear in their video they said it it
would
happen yeah I'm guessing that didn't
happen it did not happen I had a friend
and again like there's so many names I
want to name but I don't think I can I
had a friend who was approached I think
by an MCN but this was like in 2020 or
something and they were super excited
because this MCN is owned by a giant
media brand like very well-known media
brand so he's like wow you know I am
super in love with a lot of the things
they've made and all this kind of stuff
like I kind of want to join Tom can you
look over the contract for me and so I
look over the contract and I see the the
the MCN is saying like we can help you
get brand deals we can help you uh
collaborate and and do collabs with the
other people who are sign with us we can
do Channel reviews we will give you a
free subscri ion to epidemic
sound which costs $15 per month or
something like that yeah notice I'm
saying can for most of these things so
there's no obligation for them to do any
of this and then on the Creator side the
MCN would literally own any content that
they posted during the per uh during the
term own it so you lose all the rights
to your content it's on your channel
there was also language like we can put
our logo on your Channel's header
or in your thumbnails if we want
to so I'm like you want to sign a
contract where they're going to own your
content they're going to get a cut of
your AdSense guaranteed every month they
get to plaster their logo over your
channel if they want to and they owe you
nothing other than a free music account
which costs less than they will take
from your AdSense every month but they
did save him $15 I guess they saved him
$15 on his epidemic sound account which
is not as good as a car insurance owning
the content that is absurd yeah that it
was the first time I've seen that one we
don't even own the content for nebula
Originals like the the last thing I
would ever want to do is anything where
I own Creator content right that's like
the most toxic and damning thing I can
imagine doing MH if there's any one
thing like I think next in line would be
screwing up Creator money like not
getting somebody paid would be really
bad taking ownership of things they made
without giving them money for it mhm wow
yeah not paid work just like oh I get to
be associated with this brand in
exchange for
Association it's not even exposure it's
just I I can say I'm with them it's like
it's like a mob thing almost I'd like to
break down like what are some of the
criteria that people should keep in mind
when
considering uh whether to sign with an
agency or work with an agency you know
could be exclusive could be
non-exclusive like what should people be
looking for
transparency look for Scar Tissue look
for accountability look for uh the
relationships that they have although
that can be tricky there's there's
certainly agencies out there that are
like clustered up groups of YouTuber
friends where everyone is just kind of
like in the click and then they'll bring
others in and the idea is like if you
sign this deal you get to be part of the
the click and that can be attractive but
like what what are you trading and what
are their obligations uh I would say
look at what they're on the hook for
whatever the agency what are they
promising you not vely not hand wavy we
might what are they actually on the hook
for MH we are on the hook we have an
obligation to make a best effort to put
a sponsor on any video you say you want
to sponsor on we have an obligation to
get you the fairest rate
possible and the way we we account for
that is we negotiate for data we get as
much conversion data as we can from
every sponsor we work with so that we
can say here are the numbers here's what
you're worth if you want us to go in and
ask for more we can we don't have a good
argument for it but we can we can go do
that we have an obligation to help build
and then maintain those relation
relationships so if if things are going
south if things sour we have to be
accountable for that and sometimes they
that's unavoidable but we're always on
the Creator's side if things are tricky
we go to the Creator and it's what do
you want us to do here here's how we
think we should navigate this what do
you want me to do is there is there
somebody are you signing a contract with
somebody you can trust to maintain those
relationships because they are
accountable for the relationships are
you signing a contract contct with
somebody who is going to be transparent
with you about those relationships for
example and this isn't a sales pitch but
like the kind of thing that should be
done uh we get through the the contract
ebits with any sponsor and the Creator
and communication at that point is still
between the Creator and the sponsor we
don't get paid because we know an email
address that you don't right if the only
thing we have is a secret list and we
don't want you to know who this
marketing person is we're not adding
value yep if you're ever thinking to
yourself I could just cut these people
out of the email chain and save the
commission somebody's probably not doing
a spectacular job that's a conversation
you should have similarly when you look
at the the contractual obligations and
responsibilities who signs the deal with
the
sponsor what do you mean like the
Creator signing the deal versus you
signing the deal right so we we had a
conversation with uh somebody from an
agency on clubhouse a couple years back
during that two week period when people
use Clubhouse and um they were it was a
few of us and then somebody from this
other agency and then somebody from a
sponsor and they were talking about how
they and the sponsor had such a great
relationship and uh it say is there
something in the in the phrasing around
like uh We've we've brought them lots of
creators or something or we've something
that sort of like hinted that they were
working for the sponsor and so I teased
that out I'm like wait who do you have
an obligation to in that relationship
like is the deal with the Creator
exclusive do you have a fiduciary
obligation and the answer is well no no
it's non-exclusive like they can still
get brand deals elsewhere too we just
like help manage these relationships I
like okay but like what happens if
something goes wrong in that
relationship oh we make sure that it
doesn't right right right but if it does
is your obligation to back the Creator
and support them or is it to back the
brand and support them and he said well
we'd like to think that we make both
sides happy and it's
like if somebody's getting sued I said
okay who signs the contract does the
Creator sign a contract with you and
then you sign a contract with the
sponsor they oh no no no the Creator
signs the contract with the sponsor I
said do you do you review it for them
and like walk them through what it all
means and they said no the Creator would
be responsible for bringing their own
legal counsel and doing contract review
and it's like and if anything breaks
down in that well it would be between
the Creator and the sponsor
huh so what would you say so what
exactly yeah what what exactly is the
value you're bringing to that
relationship what is like who do you
work for it doesn't sound like you work
for the Creator and does you say you
don't work for the sponsor so who like
to whom do you have a legal
responsibility the line goes dead for
what felt like an hour which I thought
was funny but the the reality is that in
that case there is no responsibility
they signed nothing right they match
made and then took money they introduced
two people to one another and then got a
commission for it mhm nice work if you
can get so they're tender I guess right
right so in in this
scenario the the the pain point the
problem I'm pointing out here is that
the Creator still has to go through the
contract themselves they still have to
do legal review they still have to
understand all of this stuff and I can't
stress this enough creator econom me the
creators largely a group of younger
people who don't have a lot of business
experience don't have a lot of contract
review experience and so suddenly every
brand who comes along is putting a
contract in front of you and you're just
like I want the deals I want the deals
and you sign things bad precedent it's
hard to know what you're signing up for
every time sometimes they sneak stuff in
not because they're evil necessarily
they might be um but it might be that
like just legal put that in because it's
boilerplate for a different kind of
contract and they just reused over here
yep I mean I had a contract with a brand
not for a sponsorship or something else
where it was like we get a license to
any content youve ever made to use
however we want and I'm like not only is
that a bad thing for me but like I
literally can't sign it because there
are other parties who I would violate
their agreements if I were to sign this
yep there's um the stock footage
companies that you had to get licenses
from music companies you had to get
licenses from of course you wouldn't be
able to do that that's insane so if if
you're going to work with somebody whose
job it is to bring you sponsors as your
agency and they're still going to have
you sign the the contract with the the
sponsor what is it you'd say you do here
right what is your role as an agency if
you're not that buffer so I want a
Tinder I can complain to when my date
breaks up with
me and they'll go do something about it
uh what what you want is a shield you
want you want somebody who is managing
the relationship who has skin in the
game for any of our creators they never
sign a deal with the sponsor we do yep
every every insertion order is between
us and the sponsor and then we have
contracts between us and the Creator
where the Creator is on the hook for
certain things like it's stipulated in
the like we expect that you'll uh hand
in um like the the sponsor reads for
review uh two business days before
publishing so that the sponsor has a
chance to do that and then we tell the
sponsors you have two business days to
review this and if you don't then we
just publish yep well they have
expectations of us we have expectations
of you you have expectations of us we
have expectations of them the money
flows this way and if there's anything
that breaks down we are there to make
sure that you still get paid we are
there to make sure that things get
smoothed out because if we don't then
suddenly we don't get paid anymore or if
you run into a problem they can't sue
you because how bad would it be for us
if a bunch of sponsors we work with
start sponsoring a bunch of creators we
work with well I mean we'd have to pick
a side and the side that we would
legally be obligated to pick is the
creator in a world where you start suing
creators working with yeah like if a
sponsor were to say uh you deleted the
video because of
whatever now we're mad right I can say
there's no provision guaranteeing that
the video will be up forever
mhm there a relationship issue there
we're going to have to talk through this
but you you don't get to sue anybody for
it I can say that if I'm in the contract
chain yep if the contract is directly
between the sponsor and the Creator and
the sponsor is grumpy and the Creator
signed a thing they shouldn't have
signed and nobody told them not to and
the Creator says well I absolutely will
not do that and the lawsuit ensues
there's nothing you really can do or
have to do we just go good luck guys
yeah and but you still got your
commission yep so like who did we serve
in this relationship what relationship
did we manage what value did we provide
other than like hey you guys should meet
give me money so I think we can we can
add a very uh hard item to the list
there uh an agency you work with should
represent you yes which means ideally
there's a contract you sign with the
agency that way the agency can be the
one signing the contracts with the
brands for you and then they go to bat
for you if something goes wrong and look
there's there's plenty of of types of
agency relationships where if an actor
is doing a deal with a movie studio they
don't sign a movie contract with their
agent and the agent does with the studio
but that's not what this is we have the
resources we have a legal team our
contracts have all been reviewed and we
have the size and gravity and leverage
to push back MH we should do that
Collective action is a good thing going
in and negotiating your own deal signing
your own contract you're getting the
thing they were willing to hand you
right or you're getting the thing you
were able to negotiate isn't the point
of somebody in the middle that they do
that isn't the point of having an agency
a management agency in this case for
sponsor bookings isn't the whole point
that they sort that stuff out and that
what you're paying for is the leverage
and scale that they bring to the table
to get you a better deal or to get you
better data or to ensure longevity in
the relationship which is how you get
sustainability I I just don't understand
why this isn't the default and I I say
all of this but the truth is that that's
actually really hard to find most
agencies don't work that way in my
experience the other thing I would say
is if you're going to work with an
agency you should work with an agency
that actually represents you and on
paper in the contract has an obligation
to serve you first and foremost versus
the other party in a contract that's
also very very rare most sponsor booking
companies don't sign the creators to a
contract right which is weird it's like
well we were talking about a minute ago
uh it's it's like you're going in to get
a divorce and you and your soon Tobe
ex-wife both have the same lawyer and
they don't actually owe either of you
anything but you're both going to pay
yeah what or it's like um you know
getting a real estate agent and you find
out like the same agent is the seller's
agent right right which can happen and
they have to do a thing and whatever um
but you you wouldn't want that no no
certainly shouldn't like why would you
want your agent to be someone who is
also ostensibly supposed to be trying to
get the best deal for the seller right
so we're going to get a divorce and
we're going to use the same lawyer and
that lawyer don't worry will the way
they're going to get paid is a
percentage of
alimony wait what right that sounds like
a bad deal it's hard to find there's
only uh in my travels there's only a few
agencies who who even operate remotely
like this and I I wish that that weren't
the case but unless and until we see
more Savvy creators pushing agencies for
these things we're not going to get them
we're going to get go and sign with the
agency for brand deals and then if that
eventually doesn't work out people leave
and they just go to the next agency and
they just cycle through which is just a
layer of abstraction above the current
problem of hopping from sponsor to
sponsor y so I don't know kids go and
demand better from your agency anyone
you talk to tell them that you will only
work with them if they do X Y and Z
that's kind of what I'm hoping for here
is like to put out a list of essentially
demands so more and more creators start
asking for exclusive representation
ideally with a clause that lets you
leave in a reasonable period of time if
you don't like the relationship you know
like we have 30 days and puts the agency
on the hook for specific things that
matter to you and where the agency is
focused on on getting you not just as
many dollars today as possible but as
much information today as possible
because that information will lead to
dollars when you understand what the
kpis are when you understand what the
target metrics for the sponsor are and
how well you're doing then the dollars
that's just math that's easy so let's
get into that for a second and and I
want to wrap back around to it a little
later because I do want to talk about
people who want to at least right now
book their own deals there's going to be
a lot of people out there who are like
either don't want an agency or agencies
don't want to work with me yet and I
want to go pitch my own sponsorships
like yada y y there's going to be people
like that uh so I do want to wrap around
to this question for that crowd
eventually but from the agency point of
view how do you go about getting
conversion data from a brand because the
brand obviously knows what their kpis
are but when you the agency go hey we
want to know what your CPA is is so we
can set a fair rate how do you how do
you incentivize them to actually give
you the correct rate say
no so you just say I'm not going to work
with you if you don't share data yeah
and and then how do you ensure you're
getting the actual
CPA uh work with more than one sponsor
okay so it's really like an averaging
thing yeah like you can see if five out
of six sponsors are giving you data that
seems pretty consistent and one is like
oh you're way underperforming unless
that I mean maybe that one sponsor
genuinely it's not performing as well
bad audience fit or something but
chances are they're uh but like the
truth is that if they're willing to
share data they're going to share the
real data okay they're i' I haven't I've
never we've never caught a sponsor lying
in that way not once getting them to
share the data tricky and the only way
we've ever gotten a sponsor to share the
data is by
saying we will work with you if you
share the data so it's just a
contingency or not contingency it's it's
contingent upon mhm yeah uh when we now
when we go into any new sponsor meeting
we let them know this is an open data
relationship we'll give you demographics
data we'll give you retention data
anything you want to know about a video
that you sponsor we're going to share
that data with you let us know we'll
share all the numbers you're going to
share the conversion data we need to
know what your targets are we need to
know where each Creator landed and
because we it works as a portfolio the
the big biger we get the easier it is to
get them to say yes for a couple of
reasons one it's it saves them work
because it's basically what they're
doing we're doing a portion of their job
for them in managing these things um it
helps to balance out the the rates
across the portfolio which is good for
them uh but
also when when you have a large enough
collection of data uh and the the data
sort of normalizes you can see from
month to month what the UPS are what the
Downs are you'll see that yeah this one
was a little bit lower and we can see on
our end the metrics for that particular
video were lower than normal when these
things match up I mean it's it's not
it's not an exact science like anything
you're building a trust relationship and
that trust will be strengthened or
weakened over time we haven't we've
never caught a sponsor lying to us or
showing us things that didn't make sense
it's always we've always been able to
understand the data um but the the big
thing is when you when you have a number
of creators you have l
so we talk about things like action
talking right you look at at uh like the
guilds in Hollywood the writer Guild the
Director's Guild The Screen Actor Guild
the the power that they have is that if
you want to work with writers There are
rules that you have to follow okay as a
writer you can't sign a deal outside of
wga rules M according to negotiated
terms and you can't work in Hollywood as
a writer unless you're in wga you don't
get to be in a movie unless you're sag
right Screen Actor guilded and if you do
things or if you take less money or if
you go outside of what the Sager proof
guidelines are you get in trouble MH so
the studios know that if they do things
that are
untoward uh to a certain group of
writers because they could get away with
it then the big writers will be required
to take action along with the little
ones that is collective action everyone
working together you don't screw one
writer over you're screwing all of the
writers over you're not negotiating one
deal you're negotiating the the the
terms of all deals like this is the the
foundational stuff and you know there
can be additional things for a given
writer or a given project but like
bottom line here are the rules we don't
have that for every one of us there's a
100,000 YouTubers out there m who can do
whatever the hell they want so what do
you do if when you say no like sponsor
can just go to any of them right so much
easier to get data in the first place
when you have 180 creators behind you
and you can say the only way you get to
work with this group of
creators who are demonstrated High
performers is if you play ball right and
we tend to uh there are certain genres
in which like if you want to to sponsor
creators that within that genre it kind
of have to come through us right and so
we put down the thing gabble I don't
know um we we put down our foot and say
Here's the way in which we work and we
don't go in and yell at them and say all
right but you better share data yeah or
we're going to be mad never going to
work with you it's so much simpler than
that they they come in we have a
conversation we explain how we work and
how important the data is how much how
much value that can help to bring them
we're going to help you understand the
portfolio of creators that you're
booking and we're going to help you
understand how those numbers can go up
and down over time it's going to save
you a bunch of time and
effort this is good for you and the
long-term relationship is good for the
creators M uh
and we've hit a point now where more
often than not the answer is like yeah
that sounds great so it's much more like
let's build a partnership yeah and and
if you're going to have a productive
partnership then each side of the
partnership needs to know what's going
on any relationship is a partnership
right ideally in this space uh when
creators collaborate together to make
something that collaboration is a form
of partnership when creators hire people
their team that's a form of partnership
when creators work with an agency that
should be a partnership when creators
work with a sponsor that should be a
partnership if at any point
these relationships are imbalanced and
they fall out of being partnership then
you should look at why that is and
address what needs to change here so
that this can be a partnership because
you can get a sponsor to come in and pay
you more than your worth MH and you will
have a sponsor you will not have a
partner and for some people cycling
through sponsors fine they don't need
Partners those people may eventually get
very frustrated with the lack of new
partners available to them or they may
see that the the landscape underneath
them has changed in the beginning they
were getting overpaid and now two three
years in they're asking for that same
number or inflating it and they're
actually getting underpaid relative to
the value they could have delivered
right if you don't have the data you
don't know I'll add a little bit here on
the Creator's perspective ever since I
started doing brand deals I've always
wanted it to be like a win-win win every
time so like number one has to be win
for the audience MH oh of course yeah
yeah like the audience is is the partner
as well and if it's not a slam dunk for
them you know rage Shadow Legends could
come and say I'm going to give you a
million dollars for a sponsorship and
I'd say no because it's not a win for my
audience like I literally don't care I
have enough faith in myself that I can
make the money I need to make without
selling my audience out and throwing
them under the bus is this sponsor a
logical Next Step but beyond that like
win for the audience win for me because
I'm getting paid my fair rate but it has
to be a win for the brand too
yeah like and I'm a business now too
like I sell products so I'm on the other
side like if I'm going to work with
influencers to help me sell my products
I want them to see the relationship the
exact same way I not want them to be
like oh here's the talking points let me
just read them to the camera check off
the boxes and take my paycheck I want
someone who's going to be like all right
well I am now a marketer for this
product and I'm going to do as good of a
job as I can and that is extended to um
me sending critique on talking points or
me literally like I've redesigned
landing pages for sponsors because I'm
like your landing page is bad yeah
you're not going to get conversions if I
send my audience to this landing page
it's also good for you more conversions
more money yeah so that's I've always
thought as like why wouldn't you want to
give me the data because if you give me
the data it's not like I'm going to you
know be like haha let me take more money
because I'm you know I'm overperforming
it's cool like I should be paid better
if I'm overperforming but if I'm
underperforming give me the data so I
can see what I can improve the next time
around and if I have the data on 10
different spots and I can see these two
did really well well now I know how to
write my ads for all my future videos if
somebody says well I'm only going to
take
$100,000 and you know they they can get
somebody to pay that at at some
frequency they're going to feel like a
winner except if they just started at 50
and built those relationships and learn
from the data then two years later
instead of still getting 100K per they
might be at 200k per yep and then what
does that extend to in the future and
what are those relationships the other
thing and I keep saying this I don't
mean to infantilized but uh YouTubers
tend to be a younger group of people
without a ton of professional experience
it's it's easy when you're in your 20s
to miss the fact that the people that
you're working with today at these
sponsor companies these are people who
are in the Creator economy these are
influencer marketing professionals yep
you are an influencer doing influencer
marketing do you think that this is the
last interaction you'll ever have with
this person exactly do you think that
nobody who you burn Bridges with will
ever be in a position to help you again
you have to build these relationships
because if you think you're still a
YouTuber in 10 years you should probably
rethink how you're playing the game yeah
I mean careers are long I I'm slowly
becoming a programmer the world is much
smaller than you think there are people
I went to school with and I became a
YouTuber and I'm like I can't see how I
would work with this person now but like
now I'm 32 and I'm like oh I might be
able to actually do something with that
person now 10 years into the career I
don't like burning relationships in on
any front
because there's like the process the
role the individual right is this a a
thing
where I'm okay with the process not
working out between us I'm okay with our
roles not being a match I don't want to
do anything where as people you avoid
working with me in the future right uh
I'm not a fan of venture capitalists M
um that like I I don't uh coming from
the software industry I've I've never
wanted to be part of that culture I've
never had a good experience with it and
now I see Venture capitalists doing
stuff in with Creator economy businesses
and it makes me really
itchy however I have friends who I know
from one thing or another who are doing
the Venture Capital thing now and my
responsibility is not to say well you're
awful you're terrible burn or I'll work
with sponsors who are VC backed and I'm
not going to go in and say well because
you're VC backed you must be terrible
right we can set aside these differences
we can have interesting conversations
and we can build stuff or maybe it
doesn't work out and we don't want to
build things but understanding that this
person who's a a VC bro and coming to me
wanting to do thing a today I don't need
to be a jerk to this person MH because
chances are one of the companies they
invest in could do something really
interesting or could want to reach out
to our creators and having a positive
relationship means that person will
probably be more likely to think of me
and say hey let's get some stuff
together with this thing that I'm
working on Yep this actually happens all
the time people that I worked with 10 15
years ago hitting me up because like hey
you're in this space now I'm doing a
thing what do you think of this and then
New Opportunities can be forged out of
that when you go around and every single
sponsor you talk to is you taking a
$100,000 check when you should have
gotten a $50,000 check and all all of
those people are like yeah that was not
worth it right do you want everyone in
town to have the idea the the image that
they have in their head of you is that
you weren't worth it right damn that
will pay off yep just not the way you
want right so win win win like triple
win is what it has to be uh okay so we
talked a lot about the collective
bargaining here and and one point I will
make on the collective bargaining Before
we or I guess collective intelligence
actually uh I talked earlier about how
you know if a sponsor is actually
sharing data and I can see two spots
that did very well that compounds when
you have a collective because we all
talk and maybe one person's like hey I
tried this for this brand and it worked
like Gang Busters I can take that as a
data point and try it myself and maybe
it doubles my rate or something uh
that's useful as well so yeah I I think
that uh talking earlier about
consultants and strategy coaches and
courses and all of this most most of
those
people from what I've seen behind the
scenes and in things they've shown in
public most of what they do is repeat
things that they've heard other people
say either on Twitter or that they they
took a class now they feel like they're
an expert and they want to pass on the
class thing I see a lot of conversations
behind closed doors amongst creators and
the things that they share with one
another and then I see coaches going out
coaches who I know have friends within
that group going out and saying things
that I've heard creators say so I have
to
imagine that what you really want is not
a coach or a consultant what you want is
better friends yes what you want is a
community what you want is to be part of
a group of people who are sharing that
information because these coach people
uh however however lovely they might be
and however altruistic their intentions
may be um the information they're
getting is not like it's not mined from
the Earth's core yeah uh it is it is
forged in experience and that experience
comes from a collection of creators
going through these things and then
sharing that knowledge or it comes from
relationships with the platform where
the people who are you know pulling the
levers and building the machine will
communicate how it works and collecting
the the data and the experience and um
learning the tools over time is a thing
that a Comm Community does MH Even in
our case so much of what we know is
because we are a collection of creators
and when you're a collection of creators
and you all talk to each other that can
lead to tribal knowledge so like check
your work but if you've got a strong
community of creators who have found
success chances are there's going to be
some really interesting nuggets of
information there and the stronger the
community over time the more you'll be
able to like verify that this concept
works like early on one of the things we
learned which is is default practice now
is if a video is underperforming try
changing the thumbnail and we thought in
the early days that the magic was
somehow when you change the thumbnail it
resets the algorithm that's tribal
knowledge [ __ ] we really thought
that I've said that to people the
reality that we know now is when you
change the thumbnail people see a better
thumbnail and they're more likely to
click it yep when you take a second
swing at a thumbnail you're not just
making it different you're probably
making it better you're making a
thumbnail with the knowledge that nobody
click the first one so even if you
weren't going out of your way to make a
better one you're probably still making
a better one of course that's going to
bump it up there's also a huge value in
being part of that Community long term
like we used to believe that you need to
turn AdSense off for sponsorships to
work and that might have actually been
true it definitely was time what we
don't know is when it stopped being true
right so like if you're not part of a
community that's constantly doing the
work then you might get AES of advice
that was true at one given time and then
you just go on thinking it's true
forever yep and in this case maybe you
keep AdSense off forever and you're
throwing money away yeah in the early
days we had plenty of data science
evidence to show that videos with
AdSense on performed uh weaker than
videos with AdSense off what we've since
learned is uh one I think the market
matured but two the tools have matured a
little bit and now what you can do is
you can manually Place ads and you can
make sure that none are placed within 2
minutes of the sponsor read yep because
again logical next step if you get to
where the ad Read's about to start and
an AdSense ad kicks in and then when it
comes back it's into sponsor read nobody
stand around for that I guess there's
like a quotable here like if you're in a
changing meta and you're hanging out
with people who aren't playing the
game you're just going to have old
information uh or you're paying coaches
with the hopes that they're in the
communities for you yeah and hopefully
they're getting updated information and
they're sharing accurate information and
it's it's not you know with an ulterior
motive that's not good for you no and
and there's plenty of really great
resources out there today um following
uh our friend Renee Richie the Creator
liaison I think Creator liaison on
Twitter he's always sharing nuggets and
he works very closely he's he's a
YouTube employee and he's also one of
our creators one of our owners so he is
a person who I've known for well over a
decade I trust the guy with my life and
I know that he has insight into the
YouTube machine that I can't he's in
meeting that I'm not going to be in and
so when he says the thing works like
this I have zero reason to believe that
he's lying to me MH he has no incentive
to lie to me yeah his goal is to try to
share information so when I tell people
go follow Renee and listen to what he
says or uh follow um there's a handful
of accounts I want to put in the
description but like uh following Todd
the guy who runs the algorithm Todd will
definitely be in the description if if
if uh if you want to know how the
YouTube algorithm works I recommend you
follow the guy who's in charge of it and
when he
says when you're concerned about uh Al
like the algorithm doesn't like this or
doesn't like that replace the word
algorithm with the word audience that's
not a handwavy [ __ ] thing he's doing
he's telling you how the Machine
Works you can choose to ignore that at
your own Peril and I've certainly seen
people do that uh or misunderstand what
that means like take it in bad faith but
if you if you take a step back and look
at the resources and collect all the
information and and parse what that
means to you and have conversations with
other creators about what it means to
you what it means to them how do these
things apply to your particular
situation getting context and
perspective outside of yourself and your
channel uh this is how you grow getting
into a group of people who are playing
the game and if you can get a person or
a group of people in that group of yours
who are playing uh a different game with
another part of the industry say like an
agency who are working directly with
Brands and getting actual conversion
data or you're uh at least listening to
if not building relationships with
people who work at YouTube like the the
more your network grows and the more you
get qualified people who are at the top
of their game in your network the better
information you're going to have so
whether or not you sign with an agency
like be building that network of active
players yeah it's it's it would be easy
to say well sure you can say that
because you're a successful creator mhm
of course you
know we weren't born knowledge of who
but but you know what creators love
talking to other
creators you know what creators love
watching YouTube videos every year when
it's not co uh we go to uh Anaheim for
the VidCon thing yep and it's always
like oh I'm going to meet up with so and
so or you go to an event and two people
meet each other you're like oh I love
your videos I watch your stuff all the
time as contemporaries as peers as
colleagues people say this to each other
if like whatever level you're at I mean
if you're getting any views at all if
you've made more than a couple of videos
chances are someone in the room has seen
your stuff reach out to creators yep say
like I really really love your stuff I'd
love to chat I'd love to pick your brain
on something mhm this is not like a
Walled Garden I wish I had known that
early on I think uh might not have been
as true then but certainly now like the
the best and brightest creators I know
are really into talking to other
creators and like building that
Community because the creators who I
would consider best and brightest now uh
from anyone that we work with up through
Jimmy uh one thing they have in common
is they recognize that the small Creator
who wants to chat with you today is g to
be the Creator who's who's lapping you
tomorrow and you're going to wish you'd
made a friend so to sort of wrap this
section up before I go into the next big
thing that I think a lot of people are
going to want to know about uh I had
started building like a list of things
people should look for in agencies you
had said you know buyin are they serving
you uh and I think that's all very
important like are they building this
long-term partnership with you what are
the
markers when you get the pitch like what
are the questions you should ask and we
have already mentioned like you know the
rolling contract what's the
actual commission they take is that the
same for all creators are there any
other things that people should be
specifically looking for are you getting
data from the sponsors do you have a
real relationship with the sponsors what
is the relationship like with your
creators uh what does the contract look
like and can I talk to the folks you
work with now I would I would say to any
creator that we are in talks with uh
whenever they'll mention like oh I know
so and so who works with you and usually
the the the conversation ends with like
next steps we'll send you the contract
Etc and I always say you know ex person
go talk to them whatever they say about
us that's true MH whatever their
experience it's true every word I cosign
and if somebody says I'm you if they
don't know any of our folks but but they
say um like I'd love to chat with this
person or that person I'll reach out to
that Creator and say do you mind if I
make an intro and then it's always like
a add move me to C BCC have an honest
conversation whatever you say goes U
that doesn't happen as much anymore
because all of our creators come in
through creators yeah so there there's
always there's always a a a
pre-selected um uh uh introduction but
the the important part to me is that we
don't work with somebody who hasn't we
wouldn't want to work with anybody where
we wouldn't be comfortable with that
person sharing their experience if
there's anyone we work with who I
wouldn't feel good about them telling
somebody else a story then we need to
fix that first right so if you're going
to go work with if you're going to go
sign with an agency you're thinking
about signing with an agency talk to the
other creators on the roster not just
one or two that the agency Cherry picks
for you to talk to like talk to people
who are like you roughly at your level
roughly your genre see what their
experience is like do you think it's
important for an agency to publish their
entire roster yes okay so there's
another thing the agency should show
everyone they're working with not just a
few magnet creators or something yeah
because if uh if you aren't able to
publish the list of
creators why not mhm is it because you
don't actually have contracts with these
people and you don't have the right to
share a list because they're not
actually your client right uh or is it
because they wouldn't necessarily want
to be associated with you or is it
because you're trying to jealously guard
your client list so nobody can come and
poach them in which case if that's
possible
maybe your relationships aren't that
strong right we have from day one always
published our entire Client List M if
somebody wants to come and try to poach
somebody like come try yep we we'll hear
about it and we'll have to like make a
better offer right if it comes down to
that um I don't know what that would
look like in this case but you know
because everybody get the same contract
but like we would have to re-evaluate
the relationship and how we're
approaching it versus um you're here
because you're not allowed to leave
right so if everyone's allowed to leave
whenever they want to and our list is
public you could come try and poach and
people don't leave why must that be one
would assume that it is because the
relationships are strong enough and if
for anyone we work with that isn't the
case we need to go and fix that we need
to rebuild that relationship and and
adver um strength so uh for a Creator
looking
for I feel like I'm selling
us not what I want to do uh if you're if
you're looking for someone you should
you might want to work with um look at
the strength of their relationships and
look at how resilient those
relationships are designed to be another
one that I would add and I don't know
how you could evaluate this probably
through talking to other creators but uh
make sure the agency will go to bat for
you if say a brand is asking me for too
many revisions or they're like hey has
be in the contract really yeah stuff
that like needs to be in the contract
like will he go B for you and enforce
the contract but also you know if a
brand is doing something that is
uncool are they getting in front of it
are they handling it for you or are they
sort of just stepping aside and being
like figured out and is there enough
relationship there that you can be
flexible on either side there's
certainly been cases where a sponsor has
come back and ask for something and it
was technically outside of scope but it
was early enough or it was a re actually
this is a pretty good idea maybe we
should do this and we'll go to the
Creator and we'll say like
it's probably a good relationship move
and it probably really would help this
thing you don't have to you can say no
but like what do you think like I would
do it what do you want to do and most of
the time the C is like yeah I may as
well just do it y like you know what I I
can add that line no problem it'll take
me two minutes or I can cut that thing
out that's kind of confusing not a
problem at all not about revision uh or
it's not within the revision round thing
it's more of like a side request because
that wasn't part of the talking points
but like oh hey would you mind sometimes
you just do that because it's a nice
thing to do right and if is super rigid
and there's no relationship then you
don't get to like navigate that in the
same way yeah so again it's going back
to the win-win win yeah and you sort of
acting as a partner for the brand yeah
similarly I would say uh we have we have
had creators referred to us by sponsors
sponsors have told creators like you
should go work with those guys it's a
great fit um not not as a matter of
selling us but like that relationship
should be there and it should be strong
enough that like everyone feels good
about it and on the sponsor side there
should be a little bit of tension but
not that much mhm um the other big thing
I would say is look at genre if someone
is a prank video creator or a beauty
vlogger like there's a a ton of genres
of YouTube content that we would not
serve well at all right and sometimes we
get like for whatever reason a week or
two ago I got a bunch of emails from
Minecraft video creators okay it's like
that's not what we do it's not a good
fit best of luck to you they should have
gone and looked for an agency that
specializes with that kind of Creator
because they're going to understand that
kind of relationship and what those
creators will need and the sponsors that
uh would be best suited for those sorts
of creators we serve a collection of
genres expanding over time but you know
you can't can't get everything I think
that's an important point to make like
we have a lot of creators we have a lot
of relationships but we can't have every
relationship and we can't understand
every Niche perfectly right so there's
going to be other players that are going
to serve other niches better MH MH
that's just the way it goes yeah like we
we just can't be everything to everyone
yeah I've I've certainly had
conversations with like
vtubers uh and with with beauty uh uh
creators those are people who like
they're awesome and we have great
conversations but I look at their their
business and it's like I don't know how
to add as much value for you as I could
for somebody who makes Logistics videos
or video essays about movies you're
doing a different thing our machine
isn't built for that so like let's be
friends and keep sharing information cuz
I'd love to learn from you but I don't
want to put you in a position where
we're promising you a thing we can't
deliver gotcha so another big one make
sure that the agency understands your
Niche yeah yeah uh if a Minecraft
Youtuber comes to us I'm just like I
don't know what you are yep well there's
like there's uh like kids content can be
uh animation animation content sort of
verges on the edge of this where when
the primary audience for a channel is
young very young people how does that
audience even respond to a sponsor right
can you get sponsor dollars when your
audience is and like analytics will say
it's all people who are 35 it's like
yeah because their parents YouTube
account they're
30 uh so you can't really trust the data
on that but you you just know right
there's things you can
triangulate how do you how do you serve
that audience yep how do you serve the
Creator for whom Their audience is like
eight years old exactly I don't know I
don't know so people who are
intentionally making content for
children I wouldn't know how to help
that Creator okay so there's a group of
Creator who either they don't want to
sign with an agency or they're not there
yet um I happen to know creators who are
in very uh you know small niches like
how to take care of your pool my friend
Matt runs the biggest pool care channel
on the internet
uh would he be able to sign with an
agency maybe maybe not would he be able
to go and pitch a brand directly who
sells robot pool cleaners on a brand
integration almost certainly yes um so
for that group of people but also maybe
for the group of people who are going to
sign with an agency and um they're
trying to P they're pricing their first
spot like how do you price your first
spot we've talked a little bit about how
you want to air on the side of maybe a
little lower than your worth so you
build a strong first impression and you
can help you know make that relationship
Blossom but how do you even land on what
your rate should be in the first place
erir on the side of not charging too
much not erir on the side of charging
too little if you have to choose between
one or the other then undercharging is
better for a relationship are you
maximizing for today dollars or tomorrow
dollars yeah so to be clear on that I'm
not advocating that anybody get
intentionally underp yeah I don't unell
yourself but if you're like say you're
like I'm not sure if 10K is right like
go for 9 versus 11 but if I'm brand new
to this and I'm like I don't know if I'm
worth 10,000 or 1,000 yeah like what
sort of markers can we look at to set
that initial
pricing bad version terrible metric but
you got to start somewhere
M if you're pulling in about 100,000
views per video and you're not on camera
about $1,000 is not a bad place to start
okay if and everything's a flowchart uh
if you have an audience not the audience
you're not getting 100,000 viral views
per video but you've got like 20% views
from subs and you've got a decent amount
of returning viewers um then yeah sure
like $1,000 per
100,000 why not okay uh if you're on
camera you can probably go higher if
you've got a really attached audience
and a strong Pat on you've been doing
this for a little bit then 100,000 views
might be worth $5,000 it might even be
worth 10 but looking at how strong how
strongly do you believe that the
audience who watches your videos does it
on purpose and how much do you think
those people care about you if you've
got a strong patreon and you're making
money there assume that those people do
care and they're watching you on purpose
okay charge more but as a bottom line
here's a place to start $10 CPA or CPM
is okay it's a [ __ ] number and for
people who don't know CPM is cost per
10,000 views cost per Mill yeah cost per
Mill that's price per 1,000 views uh a
$10 CPM for sponsorships is not the
answer but if you need a lump of clay
that you can shape into the right answer
it's a lump of clay yeah and I guess to
provide people with like
I feel like giving people numbers that
other people had is not necessarily the
best thing because they're going to
Anchor toward it but like with my
channel we eventually got into a rhythm
where my videos would get between 1 and
200,000 views and they were basically
always worth 10 to
12K but I started my first ever
sponsorship was 4K and they wanted a
full integration so I did like a
mid-roll ad and they wanted a video that
was very very tightly uh about skill
acquisition cuz it was skill share and
then the first spot I ever did with you
was 2K for at at the end of the video
you know maybe my my audience was worth
10K per video back then and I took two
but obviously it quickly scaled up and
we we converged on the right rate and
then it stayed there and I had 10 grand
per video four times a month coming in
for like five years yeah uh are you are
you mining or are you farming right
these relationships if you're mining the
relationship
ask for a giant absurd dollar amount
right and I've seen I I mentioned this
earlier but I've seen a community of
creators
where they had one person go in and ask
for
30k on a 1 million view guarantee mhm
and get it and then because that worked
somebody else did the same thing and
they were able to get it and maybe a
third person did it and now it's like
okay well if that worked three
times the answer must be $30 CPM and So
within that Community everyone defaulted
to anytime they would do anything with
the sponsor they would price it at $30
CPM and so they had a spreadsheet with
all of the deals they' done proving that
brand deal should always be $30 CPM
right when all they've proven is the
brand said yes to a $30 CPM three
times yep that's not science okay uh so
if you're if you're a voiceover
Channel and you have 20% views from
subscribers and you're still relatively
new at this $1,000 so a $10 CPM $1,000
for 100k views sure if you're on camera
highly
parasocial um giving lifestyle advice
and you get lots and lots of comments
and engagement you've got a really
strong
patreon ask for more do you think
patreon should be used as a stepping St
to Brand
deals I think that it's a good metric I
will often look at uh if a creator has a
patreon I'll look at how well it's doing
M and if
it's a large dollar amount or a large
number of patrons it's like okay there
might be some there there this is
somebody who can like activate an
audience who cares about them that's
interesting if they have no patreon I
don't know I can't tell you anything or
if they have a patreon where it's like
uh a barely watered plant and there's a
relatively low number of patrons or a
small dollar amount it's like that could
be that they've just not put any effort
into it or it could be that the audience
doesn't love them there's no clear if
this then this then this correct answer
here there just can't be yeah I mean
we're talking about the widest breath of
content in the world and and many
potential different advertisers so
there's there's no real answer here yeah
it's it's like uh how much should dinner
cost right
no other information just how much
should you pay for dinner how much
should how much should a meal cost right
well am I having dinner or is it like
like am I having dinner at 700 am I
having dinner at like 5:00 p.m. like an
old person am I having dinner at
McDonald's or am I having dinner at a
Wolf Gang Puck restaurant right a lot I
don't know and even
from a McDonald's in um New York City
versus a nice restaurant in uh rural
Kansas MH or a McDonald's in rural
Kansas versus a nice restaurant in New
York City these things like location
matters and and there's like a million
factors here you can't there's no one
single answer that can that can explain
it and so I don't want to lead anybody
to believe that that I think that
there's here's what you do a lot of it
is Instinct a lot of it is like you look
at it you kind of feel it up but
ultimately air on the side of
relationship is this somebody that you
want to be working with later right and
if this if it's it's a good sponsor that
you would like to build a relationship
with go in and say I'm willing to bet on
you MH you share information about how
well I perform I'll start low if you
give me that information and if I
overperform we make it up on the next
one I like that a lot so I think that
actually is is the perfect answer uh and
I will ask my follow-up question anyway
but I like the answer being let's start
low we can use your metrics as like the
bare bonus to Frameworks but let's make
a partnership and if I overperform let's
make it up in the next one I love that
and and that's basically what we done
together yeah yeah yeah okay so I wanted
to ask you how do you feel about
affiliate marketing as a way to get data
before you go pitching brands on on
prepaid deals again uh it depends on
genre depends on Creator depends on the
affiliate depends on uh God so many
things but the audience is sad
and they have recognized that there is a
type of sponsor and there's a collection
of sponsors and this means something
seeing Squarespace over and over again
seeing skillshare over and over again
they became a mark of quality I remember
uh I think it was Sarah Zed 100% natural
respect women juice uh the first
sponsorship she ever did was Audible and
there was concern right like there was
there were one or two comments on that
video about like you took a sponsorship
you sold out and there was a moment of
like oh God right but then you look
through all the comments let's just
let's just command f for the word
audible you go through the list and it
was it was like two or three complaints
and then dozens literally dozens like oh
my God you've been sponsored by audible
now you've made it right that's
interesting the audience Associated the
sponsorship with a mark an external Mark
of quality like a band getting signed to
a record label in this new weird Creator
economy there's no governing body so the
external Mark of quality the seal of
approval has to come from somewhere it's
like some of these brands are seals of
approval right if you know in the same
way that the trust relationship is I see
on your videos every time you've always
got a quality sponsor that's relevant to
my interests even if it's not relevant
to me right relevant to your audience
there's always a logical Next Step
component there's always a I believe in
you the sponsorships that you run on
your channel you holding up a mirror
here's how I see you audience and if
that mirror is distorted and I don't
like what I see I can start to mentally
psychologically self- select out right
if you say to your audience I think
you're a person who wants to better
yourself and I'm going to show you
products for people who want to be
better I might think to myself I don't
want that product but I am a person who
wants to better myself if you show me
hey audience I think you're a [ __ ]
rude and you'll buy any [ __ ] thing I
sell you because I got paid I'm going to
think well I'm not a [ __ ] rubbe maybe
this guy's just a sellout prick and
that's going to build over time that
that that trust relationship matters but
it also goes the other way if I'm used
to seeing quality videos that end with a
skillshare ad MH if I'm used to seeing
quality videos that end with a brilliant
ad I know that there's an association
there and I will as much as I'm learning
to trust you the Creator I'm also
learning to trust that brand MH that
brand is is now a mark of quality so
when I see brand I know sponsor I know
Creator I don't it flows the other
direction so if you can get some of that
juice out of the squeeze from an
affiliate deal good that that can be
something but the audience is Savvy
enough to know that that link is going
to be sponsor. tldc Creator name and if
what you put in there is affiliate do
garbage links
robot vomit then make your own redirects
right uh but even then there's there's
markers uh and it's a a sponsor that
nobody has heard of before or it's a
weird product that doesn't do this kind
of marketing and you're just kind of
making up your own read based on
whatever you think might work again the
audience is Savvy they're going to pick
up on a read that is from talking points
that is polished versus a read that is
just somebody making something up
because they want to try to sell you a
vacuum cleaner cuz get the best
Commission on that vacuum cleaner
approach it as if it's something worth
researching mhm uh look for The Logical
Next Step component I don't like
affiliate marketing because it is
infinitely beneficial to the company
with the product but it can be
infinitely beneficial to the Creator as
well yeah there's some definitely over
here and a little bit of maybe over here
it's definitely good for them and it's
maybe good for you and that imbalance I
don't like so I guess there's there like
a context here that I kind of want to
get to which is like is using an
affiliate relationship purely as a way
to kind of gauge like how many
conversions can you get in order to
bring data to sponsors you're
pitching on on prepaid sponsorships is
that worth doing in a similar way to
using patreon because you can literally
see like earnings per click you can see
conversions like in the affiliate world
you know for all its faults one thing
you do get is very transparent data so
if if your goal is or if your scenario
here is before you go and talk to
sponsors you want to collect data so you
go and informed I don't think this is
good information I think you don't think
it's good information I think there's
too many variables here okay and you're
going to end up either uh under or
overperforming for any of a hundred
reasons beyond your control or
understanding at this stage and you're
going to go to sponsor with maybe good
maybe bad data that may or may not be
worse than just going in with a madeup
number I guess that could make sense cuz
like you could have one piece of content
that performs incredibly well for an
affiliate you match well and you go to
the General sponsors like audible or
billion or skillshare and you're like
hey I to pull an example of my own blog
like I have got this blog post that made
a million dollars on
Affiliates can you give me a million
dollars like No And there there's just
so many factors there's so many
variables over here that influencer
marketing person over here is not going
to their world doesn't look like this so
while this might be numbers for product
purchase and those influencers saying
this the campaign is built differently
the landing page would be built
differently uh the relationship overall
is just a different structure so when
you come over here you may have just set
yourself up to misunderstand how this
relationship is going to work if you
can't get this to happen at all and you
want something and you're trying to get
a sense of whether or not you could move
you and do anything interesting or if
you are a good sales Channel and these
people aren't talking to you yet no
matter how hard you try maybe but I
would argue based on the Creator inboxes
I've seen it is really hard to be a
Creator who's getting any numbers at all
who is not getting flooded with sponsors
wanting to talk to you I would agree
with that so my concern the reason I'm I
push back on on uh affiliate deals is
because
there are so many sponsors hungry for
creators and while you might learn
something anyone's guess as to whether
what you're learning is helping or
hurting okay that makes sense like this
is a world where I have a lot of
experience and do make a lot of money on
Affiliates but I think that there's I
think that there's Merit to the fact
that you could definitely misinterpret
data from this side and try to just cart
blanch apply it to this side well your
affiliate data history is from uh websit
initially and then when you do it on
YouTube stuff uh it's a companion to
everything else you're doing so you are
a much more sophisticated animal than
somebody who's just starting out as a
Creator your risk reward system is
different your level of knowledge and
engagement are different and your level
of relationship with different parties
along the chain is different so the
assumption that somebody coming in
fresh uh still green having your level
of sophistication and understanding I
wouldn't give them the same advice I'd
give you that's true I did do Affiliates
for about five years before I ever took
a sponsorship on YouTube so it's and two
years of nothing before that so seven
years of learning a lot before ever
getting into this world and then once I
got into this world like we mentioned
earlier we started with a rate that was
like five times lower than where I ended
up so maybe it's not as useful for for
gauging that it's worth noting because
I'm sure that there's someone somewhere
in the comments who will say this is bad
you started too low this is why this
structure doesn't work or you're
underselling you're telling people to
undersell themselves the thing that we
learned with you and the reason why I
stand by it is we went in with the
objective of build relationship for
longevity and then the rate that we
landed on was so consistent for so
long we don't know let's go back to the
beginning would you have performed at 10
to 12K on spot one
I don't think I would have yeah unless
you're really sure of that based on
everything not just I'm super swell and
people love me but actual what you know
now looking back would you have made
that much money for the sponsor that
you'd be worth this rate yeah I mean
it's tough to know but I don't think so
one one might argue that you could have
burned a bridge here MH and then become
frustrated try again somewhere else and
now our relationship becomes frustrated
because nobody's taking the bait at this
number and eventually things dissolve
and you're out there doing a uh a
sponsor deal on every third or fourth
video instead of on every video because
when we say 10 to 12K per video that was
every week it was every week and it
actually goes further than that so I I
recorded this bit in a voice note to
myself and I want to bring it up back
again um so for skillshare in particular
I believe they were my biggest sponsor I
think so uh and to tell people like I'm
saying were because I I stopped doing
sponsors because I started selling my
own products which happened to perform a
lot better you know turns out audience
fit is very good when you're selling
your own products logical Next Step but
they were my biggest sponsor and I want
to say I made around 400k from
sponsorships from
skillshare through the relationship that
we built with skillshare working with
you I was able to make original courses
on skillshare and and I had a strategic
thought when I went into this I was like
well they put a lot more marketing
effort into their Originals than they do
into anything else wouldn't it be cool
if I was like the face of skillshare on
their homepage or something through
doing that I've earned
600,000 through course sales on
skillshare so literally more than I was
ever paid from sponsorships came as
basically passive income after making
those courses and just putting them on
the platform a secondary benefit to
having invested in the relationship yes
that came out of the relationship I
don't think it would have happened if I
was just like this random guy emailing
them out of the blue being like hey can
you make an original course of
me but we've done this for like uh I
think it was at least a year at that
point when I did the first one yeah it's
the difference between sales and
Business Development mhm there's an
operational component here which is are
you building to maximize Revenue in the
short term or are you are you building
to maximize Revenue in the long term
that that's the easy part to
conceptualize what's harder to to
conceptualize uh I think is the way you
get to option b the way you get to
long-term success to sustainability is
not through number hacking it's through
building a relationship here you're
planting a seed and in planting this
seed you don't know in the beginning
what it's going to grow into MH and
along the way as a as a YouTuber really
any business you've got a couple of
paths but as a YouTuber you can go from
point to point to point to point to
point mining as much as you can from
each of these relationships and if
you're getting returns every time you
take out your Axe and mine at each of
these points it might feel like you are
an expert minor and that you are worth
it and you will always be this
successful because you're that swell and
everybody loves you and you're special
and there's no one else on YouTube who
could do what you do there's no cheaper
version of you that they're going to
eventually get there's no Army of
15-year-olds out there wanting to be you
and who will eventually get there with
more understanding of the Creator
economy more understanding of the tools
as they develop you're just going to be
that great forever and you just keep
mining keep Mining and if you're lucky
it keeps paying out MH there are
certainly people for whom that's true
the other path is at each point along
the way you plant a seed you plant a
seed you plant a seed and the hard part
is that you don't necessarily know what
those seeds are going to grow into but
when you get to here and you look back
at what's grown it's meaningful not
everyone is going to be a Mighty Oak
when you turn around but you start
things start to happen then you get here
and you look back and even more things
start to happen and in this world it's
not necessarily a straight line
sometimes you Circle back and you
revisit some of these points and you get
to collect the fruit right or vegetables
or whatever from the the seeds that
you've planted and then that's what bu
the sustainability and when you put a
dollar value on that in the earliest
days of mining versus the earliest days
of Farming Farming might look smaller
yep it also might not but it might but
it might I I think that too many people
look at this and they think you're a
sucker right because they don't
understand that you're not planting
seeds for Money Trees the seed that
you're planting is not not uh uh fruit
that you can sell it's a relationship
and this person who's here today when
you Circle back this person might not be
here they might be over here working for
a much bigger company with a much bigger
budget and you've built this
relationship with them over years right
and now you can do bigger cooler more
interesting [ __ ] because this person
knows you and trusts you and they get
that you can deliver they understand
your value and you understand theirs and
frankly you understand yours mhm so when
you want to go build something cool and
the person who used to work here is now
heading up the something something
division at this big Media Company you
have an in those are the things that I
think it's easy to miss when
you're young in a career right not young
in age but young in a career or young in
age or both it's still a new industry
and the level of sophistication is
growing and that's cool but it's too
easy to miss the fact that you will get
much more in the long run out of farming
farming is sustainable mining is not
it's interesting to think like this this
whole process of getting brand deals is
actually a relationship building process
that can be a lot more than just getting
10K for a video and it is like you
literally make relationships you make
friends you meet people there are
opportunities that are going to come out
of that look at look at our dots along
the way we built a relationship with one
sponsor yep I mean many but in one
particular case we built a relationship
with a sponsor and then we built our own
little streaming service as a let's have
fun and see what this turns into little
side project and somewhere along the way
it got far enough along that in our
friendly conversations with this sponsor
we said crazy idea what if we did like a
bundle thing and that they're like you
know what that sounds pretty interesting
let's do that let's try it let's just
see what happens do you think we can
make that happen on day one no do you
think we go in with a pitch no this is
like we're sitting around having a
completely different conversation
and the idea happens and that turns
into a bundle deal that lasts years and
now a business of ours making millions
upon Millions upon millions of dollars
for creators and is now one of the
biggest sponsors on YouTube in its own
right you think that could have happened
if we hadn't gone down this path of
building the relationships
nebula is 100% built on relationships in
all directions including the sponsor
relationships including the the platform
relationships if you don't plant those
seeds and then go back and water them
sometimes you don't get stuff like that
so it's much like that that graph you
often see where it's like you know
employment is like linear and then
entrepreneurship can be like this
exponential curve I think we're looking
at the same thing here with what is your
mindset going into building uh
relationships with sponsors like you
said are are you farming then it might
be that small in the beginning but
exponential in in the longterm kind of
and if you're looking at as a minor you
might get more in the beginning but
maybe it's that linear thing or maybe it
just Peters out eventually looking at
creators who I respect and admire who
are like doing things on their own but
you know we have conversations about
numbers and I see them mining they'll
they'll do the thing where they're like
oh yeah I'm up here I'm up here I'm up
here I'm up here and I'm like yeah yeah
that's way better that's way better
that's way better bye and uh it's not
because they're dumb it's not because
they're a bad person it's just they they
took a different approach they optimized
for this part yep um and I I suppose it
is possible if you if you do things
right or if you're fortunate and you get
to build relationships over time you can
do this and then catch that wave of
relationships and I would hope that a
smart Savvy Creator the trouble is that
if you get so much validation from this
it's really hard it's really hard to
justify switching paths yep and we've
we've seen that we've parted ways with
creators who were very much on this
trajectory and thought they always would
be and then they didn't understand why
they couldn't get the sponsor rates that
they felt they were worth yep and that's
okay I've got nothing against those
people they've got nothing against their
approach to to building their own
business that's uh they're all um doing
cool stuff and I wish them the best but
I don't know how to make that
sustainable I don't know how to make
mining sustainable and there's also like
a piece of this is a philosophy to what
I want to create here that I have a very
specific target audience M it's the
Creator who wants to have a long career
and who wants to build Partnerships MH
so like if there's a Creator out there
who's like I just want to get the bag as
much as possible I'm not really making
this for them right I don't really want
to serve them if they change their mind
say that up FR I probably will like
there's going to be a thesis it's like
you know I'm I'm making this this video
for creators who want to build a
sustainable career as a Creator and part
of that is relationships and part of
that is is accepting a little bit less
than maybe you could get right away to
build those long-term
relationships you know you can't serve
everyone with what you say yeah so
that's my filter Farming versus mining
uh it can look like the same amount of
work MH for widely different uh initial
returns I have some lightning round
questions for you go so and that means
we're going to round up we're going to
wrap up soon which is probably
good um but been here for hours we we've
been doing this for a while uh but like
I said I'm make the ultimate guide sorry
what CPA CPM what do those mean and
which should be look which should we be
looking at uh if we're talking about
AdSense CPM sure why not uh cost per
thousand views cost per Mill CPM Mill
being Latin I think for thousand yep
cost per thousand cost per thousand
views uh CPA is cost per
acquisition that's a sale when somebody
clicks through and they sign up for the
thing they have been acquired the
customer relationship now belongs to the
sponsor acquisition cost for acquisition
that is uh they will pay you because
they got paid so that's what we should
really be focusing on that is what the
sponsors focus on okay so I would say
that's what we should focus on all right
um should I give a brand access to my
analytics or screenshots and demographic
info when they ask for it uh yes if they
are yes only if they are willing to
share information with you okay TI for
Tat on that and only share the
information for the video they sponsor
okay you can share Channel my Graphics
like if they say like yeah we'll share
data with you and they ask for stuff up
front like feel free okay like you're
You're Building trust and that's not
keys to the kingdom data um sometimes
that'll be table stakes and sometimes
when you're pushing on how important
data is showing a little bit is is not
the worst way to get the conversation
moving okay but like don't if they if
they sponsor a video but won't give you
any data then like what they yeah right
uh should you ask to be paid upfront
should you ask for a deposit or just
wait for them to pay you at the end and
how how soon should they pay you you
should have a contract with payment
terms okay and they should pay you when
they say they're going to pay you paying
after is normal that's customary it's
very rare for a sponsor to pay before it
publishes for a bunch of reasons um in
terms of accounting I believe you have
to book the
sale uh when you publish the video so if
you publish in June but you don't get
paid until August that's a that's a June
well that depends if you're doing a
cruel versus cash that's the whole thing
but uh we usually get it's like net 30
to you well the reason I I go down that
path is sponsors will invariably be on a
cruel base not on on cash so they don't
care they will pay you as soon as you
invoice but it has to go through their
their their uh accounts payable system
which uh if there's like a net 30 or net
60 it's not because they're trying to
hang on to the money to screw you it's
because that's just how their system
works so make sure you understand what
their payment terms are and then like
you know if you have to send a a polite
letter and then a less polite letter um
and then round three is you CC a
lawyer yeah yeah I've never we've never
had a sponsor not pay us by lawyer round
ad placement we kind of covered this but
pre-roll mid roll always end always the
end logical Next Step how about quick
mention in the early part of the video
uh sure which is great for disclosure
for FTC requirements by saying like blah
blah blah blah blah in this video I'm
going to something something something
uh this video brought to you by the
concept of diapers blah blah blah blah
blah blah blah blah um and then at the
end you talk about how great the diapers
are uh if if that's a good fit for your
video um cool yeah like letting letting
the audience know that this is coming uh
and that this is the sponsor and that's
context that might be interesting for
them um they just like planting the seed
in their head I do that with with videos
where I'm going to pitch my templates
I'll be like you know if you want a done
for you productivity system I have it
more on that later back into the video
we do a lot for nebula spots mostly
because the Creator can say like if you
want to watch this video add free here
the the nebula link is in the
description or whatever because there's
an actual value ad again logical next
step when you hear that you be like oh
click I want to see this that ads or
whatever um right but generally like a
quick mention of the sponsor it happens
so quickly it's not even worth skipping
it's fine I think that's and that's also
a context dependent thing I remember
watching a real life lore video where in
the beginning he's like hey I have a
fulllength companion to this video like
that's the kind of thing that's great to
mention because now the entire video
that the uh viewer is going to watch is
almost an ad for the companion on nebula
but if it's like hey let me just do a
60-second ad for diapers or away
suitcases or whatever it is that just
blocks people from watching the video so
it's like it's different context yeah uh
okay um when you're writing up your
contract how many revisions or like what
what sort of language should you put in
there regarding revisions to your spots
I put a time limit on it more than
number of revisions uh humans only have
the ability to send you so many
revisions in two business days M we've
never had like our our contracts say two
business days so it's just we submit
within two business days they have to
approve or ask for mhm and and you have
basically two business days to figure it
out right because the thing that's not
quite stated there but is is implied and
it all like functionally it works out
fine um but you have two business days
in which to make
revisions we are not the Creator is not
required to do a 100 rounds of revisions
and it takes them as long as it takes
them right so you send back notes on on
the first round the Creator implements
those notes we're done right
yeah and I guess I would add to that uh
when you're getting a brand deal make
sure that they send you a document with
the talking points that way you can say
I followed your talking points here they
are yeah um a big part of why you want
the approval process is so that they
can't come back and say you didn't do
this we're not going to pay you the
approval is there more for you than for
them they think it's for them but it's
more a mechanism for you to say you
approve this which we've actually had
that happen we we had a sponsor uh come
back and say
like the the boss came in and said we
don't like this isn't okay they
shouldn't have done this and we're like
your people approved it it's like they
shouldn't have and I'm like sucks for
you this has happened with me or like
the talking points it it wasn't like I
did a thing that was bad for the brand
but it was like the talking points had
mentioned a certain sale they were doing
I said the sale two weeks later they
come back like we weren't running that
sale you should have got me new talking
points send me the accurate talking
points the instructions uh and while I'm
thinking about that um I will give a tip
when the sponsor gives you your link go
to the link and make sure not make sure
not only that it goes to the right page
check the URL because I have had
multiple times where a sponsor has given
me another Creator's link that goes to
the same landing page and all of the
conversions would have been attributed
to that Creator I've had other times
where they'll send me one of my old
links well you'll see like uh campaign
equals Thomas Frank and period equals no
November 2020 and it's 2022 and I'm like
cool so that's that's just a really old
link and I'm going to get no you know
your data is going to get all messed up
at at the very uh least so just make
sure you check your UTM parameters on
there I think you mentioned that our
contract doesn't have terms on how long
content has to stay up is that something
like as long as it's not in the contract
there is no term or should you specify I
wouldn't okay it's pretty uncommon for
that to even come up now people expect
that YouTube videos are going to stay up
if you're going in after a month and
using the YouTube Editor to cut out the
ad reads that's a real dick move and
people are going to catch on because
like while the bulk of your conversions
are going to come in within the first 72
hours and then one week then one month
Etc after a month you're still getting
conversions especially if you run the
same sponsor repeatedly over a period of
time all of those old videos are still
stacking conversions in your favor today
if you cut go back and cut them all out
your today performance will be weaker so
you're just like weakening the overall
relationship so one kind of a dick move
you shouldn't do that two it'll hurt
your numbers last question this is the
most fun one how do you make more money
from your
sponsorships how you raise your rates
build a better relationship with your
audience okay the only way your sponsor
rate goes up is if the audience is doing
more to signal to the sponsor that it's
working the only way you're going to get
that is by getting a larger audience and
a larger group of people within that
audience who will follow through and
sign up that can be better titles better
thumbnails better storytelling tighter
editing in the first 30 seconds of the
video you should be doing all of those
things anyway um a lot of it is making
sure that when you run a sponsor you're
running a sponsor that speaks well of
how you see the audience when you hold
up that mirror the person in the
audience should feel like you see them
as a smart and intelligent attractive
person who is capable of doing amazing
things and um isn't going to fall for
dumb scams right like if you're out
there selling people nfts then your
audience is probably going to take you
less seriously you want to build a
relationship you want to build your
audience and then build your
relationship with your audience that's
how you get more sponsor dollars how
about some of the Tactical things let me
rephrase it this way uh assuming you
know I've done all this like I'm picking
the right sponsor I've built a great
relationship with my audience what are
some of the
mistakes that we see creators make that
either you know encourage viewers to not
watch the ad or don't pitch the brand
well enough yeah uh giant gaps never
never leave a big Blank Spot before the
sponsor read and never ever say thanks
for watching that is uh it's what we
call permission to leave when you say
thanks for watching really glad for blah
blah blah uh thanks so much to my
patreon supporters for making this video
possible and now I want to tell you
about this video sponsor by the time
you're done saying thanks the audience
is gone right they know that they can
leave now and they do MH not because
they're jerks or because they want to
bail on you and you're not tricking them
into staying by not doing that but when
you say thanks for watching that's the
end the credits have rolled the credits
have rolled get up and leave nobody's
being a jerk here just the lights came
on and the credits are rolling it's time
to get up and go and you can roll the
credits you say well you should stay
look at like the craft Services people
they're really nice so you should see
their names and uh sure you should but
like people don't so when you get
permission to leave people leave if you
give people a good reason to stay
connecting the value of the sponsor to
whatever you're talking about logical
Next Step um then you you make it part
of the content the difference between an
AdSense ad and a sponsor read should not
be one has your face the other doesn't
the difference should be some connection
to whatever the hell it is you're
talking about that doesn't mean you
should fully integrate the ad into the
video every time but when you are on
camera saying this or it's your voice
your persona even if you're getting paid
to do it you're still doing it this is
part of your video it needs to be part
of your video that's the reason it works
so if you're making it an other thing
then the audience will see it as other
thing right and they will bail because
that's they're here for the video this
is other thing make it part of the video
one thing that I'll add to that is I try
to follow the Ada framework when I'm
writing an ad so it's like get their
attention build the interest build
desire enough for them to go take action
and I want to mention that because
definitely what you said like make a
part of the video but some creators will
interpret that as well I should write a
fun song about the sponsor or like I've
seen Jimmy a couple times like uh few
years ago do sponsorships where it's
like the brand barely is the focus of
the ad read it's like here's more of the
video and by the way like this is
sponsored by this and he's gotten much
better at that over the years I think
like if you're going to do a sponsor
read you have to make people care about
the sponsor and you do that by keeping
their attention but then getting them
interested in something they care about
and tying the brand or the product to
that interest which in gender desire and
that gets them to go actually click and
convert yeah yeah uh you want to you
want want to
make clicking on the sponsor link
interesting enough that even if I don't
do it I understand why I would right I
would also say before you mention the
name of the sponsor I the audience
should understand the value of the
sponsor if you say I'd like to thank
skillshare for sponsoring this video
skillshare is an online blah blah blah
blah blah me yeah it doesn't perform
very well if you go in with like uh yeah
these are the the these are the 20 best
ways to what was my example earlier
these are the 20 best ways to uh the 20
tips for creating videos as a side
hustle to earn money and like when I got
started doing this I did all of my own
editing like there's a lot of work here
but it doesn't there's plenty of great
tools out there that can help you along
that Journey you don't even have to like
you don't necessarily have to go to a
fancy video editing school I didn't I
learned how to edit video by watching
tutorial videos like the ones you would
see on skillshare so by the time you
land on the word skillshare I already
get it I already know why I want this or
even better this editing course like I
literally took Ali's Final Cut Pro
editing course or something like that
yeah being able to say being able to
place the value before the name the
audience will at least respect that
there is a purpose to it they understand
the purpose for this sponsor being a
part of this video when you say and I'd
like to think they're never going to get
to the purpose
they just know sponsor and again the
audience is Savvy they know some
creators will like do uh when they start
the segue they'll change the music
underneath so like little psychological
cues to let the audience know that the
thing I did that right uh and that's
fine that's all healthy it's not you're
not tricking somebody you're making a
point by connecting two things yep in
fact I I did the music change uh
specifically to kind of indicate like
this is the sponsor segment cuz I always
wanted to make sure like the content of
the video is useful on its own it does
not depend on the sponsor even if the
sponsor happens to be a great fit for
what I was talking about I think maybe
some of that was like me just being
overly cautious and I would rather be
overly cautious than tarnish my
relationship with the audience of course
and that that's part of the the um
philosophical and and ethical promise to
the audience that builds the trust
you're not tricking them you're not
saying like a thing you want thing you
want haha I tricked you into seeing a
commercial right that's toxic that
poisons the relationship what you want
is a fair and Equitable exchange of
you're still paying attention you knew
there was going to be a sponsor in this
video yep that's you got this video for
free it's in the description probably
mentioned up front right like you knew
this was coming what I'm doing is I'm
ensuring that when we get there you're
not
wondering how this has anything to do
with anything by the time we get there
uh it's like the marshmallow man at the
end of Ghostbusters like if you put that
in the first 10 minutes of the movie it
seems silly right but you start out with
skepticism and there's a stack of books
what's going on and it slowly builds and
by the end you get to marshmallow man
it's like oh yeah sure that makes
sense uh you should treat your sponsor
reads the same way treat your sponsor
reads as marshmallow man yeah by the
time you get to the word the name of the
sponsor it should be like okay I get it
I understand why that's there then
nobody's thinking like oh you jerk you
tricked me in fact the opposite is true
there was a period of time there when
the smooth segue thing was still new
where the audience regarded it like a
magic trick like there's the reveal like
oh you got me I didn't even see that oh
that's so good yep like this is the
smoothest segue I've ever seen they
always misspell segue s g w a y yes they
do uh but yeah they like the the
audience is Savvy they're smart they
understand how this whole machine works
and they want you to succeed that's the
whole point of the parasocial
relationship is that they feel like they
know you they feel like they're on this
journey with you they don't want you to
die of starvation and not make videos
anymore they want you to be wellfed and
successful and happy so you keep making
the videos that they love so much and
they know if they're not paying money
then ads are part of the deal right and
I suppose we should emphasize that we
have six at least years of plentiful
data to show that this is true and this
creates sustainable careers so you will
inevitably get one or two people in the
comments that are like ah whatever I
don't like the segue it was too smooth
or something like that or or they'll be
like oh there's an ad in this I hate you
some people are just going to complain
yeah that's like I don't know that's
having to clean the bathroom it's part
of it's part of your job you're going to
have some people who go into your
bathroom and mess it up uh but you still
get to run your business and you get to
grow it yeah you can try to make
everyone happy all of the time and
you're going to be very frustrated
because it's impossible and you will
will have sacrificed every opportunity
you had to thrive right okay I will
finally let you go oh my God if people
want to follow
you it's like 800 p.m. you don't need
coffee if people want to follow you if
people want to see we started at 5:
where should they go uh all right well
I'll just tell them go watch the NDA
podcast on nebula if you're on nebula
I'm uh if you look me up on on uh nebula
it's it's NDA is the name of my show
where it's kind of like this but um I I
talk a little less uh or there's um my
YouTube channel you can look me up by
name Twitter at
dsus um that's probably good enough cool
all right y'all see you later sign up
for nebula one last little bit of promo
for you if you want to learn how to
actually run your creator business then
you may want to follow up this
conversation by going and taking my
class over on nebula called business 101
for creators this is a class that will
teach you how to structure your creator
business whether to choose an LLC or
different business structure how to deal
with business expenses and taxes how to
get organized and build processes and
even how to start hiring people to scale
your business this class is taught by
you guessed it me and pulls from my over
12 years of running this Creator
business full-time it's an hour of
content there are a ton of useful tips
in there if you are a Creator trying to
scale your business and you can watch it
right now over on nebula using my
special link in the description down
below which will get you nebula access
for just
$2.50 per month a 40 40% discount over
the normal price and as far as streaming
services go a pretty darn good deal if I
do say so myself with nebula access
you're also going to get access to my
new videos from this channel a week
early and without ads you'll get tons of
other exclusive content from lots of
other great creators and you'll be
helping to support not only my work but
the work of independent creators in
general nebula is a Creator run and
creator-owned streaming service it is
the largest of its kind we are working
to redefine what it means for
independent creators to build something
truly amazing and you are really going
to want to stick around for some of the
stuff we have coming down the pipeline
in 2024 so sign up with that link in the
description down below if you do thank
you so much for your support and even if
you don't thank you for sticking around
to the end of this video I know it is a
fantastically long video so thank you
for watching it hopefully you found it
useful and I'll see you in my next
video