Hey, what is going on guys? So, it is
Labor Day as I record this. I just
knocked out a 25 mile bike ride and I
thought it would be a cool idea to
answer some of your questions. So, a few
days ago, I asked for questions over on
Twitter. A lot of you guys responded,
and I'm going to crank through a bunch
of them in this video. Now, if you want
to get your questions answered in future
Q&A videos, cuz I think this might be a
fun thing to do in the future, you can
follow me on Twitter over at Tom
Frankly. So, with that being said, let's
get into the first question. Do you have
any tips on creating a creative yet
productive work area? So, I thought this
might be a good question to start out
with because you might have noticed that
the workstation in the background has
changed a bit since uh maybe two videos
ago. And I'm going to do an updated
workstation video pretty soon, I promise
you guys. But I did want to give you a
few pointers that I have discovered
through my own multiple multiple
workstation iterations. What I found
works really well for me is to create a
balance of having access to all the
things I need to be creative and to get
work done, but to also have everything
that isn't related to my current task at
least out of sight and preferably out of
hand or out of access. What I mean by
that is I have a lot of tools in this
little spinning drawer thing over here.
I've got books behind me. I've got all
my camera gear within easy reach. And I
usually have my overhead shooting setup
over in the other room if my friends
don't need to use the table. But when
I'm working, I also try to shut down all
of my other tabs, all my other apps, and
I put everything away. And I try to keep
the desk as clear as possible. And I
also use a Pomodoro app called Tomite,
which basically keeps me focused on the
task at hand. So remember, a balance
between access to your creative and
productive tools, but also focus and
lack of distraction. How did you decide
to start a YouTube channel? So that's a
bit of an interesting story, actually,
because my channel has been on YouTube
since 2006. And back when my brother and
I created it, we shared it and it was
just a place for us to dump all of our
dumb home videos and ninja fights and
all sorts of really dumb stuff that I've
since pulled off for good reason. But
the reason I started making educational
videos is because I was an educational
blogger in college and then I moved on
to being a podcaster and I realized in
about 2014, middle 2014 I think that I
was watching a lot of YouTube videos and
I was having more fun watching videos
than I was reading blogs. So, naturally,
I thought to myself, why don't I start
making videos as well? And the rest is a
2-year history. Now, if that is not
enough detail for you, I did make an
entire YouTube story video, which
explained my entire journey to becoming
a YouTuber. And you can find that by
clicking the box right there or finding
the link down below the like button. And
that's about 10 minutes of my full high
school story and everything that kind of
led up to this point. When and why did
you decide to become super productive?
So, I like to tell myself that I'm a
naturally productive person. And in
truth, I do get kind of antsy if I
haven't really done much for a while and
if I haven't accomplished anything for,
you know, span of a few days. In fact,
when I travel to places like San Diego
recently, for example, I could only make
it about 4 days before I started working
again. So maybe it's a little bit in my
DNA. That being said, there is one sort
of catalyst from my past that made me
work even harder than I probably would
have worked by default, and that was the
2008 stock market and housing collapse
crisis. You know, alien invasion,
basically. Uh, this was really traumatic
for me basically because I was scheduled
to graduate in 2009. And when this
happened in 2008, there were all these
articles and news reports and people
like talking heads on the TV saying
college graduates of this year are
completely screwed. They're not going to
be able to find a job. And I was scared
by that. And I was even more scared
because there were adults that I knew
personally in my life who got laid off
from their jobs or whose entire
companies went under. And I was thinking
to myself, am I going to go into college
and have to deal with that four years
from now? And I don't want to make it
sound like fear was the only motivator
because I do really have a lot of
passion for what I do. But when that
happened, there was like this switch
flipped in my brain. Like I never want
to have that happen to me. I never want
to be in a situation where an economic
downturn or a company going over or
under or basically anybody just saying,
"Hey, we don't want you anymore." I
never wanted external events like that
to be able to totally throw me out on
the street. So when I went into college,
I had this mindset of I'm going to get
ahead and I'm going to collect as many
skills as I can. I'm going to have a
really versatile skill set so that way
if one thing doesn't work, I can move
right into something else and I'll
always be employable. Now today, I don't
even want to be employed by anybody
else, at least not for the foreseeable
future. But that was at least part of
the motivation for working really,
really hard when I started college. How
do you study efficiently when you're
sleepd deprived? Stop trying to work and
get some sleep. Who do you mean in Super
Smash Brothers 4 and Overwatch? Some of
you guys might hate me for this, but my
main character in Super Smash Brothers 4
has always been Diddy Kong. And yes, I
know he is the top tier character, and
you could just say I'm picking him so I
can win as many matches as possible, but
I really truly did enjoy playing him.
That being said, ever since Bayonetta
got released as a DLC character, she is
my new favorite because her movement,
like the speed and the agility and her
skill set, it's just sick. I love it.
So, I'm going to be practicing with her.
With Overwatch, I do actually make an
attempt to play every single character
other than a few that I just don't like.
And I also spend a lot of time in each
of the four classes, so I can be a very
versatile player. That being said, my
mains right now are Reaper, uh, May,
Junkrat, Zenyatta, and sometimes Winston
if I'm feeling like I want to go tank.
When do you think is the right time to
start applying for scholarships? So,
believe it or not, you can start
applying for scholarships as early as
your freshman year in high school. And
in fact, there are probably private
organizations out there that cater to
even younger people. So, if you are a
future-minded person who is even in
sixth grade or something, you could
start, but I would say that you want to
start getting serious about it when you
are in 11th grade. That gives you two
full years to start making sure your
resume is how you want it to be and lets
you start thinking about clubs and lets
you apply for a decent number of
scholarships. Also, don't stop applying
for scholarships after you graduate from
high school because the majority of the
scholarships I won came after I had
started college. I probably won five or
six scholarships in college and I won
one scholarship in high school. So, keep
applying throughout the entirety of your
educational career. When you're feeling
lazy, how do you personally muster that
last bit of energy and focus on what is
at hand? Okay, so I'm going to share a
few different tips here that really help
me. But please, please listen to me on
this first one because I have learned
through personal experience that no
matter how tired I am, no matter how
much I think the day is wasted, no
matter how much I think this particular
tip is not going to help me, it always
helps at least to some degree. And that
tip is to take a walk and to do it
outside because the sunlight exposure
and a little bit of exercise is really
going to rejuvenate you. And sunlight
actually does help us uh to suppress the
sleep urge which contributes to that
afternoon slump and a lot of those tired
feelings you get when you're studying.
So go for a walk, do it for just 15
minutes, 10 minutes even out, make it
outside and then when you come back,
choose one task, clear off your
workspace and do a pomodoro session.
This is basically a 25minute work
session where you focus only on one
task. You have an external timer either
an egg timer or your phone or the app
that I like to use which is for both Mac
and Windows and is free which is called
to Mighty. And basically this external
timer is going to help you to one put
the task in perspective. It's just 25
minutes of work. You don't have to worry
about finishing it. And number two put
everything else out of your mind. Tell
us everything. All of the knowledge.
Dude, it's like you don't even know that
all the knowledge in the universe
becomes unlocked once you purchase 42
Lamborghinis. I thought everyone knew
that. What is your favorite YouTube
channel besides yours, of course. All
right. Number one, my channel is not my
favorite channel, though I am quite
proud of animations like the one you're
about to see in a second. And number
two, I don't have a favorite channel
because my interests really do change on
a pretty quick basis. So, instead of
giving you a favorite one, which will
change like 2 seconds from now, I'm
going to give you a bunch of them. And
definitely go check these channels out.
Crash Course, Vsauce 3, Linus Tech Tips,
Satchel Drakes, Catacris, Johnron, I
like to make Stuff, Gary Vayner Truck,
The Nerd Rider, Ana Aana, H3H3, Motendu,
Tom Scott, CGP, Grey, Geography Now,
Casey Neistat, Comics Explained, Regular
Car Reviews, Braincraft, Caleb Wic,
Alpha M, The School of Life, Colin Furs,
Youngtown, C Nanners, Smarter Everyday,
Digino Gaming, and Smooth McGroove. How
can you develop discipline instead of
motivation? I think the main
contributing factor for going from
fleeting motivation over to regular and
reliable discipline is the
habitualization of your work. basically
showing up every single day, sitting
down and getting it done without needing
inspiration and doing it on a schedule.
And that is actually the main idea of a
book I've been reading recently called
The War of Art. Now, this is a book
mainly for writers and creative people
and people who feel like they have a
calling in their lives. But I think this
is actually essential read for anyone
who struggles with procrastination. One
of the big concepts in this book is this
idea of going from amateur over to
professional. And I want to share with
you a couple of sentences from the book
about this idea of what a professional
is. I think this particular paragraph in
the professional section sums it up
pretty clearly. Someone once asked
Somerset Mum if he wrote on a schedule
or only when struck by inspiration. I
write only when inspiration strikes, he
replied. Fortunately, it strikes every
morning at 9:00 sharp. That's a pro.
Which is your favorite One Piece arc?
So, I guess this is another confession
time because I only watched about the
first 200 episodes of One Piece before I
gave the show up. Now, I love the show.
I love the characters. I have bought
stuff like One Piece stuff in Japan,
like a ship and a t-shirt. Uh, but
there's just too much. There's like 700
episodes at this point and I had to move
on with my life and I think they pat out
the anime way too much. So, the manga
and the wiki is good enough for me. And
the the films are pretty cool, too. But
that being said, within the first 200
episodes, my favorite arc is Alabasta,
which I have on DVD. And I think I like
this one more than the Skypia arc, just
because the the setting is cooler, and I
think the villains are a bit more
compelling as well. Is there any video
making equipment that you would
recommend? Oh, yes, there is. It's right
here. Okay, just kidding. I'm not Casey
Neistat, though, I do think there is
something to be said for caring way more
about the story and the content than the
gear. if you're a beginning YouTuber or
you're somebody who has any sort of
aspirations and dreams for making video
of any sort because those are way more
important. I mean, take for example
Jenny Nicholson's channel. Now, I think
she literally is filming these things on
a potato, but one of them has over 2
million views and she's funny. Her stuff
is compelling, but I know you guys don't
want to hear just that. So, here are
some quick recommendations if you're a
beginner. Number one, I would start by
filming on a smartphone. This is an
iPhone 6S. This can film in 4K. The
quality is just bananas. It's it's nuts.
So, you don't need to worry too much
about a camera, but audio is much more
important than video for the pleasure of
a viewer. So, this thing has an okay
mic. It's not that great. I'm filming on
a shotgun mic, which is right above me.
But, if you're just starting out, I
would recommend a cheap lav mic like
this one from Royal Voice. And I got
this on Amazon for I think 16 bucks. So,
it's just a wired mic. You can put it
into your phone. And I use an app called
Road Wreck to record my audio
recordings. And I actually tape it to
the inside of my shirt just using
masking tape. And that really helps to
cut down on any wind noise. Now, if you
guys want gear recommendations beyond
that, I'll probably make an updated gear
video about my own setup in the near
future. But until then, you should
definitely go over to my friend Caleb
Wajik's channel and subscribe to him
because he makes excellent videos about
video gear, video techniques, and he's
the guy who taught me a lot of what I
know about how to make good videos.
Favorite fictional books. So, I did make
a video on my top 10 favorite fictional
books a little while ago, and you can
check it out right there because my
picks have not really changed. That
being said, I am currently reading a
book called A Darker Shade of Magic, and
this is highly enjoyable, so I can give
it a recommendation even though I
haven't finished it yet, but I'm getting
there. That about does it for the
questions I'm going to answer in this
video. Hopefully you guys enjoyed this
new Q&A format. And if you did, I would
love it if you went down in the comments
and let me know. And if enough people
did, I'll probably make this an ongoing
Q&A format that I'll sprinkle in with
the regular videos. Also, if you want to
ask me your own questions, something
that you just need to know, you can
follow me over on Twitter, Tom Frankly,
and sometimes periodically I will put
out a tweet asking for questions which I
will pull from for these videos. Also,
if you want to get my free book on
earning better grades, you can click the
link right there and get it delivered
right to your email address. And you can
subscribe to this channel for more tips
on being a more effective student every
single week right down there. If you
missed last week's video, we talked
about a habit that can keep you
motivated and organized all semester.
So, check it out right there. And if you
want to connect with me, send a raven.