when you've got a task that you know you
need to do but you just can't get
yourself to start it you have hit
resistance when we hit resistance we
need to reframe our tasks because
think about what causes us to
procrastinate there are several
different factors the main ones or the
tasks are boring
they're difficult they're frustrating or
they're vague
and if you reframe your task as input
based instead of output based
you can eliminate two of those at least
right off the bat here's an example
let's say you have a paper you need to
write
write a paper is an output based goal if
you reframe that as
work on my paper for 25 minutes you've
gone from output based to input based
and you've done
two things number one you've made the
task less difficult
now instead of writing the entire paper
you just need to work for 25 minutes but
number two
you've made it less vague writing a
paper is a very broad goal
the next action item isn't obvious but
if you refrain that as right for 25
minutes you know exactly what you need
to do
if you want to further strengthen your
motivation use the pomodoro technique
get an actual timer work to that using a
timer creates an external motivator
which is much better keeping you on task
than your own brain is