If you're the kind of student who deals
with a demanding, ambitious schedule,
then it's possible you've experienced
feelings of burnout, especially if
you're watching a video called How to
Deal with Student Burnout. But what
exactly is burnout? Yes, it's a series
of near-perfect arcade racing games that
sucked up large amounts of my time as a
teenager, but it's also a debilitating
state you don't want to find yourself
in. If you're looking for a definition,
David Ballard of the American
Psychological Association defined job
burnout as an extended period of time
where someone experiences exhaustion and
a lack of interest in things resulting
in a decline in their job performance.
Replace job with student and that
definition doesn't lose its accuracy.
But here's a more practical definition.
Everything makes you tired. You don't
care about anything and everything
sucks. Burnout is characterized by near
constant exhaustion, a lack of
motivation in everything, frustration,
cynicism, and a lot of other different
symptoms. It's something that can happen
when you're dealing with large amounts
of stress for a long period of time,
which is something that's sadly all too
common for students. Here's the kicker,
though. Burnout is a state of being that
takes a while to get to. It doesn't
happen overnight. And the good thing
about this is that you can recognize the
signs that are indicative of burnout and
take steps to prevent actual burnout
before it actually happens. The first
step in being able to prevent burnout is
to figure out what exactly causes it.
Now, a 2006 study at the University of
Southern Maine surveyed 354 students to
figure out what the cause of student
burnout is. A small percentage reported
mental or physical issues to be a cause,
and a few others reported that problems
with professors were causing their
burnout. About 13% felt that it was
caused by a lack of personal motivation,
either a lack of interest in their major
or, as they described in the paper, an
overactive social life. A full quarter
of the students surveyed reported
outside issues to be the main cause,
either family or financial issues or
time management problems, mainly caused
by things like part-time jobs. However,
by far the largest cause reported was
assignment overload. A full 49% of the
students who actually reported feelings
of burnout cited an overbearing, overt
taxing course load as the main cause of
the problem. So, now that we know some
of the common causes of student burnout,
we can actually tackle the issue of
preventing it or fixing it if you're
already feeling it. Now, the most
important thing to note here is that
it's essential to recognize the early
signs of burnout if you can and prevent
actual burnout before it happens. You're
going to be much better equipped to
tackle these problems if you're not
hampered by constant exhaustion or the
depressive state that burnout brings.
So, if you feel like you're on the road
to burnout or you're experiencing some
of the symptoms I mentioned before, take
that seriously and take steps to prevent
what they lead to. That being said, even
if you feel like you're past that point
and you're completely burnt out right
now, hopefully some of these tips that
I'm going to round out the video with
can help you out. My first and foremost
tip is learn from that 49%. Don't bite
off more than you can chew with your
course load. A more general way you
could put this is think very carefully
before committing yourself to
overstretching for long periods of time.
Be willing to challenge yourself, but
realize that you do have limitations
just like the rest of us. And if you go
beyond those limitations for too long,
there are consequences. Now, if you've
had a look at my free book on earning
better grades, you'll realize this as a
rewarding of the very first tip in the
first chapter of the book, which is
don't overload the system. And speaking
of the system, my second tip is to make
sure that your system, your brain, and
by extension, your body are in working
order. A lack of sleep, good nutrition,
or exercise can put you in a nonoptimal
state. And when you're in a state like
that, you're less able to deal with the
challenges of your schedule and also
things that can cause burnout. A third
tip is to make sure that you're
organized. I found in my life that if I
feel unorganized, if my task management
systems are full of tasks that I don't
need to do anymore and everything just
seems messy, it causes a lot of undue
stress, which can lead to feelings of
burnout. So, if you're feeling like
this, maybe take a day or a weekend to
clear out your task management systems,
get all that entropy out of there, clean
your room, and make sure that going
forward you feel like your life is
organized. Another tip, and I think this
is a really important one, is to make
sure you're taking breaks. Get away from
your school or work life on a regular
basis and give yourself some time to
relax. Now, as I've talked about in a
previous video, when you're taking
breaks, you want to make sure you're
having high density fun. Don't just go
on Reddit or Facebook and give yourself
like 10 minutes away from your work.
Actually schedule some time to
completely separate yourself from your
work life and find something else you
enjoy. You also want to make sure that
your work or school can't seep into that
break time that it's sacred. As an
entrepreneur, I found that in
particular, my email is something that
can seep into my break time. So, I make
sure my phone has no notifications on
it, and I make sure I only check email
at certain times of the day. That way,
my breaks are actually relaxing. Now,
small breaks should be a regular
occurrence in your schedule. There
should be little ones each day, and then
you should give yourself some time each
week to really unwind. However,
sometimes that alone isn't enough, and
you might need a longer break. Part of
the reason I took my 3-we vacation to
Japan is because I was starting to feel
some of the early signs of burnout.
Making a video and four different
podcast episodes each week was really
starting to be taxing, and I just needed
some time to unwind and not have to
work. Now that I've had that break, my
mind is reset. I'm energized again, and
I'm ready to jump back into making
videos and podcasts. Now, related to
taking breaks, I find that it's useful
to have a hobby or pursuit where you can
feel a sense of progress when you do it.
For me at least, I find that taking
breaks that only consists of consumption
of media like movies or video games,
which is honestly what a lot of people
do, is not enough. So, instead, I think
it's good to take at least some of those
break times to do something that has
some progression to it. My next and
final tip is to simply ask for help. You
don't have to do this alone. And if
you're in college, there's probably
somebody on your campus whose job it is
to help you deal with stress related
issues. Even if there isn't, or maybe
you don't want to, talking to friends or
family about what's causing your stress
can really help you relieve it. So,
that's it for this video. Hopefully,
these tips will help you deal with some
of the feelings of burnout that you may
be feeling. And we will be dealing with
more stress related topics in the future
on this channel. In the meantime, if
you've got other tips for dealing with
burnout that I didn't mention in this
video, feel free to leave them down in
the comments, and I will see you next
week.
Hey guys, thanks so much for watching my
video on dealing with burnout. Now, if
you want to get new videos every single
week on being a more effective student,
then you can click that big red
subscribe button right there. If you
want, you can also get a free copy of my
book on earning better grades by
clicking the book's picture. And if you
want to find links and other resources
that I use to research this video,
you'll find them at the companion blog
post, which you can get to by clicking
the orange logo right there. If you
missed my last video, it was the
conclusion to my accelerated Japanese
learning challenge, and you can click
the thumbnail to watch it. And if you
would like to connect or ask questions
or have ideas for new videos, you can
find me on Twitter, Tom Frankly, or
leave a comment below. Thanks.