so there's this awesome quote from Steve
Jobs that I like to revisit every once
in a while and it goes everything around
you that you call life was made up by
people that were no smarter than you and
you can change it you can influence it
you can build your own things that other
people can use and I wanted to share
that quote with you guys because well
for one it's just an incredibly
insightful quote taken as a whole but
more specific to the topic of this
particular video I think the first half
of that quote can really help you to
build the correct mindset for going into
college we are kind of in the back to
school season right now and I've been
getting a lot of questions via email via
Reddit via Twitter from people who are
justifiably worried about what college
holds they've been told that the
workloads are insane and there's just a
lot of uncertainty and things that they
don't know about and a lot of people
feel like they can't handle what college
is going to dump on them and I want to
tell you that yes you can handle it and
you're going to have a much better
chance of handling it in the best
possible way if you set your mindset
right so let me dispel a myth for you
really quickly there was actually a
survey done of college students recently
that found that 60% of students felt
that they were emotionally unprepared
for college and more than 50% felt that
they were stressed either most or all of
the time and honestly these are worrying
statistics and they're not good and I'm
hoping that the content on this channel
can help in some small way to bring
those numbers down as time goes on but
there is a silver lining to those
statistics and that is the realization
that you are not alone if you are
uncertain or stressed or afraid about
college I'm 25 now I've been out of
college for 3 years and I can tell you
this secret of sorts and that is that
nobody knows what they're doing we're
all basically just making things up as
we go along we're adopting models and
best practices to hopefully get the
outcome we want but nobody knows what
they're doing so the game is basically
to appear to know what you're doing and
to make the best educated guesses that
you can and the people who play that
game best are the ones who constantly
evaluate their choices and the results
of their actions and where they're going
but also the ones who have learned to
react to things and to adopt the correct
attitude and to accept help and to seek
out help when they need it and honestly
college is a huge concentrated ball of
help and resources and people who are
really invested in your success so going
to college with the mindset that you are
going to do as best as you can but also
you're going to adapt to things that you
can't predict right now and honestly
that's good because that's the whole
point of growth and in pursuing New
Opportunities if you knew exactly what
was coming then it wouldn't be
interesting right you're going to
college because you're going to you know
find New Horizons basically and when you
run into something that you can't deal
with on your own be willing to seek out
help college has a ton of help for you
to seek out for one there are academic
advisors there are academic success
centers with tutors you can get uh
hooked up with but number two if you're
living in the dorms get to know your ra
I was actually an ra once uh during my
junior year and let me tell you we went
through intensive and extensive training
to basically be able to answer every
question a student might have in any
area of your life and even if we didn't
know the answer ourselves each of us had
a huge binder in our dorm room with lots
of oncampus resources and at the very
least we would be able to point a
student in the right direction for any
problem so get to know your ra now of
course there is a lot more you can do
Beyond just being willing to accept help
and one of those things is preparing
yourself for everything that college is
going going to throw at you by reading
books and listening to podcasts that
have been made to help you out this is
actually what I did when I was a high
school student I went down to my local
library and I read every single college
prep book they had on the Shelf
including one that I still personally
own which is how to win at College by
Cal Newport and I think this is a great
book I also wrote a book on how to earn
better grades so that might be helpful
and a few weeks ago my friend Martin and
I did an entire podcast series called
the path to college now the first
episode was about how to get into
college the second one was about how to
pay for it but the third one was a much
more holistic look at everything you
need to learn to be able to take on
College it was basically the episode
about becoming College ready so if you
want a lot more detail on this whole
process of becoming College ready you
can click The annotation on the screen
right now or the link down in the
description below uh but hopefully this
particular video just helped to ease
your nerves a little bit if you are
still worried about college and helped
you to set your mindset in a very
positive and productive way now before I
leave you guys I did want to mention one
more thing and that is that we just
launched a new page on College infogeek
called the ultimate College packing
guide so if you're still wondering what
all you should bring to college this is
our attempt at creating a comprehensive
resource that should answer that
question for you and right now it's
totally v1.0 I still have a lot of
different features to add but I wanted
to get it up as early as I possibly
could so you guys could make use of it
so once again cards on the screen if you
want to check it out and there's a link
down in the description below that is
all I've got for this particular video
so hopefully you guys enjoyed it and if
you did you can leave it a like to
support this Channel and if you've got
additional questions be sure to put them
down in the comments below so I can make
future videos tackling those topics also
if you want to get new videos every
single week on being a more effective
student you can click your mouse button
on the big red subscribe button down
there and if you want to get a free copy
of my book on earning better grades you
can click your mouse button on the
picture of the book right over there if
you missed last week's video we talked
about a concept called space repetition
which is a really effective learning
technique so check it out if you missed
it and you can find the full article as
always for this video at the full
article button right there if you want
to connect with me I'm right behind you