in this video we're gonna be answering
the question of why it's so hard to
stick to a workout routine over the long
term and this is a problem that i've
actually struggled with for most of my
life i've always been a pretty active
guy but when it comes to actually
sticking to a workout routine and seeing
progress over the long term i've always
had a problem with it however back in
2020 i actually did start a routine that
i've stuck to for the past two years and
that has come with some results i've
gained about 30 pounds of mostly lean
mass in that time going from around 185
pounds to 215. i've achieved a 300 pound
bench press a 350 pound squat and a 440
pound deadlift and i've managed to
improve my cardio at the same time
mostly thanks to picking up tennis which
is now my favorite sport so today i'm
going to share what i've learned with
you including sharing some of my actual
workout routines within a notion
template of course because hey it's me
and along with that i also want to share
some of the tricks that i've learned for
making sticking to that routine a lot
easier and i want to start by first
breaking down the problem because as i
see it they're really four main sub
problems that make it so hard to stick
to a workout routine for a lot of people
and those problems are number one you
don't know what to do or where to start
number two you aren't seeing any results
when you do stick to the routine number
three there's too much friction involved
and number four you're making it too
easy to fail so let's tackle these one
by one starting fittingly with not
knowing where to start now there is more
fitness advice on the internet than
there are grains of sand on a beach and
no matter what routine you pick it seems
like athlean x is going to be out there
telling you that it's killing your gains
and part of the problem part of what
causes this is that it seems like people
think there are these vastly different
things you need to do depending on what
you want like if you want to gain mass
it requires following a much different
routine than you'd follow if you wanted
to get stronger or if you wanted to lose
weight and while that is true at a
certain level the fact is that most
people and that included me especially
at the start of 2020 aren't at that
level yet and that means a basic
strength training routine with some
added cardio is likely going to help you
improve in nearly every area you want
strength lean body mass cardio even
weight loss which to be honest is more a
function of diet anyway and if you are
at that more advanced level already
where specialization truly is important
you're probably not watching this video
you're probably off watching jeff
nippert instead so for the rest of us i
want to make this as easy as possible
and to do that i'm going to actually
share a couple of the routines that i
have been following over the past couple
of years including my current routine
which does require some gym equipment at
least a power rack and a bench along
with my original lockdown quarantine
workout which needed nothing more than a
single kettlebell like this one right
here and one of those door frame pull-up
bars that costs around 20 or 30 dollars
and what i've actually done is put these
into a notion page that you can find
over at thomasjfrank.com
workoutdb and there i've got each
workout with its exercises it's sets and
it's reps the ones that i actually
followed there are also some sample
weights that i have used so you'll
probably want to adjust these so they're
right for you and lastly i've included
both a video tutorial from strength
coach along with a clip from my own
recordings for every exercise so you
have multiple references for how to do
these and i wanted to share my actual
routines because while there are a ton
of different routines out there tons of
fitness advice literally thousands of
people on the internet giving it out
these are what i have actually done
which is why i feel most comfortable
putting them out there they're what have
actually given me the results that i've
seen and they were also programmed by my
coach who is an expert strength coach
our second sub problem is that a lot of
us deal with not seeing any results and
if you're not seeing any positive
changes then what's the point of putting
in all this effort right well one of the
biggest reasons that a lot of people
don't see any progress is that they're
not recording it see in strength
training and in pretty much every other
skill area as well you make progress by
using a technique called progressive
overload and this is just a fancy way of
saying you push yourself to near your
limit so your body is forced to get
stronger it's an adaptive response but
the problem is a lot of people don't
actually commit to progressive overload
a lot of people just show up at the gym
and decide on the fly what they're gonna
do and for those that actually do show
up with a predetermined routine a lot of
them get stuck following the same
routine with the same numbers for months
without seeing any real gains and the
reason for this is that they're not
recording their progress when they don't
do this if you don't record your
progress then you don't really know what
you're doing or how you're doing and you
can't make intelligent decisions that
are going to help you get stronger so if
you want to see results start recording
your progress now since i work with a
coach i actually use their app the
barbell logic app to do it through my
phone but you can also do it with an old
school trusty notebook as well just
record your sets your reps and your
weight for each exercise maybe time and
distance for things like cardio and then
use that data to push yourself for
example here's my journal for a workout
where i hit three sets of five reps at
275 on the squat so on the next workout
i or actually my coach in this case
bumped that up to 280 pounds for a 3x5
and then 285 on the next one and i will
also note that recording my progress in
this way has caused me to be more
excited to get into the gym because
while changes in my overall body
composition are really slow and take a
long time to notice i can see changes in
my numbers pretty quickly when i'm
recording them and that gets me excited
to see them improve now our third sub
problem here is that there's often too
much friction involved in getting into
the gym or getting started with your
routine and you probably have a lot of
days where you feel like this or you
feel like you're just too busy to work
out or you just can't fit into your
schedule i know i do and that's why it's
crucial to do anything you can to reduce
that friction this is actually why i
built a garage gym recently it's at home
so there's very little preventing me
from just getting out there and getting
my routine done the commute has been
eliminated so it's not a potential
source of an excuse now you don't have
to build a home gym like i did just to
reduce friction because smaller changes
can help as well like for example laying
out your gym clothes and packing your
bag before you go to bed so it's already
the moment you wake up also keep in mind
the actual problem you're trying to
solve here because in the beginning what
you're really trying to do is build and
stick to an exercise routine so if
you're feeling like there's just too
much friction right now because your
routine is too long or too difficult
just remember that doing something is
better than doing nothing at all case in
point my best friend martin doesn't like
going to gyms and he wanted something
dead simple to start with because he
hadn't really exercised at all in quite
a while so back in december he literally
started just running in place in his
apartment and to keep things a little
bit exciting he put on these videos from
a youtube channel called virtual run tv
to make it a little bit less boring but
that's it and crucially he started out
running for just three minutes a day i
got you for three minutes now that
doesn't sound like a whole lot but it
helped him build the habit and as of
today he's been doing this for 45 days
in a row and is up to running for about
23 minutes at a time so his endurance
has improved quite a bit finally our
last sub problem here is that it's
probably too easy for you to fail ask
yourself what happens if you decide to
push a workout off until the next day or
you skip it all together well if you're
like most people the answer is probably
nothing other than the fact that you
don't make any progress from that
workout and that's a problem if you want
to more reliably stick to your routine
you need to make it somewhat harder to
fail which means that you need to
introduce some accountability into the
mix and this is actually probably the
number one reason why i've been able to
make so much progress over the last
couple of years i have people in my life
that hold me accountable to my workout
routine now the primary source of that
accountability is my lifting coach matt
who actually coaches me remotely i've
got to journal my sets and my reps and
then i actually film the final set of
each exercise and the next morning i get
a forum critique on that video and
updated programming for the next workout
but the most important thing i get is
the knowledge that he's actually
expecting me to turn in my workout log
now in addition to my coach i do have
one other big source of accountability
in my life and that is the activity
sharing feature on my apple watch which
i use to share my exercise data with a
few different friends and who do the
same with me and this actually brings in
a different dimension of accountability
and support as we typically don't hound
each other when we don't do a workout
but we do send each other emojis and
other support when we do complete our
workouts and that's something that i
feel doesn't actually get talked about
as much in the realms of habits and
productivity it's useful to not only
have accountability to know that
somebody's going to hold your feet to
the fire but also to have positive
encouragement from people who care about
you as well those positive messages can
really keep you going so if you can find
a way to get both of those by enlisting
other people that's going to help you
really stick to your routine you can
work with a coach like i do but there
are other methods as well like getting a
workout partner using the apple watch
thing or maybe even using the social
features in an app like habitica to
party up with other people and track
habits together if you want to learn
even more about how you can build strong
habits in any area of your life i also
have a full one hour class on habit
formation over on skillshare who have
sponsored this video this class will
teach you how to take any goal you have
to find it more clearly and then break
it down into actionable habits that you
can work on every single day you'll also
learn how to stick to those habits over
the long term by using external
accountability systems by anticipating
and dealing with pain points ahead of
time and by gracefully dealing with
failure so it doesn't completely derail
you and because my class is on
skillshare you're also going to get
access to thousands of other classes
that can help you learn new skills and
really make 2022 a year of personal
growth for yourself for instance one of
my favorite creators mkbhd has a class
on skillshare about how to craft great
youtube videos from start to finish and
you're also going to find classes on
illustration personal finance and even
how to grow your social media presence
skillshare is completely ad free they've
got new premium classes that are added
every single week and the best part is
that if you're one of the first 1 000
people to use mylink and sign up you're
even going to get a free one month trial
which means that you can take my class
and all my other classes completely for
free during that first month so to get
started use that link in the description
down below or click right there to sign
up and start learning and support my
channel you can also check out one of
these videos right here and i will
especially recommend this one on the
five levels of self-discipline which is
a great follow-up to this video thanks
as always for watching hit that like
button for yield algorithm and i will
see you in the next one