about a week ago an acquaintance of mine
named Tom Scott put out a video called
why you should write down your goals and
in that video he recounted a failed
marketing stunt SL experiment put on by
the British television network ITV where
they asked people to publicly commit to
goals and those goals were then etched
on to monuments and these monuments were
placed all around the UK in lots of
historic places and they were really
excited about punctuating the new
millennium with this project but after
just a couple years the television
network actually scrapped it because
well nobody cared about it and it didn't
make any money the point of Tom's Video
though was the financial failure of this
Monument project didn't stop it from
doing some good because as Recent
research has pointed out the simple Act
of writing down your goals really does
help you become more likely to achieve
them so itv's project despite its
failure most likely did benefit the
people who committed to those goals or
did it see these people didn't just
write down their goals privately they
publicly stated them and had someone
etch them onto a monument for all to see
and therein lies the problem they told
someone or rather several thousand some
ones on National Television what their
goals were and it turns out that telling
people about your goals actually does
you more harm than good now maybe this
is confusing to you after all
accountability and stuff right won't
telling my friend about my goal to run a
marathon make me accountable to them
well in one word nope unfortunately
that's usually not how it works here's
the thing most of your friends won't
care enough to actually keep you
accountable they'll patch you on the
back they'll give you some
congratulations on your goal but most of
them are too busy dealing with their own
lives to break into your house at 4:00
a.m. with a boom box playing Eye of the
Tiger unless you're me more importantly
announcing your goal widens your
intention Behavior gap which is the
disconnect between knowing you should do
something and actually doing it now
psychologists have been studying the
intention Behavior Gap since the 1920s
and what they've learned is basically we
humans we like to dream a lot we've got
tons and tons of Dreams aspirations
goals and Fantasies and we're usually
smart enough to know what the first step
is in order to achieving that goal
unfortunately we often have trouble
actually taking that first step to say
nothing of continuing on to the next
ones being aware of this fact in 200 a
group of researchers at NYU decided to
study how the intention Behavior Gap was
affected by people telling others about
their goals and across four different
experiments they had people first state
a goal and then they gave them 45
minutes to work on it for each of these
experiments the people were divided into
two different groups the first group
announced their goal to the room before
starting work while the second group
kept their mouth shut and here's what
happened the group that said nothing
tended to work for the entire 45 minutes
on average and when asked about their
progress they were pretty realistic they
tended to say that they still had a lot
more to do before they'd be done by
contrast the people who announced their
goals quit after only 33 minutes of work
on average and when they were asked
about their progress they were a lot
more confident and tended to say they
were pretty close to completion even
though they weren't these latter groups
made so much less real progress because
announcing their goal gave them a fake
sense of accomplishment see when you
announce your goal to somebody and they
affirm it you feel good you almost feel
like you've actually taken a step
towards achieving that goal and that
gives you some small sense of
satisfaction this is called a social
reality the a formation of your goal by
somebody whose respect you desire
actually makes you feel like you're
closer to achieving it even though in
reality you haven't done anything now I
first heard about this study in a TED
Talk given by the entrepreneur Derek
cers who I have massive amounts of
respect for and after presenting the
research findings in the talk here was
his advice you should resist the
temptation to announce your goal delay
the gratification that the social
acknowledgement brings and understand
that your mind mistakes the talking for
the doing now as a general principle I
totally agree with this and I think that
we should heed it for the most part I
don't think that it disproves the
usefulness of accountability Partners
but I do think that it highlights the
importance that if you're going to get
one and tell them your goal you should
make sure it's somebody who will
actually keep you accountable also it
helps to frame your goal in terms of the
work you need to put in rather than the
identity that you want to assume so
instead of saying I want to run a
marathon which paints you as a cool
tough marathon runner just say I'm going
to run an hour a day that's work you
have to put in and it's much easier for
them to keep you accountable for it that
being said the main conclusion of Tom's
Video is still completely valid I
defitely think that you should write
down your goals and now that you
finished watching this video go give
that one a watch it's a good one you can
also check out dereck's original Ted
Talk which I've embedded in the blog
post for this video and if you want to
read that you can click the orange
button right there if you want to get
new tips on being a more effective
student every single week you can click
that big red subscribe button down below
and I wrote an entire book on how to
earn better grades so if you want a free
copy sent to your email click the
picture of the book last week's video
was all about how I use my calendar so
check it out if you missed it and if
you'd like to connect I'm on Instagram
and Twitter at tomf frankley or you can
leave a comment down below thanks for
watching