sleep is really really important and
unfortunately we just don't get enough
of it and I think one of the reasons for
that is that our lives are increasingly
dependent on Tim taes and schedules and
things that tend to start early in the
day at a specific time which makes us
subject Our Lives to the tyranny of evil
alarm clocks unfortunately we don't use
these same alarm clocks to tell us when
to go to bed often so for a lot of us
getting to bed on time to get adequate
sleep is tough I know I've had this
problem and if you're watching this
video you probably have that problem as
well but this is not a pity party this
is not an empathy video this is a
solution video and today I'm hoping I
can give you some tips for building the
habit of getting to bed on time and thus
getting adequate sleep but before I can
get into those tips we do have to answer
the question what time should you go to
bed well everyone has individually
different sleep needs but we can use two
main pieces of information to establish
a kind of Baseline rule here number one
according to the National sleep
Foundation people between the ages of 18
and 25 want to get between 7 to 9 hours
hours of sleep a night on average also
we know that when you're sleeping your
brain goes through multiple iterations
of What's called the Sleep Cycle it
starts off at a higher level of brain
activity then kind of comes down to a
really low level for a while before
shooting up into a very high level of
activity called rem or rapid eye
movement now in a perfect Ideal World
where every alarm clock had long since
been smashed to tiny tiny pieces you
would naturally wake up at the end of
one of these sleep cycles and these
sleep cycles take on average about 90
minutes but when you're using an alarm
clock you run the risk of waking up in
the middle middle of one which is going
to make you feel like a truck hit you so
you want to try to time when you fall
asleep to wake up at the end of one of
these sleep cycles and if you want to
make this really really easy head on
over to a website called Sleepy ti.me
where you can input when you need to
wake up and it'll give you some times
where you should aim to fall asleep now
keep in mind that the average adult
takes about 14 minutes to fall asleep
after the lights go out so pick the
window that works for you add about 15
minutes to it and that should be your
established bedtime and the key word
there is established you really want to
pre-commit to going to bed at this time
instead of just being real casual about
it a lot of people just go to bed when
they feel tired which would work in a
perfect Ideal World Without those alarm
clocks but it doesn't really work in the
modern world and the reason for that
well to explain that we're going to have
to get into some science basically your
sleep is regulated by two biological
mechanisms one is called the sleep wake
homeostatic process and this works kind
of sort of like an internal timer it
basically records when you slept last
how long you slept and then it creates
this internal desire to sleep which
increases in intensity as time goes on
and this process is complemented by
What's called the circadian clock which
is a mechanism that basically syncs your
biological uh processes with the day
night cycle basically keeps you awake
and active during the day and wanting to
sleep at night unfortunately in the
modern world we have a lot of artificial
light that we expose ourselves to and
this can actually uh dampen the
secretion of a hormone in the brain
called melatonin which makes you feel
tired so when you're up at night staring
at screens and having all these bright
lights on you your brain thinks
basically that it's daytime and you
don't feel tired until it's too late so
number one tip here if you're getting up
at a specific time then go to bed at
that pre-established bedtime you've set
for yourself and I found that when you
stick to this and you do it for a while
it actually becomes a habit and your
body responds in kind it'll start
feeling tired when it's supposed to now
the main impediment to progress in
building this habit is the fact that we
tend to do stuff that's really highly
mentally active late at night whether
it's homework or Netflix or video games
or whatever it is we tend to do stuff
that causes us to push our bed times off
further and further which is why I think
one of the most important things you can
do to increase your chances of going to
bed on time is to create what I like to
call a windown ritual basically a
sequence of activities that sort of
bring down your brain activity calm you
relax you and get your brain into the
context of knowing that the day is about
over and it's time to start going to bed
now you can structure your windown
ritual in a number of ways a lot of
people like to get ready for bed early
brush their teeth have a shower a lot of
people like to do some light reading or
journaling or maybe even have a cup of
tea and meditate you can basically do
whatever you want but I have a few tips
for making it as effective as it can
possibly be number one have an alarm for
it have something on your watch or your
phone that tells you hey bro it's time
to start winding down it's time to stop
playing video games or finish up the
episode on of TV you're on or stop
working and start winding down number
two you're building a habit just like
with any other there are certain things
you can do to increase your success in
building that habit and one of those is
to track your progress so use a tool
like habitica or coach.me or even use
something like Excel or a journal to
record the time that you start your
routine and the time when you go to bed
so you've got data and you can actually
see your progress and that will in turn
increase the likelihood that it'll
become a strong habit finally I think
the first step to your windown routine
should be to stop using the internet for
the day either turn off your computer or
maybe use a Chrome extension like stay
focused to set a time where your
internet access gets shut off because I
know that personally the internet is the
worst offender among the host of
distractions that can keep me pushing my
bedtime off it's so easy to say oh it'll
only take 30 seconds to check this email
or 30 seconds to look at this stat thing
and then an hour's gone by so the
internet has to go so now we've got a
set bedtime we've got the windown ritual
and we're building that as intelligently
as possible and there's one last tip I
wanted to share with you which comes
from the author Gretchen Rubin who wrote
The Happiness Project and also the book
better than before and she says remind
yourself how great it feels to wake up
naturally before the alarm goes off
without that sickening jolt into
wakefulness then when you're surfing the
internet at 11:30 p.m. ask yourself am I
making a good tradeoff I really like
this tip because it's all about pausing
and deliberately doing the cost benefit
analysis and asking yourself is the goal
I want a little bit later more important
than the thing I can get right now
because remember as humans we're wired
to Discount the value of future rewards
and increase the value of what we can
get now but I think the value of waking
up and feeling well rested is a little
bit more important than being able to
check one more Facebook post and if if
you tell yourself that deliberately I
think you're going to get your brain to
agree as well so that is what I've got
for you today in terms of tips on
getting to bed on time hopefully you
found them helpful and I do know that
this is only one part of the equation
once you've actually gotten into bed you
do need to fall asleep and I know most
of us have a pretty easy time of that
but I know some people don't so in a
future video I'm going to have some
extra tips on falling asleep on time and
getting better quality sleep before I go
I wanted to update you on my reading
progress because in the video I did a
couple of weeks ago on how to read more
books I told you I was committing to
read 25 Pages a day without fail for at
least the next 3 months and I can tell
you that now it is 19 days into the
challenge and I have done it and so far
I've read 472 Pages which is awesome for
me I've never read that much non-fiction
before on a consistent basis and I
picked books that had a lot of like
crazy science in them they were pretty
dense and I'm finding that as I've built
this habit as I'm doing it every single
day my mind is more easily able to slip
into a flow State it's more easily able
to stay focused and not get distracted
or bored so there's definitely a lot of
Merit in building a daily reading habit
Beyond just the accumulation of pages
and to give you a bit of an update on
the books I've been reading I did finish
the first book that I chose to read
which was spark the Revolutionary new
science of exercise and the brain and
let me tell you I loved this book I knew
exercise was really important before it
but I never knew how it affected all the
parts of the brain and solves a lot of
the different problems our brains can
have and I like this book so much that I
actually invited the author Dr John Rady
onto my podcast and the episode with him
will be coming out in a couple of weeks
so subscribe to the podcast if you
haven't and keep your eyes peeled for
that one I actually finished that book
when I was out in Colorado and of course
I had to stop at multiple different
bookstores when I was in Boulder and
Denver and when I was at the boulder one
I picked up a book called good calories
bad calories by uh Gary TOS now I've
heard this is one of like the best
nutrition books out there and I wanted
to really dig into the science of
nutrition so I've started reading this
one it's very dense it's very very
detailed and I'm about halfway through
so far it's pretty good and while I'm
not tracking fiction I did want to tell
you guys about the fiction book I'm
reading because I got my hands on an
early copy of a book written by a good
friend of mine it's called Uh Mr
Fahrenheit which was actually written by
my good friend T Michael Martin who you
may be familiar with if you happen to
watch the channel how to adult and if
you don't you should definitely go check
it out and subscribe it's an awesome
Channel but yeah Mike is in addition to
being a YouTuber he's a fiction author
in fact I had him on my podcast recently
about how to become a published author
get your work on bookshelves so check
that out if you're curious but this book
has been really cool so far I'm really
excited to finish it but it's basically
kind of like super eight mixed with that
movie Chronicle mixed with like Friday
Night Lights the basic premise is these
four high school students accidentally
shoot down an alien spaceship and then
smartly decide to try not to tell anyone
about it so fun things happen from there
but I'm really enjoying it so far and if
you want to check it out I've got a link
down in the description where you can
pre-order it because it comes out on
April 19th it's not out yet which why I
have this super secret uncorrected proof
copy and uh Mike's also doing some cool
giveaways and pre-order bonuses and I've
got a video that he has made explaining
all that stuff down in the description
as well hopefully you enjoyed this video
overall and found it useful and if you
did and you want to support this channel
you can give it a like and also if you
want to get new tips on being a more
effective student every single week you
can click that big red subscribe button
down below if you want to get even more
study tips I wrote an entire book on how
to improve your grades and it is free so
if you want to get a copy click the
picture of the book and I will send you
one last week I was actually out in
Boulder Colorado with my girlfriend
hiking and I decided to make a fun
little Vlog about it so if you'd like to
be entertained hopefully then you can
check it out right there and if you want
to find the full article for this video
along with extra tips and resources you
can click the full article button right
there lastly if you want to connect with
me I'm on Twitter and Instagram at tomf
frankley or you can leave a comment down
below thanks for watching