so there is a lot of advice floating
around on the Internet
and not all of it is good so what we're
gonna do today is get away from the
productivity tips and the
self-improvement advice that I think is
actually good and should be implemented
into your life and talk about three
pieces of advice that I took very
seriously in some cases tried to follow
for quite a long period of time before
realizing that they were ultimately bad
advice or at least I interpreted them in
a bad way and ended up doing something
more destructive than positive in my
life and we're just gonna jump into it
with one that I get emailed about all
the time which is the comment saying
that you are the product of the five
people you spend the most time around
now on the surface there isn't a whole
lot to object to with this quotation or
this aphorism whatever it is you want to
call it because we are influenced by the
people we spend the most time around
it's obvious people are the products of
their friends their family the people
that they tend to hang out with or at
least they're very much influenced by
those people but where they start going
down the wrong path I think is when they
take that piece of advice and they draw
the conclusion that if I'm an ambitious
person if I have a lot of goals if I'm
really high energy and I want to be
successful then I have to ditch everyone
in my life who doesn't operate in the
same way that I do if I'm friends with
somebody but they're a little bit more
chill or they don't want to be working
24/7 I need to stop being friends with
those people immediately and go find new
friends who are gonna be a lot more
ambitious and I really don't like this
piece of advice because it leads people
to think these things and in fact when I
was younger and I think more foolish I
thought this as well now luckily I
didn't end up following through with it
and actually ditching my friends but
there were times when I was thinking to
myself man maybe I need to go find a
different friend group because I seem to
be interested in different things I seem
to be wanting to work on my
entrepreneurial projects all the time
while my friends kind of don't do the
same thing and what I realized later on
is that you don't have to be on the same
ambition 'el wavelength as your friends
to be friends with them because
friendships are separate from your work
and your goals and ambitions but what
you do need make sure you are doing is
spending some of your time surround
yourself with people who do build you up
and who do motivate you and encourage
you and challenge you so a better way to
put this and the way that I would prefer
it be communicated to people in the
future is don't worry about the time
breakdown
don't try to list out the five people
you hang out with most often and then
rank them and give them qualities
because number one friendships don't
have to be based on having the exact
same ambitions or even the same level of
ambition you can be friends with
somebody just because you like them and
enjoy spending time with them but make
sure you are spending time with people
who do challenge you so a practical
example this would be if you're in
college and hanging out with your
friends in the dorms playing video games
playing board games whatever it is also
make sure that you have some time during
the week that you go and participate in
a club or you go to networking events
just do something where you are
regularly exposed to people who do
challenge you and this could be really
simple it could even be a once a week
mastermind group through Skype or
discord or any other online chat
platform just make sure you get that
regular exposure and when you go about
it in this way you're also not ditching
people who quite honestly probably need
you remember that if you're an ambitious
person if you have a lot of goals if
you're kind of going somewhere in life
where you feel that you are then you're
probably an inspiration and a source of
motivation and strength for somebody
else and if we all took this literally
if we all said I have to be around the
five people who are most inspiring or
gonna challenge me than most we would
all only look upwards we would be
constantly ignoring the people who
probably need us and trying to chase
people who we think we need and instead
we should be thinking in both directions
we should be pursuing relationships with
people who do challenge us and who we
can learn from but we should also make
sure that we keep cultivating
relationships with people who we can
help alright the second piece of advice
that I want to talk about here is simple
be everywhere and again this is another
one that on the surface seems like a
really good piece of advice especially
if you want to get your name out into
the world now when I heard this piece of
advice it was in the context of how to
build a successful blog how to build a
successful online following and again it
seems like a really good piece of advice
because if you are everywhere if you're
on LinkedIn and Twitter and Facebook and
YouTube and commenting other blogs and
all kinds of stuff then there are so
many different opportunities
nice for people to find out who you are
but again it's the way in which you
interpret this advice that really makes
the difference in the way that I
interpreted it was actually destructive
because I took be everywhere as a call
for me to be active on every platform
all the time so I was on LinkedIn and I
was writing articles on LinkedIn that
was commenting on other people's
articles I was on Twitter and I had a
habit in my habit tracker at one point
to tweet five articles a day and a
certain amount of quotes per day I had
Facebook pages I was even on app net for
a while and probably nobody watching
this video even remembers what app dot
net was because it died a pretty quick
death so I would say that looking back
on my career the points at which I made
the most progress were the ones where I
failed to be everywhere there were the
times when I got one idea in my head one
piece of content that I wanted to make
one article one video and I ignored
everything else for a period of days
sometimes even weeks to make one great
thing now there is a quote that I do
want to share here which I'm going to
edit a little bit to remove an expletive
but the quote goes self promotion if you
don't like it stay in your basement you
do have to self promote you do have to
put your work out there but I think you
need to take a majority of your time and
use it to focus on creating something
that is really worth paying attention to
or honing your skills so you are in the
top 10% or 5% of people in your field
once you've done that then you can take
the little bit of time that's left over
and use it on self-promotion and you can
be everywhere to a certain extent you
can have a presence on all these
platforms but if you're splitting your
time up into little chunks every single
day trying to be active on all these
platforms you don't have any time left
over to do something that's worth
sharing so focus on that first
and speaking of focus that brings us to
our third and final piece of bad advice
which is the common advice to focus on
your strengths and ignore your
weaknesses
now again just as with the first two
pieces of advice we talked about here
this is something that can be
interpreted in a positive way if you
know what your strengths are but the
problem is we give this advice to people
who are often very early in their
careers or sometimes to kids and when
you're a kid or when you're a teenager
or when you're early in your career
often haven't put it in enough work to
know what's actually a weakness and
what's just something that you haven't
put enough effort into something that
you're just in the dip right now and you
haven't kind of come out of that initial
area of difficulty that almost nobody
makes it out of so for example a lot of
people in the world say I'm bad at math
or I'm bad at learning languages or I'm
just not cut out to play music that's
just a weakness of mine and that third
one is a big one for me I went a lot of
my life saying that I'm just not cut out
for music I don't have it in me to be a
musician I should go and do something
else and I've learned in recent years
that that isn't the case at all I just
hadn't put in the work to become a
somewhat decent musician and now that I
have I realize that no music is actually
a strength I have like this
pretty nice improvisational talent that
allows me to play music that's pretty
decent at least to my ears it just took
me a while to develop that skill so I
think a better way to go about this is
to follow your interests if you're
interested in something be it speaking
Japanese or learning calculus or
learning high-level statistics or
playing the guitar or the piano put
ample time into the practice of whatever
that thing is
now you may realize down the line that
yes this is a weakness of mine I'm
trying to play basketball and I'm just
not tall enough to dunk the ball okay
maybe that's a weakness but I think more
times than not you are going to discover
that what you thought was a weakness was
just something that is inherently
difficult to learn for a lot of
different people and that just requires
more work now on that note of following
your interests one common objection to
this might be that I don't know what my
interests are or I don't have an
interest that's compelling enough to
really follow right now and if that's
the case for you then you might want to
go expose yourself to new information so
you can develop new interests and there
are plenty different ways to do that he
can go browse the stacks here look a
library or you could go watch a really
interesting documentary on a service
like curiosity stream curiosity stream
is a new streaming service with over
2400 high-quality documentaries that was
actually created by John Hendricks who
was the founder of the Discovery Channel
which was the way that I discovered a
lot of my interests as a kid now the
great thing about curiosity stream is
that unlike the Discovery Channel you
don't have to wait for a certain thing
to come on at anytime and almost
anywhere
since you'll find curiosity stream on
iOS Android Roku and plenty of other
devices you can access any documentary
you want there are science documentaries
history documentaries technology
documentaries there are even
documentaries from people like Stephen
Hawking and Sigourney Weaver and if
you're looking for a place to start then
I would like to give you a
recommendation because one of my big
interests that I don't talk about a
whole lot on my channel is the
development of artificial intelligence
this is something that I've been
interested in for probably five or six
years at this point and on curiosity
stream you're gonna find a documentary
called the road to the singularity which
explores how the development of several
different technologies including biotech
and nanotech could lead to the
development of artificial intelligence
and the singularity in the intelligence
explosion so if you want to check out
that documentary or any of the others on
the platform then you should give
curiosity stream a try it's really
affordable just $2.99 per month and if
you want to give it a try for free you
can actually get a free 30-day trial of
unlimited watching on the platform by
going over to curiosity stream comm
slash Thomas and using the code Thomas
at checkout huge thanks as always goes
out to curiosity stream for sponsoring
this video and being a big supporter of
my channel and the content that I create
and thank you as well for watching if
you found this video useful definitely
hit that like button and also get
subscribed right there so you don't miss
future videos when they come out and
also click right there to get a free
copy of my book on how to earn a better
grades if you haven't done so already
last but not least you can check out one
more video on this channel right over
here or watch our latest podcast episode
right over here thanks for watching see
you in the next