if you've ever wanted to count yourself
among the ranks of geniuses like
Leonardo da Vinci Margaret Atwood and
Frank Lloyd Wright then you're in luck
because there is at least one dimension
in which you me and probably everyone
watching this video is already like them
that's because each one of these
geniuses is or was a massive
procrastinator da Vinci took 16 years to
finish the Mona Lisa which is to say
that he died 16 years after he started
it and over the course of his life he
only finished a handful of projects
often leaving angry patrons scrambling
to hire other people to finish the
projects that eventually slipped from
his attention likewise the author
Margaret Atwood is pretty open about the
fact that she spends every morning for
cras nating only getting to work around
3:00 in the afternoon and as the story
goes the architect Frank Lloyd Wright
drew up the initial plans for the famous
falling water house just hours before a
scheduled meeting with the man who had
commissioned it procrastination is a
problem that plagues most of us to some
degree from famous polymaths and artists
throughout history to youtubers
ironically making videos about
procrastination to students just trying
to get their homework done almost all of
us deal with it along with its
consequences of which there are many
despite the justifications that
procrastinators love to make like I work
well under pressure man it's fine
research has shown that procrastination
is significantly correlated with poor
study habits with depression anxiety
like kantha B low self-esteem and yes I
may have made one of those up but the
fact remains that procrastination is a
damaging habit to be in so over the
course of the next three videos we are
going to dig deep into both the causes
of procrastination and how we can
finally overcome it this video in
particular will focus on the science of
procrastination and we're gonna pull
from a wide body of research to find out
exactly why we tend to put off our work
as the ancient proverb goes know thy
enemy then in the next video we're gonna
go over several tactics you can use to
stop procrastinating in the moment once
you catch yourself doing it and the
final video will wrap things up by
looking at how each of us can once and
for all
shed the label of procrastinator from
our identities and permanently reduce
our tendency to put things off for now
though we are focused on the question of
why why do we procrastinate one of the
most popular theories that attempts to
gather and integrate the many potential
answers to this question is called
temporal motivation theory which was
created by dr. Pierce steel and which
was most thoroughly
in his book the procrastination equation
as the books title implies temporal
motivation theory attempts to explain
procrastination in terms of a formula
which aims to solve our tasks utility or
the general motivation to do it the
higher the utility or the higher the
motivation the less likely someone is
going to be to procrastinate on that
particular task and the elements of that
equation include number one expectancy
which is your belief that you can
complete the task number two value which
is how valuable the reward the task will
give you is to you number three
impulsiveness which is the likelihood
that you're gonna be distracted by
something that would give you instant
gratification now and finally number
four there's delay which is how long
you're gonna have to wait to get the
reward so to solve for motivation or
utility you simply set the equation up
like this and then if you want to raise
your motivation and stop procrastinating
you just need to figure out how to
manipulate one or more of the equations
elements for example you could raise
expectancy by getting clear on the
details of your task or by breaking it
down into little subtasks e 2 which
feels more actionable likewise you can
raise the tasks value by setting up
additional rewards for completing it
like giving yourself a pre plan to break
once you finish it and of course you
could lower impulsiveness by
disconnecting from the internet or
working on self-discipline exercises to
make yourself less vulnerable to
distractions or by changing your study
location to increase the distance
between you and your VR headset and
finally there is delay which is probably
the hardest element in the equation to
manipulate since a lot of tasks have a
set in stone due date meaning there is a
set in stone reward now temporal
motivation Theory has its roots in
behavioral economics proposing that the
reason we procrastinate is purely due to
our current perceived utility of a task
and to be fair it is a model that does a
pretty good job at collecting many of
the reasons we do tend to put things off
the expectancy piece accurately reflects
the fact that we tend to be more
resistant to starting a task when we
know that it's difficult likewise the
value and delay variables reflect how we
tend to opt for instant gratification
over rewards whose value we don't much
care about or that we've discounted
because it's far off in the future but
it's worth mentioning that this theory
does have its critics including dr.
Timothy Mitchell who heads up the
procrastination research group at
Carleton University and a critique that
he wrote for the website Psychology
Today
Mitchell points out that in the attempt
to unify everything under this
utility-based equation this theory ends
up making too many assumptions for one
it assumes that some tasks like
socializing with friends have a fixed
utility
that isn't sensitive to delay while
others like writing an essay definitely
are sensitive to that delay and in fact
these two tasks are used together to
form an example on dr. Steele's website
according to the graph there the utility
of socializing remains higher than that
of writing the essay until right near
the due date at which point the lines
intersect and now it's time to start
chugging red bulls and scrambling to
finish that essay but Mitchell's article
asks what would happen if a party
scheduled for this Friday were postponed
to next week since this increases delay
the overall utility of socializing
should be decreased and now the utility
of writing the essay should be higher
which means that you should choose to do
it right of course in the real world
most students wouldn't decide to work on
an essay far advanced at the deadline
just because a party got postponed now
for my part I feel like pitches critique
of this one example isn't a perfect take
down because it kind of frames things as
a binary choice and in reality I'm gonna
be considering more options if the party
gets postponed I'm probably still gonna
consider playing overwatch all night
rather than just choosing to do the
essay still I do agree with his overall
conclusion Murray says the point is that
complex human behaviors are not best
understood by simple equations or
formula although the theories that these
formulae represent can be useful in our
discussion of behavior and I especially
agree with this view that temporal
motivation is just a little too focused
on this idea of people as rational
decision makers carefully weighing
different actions like ingots on a scale
because that isn't how it works
we humans with our squishy multi-layer
brains are a lot more irrational than
economic theories would like to pain us
at all times the irrational part of your
brain is locked in an eternal struggle
with the more instinctual emotional side
and it's this emotional side that plays
the biggest role in our tendency to
procrastinate especially for people that
have a hard time regulating it in a
study that was published back in 2001
the researcher Diane theis found that
students who are primed to believe their
mood was fixed or frozen were less
likely to seek instant gratification or
to procrastinate while students who were
led to believe that their moods could be
changed were much more likely to do both
and even though procrastinators tend to
feel guilt when they do this they for we
I should say actually because I do this
too we tend to rationalize it and we
convince ourselves that it's really not
a big deal
for an example of this study done at
Bishop University had students react to
scenarios where procrastination actually
caused a problem
or at least exacerbated it including a
scenario where somebody had come back
from a Sunday vacation with a suspicious
mole but then put off going to the
doctor to have it checked out for quite
a long time and in reaction to that
scenario the chronic procrastinators in
the group tended to say things like at
least I went to the doctor before I got
really really bad
instead of saying things like if only
I'd gone to the doctor sooner all their
statements tended to be what are called
downward counterfactuals which are
responses that reflect a desire to
improve one's mood in the short term and
these are in contrast to you guessed it
upward counterfactuals which are
responses that tend to embrace
difficulties now in an attempt to learn
something new about the future as the
head researcher for the study put it
procrastinators focused on how to make
themselves feel better at the expense of
drawing insight from what made them feel
bad despite the guilt that we feel this
habitual urge to seek an emotional
pick-me-up in response to a task that's
boring or difficult or in response to
anxiety causes us to construct arguments
that rationalize a procrastination and
keep us in a never-ending cycle of doing
it and those studies are just the start
because there is even more evidence to
support this idea of procrastination as
primarily an issue of emotional
regulation for instance a study from
Brooklyn College back in 2010 found a
significant link between procrastination
problems and problems with executive
functioning which is an umbrella term
for all the higher cognitive functions
that control our behavior when the
researchers first tested students on
procrastination and then on nine scales
of executive functioning such as
self-monitoring and emotional control
and organization they found a
significant link between problems with
procrastination and all nine of these
scales and another study even found a
biological link when a research team
over in Germany did fMRI brain scans on
264 adults they found a link between
difficulties in initiating action on
tasks and a greater volume of gray
matter in the amygdala which is the
brains fight or flight center though it
is worth mentioning just a couple of
things about this study the first of
which being that the results merely show
an association rather than claiming a
direct causal link and the second being
a reminder that the physical structure
of the brain is in fact quite adaptable
in fact setting them back in 2013 showed
how just eight weeks of training in
mindfulness meditation can actually
shrink the volume of the amygdala and as
the study notes as the amygdala shrinks
the prefrontal cortex associated with
higher-order brain functions such as
awareness concentration and
decision-making becomes thick
and I think that this is very important
to include because while all of us are
born with different brains were also
born with brains that can in fact change
adapt and improve so to sum things up
the current body of a crass donación
research seems to point the finger of
primarily at an inability to
self-regulate emotions and mood as the
cause when you're a chronic
procrastinator you consistently given to
feel good even though you were keenly
aware of the harm you're causing and
even though you feel guilty about it and
make no mistake even the greats felt
guilty about it in fact Walter
Isaacson's biography on Leonardo da
Vinci makes this pretty clear stating
the most obvious evidence that he was
human rather than superhuman is the
trail of projects he left unfinished
tell me if anything was ever done he
repeatedly scribbled in notebook after
notebook tell me tell me tell me if I
ever did a thing tell me if anything was
ever made of course this primary reason
is connected to other causes as well
such as those problems with executive
functioning and the expectancy value and
delay issues laid out by temporal
motivation theory and by how close we
are to our distractions
as well as how addicted we are to them
which i think is an important point to
note since now more than ever our
distractions are specifically engineered
to keep us coming back again and again
now in the next video in the series
we're going to dig into some specific
tactics that you can use to stop
procrastinating in the moment when you
notice yourself doing it but before we
end this video I do want to address one
of the most common fixes for
procrastination that I see being touted
on the Internet which is to simply go
and do the work that you love to follow
your passion because if you're
procrastinating right now it means
you're doing the wrong work and you need
to quit if only it were that easy but
alas even people who are quote unquote
following their passion have elements of
their work that they tend to
procrastinate on I mean most these
people would probably feel pretty silly
telling Margaret Atwood the work she
spent her life doing is in fact the
wrong work for her because she
procrastinates on it more importantly
though this is just dangerous advice
sure occasionally you're gonna see
somebody who quit everything dropped at
a school and went all-in on underwater
game development and they made millions
of dollars it became an inspiration to
us all those are the stories that get
told but they are the exception to the
rule and as the author Barbara Oakley
wisely points out
her book mine for numbers over the past
decades students who have blindly
followed their passion without rational
analysis of whether their career choice
truly was wise have been more unhappy
with their job choices than knows who
couple passion with rationality a better
path is to dedicate your free time to
exploring your interests and passions
and to double down to the ones that you
seem especially interested in and by
deliberately learning what triggers your
procrastination with your main work and
then by learning to combate those
triggers which is what the other two
videos in this series will be about
you're gonna find yourself with more of
that free time than you would have
otherwise had of course another way to
start moving something that you're
passionate about from being just a side
project to becoming something that
eventually may be something you could
turn into a career is to accelerate your
skill development in that area by
learning from expert teachers for
example if you eventually wanted to
build your own successful YouTube
channel then you might want to learn
about content creation from somebody who
already does that for a living and
fortunately my friend Evan who runs the
excellent channel poly matter recently
released a course over on Skillshare
that talks all about how to do that
evans course covers the entire creation
process for making an animated youtube
video starting from topic selection and
research then moving on into story
crafting and finally heading on into a
section about how to actually make the
animations and one thing that I was
really surprised to learn especially
given how smooth and awesomely animated
Evans videos are is how simple his
process for making those animations
actually is and beyond Evans course
you're also going to find over 24,000
different classes in skills library
covering UX and design productivity
entrepreneurship and tons of other topic
areas plus classes are hands-on all of
them feature projects and many have
downloadable example files so you can
immediately start using what you're
learning and learn actively the
membership of school chair is also
really affordable costing about as much
as your Netflix subscription but of
course being a lot more useful to your
future skill development and what's best
if you use link in the description down
below and sign up you're gonna get two
months of completely unlimited access to
their library for free so if you want to
start accelerating your skill
development today then definitely use
that link below and sign up because
there is a lot you could learn in two
months
big thanks to Skillshare for sponsoring
this episode and as always thank you
guys for watching if you like this video
definitely hit that like button to
support this channel and if you want to
make sure you get notifications
especially for the next two videos in
this series about how to stop
procrastinating in the moment
and then how to become less of a chronic
procrastinator long-term you're
definitely gonna want to get subscribed
right there and possibly hit that Bell
for notifications you can also click
right there to get a free copy of my
book on how to earn better grades in
school whether you're in high school or
college I think you're gonna find it
very useful you can also follow me on
instagram at Tom frankly and when those
other two videos in the series go live
I'm gonna have them right here on screen
until then there's probably one other
video that you may want to watch if you
haven't seen it all right thanks for
watching and I will see you in the next
video