this video is sponsored by Skillshare
where you can take my new class on
building strong habits be one of the
first 500 people to sign up its link
below to get a 2 month free trial
offices are not always the ideal place
to work
they're often uninspiring they take way
too long to get to and more often than
not the printers are broken luckily
there is an alternative and getting to
it doesn't take a whole lot more than
simply getting out of bed ok so it's
more than likely that you've recently
found yourself working from home not by
choice but by necessity that being said
as someone who's been working from home
for more than a decade I can tell you
that working from home is kind of
Awesome your commute gets eliminated you
have a lot more control over how you set
up your workspace and technically you
don't even have to wear pants that said
it also does come with certain
challenges when there are no bosses or
co-workers around it can be a lot harder
to stay on task and to avoid certain
temptations and every decision becomes
yours to make which can be a little
overwhelming when you're used to having
your schedule at least partly set by
someone else so this is a start of a
series of videos on this channel that
will teach you how to work from home as
effectively as possible and with this
first video we are starting with your
environment with your workspace now the
first thing I want to say here is that
there are no hard and fast rules when it
comes to setting up your workspace one
of my friends often works from his couch
and another one writes all of his video
scripts from a beanbag chair that being
said I think there are two main elements
that you want to consider when setting
up your workspace separation and
isolation so my separation I'm talking
about having a space that has a singular
purpose you want to set up a space that
is only used for work and then have
another space that's used for relaxation
the surroundings that we put ourselves
in have a certain amount of influence
over our psychological states and in the
choices that we make so you want to make
sure that your brain doesn't have to
work too hard against your environment
to stay on task secondly you want to aim
to be isolated from people who might
interrupt you and honestly this is a big
problem offices as well especially since
many of them move for that open office
concept without walls but it's an even
bigger issue when you're at home with
family so at my house I've built a
dedicated office that serves both of
these purposes
I have a desk that I use for research
and for writing which is where I wrote
the script for this video and then a
reading area next to that and if I need
to I can close the doors to that office
and be alone in that room but what if
you don't have the room for a dedicated
isolated workspace
well when space is limited you can
either get creative maybe putting your
desk underneath a loft bed in your room
like my friend Alex does or you can turn
to another resource that you have at
your disposal time if you can't set up a
permanent workspace you can get into the
habit of setting up a temporary one each
day and you can even make this part of
your morning routine have your shower
make your breakfast make your coffee and
then clear off a space on your kitchen
table or get out a folding table and in
the case of the latter option you also
have the flexibility to experiment with
where to put that folding table now my
main tip here would be to make sure
you're not facing a TV especially if
somebody else in your family is watching
that TV and in general don't face
anything that is going to distract you
if you have to face a blank wall then do
that but in any case you can experiment
and see what works best for you then
once you've finished your work for the
day or we've hit a preset stopping time
which would be a good thing to have you
can reverse the routine and put your
gear away and this actually comes with a
really great benefit because it's a way
of really committing to the act of
disengaging from work mode and going
into relaxation mode and this I can tell
you from experience is quite hard to do
when you live and work in the exact same
space now another question that I've
been getting pretty often is how to deal
with interruptions from family and other
people who live in the same place that
you do and honestly the main answer to
this question is just good communication
but there are some additional tweaks you
can make to your actual workspace that
can help here as well the first is
something that you can steal from the
broadcasting industry which is the idea
of an on-air sign radio stations and
Studios often have these light up on-air
signs outside of recording booths which
light up when somebody's recording or
filming like I am right now
and this lets other people know that
they should stop talking they should
creep round on tiptoes like little cat
burglars and quite honestly that they
should stop breathing as well you know
preferably but I'm guessing that your
family's probably not going to agree
with that
anyway you can set up a similar sort of
system to let your family know
implicitly that you're trying to focus
and they shouldn't interrupt you for
example my friend Martin uses a hue
light bulb plugged into a regular desk
lamp which when set to a specific color
lets his fiance know that he's really
focusing in on a difficult problem and
shouldn't be interrupted unless it's a
really urgent issue of course you could
just keep things simple and close the
door to your workspace or pop out a pair
of headphones we need to focus but the
main thing here is that you and your
family should set the system up together
so that they know how to respect it next
let's talk about some tools and other
physical items that can make a huge
improvement in your workspace now
naturally you're gonna want to have any
tools that are specific to your work
close at hand easily accessible but
there are a few more general items that
I would like to bring to your attention
as well first I have a white board
mounted to the wall right next to my
desk and every night I look at duyst or
the Google Calendar and I write a list
of everything that I'm gonna do the next
day preferably in the order that I'm
going to do it and I find that having
this physical reminder of my priorities
for the day right there in front of me
and easily glanced up at it's a great
addition to my workspace I also have a
second monitor which is hugely helpful
when I'm doing intense research when I'm
editing a video or really what I'm doing
anything that benefits from extra screen
real estate
now you could of course go out and buy
an extra monitor which I have done many
many times but if you have an iPad or an
Android tablet lying around you can also
use those on Mac OS there's a feature
called sidecar that's built-in now let's
use an iPad as a second screen and if
you're on Windows there are Android apps
like space tech let you do the exact
same thing with an Android tablet you
might also consider keeping some plants
around like this dragon plant that I
keep next to my Reading area that I
think really improves my work space and
keep some healthy snacks and drinks
around as well for snacks like to keep
carrots and almonds and apples around
and then for drinks I have a fridge
stocked with sparkling water and of
course I have lots of coffee and tea
above that and finally I would recommend
getting yourself a good pair of
headphones as much as I love to blast
music over my speakers while I'm working
I think every good workspace should have
a quality pair of headphones in it not
only will this allow you listen to
whatever you want without disturbing
anyone else more importantly they can
provide some isolation and help you stay
focused now if you live in a
particularly noisy environment then you
may want to look into active
noise-cancelling headphones these
essentially listen to the sounds in your
environment and then create opposite
sound waves that basically cancel both
out so that you hear theoretically
nothing now in practice are they
completely silent well not completely
but I think you'd be surprised at how
much they really do help when I tried my
first pair they were an absolute game
changer and they enabled me to work in
many places that were previously way too
loud now they gonna let you finish that
TPS report in the front row of a
Metallica concert well probably not but
they do help quite a lot so these are
the bose qc25 so I've had these for
several years now and if they were to
break I'll probably go out and buy the
exact same pair once again I absolutely
love these headphones but that said
these and most noise cancelling
headphones are actually quite pricey I
think these were like 350 bucks when I
bought them they're about 260 now so
they've come down quite a bit but for
the most part active noise-cancelling is
something that's got to cost you a bit
of money except I recently saw that
anchor came out with a pair of active
noise-cancelling headphones that go for
about $60 I haven't tried them myself
but they do seem pretty well reviewed
now if you want to go even cheaper than
that then you're gonna want to look into
a pair of normal headphones that have a
closed back design this is different
from an open back design so these
headphones which are the audio technica
ath m50 have a closed back design which
basically means that they're pretty well
sealed up they don't have active noise
canceling but they do provide a good
amount of isolation when you're wearing
them by contrast open-back headphones
like these sun highs are HD 650s which
are honestly my favorite headphones they
don't have very much material at all
other than this metal grate separating
your ears from the outside world
which means that your poor naked
defenseless ears are gonna hear
everything going on in your environment
now open-back headphones do have their
benefits they have this wide open airy
sound stays a lot of audio files really
like but a tool for isolation they are
not anyway if you're looking for an
inexpensive recommendation for closed
back headphones I'm gonna recommend the
audio technica m20 s which are
essentially the base model of these ones
they're still great but they are quite a
bit cheaper now what specifically should
you be listening to in those headphones
while you work
well scientist
working around the clock looking at lots
of spreadsheets and poring over data
have definitively proven that the best
source of productivity enhancing audio
in the world is my soundcloud it is
straight productivity enhancing fire who
wrote this oh okay
barring that of them in silence you have
three main sources white noise ambient
noise and of course music now for both
white noise and ambient noise I have a
few recommendations that you might want
to check out first is a site called
ambient mixer where people have uploaded
custom mixes that you can use to study
with including lots of common rooms for
Hogwarts houses my favorite being the
ravenclaw one even though as my
girlfriend likes to tell me I'm a
Slytherin and you can even open up the
mixes and change the levels of the
sounds or even add in more sounds if you
want there's another site called noise
lee which is the one that i used for
most college and that one also lets you
mix your own ambient sound scape with
white noise pink noise brown noise
babbling brooks rain all that kind of
stuff but unfortunately after being very
much free forever they have recently
went to a paid model where now there's a
free plan you can I think listen to for
90 minutes a day but after that you have
to pay kind of a bummer also of course
there's YouTube type in basically any
kind of ambient mix you want into
YouTube and you're gonna find lots of
10-hour mixes that you can listen to and
when it comes to music YouTube is again
a great place to start not least of
which because for several years I have
been building my own ultimate study
music playlist here on YouTube which
I'll have linked and description down
below and if you happen to be a Spotify
or Apple music user I have a playlist
called Sunday study which attempts to
replicate that playlist so I'll link to
that one as well and if you're a Spotify
user in particular I also want to
mention my friend Ali Abdullah has his
own excellent study music playlist which
I will also link to and his is much
longer than mine since he tends to put
entire albums on it to where I tend to
curate individual songs so the digital
environment that you build is just as
important as the physical one if your
computer or your phone are constantly
distracting you and pulling your
attention away from the work that you
need to be doing well then you're really
gonna get much done but luckily there
are some tweaks you can make to that
digital environment that are just as
effective as the ones we've made to the
physical one so first and foremost I'm
gonna recommend actually creating a
secondary work account on your computer
and ideally this account shouldn't have
access to steam to origin to epic man
there are a lot of game launchers now or
really to any other program that you
find distracting you can also use a
program like freedom which will actively
block distracting websites and apps blog
you're working and your phone is also a
potential distraction possibly more so
which is why my main recommendation
would be to keep it away from your work
area while you're working so it did hit
something you were right anyway yeah
keep it away from your main work area
while you're working and when you get it
for a break you can check it then if you
absolutely must keep it near you while
you're working at least try using an app
like forest which encourages you not to
touch your phone for a specified period
of time that you set by letting you grow
a virtual tree if you don't leave the
app during that period you get the tree
but if you do you kill your virtual tree
and then mr. beast will be sad now well
we're talking about your digital setup I
do want to briefly mention internet
speed if you're gonna be jumping on lots
of zoom calls with your team downloading
lots of files and generally trying to
use the internet to continue to earn a
living then you'll want to make sure
that your local network speeds are as
good as they can be personally if I can
get a hardwired connection I will always
take it you can do a lot to improve your
Wi-Fi for sure but nothing beats an
Ethernet cable running straight to a
router that said if you do need to use
Wi-Fi at least try to position your
router in a central location within your
house or apartment that way the signal
will have the best chance of covering
your whole living space now aside from
setting up your environment in the right
way you're also going to want to work on
improving your habits and your daily
routines if you want to work effectively
from home optimizing these will help you
get a great start to your day and will
help you stay more productive as they
automate a lot of what would normally
fall on your willpower and again when
you're working at home this is
incredibly important since every
decision is essentially yours to make
now if you want to learn how to
effectively build these habits in these
routines check out my habit building
class on Skillshare this class will help
you to take your goals which might be a
bit fuzzy and loosely defined and turn
them into concrete plans that can be
down into actionable daily habits once
that's done the rest of the class is
dedicated to helping you stick to those
habits long term and the best part is
that you can take this class for free by
being one of the first five for people
to sign up for school share it using the
link below doing that will unlock a two
month free trial which is more than
enough time to take this class since it
runs just over an hour from there it'll
be up to you to put what you've learned
into action but I will know that there
is an area where you can ask questions
and get feedback from both myself and
other students taking the class and
since this is scale share you'll also
have access to my other class which is
all about building your productivity
system along with thousands of other
classes taught by expert teachers and
covering topics like video editing
public speaking interior design and lots
lots more so after taking my habits
class I highly recommend checking out
something that interests you and working
to broaden your skill set which is
something that I personally am always
trying to do once again be one of the
first 500 people to sign up with that
link down below to get a two month free
trial with unloaded access to skill
share and as always thank you so much
for watching this video also big thanks
to all my YouTube friends who
contributed footage for this video I'll
have all of their channels linked in the
description down below so check those
out and if you enjoyed this video
definitely hit that thumbs up button so
the YouTube algorithm knows - hopefully
recommend my channel a little bit more
often other than that you can get
subscribed right there if you haven't
done so already check out a free copy of
my book over here well you have to check
it out it's like a library you just get
it you can download it but anyway go
right there and you can get it otherwise
love a couple more videos on screen you
can check out by smashing your face into
your phone screen as always to do that
and other than that go do whatever you
want I'm not your dad