this video is sponsored by skillshare be
one of the first 1 000 people to sign up
at the link below to get a two-month
free trial
it used to be so simple wake up at the
crack of dawn
grumble at your alarm a little bit then
get ready
and go to class but then we had to go
and add
computers into the mix online classes
these things have been growing in
popularity for years there are free ones
there are cheap ones they're
very expensive ones taught to you by
guys in their garages and they're even
full-blown
university courses that you can take
online even if you don't go
to that university but this year in 2020
they became the only option for most
people going back to school
so i thought it was high time that we
make a video on them because well
online classes can be very convenient in
some ways they can also trip you up and
make your life
more difficult in others hence there are
some things that i think you should know
how to do
so you can prepare to be as successful
as possible in whatever online class
you're going to take so welcome to class
welcome to my set
i bet none of your teachers on zoom have
a set like this which
honestly is okay because good education
doesn't need overblown production values
like this
unless like me you are a dancing monkey
trying to also appease an algorithm
that will inevitably one day morph into
a universe dominating super intelligence
and vaporize us all
anyway today we're gonna share five tips
for helping you prepare for
and get the most out of online classes i
think this is gonna be helpful for
anybody going back to school in a formal
setting online
but this should also be helpful for
anybody taking an online class
independently
so whichever camp you're in let's get
started tip number one is to treat these
classes
just like they are real in-person
classes see the problem with online
classes is that they are usually taught
asynchronously the instructor the
teacher prepares material ahead of time
and then you do it at a different time
now this might be changing a bit this
year since a lot of schools are going to
online only education you might see a
lot of classes talk through video
conferencing apps like zoom and hangouts
but i still think it's likely you're
gonna have a lot of asynchronous
learning time you're gonna be given a
lot of
independent reading assignments homework
assignments and you're gonna have to do
them on your own
at home and if you're taking an
independent online class like i
currently am with samurai guitarist's
class on music theory
then everything is independent and the
problem with this
asynchronous independent and distanced
nature of online classes
is that it becomes really easy to fall
behind if you're not self-disciplined
in-person classes are in person and they
happen on a schedule
and that schedule makes it a lot easier
to stay on top of your reading
and all of your homework assignments and
in addition to that it also gives your
day a bit more structure as well
with online classes a lot of that
structure is lacking
and i know this from experience back
when i was in college i took one online
class amongst all of my in-person
classes it was a food science and
nutrition class
and i bet you can guess which class out
of everything i took
i fell behind in the most it was that
one so
do whatever you can to treat your online
classes just like they're real classes
in terms of schedule in terms of where
you do them in terms of
everything now maybe your teachers
already have you covered they're gonna
make you set up a desk they're gonna do
all the classes on zoom
but in case they aren't do it for
yourself
number one set up a dedicated workspace
for yourself wherever you live i made a
whole video about that i'll have that
link in the description below if you
want to check it out
secondly create recurring events on your
calendar for all of your classes
and then at the beginning of each week
look ahead at what you've got on your
calendar
and then build a schedule for yourself
making plans for homework for any other
events in the gaps between those
recurring classes
lastly it's a really smart idea to keep
up your routines so have a morning
routine that helps you get ready for the
day
but also build some momentum so you
start your online learning feeling fresh
tip number two is to get serious about
your calendar
and your to-do list that mainly means
adding new events to your calendar and
new tasks to your to-do list
the moment you get them see it is
already hard enough to keep the jumble
of events and tasks straight in your
head during
normal times but when everything moves
online you lose
one key component to what scientists
call episodic memory formation which is
the process that your brain goes through
to consolidate and encode
new memories and that is location
location is a huge part of this process
as your memories get inextricably tied
to where you were
when you experienced them that's why
people often ask questions like
where were you when the fire nation
attacked personally i was sitting in
front of the tv in my parents living
room
probably eating a fruit roll up anyway
we also know that two pieces of
information in the brain
get linked in a two-way relationship for
instance
i can ask you what is goku's power level
and you're probably gonna tell me
it's over 9000 but i can also ask you
name me something that is
over 9 000 and you're likely to say
goku's power level
and that's why jeopardy works and i
would submit this
also applies to your recollection of
what happens as you go through a day of
classes
if you're used to going from classroom
to classroom then moving everything
online means that you're now
losing out on a whole bunch of unique
location information that would have
likely helped you recall events and due
dates
assigned to you which means that it's
now more important than ever that you're
getting this data into a system
an external system that you trust and
then at the end of the day you can
review that system to make sure
nothing slips through the cracks and
side note about calendars
keep time zones in mind as well now if
you're in middle school high school and
your physical school building is just a
few miles down the road
well then maybe this doesn't matter to
you at all but if you're a university
student who's maybe out of state and for
the first time ever
doing school in a different time zone
from where your university and your
teacher is then you want to make sure
that you have the right time zones on
your calendar and with google calendar
and pretty much every other calendar
software out there
you can actually choose the time zone of
any event you're creating and then it'll
automatically translate the time zone
when you're looking at your full
calendar and if you're trying to
schedule events with a study group or
like a virtual project group and you're
trying to figure out when everyone can
meet you can also use tools like
doodle which lets everyone input the
times they're available and it'll
automatically do the time zone
translation
for you tip number three american three
this time
gratzy is to get digitally organized
now maybe you think you're already
perfectly organized maybe you watched my
previous video and you actually went out
and got your con mario certification
and now you're a minimalism master but
we got to talk about this because
with in-person classes there are often a
lot of paper handouts creating an
emphasis
on physical organization on the
beautiful analog world with all of its
vinyl discs
but when classes move online we burn
those vinyl discs and everything becomes
organized digitally so you have to learn
how to falsely organize all of your
handouts
on your computer so don't be that guy
who saves everything to
the desktop creating a giant jumbled
mess of files and
exes and game saves and whatever else
create a folder
in your file management system for every
class that you're taking
and then create a subfolder for any kind
of project you have within those classes
that has more than one file
associated with it additionally within
your note-taking system you want to have
a notebook for each
class whether you're writing out notes
with a pen on paper or you're using a
tablet and a stylus or you're typing
them into a computer you want to have a
specific place where everything
for each class gets organized and
grouped
together and if you're a notion user
like i am then you may want to check out
the note-taking template that i created
and made a video on which has two
different levels of hierarchy so you can
easily organize your notes if you're
curious about that i will have a
template link in the description down
below which you can duplicate
and try out if you want tip number four
is actually my favorite tip in this
video
find a way to break up your day one of
the things that i missed most from
college were little gaps of time in
between my classes
because i went to college on this huge
campus it was like 100 acres or
something
and that meant that i would sometimes
have to literally power walk
or get on my skateboard in order to make
it across campus to make it in time for
the next class but those mad dashes
across campus were actually a nice way
to break up the day
they made every class feel like its own
little independent segment
they also gave me a way to just kind of
get outside and get a little bit of
exercise
and i remember being kind of bummed when
i got my first internship
and realized that all of my work was
done from one
tiny little cubicle so sometimes i would
find ways to just
get away from that cubicle and break up
my day a little bit by going for a 20
minute walk downtown or
sometimes literally just walking up and
down flights of stairs in the office
building
and if you're about to start a full
suite of online classes then
the place where you're going to be doing
it is probably not a whole lot different
than that cubicle i had so you should
find a way to break up your day
as well this could be as simple as every
once in a while getting up from your
desk
stretching a bit and going for a walk
moving around a bit just getting a
little bit of a change
of scenery if you have a decent amount
of room in your home you could also
take this a bit further by maybe
switching locations during the day
going from your desk to the kitchen
table back to the desk but even if
you're not working with a whole lot of
space
just getting up and giving yourself some
of these breaks will help to make your
learning time not feel like this
big giant amorphous blob of time that
never ends
finally tip 5 get yourself a virtual
study group
potentially one of the worst things
about learning online is
the isolation at least the physical
isolation instead of sitting in a
classroom with 20 other students
and a teacher you're at home alone
oh thomas you're never really alone
one way that you can mitigate this at
least somewhat is to form a
virtual study group you can do this by
asking a few of your classmates to meet
up with you on google hangouts or zoom
just a few times a week so you can study
together or review assignments
or make fart jokes and you can also do
what i like to call work calls
i used to do these all the time back
with some blogger friends who lived in
different states
and essentially we would just hop on
skype because these are the dark ages
and that's kind of what we had
and we just get on a call where really
nobody would talk but we would each be
on the line with the other person
knowing that they were getting their
work done and there was just
something about being in this call with
other productive people
that felt a little bit like working at
the same table together so it was
actually kind of a nice productivity
hack
and if this is something that you want
to do there's actually a site called
focusmate that is kind of tailor-made
for this purpose when you start a
session it pairs you up with somebody
else who wants a little bit of
companionship and then you just kind of
work in silence together my friend
ransom who is the head writer at my site
collegeenpo geek
who's written a couple of scripts for
this channel swears by this tool and has
been using it ever since the lockdown
started so you might find it helpful
as well now if you'd like to test out
everything you've learned in this video
and also improve your habits which can
help you study more effectively and be
more successful in your classes
then you might want to go take my habit
building class over on skillshare
this is a short one-hour class that'll
help you stick to your habits
even after the initial novelty period
has worn off and we do that
in three different ways european three
this time number one
strengthening your internal
self-discipline number two assisting
that self-discipline with smart external
systems that help keep you on track
and number three improving those habits
over time with regular
reflection over 40 000 people have
already taken this class and i think
you're going to get a ton out of it if
you choose to take it
as well and if you want to take it for
free you can actually do that by being
one of the first 1 000 people to sign up
for skillshare using the link in the
description
down below doing that will get you a
two-month free trial with
unlimited access to the platform so you
can go take my class and you can also
check out some of the thousands of other
classes they have spanning
productivity business analytics
marketing
video production and lots lots more plus
after the trial ends skillshare is still
way more affordable than most online
learning platforms out there with plans
starting at less than ten dollars
a month so once again if you want to
take my class be one of the first 1 000
people to sign up with that link in the
description down below
to get your two month free trial and to
also support my channel by supporting
one of the awesome companies
that sponsors me thanks so much for
watching as always if you enjoyed this
video hitting that like button with your
middle knuckle very gently tells the
youtube algorithm that
you like the video and that is one of
those pieces of data the algorithm uses
to potentially share the video out to
more people which is hugely helpful for
my channel
so thank you so much if you do that but
of course the biggest factor the
algorithm looks at
is just how long you watch the video so
seriously
thank you for sticking around to the end
and i'm really glad that you enjoyed
what you're watching if you haven't
subscribed already you can subscribe
right there so you don't miss out on
future content and if you want to keep
watching videos on this channel
i'm going to throw up a couple of other
videos right here and here that you can
smash your face on your phone screen
to watch but of course if you don't want
to do any of that
then don't do that don't clean your room
and go eat an entire pint of ice cream
if you want to
i'm probably going to go do that because
as always i'm not your dad