well hello there it's been a while since
I posted on this channel nearly a year
and a half in fact and this video I want
to talk about why I stopped posting on
this channel uh how doing so actually
doubled my income surprisingly uh what
I'm doing now and what the future is for
this Channel and for what I'm doing in
general but the gist of it is hey I'm
back I've got new videos in the works we
are going to be regularly publishing on
this channel again and if you ran across
this video in your YouTube feed and have
no idea who I am hi there I'm Thomas
Frank I've been posting about
productivity and personal development on
this channel for a long time and in the
last couple of years I've gone very deep
into no code notion even programming I'm
building a new startup there's a lot
going on and I'm going to talk about
kind of why I ended up leaving this
channel because I think that's the
question that a lot of people are going
to be having in fact I've got a lot of
people over my Instagram who thought
that I either died or forgot my
Instagram password and I'm sure a lot of
you thought that I forgot my YouTube
password so let's just get into it I've
got a few different things I want to
talk about but the big question a lot of
you probably have is hey Tom why did you
stop posting on this YouTube channel why
would somebody abandon a 2.9 Million
subscriber YouTube channel and a
secondary question how would doing that
actually double my income the short
answer is that I took some time off from
this channel intending for it to only be
a month but it turned into a year and
six months just about to get the focus
and to get the time I needed to go and
build an actual product I had something
I wanted to build it was a premium
notion template called ultimate brain I
still sell it and I never talked about
on this channel because what I thought
was going to be a month taken off to
build it ended up becoming a year and a
half of building an entirely new part of
my business building up my second
Channel Thomas Frank explains going very
deep into some hyper Niche technical
areas uh that i' had never explored
before and one thing led to another and
I just didn't have time to publish on
this channel our team has grown to 12
people I've actually kind of had to
become a CEO uh and and I've also sort
of gone the complete opposite direction
with some of my time and I've learned
how to code and I spend a lot of my time
actually programming these days so I've
been doing a lot uh and again I just
kind of want to go through a lot of
what's happened in this video so to get
into the story of why I ended up
abandoning this Channel I want to talk
about a little bit of philosophy first
actually I want to talk about the
philosophy of pivots and side quests uh
and I think the best way to frame this
would be to not talk about the channel
abandonment right away and instead talk
about my podcast that I deliberately
quit uh back in 2020 I believe I had
been running what I called the college
infogeek podcast later called The
Emporium for eight years started it back
in 2013 and that was like a college
advice podcast kind of morphed into a
life advice podcast over the years we
talked about productivity we talked
about personal finance but after eight
years of running it both myself and my
co-host Martin kind of had this
realization that we were kind of
clocking in clocking out every other
week doing an episode and eventually we
were getting to the point where we were
trying to find topics to talk about
because we had sort of made a job of
creating content about how to improve
your life about how to be more
productive and I kind of had this
realization like at a certain point I'm
not giving myself enough time to go out
and have additional life experiences to
go out and really learn new things uh
and I was kind of presented with what I
saw as a fork in the road I saw one path
as I'll call the journalistic path where
I could remain a Creator who makes
content about self-improvement and
productivity and the way that I could
learn new things I could kind of Garner
new lessons to share with my audience
was by kind of taking on the role of a
journalist going out and interviewing
people who were like doing their own
cool things doing lots of research or I
could take the other path in the road
and I could go out and build stuff for
myself get new life experiences for a
long time I thought I could do both of
those and I was trying to deeply
research videos while also trying to
build stuff myself uh and as my past
self who has made many many videos about
Focus could tell me and you uh that's
pretty tough to do it's pretty tough to
spin a lot of plates it's much easier to
focus on one thing so we made the
deliberate decision back in 2020 to shut
down our podcast uh it was really tough
there were a lot of people who were sad
about it we were sad about it but uh
when we did it we finally let it go it
felt like this weight had been lifted
off my shoulders because I now knew that
I had time to focus on new things to go
out and learn and try new things and
build new projects uh and one of those
projects was building a second Channel
which I called Thomas Frank explains and
I called it that because I could not
think of a better name seriously my team
and I sat around a table trying to think
of names for like eight hours one day we
couldn't think of anything better uh but
I wanted to make a channel that was all
about notion if you have watched this
channel for a while then a few years ago
you probably noticed me post a few
videos about about notion it was a
productivity app that I got really into
and I'm still very much into uh and I
had so much fun making those videos that
I kind of had this idea of like what if
I made an entirely different Channel
just all about notion uh and I had a
couple of different reasons for doing
that first I just wanted something
different to do I had this Channel and
at the time every single video was
sponsored it was a great source of
income it was a great source of uh
livelihood for both myself and my team
at the time but there was a lot of
pressure it was still fun but I wanted
something that was like an outlet and
because I'm a weird nerd instead of
making my outlet like video games or
music or something it was building an
entire second Channel about a software
product a single software product but I
also had some inspiration I think back
in like 2012 or 2013 there was this guy
who made an entire website and then sold
an entire course about Evernote uh and I
knew about him because I used Evernote
back in the day and I don't remember how
much he made or how big his audience was
but I know that he was able to build a
good living for himself possibly even
for a team just making content on
Evernote because there was a big enough
audience out there for this Niche
product and they had goals that required
learning this product learning its ins
and out its tips and tricks so they were
willing to pay for the products he was
shipping out and willing to pay
attention to the content he was making
so I just had that little seed of
inspiration and I just had this
conviction like I see a lot of Buzz and
excitement about notion online I'm
personally excited about it and I think
that there's a lot of potential here for
something that could become a business I
didn't know what it was but I felt good
about it and ever since I was like a
late teenager early in college I've kind
of had this philosophy that the place
you want to be in life is the
intersection of three different points
uh one is a thing that you're good at uh
the other is something that you actually
enjoy doing and then the third is
something that has a growing and hungry
audience so if you can get yourself at
the middle of those three things uh
you're in a good spot because you're
good at it you like it and there's an
audience who is looking for Solutions
looking for products looking for
information uh at the thing that you're
good at and that you're working on so I
went and started this Channel and it was
so funny to see how I reacted to the
initial view counts because initial
videos were getting 100 to 200 views I
wasn't promoting that channel very
heavily on this channel I thought hey
this is super Niche I think my first
video was about like recurring tasks and
notion second video was even more nich
it was like a URL Handler trick that I
had found it was excited about so I
didn't talk much about that channel on
this channel I just thought let's let
the algorithm do its work but it was so
interesting just seeing how excited I
got to see a 100 views on a video than
to see like my first 500 view video on
there it was almost like Starting Over
Again from scratch and that excitement
came back initially I thought hey I'm
going to build this Channel and I'm
going to be very bored or disappointed
with the view counts because I'm already
sort of like set and calibrating ated to
the view counts on my main Channel
that's not at all what happened I
started the new project and it was just
so exciting to see the ball get rolling
once again so I was making videos on
that channel completely for fun uh and
then I had this idea hey people seem to
be interested in these videos and
there's this cool little feature in
notion where you can actually share a
page that you've created as a template
so people can basically duplicate it and
get an exact copy of that page in their
notion workspace and the other thing
that notion had really kind of
communicated in their marketing back in
2018 when I started using it was hey
it's this all-in-one app it should be
able to do task management it should be
able to do note taking it replaces all
these different singular apps you've
been using for a long time uh it's like
the whole alt and brown thing right
don't use unitaskers get yourself a good
chef's knife it can do everything so
notion is like the chef's knife or the
utility knife of productivity tools so I
kind of took that as a challenge and I
was like hey can I build a really good
task manager in notion can I build a
note taking system in notion I did the
note taking system tutorial on this
channel actually and then I built a task
manager one for Thomas Frank explains uh
and with that I kind of created a free
template people could use just to see
was their interest in this whole
template idea and could I use these
templates to start building up a
secondary email list around Thomas Frank
explains and around my notion work
because I didn't want to be constantly
spamming my huge email list that signed
up for college tips and productivity
tips with really really technical
Notions tips so I made this whole
template I made a whole video about it
that did pretty well and then something
quite interesting happened I think there
was a Saturday morning where I was bored
so I came down into my basement and I'm
like I'm going to basically build the
template from scratch all over again I'm
going to film myself doing it and I
don't even know if I'm going to post
this uh I was so not confident about
this video idea that I used a tool
called Loom to record my screen usually
I use like a very highquality screen
recorder I'll break out my really nice
camera uh to do the face cam with this I
just use Loom I use my webcam it turned
out to be like an hour long I'm like no
one's going to watch this video it's so
long it's so technical but let's just
put it up in the channel anyway that's
kind of the beauty of having a brand new
channel is you feel like there's this
freedom to try different things and
experiment again so I put that video up
there alongside the shorter video just
sort of going through what the template
could do and how to get it uh and if you
go on to Thomas Frank explains now you
can sort by popular and you can see that
the hourlong task manager tutorial is
one of the most popular videos on the
channel and it did way better than the
shorter video that I thought was going
to be more viral or whatever uh they're
way better than that in terms of views
and retention and that started telling
me Oh there's a lot of potential here
there's a lot of interest around just
making these build guides so I started
making build guides I started creating
this whole content strategy on Thomas
Frank explains and it started to become
a bigger part of my life and a bigger
part of my business I was still making
content sent over here I think this was
around you know late 2020 early 2021 but
I was really getting interested in how I
could build up this second Channel as a
niche side business at the time my
ambitions were not super huge with it I
was thinking hey maybe we could build
this up to replace one video's sponsor
spot worth of income each month so we
could kind of go you know more in depth
on the videos we're making on the main
Channel um But as time went on I just
kind of got more and more ambitious and
this leads into what I think is the real
start of the pivot that I made in mid
2021 uh there was this huge boom in what
are called cohort-based courses
basically these are like Zoom courses
where there's like a live cohort uh
Thiago Forte is building a second brain
is a great example of this Ali abdall
had a cohort for part-time YouTuber
Academy as well and you know obviously
everyone was locked inside at the time
mid 2021 so I was thinking hey I wonder
if a cohort-based course would be
something that would be a good
monetization opportunity for uh this
side channel here so I ended up taking
this is very meta I ended up taking a
course for course Builders offered by I
think it was on deck and for four weeks
I showed up to those live courses
thinking hey I'm going to learn how to
become a great teacher and a great
facilitator for cohort based courses uh
and then I'm going to go build one and
as I was going through that cohort-based
course I started to have this
realization uh I didn't want to make a
course I wanted to make a product my
original idea for the course was going
to be like notion for creators because
ever since since 2018 I've started
moving more and more of my Creator
business into notion and we eventually
got to a point where we were managing
all of what we did on a Content basis
inside of notion from idea generation to
scripting to uh managing the edit
between myself and my editor everything
was done an oce so I'm thinking hey
let's make a course on this and maybe
this could be the way we monetize Thomas
Frank explains but as I was going
through this cohort based course I
started realizing like what if I just
took the system that I built for myself
and my team turned it into a product and
sold that instead so that's what I
decided to do I basically took the
custom notion template notion system
that we had made for managing our
channels for uh scripting videos for
collecting research for managing the
edits all that kind of good stuff and I
bundled up into a template that I called
creators companion uh and this was
actually the first real product that
I've ever sold myself it feels kind of
weird to say that because I've been
doing online business since 201
I hit full-time income my blog in 2012
and ever since then I've always had
intentions of making and selling my own
products but whether due to my sponsor
schedule or my inclination to try to
make everything that I do free I just
always kind of Kick the Can down the
road so finally I was like I think that
this really makes sense as a paid tool
it's what my team and I are using for
professional level management of a
profitable Channel I think this makes
sense as a paid product and I remember
it was kind of funny at the time there
was this online discourse where there
were kind of like two different ideas
that were thrown around the first one
being no one would ever pay for a notion
template why would they do that it's so
easy to build stuff in notion yourself
uh which I disagreed with because the
stuff I was building was very
complicated required a lot of knowledge
of databases and things like that um and
then the other prevailing message was
well maybe a template is worth like $5
or something and my thought there was
I'm not excited to sell something for $5
that's kind of always been one of my
guiding uh principles actually is if I'm
not really excited about the amount of
money I think I could make selling
something I would rather just make it
free so I did the math like $5 template
how many people are possibly going to
want to buy this this is kind of a
complex Niche tool $5 doesn't make sense
let's just challenge the assumptions for
a second what's the worst thing that's
going to happen if I decide to charge
like 200 bucks for this again it's a
professional level tool it's for
professional creators who are making
money let's try charging 200 bucks if
nothing happens if nobody buys it that's
fine I already built the system for
myself I didn't invest that much more
time turning it into a product let's
just try it and we put it out there um I
tried to go back and see just how much
marketing I did around it but I know
that I really didn't do a whole lot uh
and the reason for that was I was
worried that with my big audience I was
going to ship something out there and if
I publicized it too hard people were
going to find tons of bugs and I was
going to be overwhelmed with support and
negative comments so perhaps almost too
um timidly I I just started to very very
very gradually Market this template to
bits and pieces in my email list at
first little mentions here and there on
Thomas Frank uh explains I don't think I
ever talked about it here on this main
Channel and uh within a couple of months
it was making around $3 to $5,000 a
month which was already beyond my
expectations because I wasn't doing a
lot of marketing and that was a really
cool signal because I had gotten my
first taste of what it's like to
literally build and sell my own product
build the entire sales funnel sales
pipeline myself
uh and it was a lot of fun previously I
had been working with sponsors or my
little tiny dabblings with selling
things had been like having a a create
space book on Amazon where they totally
take care of everything for you or
having like courses on skillshare again
they take care of everything for you you
just say hey go to skillshare that's it
with this it's like I got to build the
sales page I have to handle fulfillment
I have to figure out what payment
process are to use uh obviously I went
way too in depth with that and spent way
too much time Heming and Hauling over
the options because that's just kind of
how I am but eventually I got my sales
pipeline working and yeah we were making
$3 to $5,000 a month which was really
really cool and a couple of months after
that it eventually got up to around
$115,000 a month again not a whole lot
of direct marketing I wasn't really
doing ad reads for it in my videos uh
just mentions here or there but I also
had my free templates my email list and
that was a great way to uh pitch the
template to people who signed up so that
was kind of an eye opener like this is
making 15K a month it's a niche tool on
a niche uh channel that is very small
what if we did something bigger so that
is where we get to why I ended up sort
of accidentally abandoning this channel
I had an idea for another template that
I wanted to sell and this template idea
really went back to what I wanted notion
to be all the way back in 2018 when I
discovered it all the way back when I
found that homepage and they had that
all inone productivity tool tagline
there that is what I wanted because I've
spent my entire career both as a Creator
but also as a student and as somebody
who just has to get work done juggling a
whole lot of tools out there my calendar
app my to-do list app my note taking app
all kinds of stuff uh and as I started
to hire people and started working with
teams things just got very very
complicated so I wanted to build the
all-in-one productivity template I
wanted to both apply the knowledge that
I gained as a nocean template Creator
and also a lot of the new feature
releases that they had been coming out
with uh since 2018 to really try to
build that template for myself a
notetaking system a project manager a
task manager everything that I would
need to manage my life inside of a
single template so the idea was I'm
going to take March of 2022 off give
myself 30 days to build this template
then I'm going to release it and get
right back to making content for the
main channel that was the intention what
actually ended up happening was I did
actually build the template within one
month I launched it to a small wait list
on my email list uh on April 4th I want
to say and that was around 3,000 people
and with just two emails to those 3,000
people I want to say we made
$8,000 in one month and that was
legitimately more than we had ever made
in the entire life of my business I
think the most we had ever made before
then was around 70k one month a previous
year when we had done a big new
skillshare course launch and uh did a
spot about that uh course on one of my
videos so this was instantly more money
that I had ever made from all of my
other income sources combined and that
was from an email to 3,000 people uh now
granted that was 3,000 people who had
signed up to a very specific weit list
for this template so they had sort of
like opted in and shown their interest
already but still 3,000 people was all
that was needed to do 80,000 in a single
month the next month I decided not to
make a video about it yet again I was
worried about getting too many customers
too fast I didn't have a support team I
was worried about getting inundated with
support requests and having people find
bugs so I kind of wanted to slow roll it
uh so the next month I just sent an
email to my notion tips newsletter at
the time I think it was around 50,000
people so 50,000 people minus the 3,000
who had already heard about it that
email push did $90,000 in revenue and
then in I think late may I finally made
a video about it on Thomas Frank
explains and once that video went live
we started averaging between 100 and
$130,000 a month in Revenue uh from then
on which was absolutely insane I did not
expect that whatsoever um but the video
did really well and I actually had a
very interesting inspiration like point
of inspiration for making that video uh
it was actually the channel more plates
more dates of all things um which he
makes videos about like Fitness and
supplements and things like that but I
remember he had made this video about
like a pre-workout that he had developed
and it was almost an hour and a half of
content where he just goes ingredient by
ingredient
uh just going through every single thing
that is in this pre-workout talking
about like why he chose the dosage why
he chose to have it in the product what
it does in the body and I remember
watching that and I was like this is an
advertisement I know it's an
advertisement but holy crap this is
super interesting content like I'm
learning about all these different
things and compounds and how they affect
performance uh with like Athletics and
weightlifting this is like legitimately
interesting content uh and then of
course I got influenced and I bought the
product uh used it for a while but I was
inspired by The Format of that video I
was like you can make a video that is an
advertisement through and through but
it's also like valuable content on its
own and that is something that I've
always wanted for any kind of content
that I make is it needs to stand alone
it cannot just be an advertisement that
is valueless unless somebody buys the
product that it's pitching uh and that
was a big point of like ethical concern
with my my main Channel since I was
talking about productivity and life
advice and things like that I wanted to
make sure no sponsor no product pitch
know nothing could ever be the main
focus of a video every video had to be
something useful had to have something
you could take away for free so that
video was a huge inspiration because I
realized like the entire thing is kind
of advertising as product but holy crap
it's still super educational so I
thought okay let's make a video like
that about ultimate brain I'm going to
show every single part of the template
so if somebody wants to they could
replicate it entirely for themselves
I've got all these tutorials on Thomas
Frank explains that are completely free
I had striven to make that a completely
endtoend like everything you could ever
want to know about notion should be
there as a tutorial kind of channel so
my thought was I think this will be a
good advertisement for the template but
I'm not going to really pitch it hard
until the end and otherwise I just want
to show everything I want to show people
like here's how you could structure an
all-in-one productivity tool for
yourself here's why it's so beneficial
to say have a project dashboard and when
you go into a project you can see both
your tasks and your notes for that
project gives you a single point of
reference for both all the information
and context but also everything you need
to do and that's more useful than having
it kind of spread out between different
apps so I wanted to show people the
architecture the thought behind it give
them inspiration for building things
themselves but also sort of say like hey
if you don't want to build this for
yourself if you want the faster option
if you want us to do it for you then you
can go ahead and buy it and that video
you can go to Thomas Frank explains if
you want and check the popular uh
sorting option I think it is the most
popular video on the channel it's
getting near a million views so that
just sort of made things explode and
like I said earlier we were doing
between 100 and 130k in Revenue per
month uh just off of that video and then
the sort of like email funnel we had
built as well with our free templates
but getting to sort of the next part of
the story the reason that I didn't come
back to this channel uh was I ended up
doing customer support 8 hours a day or
more more fulltime for 2 months after
that template launched because you know
you get those kind of good problems when
you have a successful product launch uh
and in our case it was tons and tons of
support requests uh I had done as much
bug testing as I could I had uh made
over six hours actually of tutorial
videos and I made like a whole
interactive uh version of the template
that had dummy data all kinds of stuff
but with a tool like notion there is a
lot of customizability there are a lot
of people who get excited about a
template like this even if they're new
to the product and don't really
understand it very well so support
inqueries are going to be inevitable and
a big decision that I decided to make
before I even launched Creator's
companion was I want to have active
support a lot of template creators out
there just give out the template or they
sell it maybe they have some
documentation but that's kind of it and
I didn't want that because I knew from
listening to my commenters and
interacting with them on the channel
itself that notion is complex that it's
easy to get stuck and I really wanted to
make sure that people were going to have
as good of an experience as possible
another thing maybe I'll come back to
this a little bit later we also offer
refunds for our templates and that
sounds kind of weird to some people
because it's impossible to return a
digital product uh there's no license
keys this isn't SAS you duplicate the
template and you have a perfect copy of
it forever but I wanted to offer refunds
and I wanted to offer active support
because one of my core tenants one of my
values as a business person is everyone
who purchases from us must have a good
experience so that means our product
needs to be excellent our support needs
to be excellent because if people get
stuck and they want to continue we need
to have an Avenue for that uh but we
also need to offer refunds because if
somebody purchases there's going to be a
certain percentage who realize this
isn't the product for me maybe it's just
not the right time in my life right now
I wanted to make sure those people had a
way to get their money back so there's
no way anybody could ever be truly
dissatisfied or feel like they were put
out because it was the wrong product for
them so we offer
uh refunds we offered active support and
in the beginning active support was just
me I had a team but everyone on my team
at the time wasn't really a notion
expert we all used notion but I was the
only one who was sort of sitting in my
basement on Saturday mornings learning
how to fiddle with databases and writing
notion formulas and all that kind of
crazy stuff so it was up to me to do the
support requests and I did that full
time for about two months uh I actually
think that was a very very useful thing
to do because that sort of gave me a
different perspective on the product and
if anybody watching this if you were
watching this and you want to build your
own products maybe like a SAS product
eventually or your own notion templates
whatever it is I would highly encourage
you to do customer support for a couple
of months after you launch at least a
couple of months because as the builder
of the product or as the CEO you're
going to have a very different
perspective than your customers are
going to have you have the architect's
eye and uh that sort of involves What's
called the expert Paradox where experts
get so good at something that uh the
things that are hard for a beginner are
almost like breathing to the expert it's
so unconscious they don't even think
about it anymore so by doing support you
really gain greater perspective on your
product you help your customers who are
stuck but you also get insights that you
can use to go and improve that product
that you just couldn't get yourself so
go ahead and do support for yourself uh
but I eventually got to a point where
I'm like there are other things I want
to do ideally I want to get back to this
Channel and start filming again but
there's some other things I want to do
so I think it's time to hire my first
like actual support person uh and I kind
of want to talk about the way that I
hired and if anybody watching this needs
to hire support for their own products
or maybe even for YouTube channel um I
think this is a good method so basically
what I did is I put together a test that
I anticipated the right kind of
candidate who had the right kind of
notion product experience would be able
to finish in 10 minutes so honestly like
not even as long as your average job
application for the right canidate but
it had two main components so there was
a building challenge I basically had
like a test in there I was like hey I
need a two database setup there's going
to be a meetings database and a CRM I
need you to show I think it was like the
last meeting date for each person in the
CRM so that required a little bit of
notion formula knowledge a little bit of
filters and rollups all kinds of like
stuff that anybody who's going to be
doing notion support needs to know that
was my product knowledge test but then I
had the other test which secretly in the
back of my head head was the more
important one and that was two sample
support questions from some fictional
characters and I asked candidates to
answer those support questions as if
they were talking to those characters
and what I was looking for there was not
necessarily perfect product knowledge
that was a plus but the real things I
was looking for are number one empathy
and number two the ability to anticipate
the next question these are in my
opinion the two uh out of the three I
think two out of the three most
important qualities that anybody doing
any kind of customer support needs to
have the other one is uh solution
finding ability so not necessarily preet
product knowledge but you know the
ability to Google well the ability to
use chat gbt these days the ability to
find references that's very important um
but empathy and anticipation are the
other two that are mega mega important
so number one you know I learned this
when I was working in the IT Tech
Support Department at my college back
when I was 18 19 years old you have to
be empathy athetic with the person who
is asking the question you cannot make
them feel stupid because they're going
to come out of it with a bad experience
so I was looking for like actual
empathetic answers like hey yeah I've
been this I've been there before uh yeah
this can be really easy to overlook the
product's kind of confusing let me help
you out the other thing I was looking
for was anticipation so this is another
thing that I learned in tech support
often the question that the person comes
to you with is not the question that
they're actually trying to get answered
it's just the first step in a process so
a good support person needs to be able
to identify the actual goal that the
person has and ideally they can
anticipate the next question that is
going to come after they answer the
question that has been asked so what I
was looking for there was did you not
only answer the question that was posed
but did you also anticipate the next
follow-up question and include your
answer there because that is the
Hallmark of efficiency support you are
getting people to their goal much more
quickly uh side note to the side note
this is also a very good quality to have
just as an individual for example if you
get an email or a message from your
co-worker they're asking you a question
if you can anticipate what their next
question is and include that information
so easy example like are you available
to meet next week the obvious follow-up
question is when are you available to
meet next week so instead of saying yes
I'm available and waiting for the
follow-up it's like yes I'm available
Tuesday Thursday uh from the 3 to 5H
hour window
that is anticipation of the follow-up
question and that is anticipation of the
actual goal so I put that test out there
uh and this guy Alex was my top
candidate uh and it turned out that he
actually was one of the founders of the
notion subreddit so I was very excited
to hire him and he came on and he just
started kicking absolute ass like he is
amazing uh and it was so amazing to to
hire somebody who was so good at support
and so interested in connecting and
building community that I think Within
just a couple of weeks support was
almost no longer a concern that I had to
think about actively I didn't have to go
in and like check all the threads make
sure that the answers were good he was
so good off the bat that it allowed me
to go focus on other things and this I
think is the ultimate uh benefit the
ultimate thing you're looking for like
the Holy Grail of hiring is that you can
hire somebody who is so good so
passionate who takes such good ownership
over their area in the company that you
totally trust to handle it you know that
they're going to go above and beyond and
that gives you the freedom to go focus
on growing the business or focusing on
the things that you are the absolute
best at and Alex has been amazing at
that Ben Smith also a huge influence in
Ocean Community he came on as our second
support guy and then Alex and Ben have
also started taking on bigger projects
they are actually helping me do upgrades
on the templates they're doing
documentation they have both
demonstrated that they have the ability
to not only take on new projects but
suggest improvements that are really
really well thought thought out and that
has just been so awesome to experience
as a business owner uh especially one
like me who really just kind of wants to
be like the Tony Stark in the cave with
a box of scraps that's another big thing
that I've learned about myself over
these past couple of years is like
managing people and making tons and tons
of decisions all day long is not really
what I want to be doing I want to be off
in my own little corner building things
and then I want to come onto the camera
every once in a while and kind of show
it off so it's been really really cool
to be able to hire people who can just
take ownership of their area of the
company and just be excellent at it
which has been super super amazing to
experience so we built that uh and then
you know once again I anticipated
getting right back to the main Channel
but part of my problem is even though I
know it would probably be more
profitable to make lots of videos about
topics that are going to go viral uh to
really lean into the whole influencer
thing um part of my problem which I will
Embrace and uh not even call a problem
really is is I am just very fascinated
by technical things so after sort of
like the chaos calmed down from the
ultimate brain launch and building out
our support department uh I had this
idea and it started out as a video idea
actually but it ballooned into what
ended up being a four-month project but
I had this idea I was like I want to
teach notion formulas if you don't know
what these are basically in notion
there's a database function looks kind
of like Excel tables and like Excel
there's a formula function where you can
like do math and you can do all kind of
stuff it's almost like programming uh at
the time noan hadn't really done
documentation for their formulas so a
lot of people weren't really sure how to
use them uh and I ended up spending a
lot of my time on the notion subreddit
just answering formula questions because
I found it fun so I had this idea let's
make this video about notion formulas
and I wanted to do it in that like five
levels of complexity style and I think
I'm still going to do it but uh spoiler
alert I have not made that video yet
because I got this idea that hey
wouldn't it be interesting if there was
like a bonus resource to go along with
that video like maybe it's like a
formula cheat sheet something that would
show a simple example of what every
function in the formula language
actually does I let that idea snowball
into me writing like Mozilla level
technical documentation for the entire
formulus language it ended up taking me
four months of work I wrote 45,000 words
of documentation made like a hundred
different example databases uh deeply
learned that formula language and ended
up publishing it on my website it's
still there it has been now updated for
the new formulas language uh Ben on my
team did the full update so that is now
more his project than mine but yeah
45,000 words of documentation four
months of effort and that just sort of
kept happening I think that is what I
could encapsulate as the theme Here the
reason that I sort of kept kicking the
can down the road for coming back to
this channel is I kept finding these
interesting technical problems s that I
knew would be useful for my audience if
I solved they were fun for me and they
also helped our business like if I make
additional notion content not only is
that another way that we can Market our
templates the one thing that we sell
that actually makes us money uh but it
also helps to build up our library of
content uh that I think I kind of forgot
to mention this but I do want to bring
it up uh that was my guiding principle
with Thomas Frank explains the idea
there was to go and build the go-to
channel for the notion Niche I sort of
had this idea like if you think notion
or if you think I want to answer a
question that I have about notion you
should immediately think of Thomas Fring
explains so that was the idea there and
to really accomplish that goal the
channel needed to have highquality
content covering anything that a ocean
user might want to do from the absolute
basics of building pages and linking to
things to the higher-end stuff like
formulas and like the notion API and
everything else so I went ahead and I
built that uh notion formula
documentation and then went right into
the next way too big project that I did
not anticipate being so big when I
started it uh and that was the notion
API the notion API is basically like
this set of tools that programmers can
use to connect an otion up to different
things um if you're curious about what
it can do I think the coolest
application of it right now that I've
come up with is I have a little
automation where I can record a voice
note on my phone and using the notion
API and also some AI tools from like
chat gbt and Whisper I get a full
summary I get a full transcript I get
lists of main points and action items
and things just for my voice notes so at
this point I can just like go for a half
an hour walk I can record an idea in my
head or I can talk to my phone and I get
the whole thing as a note and notion uh
that video is live so I'll go ahead and
link to that in the description if you
are curious about it but yeah that's an
example of what the notion API could do
and again going back to the mission of
Thomas Frank explains if I was going to
to accomplish that mission of building
the go-to resource for the notion Niche
it needed to teach the API as well the
only problem is I didn't know how to
code I'd made a couple of videos about
how you could do like no code things
with the API using like zapier and
make.com uh no code tools like that but
again that wasn't good enough I needed
to have a video on the channel That
would teach the notion API so I started
teaching myself JavaScript I started
completely from scratch and that was
about a year a year and two months ago
uh and at this point I think I've
actually become a pretty confident
backend JavaScript developer I've got a
whole video in the works about my coding
Journey that'll probably be within the
next two videos I release on this
channel so I'm not going to go too much
into how I did that uh with this video
but I've kind of become a programmer at
this point it's really fun I keep
getting ideas for things I want to build
so that's part of the reason I haven't
been on this channel in a while uh but
yeah back in I think it was like July
2022 I started with free Cod code camps
free Javascript course at the absolute
Basics learning how to set variables and
build loops and all that kind of stuff
very quickly abandon that course after
the first couple of modules because I
learned enough to start actually going
out and building I think that is a very
important principle in learning any
skill but especially how to code you got
to get a project you care about uh as
quick as possible and the project I
cared about at the time was I wanted to
teach the notion API so I took another
about three full months to build a
single video on Thomas Frank explains
ended up being 2 hours long where I
teach people how to build a full
pokeddex from scratch with no manual
data entry whatsoever pulling all of the
Pokemon data from uh poke API and use
that to teach the notion API uh I ended
up also writing I think it was like a
30,000 word blog post that is almost
like a beginner coding tutorial on its
own as well so that took up about 3
months and now on the channel we have uh
what I'm going to call one of like the
infinity gems in The Gauntlet for that
channel the notion a API tutorial is
there uh little did I know that I was
going to catch the programming bug and
now I spend a lot of my time programming
that voice notes automation that I
talked about a while ago that's around 2
200 lines of code it is actively
developed it's got GitHub repo like I've
kind of gotone the whole nine yards with
programming and it's been a lot of fun I
spend a lot of my time doing it now I've
built a lot of automations uh I use
primarily a platform called pipe dream
to do it it's kind of like zappier but
you can actually write JavaScript code
and another cool thing that I like about
it is I can actually share my workflows
with other people so it's almost like
being able to ship many apps to people
and I can even update them which is
pretty sweet but I don't have to like
build my own servers or deploy to Amazon
or all that stuff that I have not
learned how to do yet so that's pretty
cool uh and that I think explains a lot
of 2023 it's been uh pretty quiet on the
content front not because I haven't been
doing anything but because the videos
that I've been working on are sort of
like mini software projects in Disguise
and they always take a lot longer than I
think they're going to take case in
point another automation that I made was
uh adding voice tasks to notion so I now
have an automation on my phone where I
can click a little shortcut I can record
as many tasks as I want actually and
they're all going to go into notion with
their names their due dates their
assignes their projects I thought that
was going to be a two-e project ended up
taking me four months I don't really
regret it because I learned a lot about
coding learned a ton of advanced
concepts like concurrency and error
handling and all sorts of stuff that I
really didn't think I'd be getting into
this early into my journey uh but that
took about 4 months so that about brings
us up to today uh and I want to talk now
about what I've got planned for the
future both for this channel but also
for the entire business that I'm running
I just want to talk about the one that
I'm most excited about right now and
that is the new startup that we are
building it is called fly lighter and it
is going to be the best information and
idea capture tool you have ever seen we
are starting out with a notion Web
Clipper that is far more powerful than
Notions official Web Clipper or any
other Web Clipper out there so if you
are on a web page and you want to save
it you want to highlight text on that
page you want to capture an image you
want to do basically any sort of
information capture on the web fly lter
gives you a bunch of tools to not only
build these very very highly customized
capture abilities you can even like take
YouTube notes with uh timestamps to the
notes uh but also it is built for Speed
you can set up these flows and then the
moment you click a flow it'll just
instantly capture with your settings
we've been building this tool for almost
a year actually more than a year at this
point I think I hired my first developer
in August of last year actually uh and
this started out as like a very very
small idea that ballooned into something
much much bigger uh originally I had
just wanted a notion Web Clipper that
number one had better abilities to
capture like certain uh like folders in
my notion basically but number two that
use the official API because there are
other tools out there that are pretty
good but they use like non-official apis
that I'm not super comfortable with
because they kind of like hijack your
user session so I wanted to build a tool
that used the correct API uh that was
security focused privacy focused uh and
then I hired my developer Eli and we
just started bouncing ideas off of each
other uh he had all these great ideas
for like Advanced table capture and web
element capture and all this kind of
cool stuff and then I had ideas a really
big one that I had is I wanted to be
able to highlight text on a web page uh
for like blog post research or video
research capture those highlights to
notion like you would with a readwise or
a similar tool but then if you go back
to that web page you see the highlights
still so we are building it there are
going to be a heck of a lot of other
features in the product we are building
a full iPhone app what I want to do is
solve capture if you have an idea
wherever you are there should be a tool
for instantly capturing that idea using
Voice using text uh but also if you come
across something on the web you should
also be able to instantly capture that
add it to your second brain so you can
close that Tab and be sure that you can
find it later this is a big problem I
have if you ask anyone I know who has
ever seen my computer screen they'll
tell you I often have like a 100 tabs
open uh and a lot of those tabs are just
like tabs I didn't want to lose and I
haven't found a found a good enough tool
yet to capture them to my tool of choice
which is notion so we're building it and
I'm telling you now uh very early in
what I will call our like release
process you've been working on this tool
for a year but we are now I think
nearing the end of our private beta so
if you go over to fighter.com there is a
weight list sign up and as soon as we
can we are going to be releasing a
browser extension that you can use on
Chrome and Edge and any chromium based
browser and then ideally quickly after
that we're going to have a basic iPhone
app that is going to be uh from day one
the best Web Clipper for notion but
eventually a heck of a lot more than
that I've got tons of ideas um and if
you've seen some of the tutorials and
projects I've been doing on Thomas Frank
explains you might be able to
extrapolate what we are planning on
adding to fly lighter as time goes on uh
I'm also planning on building this kind
of in public as much as I can I'm not an
indie hacker building this on my own so
I do have to think about the fact that
there is a bigger audience here and I
don't want to like bring too many people
into the product before it's ready so
there's definitely going to be some
navigation there that I have to do but I
want to share this experience with you I
want to actually document the experience
of trying to build a profitable privacy
focused startup that doesn't take VC
money um that is really focused on
giving you the ability to send your data
where you want to send it we don't want
to be another one of those startups that
is like the place that actually holds
your data um I'm not comfortable with
that in the first place but also I think
that there are already so many great
tools out there uh with notion being my
focus for for having your data where you
want it for building it the way you want
for organize it the way you want and you
know a lot of my business is around
teaching people how to use notion so
what we want to do is solve the first
part of the funnel the capture part of
the funnel uh once again you can go over
to flyer.com and sign up for our waiting
list if you are interested in testing it
out and using it once we have a full
launch uh beyond that what I've got
planned for this channel is uh a bit of
a mix of content I have a lot more I
want to say and a lot more I want to
teach when it comes to productivity so
you're going to see a good mix of
productivity videos in the future but
I've also spent a lot of my time over
the past couple of years learning how to
code becoming an expert in no code tools
and building my business so this channel
is going to kind of delve into some of
those topics as well one of the videos
that I'm working on right now is on how
I learned how to code um I've got a
couple of business related videos as
well so this channel is going to be kind
of like an entrepreneur Cod productivity
Focus Channel going forward if that's
your kind of thing I think you're going
to like the content that we are building
my only real call to action for this
video other than going and signing up
for the fly lighter weit list if you are
interested is if you want to learn
notion I've got lots of content that is
coming out regularly over on Thomas
Frank explains so check that out if you
do want to become an expert at that tool
if you do want an all-in-one
productivity system for notion you can
check out ultimate brain over at thomasj
frank.com
brain uh and beyond that if you have
questions at some point I might do like
an AMA on Twitter or I might do some
like more talky content like this in the
future so let me know in the comments
what kind of stuff you would like to see
in the future what questions you have
that'll help me shape additional content
ideas and I'll see you in the next video
oh if you want to chat Tom frankley on
Twitter