thanks to brilliant for sponsoring this
video and supporting my channel over the
course of a couple of days last week I
put together this little song that
you're hearing and watching on the
screen right now I composed it I
recorded it and mixed it on my computer
and then I shot this little music video
which tied together the entire thing and
I am absolutely stoked that I actually
finished this song because even though
I've been playing guitar for more than
10 years and even though I have wanted
to be a musician for a very long time I
find it very difficult to actually
finish music projects I get song ideas
all the time if you look at my voice
notes app on my phone there are
literally hundreds of voice memos that
are made just singing song ideas into my
phone I am very good at starting music
projects I'm very good at having ideas
I'm not so good at finishing those
projects and actually putting them out
into the world and I know that this is
not something that is unique to me and
it is not something that is unique to
musicians a lot of people including
probably you if you clicked on this
video have trouble finishing the
projects that they start in your case it
might be a book that you're trying to
write or an art project you're trying to
finish or maybe even a YouTube channel
you're trying to get off the ground
whatever it is if you're anything like
me you start off with a great idea and a
lot of energy but eventually you get
into the project and you're so inundated
with choices that you could make that
you just feel paralyzed you fall victim
to what's called analysis paralysis and
that leads to you never finishing and in
many cases abandoning the project and
well there may be other factors to blame
here I truly believe is the abundance of
choice more than any other factor that
causes most of us to abandon the
projects we start especially personal
projects that don't have real deadlines
too much choice can make us unproductive
it can paralyze us there's actually
scientific evidence to back this up back
in 2002 just give you one example there
was a study done where they set up these
two booths for people to sample
different types of jams in supermarkets
one booth had only six types of jam to
sample and the other booth had 24 now
buthe that had 24 jams had 150 percent
more visitors but only three percent of
those people actually bought a jar jam
meanwhile over at the booth that just
had six types of jam thirty percent of
the people who walked up and tried
something ended up buying a jar and
going home with it and if too much
choice can affect our buying decisions
negatively then it absolutely affects
our tendency to take action on our
projects as well so at this point the
answer to this problem should hopefully
be obvious you have to create
limitations for yourself
good limitations reduce the number of
choices that you have which reduces
analysis paralysis and makes it much
more likely that you'll actually finish
the projects that you take on so here
are four different types of limitations
that you can apply to your projects the
first one is going to be good ol time
limits and deadlines I find time
pressure to be one of the most actions
spurring types of limitations that I can
apply to any project and it necessarily
reduces the choices that you can make
because you don't have very much time in
which to make those choices and when
you're under time pressure you often
have to go by instinct just go with
whatever looks best now this isn't
always good to apply to a project some
projects really need breathing room
really need time for you to kind of sit
back and think and cycle between intense
work periods and periods of rest where
you can kind of ruminate on your
progress but if you find yourself
habitually abandoning projects then it
can be worthwhile to go through the
exercise of doing a project under a
strict time limit a great example of
this is the ubiquitous one-hour song
challenge that you've probably seen here
on YouTube by youtubers like Andrew
Huang and Jared dines a lot of these
people have done this challenge
and while the songs that come out of it
aren't always the best it's a great
exercise and it proves to them that they
can make something that is a song in
under an hour and actually used a
deadline for my little Instagram song as
well I gave myself two days to finish it
and yeah it's 45 seconds but it's
actually done and that actually brings
us to our second type of limitation
which is the scope limitation it can be
very useful to take on projects that
have a purposefully limited scope even
if
don't seem as epic or grand as you would
really like them to be actually made a
video about this it was called how to
make progress on your goals I think and
that video is kind of a case study of a
couple of different people Neal
Stephenson who is an author and Matthew
Thorson who is a video game developer
both of whom kind of cut their teeth on
smaller projects which gave them the
ability to tackle much bigger projects
later on in their careers and this is
exactly what you can do as well often
times you're trying to bring together a
ton of different skills that are all
necessary to complete a project but you
haven't mastered any of them which again
makes the whole process kind of
overwhelming so if you take on tiny
little projects they are sort of like a
training ground for you to develop your
skills make them habitual and then
applied them to more challenging
projects in the future our third
limitation is the limitation of the
tools that you have available to you and
this can be really really important
especially if you're doing something
where you have a ton of tools at your
disposal as a musician who has a
computer right over there with lots of
virtual instruments and a bunch of real
instruments sitting in this room with me
I have a ton of choice when it comes to
composing a song and that can be a bad
thing sometimes when I'm creating a song
I can kind of just get overwhelmed with
a number of instruments I have at my
disposal so with my little Instagram
song I used my acoustic guitar which is
my favorite instrument and then I told
myself I am only allowed to use one
virtual instrument to kind of flesh out
the song so I chose a little virtual
piano called Noir and I doubled the
chords that I used and just kind of
added a little bit of low end and that
was it in addition with the music video
I could have used all the cameras all
the gear I have in the studio but for me
music videos are something completely
new and as somebody who makes mainly
educational videos everything I've seen
and the music videos I've watched has
again been a little bit overwhelming as
somebody who wants to get into it so for
this song I told myself I can only use
that one wall over there and I can only
use one single camera that was it and
the interesting thing is when you reduce
the amount of tools you have available
well as they say necessity is the mother
of all
vention and when you have a very limited
toolset you tend to use it a little bit
more creatively so that's another side
benefit finally we have a limitation
that you may not have thought of before
which is to restrict your ability to
undo now being able to undo your
mistakes can be great for many reasons
but it can also have a downside because
when you can easily just hit ctrl Z on
any mistake that you make then it
becomes very easy to let perfectionism
take over additionally because you know
you can always hit undo it basically
becomes impossible to get yourself into
that slightly high pressure state where
you know that there are stakes and I
think it's really important to spend at
least some of your time in that state to
feel like everything is on the line
right now and that you can't hit undo I
mean right now I'm filming this in my
studio with nobody around which means
that I can flub line after line and it
doesn't really matter my editors are so
to cut out the crap and well sometimes
it's actually a bad thing when I speak
onstage at conferences I don't screw up
because people are watching me I can't
just edit things out I have to get it
right which means that I honestly feel a
little bit more eloquent and there is
something to be said for the analog
methods that we used to use to create
art back in the day musicians had to
record onto tape which meant that they
had to play their part right the first
time there was no such thing as
overdubbing there was no such thing as
comping and artists and authors had to
do the exact same thing and author had
to commit to typing what was going to go
on that piece of paper when they used a
typewriter unless they wanted to retype
an entire page or use whiteout I guess
and artists had to commit to the
brushstrokes they were putting onto
their canvas either it was right the
first time or as Bob Ross would say it
became a happy little accident but when
you use a computer to create you
introduce the choice to undo literally
every single action you take and those
choices can again overwhelm you so if
you really want to push your creativity
and ensure that you finish try
restricting your ability to undo either
do a project in a completely analog
format or temporarily set your undo key
binding to a keyboard shortcut that
you're not used to now you don't have to
go overboard and use the
on every project that you start but
again if you find yourself abandoning a
lot of projects and you want to see
yourself finishing the more often than
try introducing some limits not only
will help you get rid of the analysis
paralysis that is caused by too much
choice but many times it'll also help
you think more creatively as well and if
you want to further improve that
creative thinking ability which can not
only help you in your own projects but
in your career as well then spend time
regularly solving tough problems that
require creative thinking brilliant is a
great source of problems like these
especially if you also want to improve
your mastery of math science or computer
science they have a library of more than
60 in-depth courses that guide you
through these subjects in a active
problem-based approach that throws you
into challenging yet bite-sized and
logically ordered problems that help you
to stay interested but also improve more
quickly because you're working actively
with material instead of just taking it
in passively in their library you're
gonna find a full math suite with
courses ranging from algebra to number
theory to more advanced things like
probability and statistics differential
equations computer science courses like
Python programming and the basics of
computer memory and even search engines
and science courses like classical
mechanics and gravitational physics so
if you want to start learning today and
improving your ability to creatively
solve tough problems head over brilliant
org slash Thomas Frank and sign up and
if you're one of the first 200 people to
use that link which you'll find it down
in the description below you're even
gonna get 20% off their annual premium
subscription thanks so much for watching
hopefully you found this video helpful I
know that this idea of using limitations
has really helped me in my own work and
in my ability to finish my own creative
projects so hopefully it is useful to
you as well and if you did find it
useful then maybe consider gently fist
bumping that like button to show the
YouTube algorithm what's up you can also
get subscribed right over here if you
haven't done so already and check out a
couple of other videos on this channel
which will be somewhere on the screen
hopefully not covering my face because
that's what I used to talk but you know
maybe right over here right over here if
you smash your face into the phone
screen then you will be able to activate
those videos and watch them but if you
don't want to do that as always go do
whatever you want cuz I'm not your dad