hey what's going on guys so today we are
pitting new technology versus old
technology because a lot of you guys
have been asking me to compare the iPad
pro to a regular old notebook when it
comes to the task of note-taking and
since I have owned my iPad pro for
several months now I feel qualified to
answer this question so in this video
I'm going to break down the strengths
and weaknesses of each one and give you
a conclusion but I am gonna shake things
up a bit and give you my conclusion
right up front because having tested
both of these things at least for me the
iPad pro with all of its awesome
features quality of life improvements
connections to the cloud doesn't beat
the writing experience of good
old-fashioned paper now I will say that
writing on the iPad pro with an Apple
pencil is hands-down no question the
best digital writing experience I have
ever had though I do have to admit that
I have not yet written on the surface
from Microsoft so if you have written on
both I would love to hear from you down
in the comments but the iPad pro vs.
Palm Pilots versus laptops that are
two-in-ones with styluses versus the old
ipad with one of those stylus as you
bought from the store with a little
squishy nub on the end
it's better than all of them by a mile
however it still doesn't beat the
experience of writing on actual paper
though I do want to mention that I've
kinda ditched normal dead tree type
paper for something called the rocket
book which is actually an erasable
notebook you can take a wet rag and
erase everything that you've written on
the pages and then the cool thing about
the rocket book is that every single
page has this little QR code on it
along with a row of icons so you can
actually set up their app to scan pages
and send them to different digital
destinations based on which icon you
marked so if you had maybe six different
Evernote notebooks for your classes
you could actually set each of those
icons to be for one of your classes and
make it really easy to digitize your
notes and still write them down on paper
but I digress this is not a video about
the rocket book this is a video about
the iPad pro versus paper and I've
already talked about the writing
experience so the rest of this video is
going to be about some of the features
you can get by taking notes on the iPad
pro so if you are the kind of person who
can get used to the writing experience
with the Apple pencil if you're not like
me and you think they're basically
equivalent then let's talk about some of
the things that you do get with the iPad
pro as well as one particular use case
where the iPad
Pro absolutely outshines the competition
and where I personally use it and to
start we have to talk about apps because
if you get a brand new iPad pro out of
the box I don't think there's a default
app on the system that lets you write
and take notes really nicely with the
pencil correct me if I'm wrong down in
the comments but I don't think there is
one so you have to go find a third-party
app and the app that I have found to be
the absolute best combination of
features and usability personally at
least this in my opinion is called Note
shelf two now with Note shelf two you
get a note shelf of notebooks and when
you open up a notebook you get a pretty
convincing piece of notebook paper to
write on and immediately as I was
writing on my piece of notebook paper
here with my Apple pencil I started to
notice one really cool feature that you
get with the iPad pro and that has to do
with the iPads ability to split screen
different apps you can actually devote
one-half of the screen to your note
shelf to app and the other half of the
screen to maybe a textbook that's been
digitized or the slides of your lecture
if they're available to you or maybe
just some research online that you're
using for a paper you have to write
having your notes on one side of the
screen and your research on the other
side of the screen and being able to
actually write on that screen is pretty
darn cool and what's even cooler with
notes shelf two you can actually copy
any piece of text in another app hold
down the pencil and then drag that text
into your notes automatically and this
is a really cool feature you can resize
the text box you can mark it up annotate
it draw over it do whatever you want
this is a really cool feature for taking
pieces of research and creating a nice
little collection of them in your notes
additionally note shelf two has lots of
different pen options you can change the
pen thickness you can change it to a
mechanical pencil style you can change
the color you can save favorites there
is a lot you can do with the pen tool
here and if you don't feel like writing
you can actually open up a text tool
pair a bluetooth keyboard to your iPad
and mix typed notes with written notes
with the pencil and something else that
actually just happened my app just
updated and told me about it you can
also convert your handwriting to text so
if you want the experience of
handwriting but you wanted to be nice
legible text this app will now do that
so that's an overview of note shelfs
note-taking features but that's not all
it can do because you can actually
import PDFs and other documents into
note shelf and then mark them up and
annotate them with the pencil and this
is the use case where the iPad pro beats
every single other tool out there from
purposes I've marked up bank statements
with it to figure out spending patterns
and as an even better example I've
imported my entire book ten steps
earning awesome grades as a PDF into
this app so I can mark up the typos I
wrote this book three years ago and as
many of you guys have pointed out to me
there are still typos in the book
because I foolishly tried to edit it
myself
so a couple of times the recent past
I've headed over to a coffee shop I've
got myself coffee and I've pulled out
the iPad and the pencil and opened up my
PDF and then setting the pencil to a red
setting I've gone through every page the
book looking for typos and things that I
want to change now this is clearly
better than printing out the entire book
and trying to mark it up with a pen
because I'm not killing a bunch of trees
but I can also bookmark pages in this
app so every single time I find an error
I've bookmarked that page and then once
I'm done marking up the entire book I'll
be able to open up the absol drawer of
bookmarked pages and I'll be able to see
every single page that has an error and
I'll be able to omit any page that
doesn't have an error and breaking away
from notes shelf two for a second this
is a huge strength of the iPad pro
overall the pencil is an amazing
highlighting tool and it highlights
really well in basically any note-taking
and reading app including iBooks and
Kindle additionally with both of those
apps you get the ability to write notes
on top of your highlights in those books
so that can be a really nice way to add
your thoughts to a space that you've
highlighted going back to notes shelf
two you might be thinking that all of
your note-taking is going to be siloed
into this app but that is not the case
because notes shelf two actually has
lots of options for automatically
exporting your notes to basically
wherever you want to send them you can
export to Google Drive you can export a
Dropbox and you can export to Evernote
and the integration with Evernote is
particularly tight because you can
select the individual notebook that you
want to be exporting your notes to note
that currently there doesn't seem to be
a way to export notes to an existing
notebook within Evernote that has a
content in it rather the notebook within
note shelf will create its own notebook
in Evernote so you might want to start
using the notebook that note shelf
creates for your typed notes as well so
overall if you decide to take your notes
on an iPad pro you do get a lot of extra
features whether using Note shelf two or
some other app there's a lot you can do
that you can't do on a standard paper
notebook like I mentioned earlier the
writing experience on paper is still so
good for me that I'm going to go ahead
and just omit all those little
quality-of-life improvements except for
the aforementioned PDF annotating but
if you're the kind of person that can
get used to riding with that Apple
pencil and you like it just as much as
writing on a paper notebook then the
iPad pro does offer a lot though it does
have to be said that an iPad pro costs
hundreds of dollars possibly even more
than thousand if you get the top model
and a paper notebook is like what a
dollar from Walmart the rocket book is
about thirty four dollars though since
you can wipe it away it should
eventually pay for itself and in both
cases they are far and away cheaper than
the iPad pro anyway I'm curious to hear
your thoughts down in the comments about
the iPad pro if you have experience with
it if you have experience with other
apps that I haven't talked about here or
if you have experience with another
device like a Microsoft Surface let your
opinions be known in the comments down
below to give people other perspectives
if you enjoyed this video go ahead and
hit that like button to support this
channel and you also might want to go
follow me over on Instagram I'm Tom
frankly over there and this video was
actually supposed to be an IG TV video
at first but I realized it was actually
a pretty great topic for a YouTube video
so we kind of converted it but I am
working on lots of new IG TV videos
answering your DMS with them and they're
gonna be a lot more intimate kind of
off-the-cuff answers and they're gonna
come a lot more frequently than the
videos on this channel so definitely go
follow me over there beyond that you
should also subscribe right there if you
haven't done so already so you don't
miss future videos when they come out
and you can also grab a free copy of my
book ten steps to earning awesome grades
which I talked about in this video the
typos aren't too bad there's not that
many of them and it's free so click
right there to get it otherwise you can
watch one more video on this channel by
clicking right over there thanks for
watching and I'll see you in the next
one