when you're learning a new skill there
are three different types of progress
gear acquisition
conceptual learning and deliberate
practice and of those three in the very
beginning
gear acquisition provides the biggest
perceived jump in your progress
after all to get started you have to get
the tools needed to do the thing but a
lot of people get stuck in this stage
and they fall victim to what's called
gear acquisition syndrome where they
keep buying new and better gear because
they think it's gonna make them better
but they shouldn't
because with gear there is a very real
law of diminishing returns
the real progress in any skill anything
you could learn
happens with deliberate practice putting
in the reps and getting the feedback
that you need
a lot of people also get stuck in
conceptual learning just one more course
one more book
one more podcast episode they never go
apply the lessons they're learning
for themselves if you want to make real
progress if you want to actually achieve
mastery then you have to put in
the reps so get the minimum viable gear
learn what you need to learn up front
and then go
and do the work