this video is sponsored by brilliant be
one of the first 200 people to sign up
at a link below to get 20% off your
annual premium subscription take a
second and imagine the burners on a
stovetop the flames that danced on those
burners are created by a supply of gas
and using that gas you can crank one
burner up to full routing all the gas to
it and creating a single bright flame or
you can choose to distribute that gas
allowing a smaller amount to go to each
burner this is how I think about the
concept of work/life balance each of us
has a certain amount of gas on time
energy our motivation and whether due to
our daily choices or to our obligations
that gas is distributed to four
different burners let's call them work
health relationships and hobbies and if
you're anything like me then the way
that your burners are set right now
probably isn't exactly how you really
want them maybe the work burner is
burning just a bit too hot at the moment
or maybe your health burner is totally
off right now you haven't had time to
work out or your sleep schedules all on
the wack whatever the cause that
imbalance may be I believe there are
some habits that you can adopt that will
help to start curing it and today I want
to share three of them now my original
script of this video actually listed
five habits with two of them being ones
that you might expect number one
creating separation between your work
space and the area where you relax
and number two putting yourself on a
schedule going through a morning routine
getting actually dressed before you
start work in the morning and having a
set end time to your work day but in
truth these are both just specific
examples of another habit which is the
creation of obligations see when you
want to do something in a balanced way
it's a good idea to get in the habit of
setting up an obligation that encourages
that balance so for example I use a
combination of two different obligations
for my videos see I want to strike a
balance between publishing videos on a
regular basis but also pushing my
editing and my production skills with
each new video that I make so I create
deadlines for my videos but I also push
myself to improve at least one aspect
with each video that I create it could
be the way that I speak it could be the
lighting could be anything but whatever
it is I write
down in my 1% rule log over my website
and the combination of the deadlines and
this log ensures that I'm never resting
on my laurels just making content that
isn't pushing my skills but also that
I'm not letting my perfectionism caused
me to just never publish and I've
learned from experience that trying to
rely solely on self-discipline to strike
this balance simply does not work nearly
as well as James Claire puts it in his
book atomic habits you do not rise to
the level of your goals you fall to the
level of your systems and obligations
are simply components of a system that
pushes you to live with a type of
balance you aspire to so here's an
example of an obligation for each of our
four burners and hopefully these
examples will help you think of your own
obligations that will help you strike
the type of balance that you want now
for the work burner I've already
mentioned the deadlines that drive me to
finish and publish my work on a schedule
so here I'll just briefly mentioned that
I also use a tool called beeminder that
will literally charge me money if I
don't upload on time now that may sound
a bit extreme for some of you but as a
notorious perfectionist extreme measures
are very helpful to me so I use them for
health easily the most helpful
obligations that I have are the ones
imposed on me by my coach whenever it's
lifting day I'm given a specific workout
to do and I have to upload videos
proving that I did it but on the lighter
side I also share my activity data with
a couple of my friends which allows each
of us to see whether the others close
their exercise and their movement rings
for the day now for your relationships I
think that you should schedule plans
with friends in advance especially right
now when we can't go to our typical
physical gathering places and hence
we're kind of at home just doing our own
thing for most the day and weekly game
night with friends is a great way to do
this and there are a ton of games you
can play remotely including jack box
games which are some of my favorites
don't starve as a great multiplayer
option and even good old chess comm
finally you have your hobbies which
could be creative and productive like
making music or just totally relaxing
like playing video games
now obligations can be a bit of a
double-edged sword when it comes to
hobbies because they can often turn
those hobbies into work so my suggestion
would be to apply strategic obligations
to the other three burners first and in
most
you'll find that you're probably gonna
have space carved out for those hobbies
naturally but you can also schedule time
for them as well just as you schedule
time with your friends
now even with well-structured
obligations I sometimes find that my
work-life balance starts to tip way too
far into the work territory and when my
work burner starts to burn too brightly
I've noticed that it's often a result of
me feeling a sort of pressure to be
successful as quickly as possible and if
you feel the same pressure it's worth
asking yourself this question why are
you in a hurry or what exactly is
causing you to feel the need to compress
your timetable for success in other
words it's useful to identify the
external sources of pressure that push
you to work harder now sometimes these
are legitimate like the deadlines
imposed by a degree program or trying to
get out of debt but I've noticed that a
lot of the pressure sources in my own
life aren't actually legitimate and
ultimately they're just negative
sometimes it's jealousy sometimes I'll
see one of my friends or my peers do
something really cool and then I'll get
this temporary feeling of inadequacy
which makes me feel like I have to push
to keep up or other times it's FOMO the
fear of missing out the screens in your
pocket on your desk show you so many
different potential paths you could go
down and they feed you this potent
combination the highlight reels inspire
you the profiles of your peers put
pressure on you to keep up the endless
tutorials can teach you anything and the
tools are often cheap or free and are
just a click away so the message is
clear you can do anything and since you
can do anything it actually feels like
you're losing something when you pass up
an opportunity finally there's the
incessant pressure to keep the metrics
that measure your success going up it's
very easy to start to peg your sense of
self-worth and satisfaction to some kind
of external metric be it money or
followers or likes or whatever it is and
you don't want to just see this metric
continue to go up you want to see that
change happen faster and faster over
time I have a term for this I call it
acceleration addiction over time the
same increases don't feel as meaningful
as they used to because our brains lack
the ability to disregard our
point of reference a $1,000 raise seems
huge when you're making $20,000 a year
but not when you're making six figures a
10% increase in followers seems great
one month within the next month you'll
be looking out for an even bigger change
your acceleration addiction causes you
to constantly move the goal posts that
define enough so you have to train your
mind to find meaning elsewhere no amount
of success will cause these pressures to
ease up if you continue to fixate on
them the jealousy the FOMO the
acceleration addiction these will always
be there pressuring you to pump that gas
more and more towards the work burner
and on the flip side there are very few
natural sources of pressure that will
push you to live a more balanced life
and to do the things that truly make you
happy which means that you have to
create those pressures for yourself and
one great way to do this is to simply
list out the things that really do make
you happy I did this myself recently and
I came with a list of seven items which
includes things like doing work that
challenges and pushes my creative
abilities forces me to learn new things
it also includes spending time outside
especially when I'm moving in quick
complex ways and I think this is why I
enjoy skating so much now going for a
walk outside is nice but there is
nothing like the rush of gracefully
flying down the pavement carving around
corners and leaping over obstacles and
there's also music time spent with
people that I care about and being
physically fit these are the things that
I truly care about that make me truly
happy so I'd recommend taking some time
and creating a list like this for
yourself and then maybe posting it in a
place where you'll see it often get in
the habit of looking at it and reminding
yourself that the items on that list are
what truly make you happy not the
pursuit of some external measure of
success now to a certain degree living a
balanced life means sacrificing the
potential to become truly great at one
thing or at least to do so quickly
people who are truly great at their
crafts especially those who become great
early on typically do so by turning down
the heat on the other burners in their
life their craft becomes their singular
priority dominating their time and if
you want to become great at your own
craft as well you'll likely have to
start moving in the same direction but a
doesn't mean that you can't be strategic
about it yes an incredibly ambitious
goal might require you to cut time spent
on relationships or exercise especially
hobbies but there are probably other
things that you can cut first so look at
how you spend your time and then try to
identify the low value activities time
spent and mindlessly scrolling through
social media or binging shows that you
don't actually care about should be the
first things to go in fact if you want
to think back to our stove metaphor the
time spent on these activities doesn't
really fit unto any of the burners it's
more like poking a hole in the gas line
with a nail and by reducing the time you
spend on these things you gain time for
your goals without making cuts to
relationships your health or even your
hobbies but making cuts in those areas
isn't enough there is yet another way to
preserve the time you spend in these
areas while still accomplishing more
when you're working work intensely move
quickly don't let a moment go to waste
now this seems obvious but a lot of
people don't really use it you have to
understand the value of time isn't
determined solely by the amount of time
itself but also by the intensity and the
strategic value of the effort that you
exert during it so do whatever you have
to do to remove any lethargy from your
work time move with purpose and move
with a plan do your best to figure out
the best course of action and the best
order of operations of course one other
way you'll be able to accomplish a lot
more during your work time is by
improving your ability to solve problems
because when you can more effectively
pull information from lots of disparate
sources and combine ideas in your mind
you'll break through barriers in your
work a lot more quickly and a great
resource for building those
problem-solving skills is brilliant
brilliant is learning library of courses
in math science and computer science
that all focus on active learning and
active problem-solving their courses
quickly throw you into bite-size
challenges that are logically sequenced
so you're immediately applying the
concepts solving problems and learning
more quickly all the while you're also
getting Universal problem-solving
practice which you'll be able to apply
to your work okay well I agree than when
we can check if
if at least one has a bigger value than
that
if so swap it then set I died minus one
now brilliance library includes more
than 60 full length courses with a full
math suite ranging from the fundamentals
to calculus and probability science
courses covering light gravity and
relativity and computer science courses
that start with the basics of algorithms
and get all the way into quantum
computing so if you want to start
expanding your knowledge if you wanna
start building your problem-solving
skills then head over to brilliant org
slash Thomas Frank and sign up and if
you're one of the first 200 people to
use that link you'll even get 20% off
your annual premium subscription so
thank you so much for watching hopefully
you found this video helpful hopefully
there was something you can apply to
your life and start getting your life a
little bit more balanced going forward
and if you did like this video
definitely hit that like button to show
the YouTube algorithm what's up you can
also get subscribed right over here if
you haven't done so already or check out
a couple of other videos on this channel
right over here on this side of the
screen as always smashing your face into
your phone screen is a more effective
way of clicking those links than using
your thumbs or even your fingers I think
the nose was just evolved for hitting
links on a phone screen so definitely do
that or don't because as always I'm not
your dad