this video is sponsored by skillshare
today we are going through 10 of my
favorite productivity apps for the
iphone here in 2021.
though i'm actually going to start this
list out with a productivity feature of
the iphone that isn't actually an app
but is useful nonetheless
it's this little magnetic wallet thing
that you can get from apple that just
snaps onto the back of your phone but
the cool thing is it's got this little
thumb
sliding thing where if you have a credit
card that you frequently use or in my
case an office access key
it's very easy to slide it up scan it
wherever you need to scan it and put it
right back on your phone
just like that so i figured i'd mention
that because i've been enjoying this
and it's definitely a purchase that i
don't regret let's get into the list of
apps and the first app we're going to
talk about is called
otter which is an amazingly good ai
voice transcription app so as a youtuber
i get a lot of ideas for content often
at times when i can't easily either
write something down or pull my phone
out to take notes
and in those cases i take a lot of voice
memos but a lot of times i would love to
have those voice notes translated into
text
so i can then port them over to notion
or use them and actually you know go
through the text and
edit it and things like that otter is
freaking amazing at doing that i've
tried a ton of other apps some that have
apple watch integrations which i really
would like for otter
but they use this built-in siri
dictation which is just
not that great at translating your voice
into readable text
meanwhile otter does not as far as i can
tell have a real
human shoved into your phone who's
literally you know acting as a court
stenographer
and typing out your text but it might as
well
the transcription is nearly as good as
the human transcription that i actually
pay for
for these youtube videos which means
that when i speak something while i'm
driving or i'm out on the bike
i can basically guarantee that when i
come and read the text later on
it's going to look pretty much like i
said it it also keeps
the audio file it's not quite as high
quality of an audio file as you get with
regular voice memos so i don't use it
for song ideas but it does keep the
audio file which is nice because it
allows me to export both the audio file
and the text into drum roll please the
very next app on our list which is
you saw this coming notion so notion is
an app that i talk about a lot in fact i
have a entire second channel called
thomas frank explains
full of notion tutorials link in the
description down below if you're curious
and if you haven't heard of notion it is
basically an all-in-one workspace app
which allows you to take
notes it allows you to manage tasks it
allows you to do pretty much anything
you want
and at this point i'm using it fully for
running my channel for managing my tasks
for running projects
and for taking all the notes that i want
to take and for writing all the scripts
for my videos the last time i talked
about notion on my channel there was no
actual official widget but now
there is and in fact there are a couple
that are very useful which i want to
show you right now the one that i keep
right on my home screen here is the
favorites bar
and a trick that i use is i keep a
dashboard page with links to a lot of
things i'm working on
because i often have more links than
will fit on this widgets
area i think it only keeps about nine
links at one time
so using this dashboard i can actually
create like a central place
for all of the important things in my
life including my tasks my notes
content with my channel with thomas
frank explains my other channel
and ongoing projects and i have like
this hub page that allows me to easily
get to anything i want to get when i
want to add something or reference
something
the other nice thing though is there's
another widget which i keep over here
on this quick access area which shows
you your recent pages
so instead of relying just on your
manually created favorites bar you have
all of your recent pages right here and
i can get to
say the research and notes for this very
video
and look there's otter there's notion
and there is our third
app which i'm going to now smoothly
transition into so authy is a manager
for two-factor authentication codes that
functions a lot like
google authenticator hopefully you are
using two-factor authentication
on any account that offers it in
addition to your passwords if you care
about your online security
now one thing you might not know about
two-factor authentication is there's two
different types
sms based or text message based and
app-based like google authenticator or
in this case
authy sms-based authentication is
actually a lot less secure because
identity thieves and you know hackers
and people like that have been known to
spoof your sim card essentially calling
up your phone company convincing them
that they
are you and convincing them to set up a
new device with the exact same sim
information
so they get the text messages that
you're supposed to get including
to factor off messages which is why
whenever i have the choice i use
app-based authentication
instead of text message authentication
but there's a problem
with app-based two-factor auth
especially with google authenticator at
least last time i used it
it didn't sync between different devices
which means if you accidentally drop
your phone down an elevator shaft you're
out of luck and you have to spend a ton
of time doing password resets
or hopefully pulling you know backup
codes that you had for your two-factor
authentication
it's a whole big mess so that's why i
like authy because you can log into your
account and get your two-factor auth
codes back
and as long as you're using a secure
password for that account i think it's
still pretty secure now the next step
that we're going to talk about is the
only one
on my list that doesn't have an android
equivalent this is an app called command
which is actually a web browser and it
has a killer feature that you
probably know about if you saw my ipad
video earlier this year
that feature is that you can highlight
text within
any web page and then once you highlight
it
not only is it going to stay highlighted
or highlit
i'm not sure how you're supposed to say
that when you refresh the page but you
can also tap your highlights and you can
add journal entries which allow you to
essentially take notes
on the highlights you make i have
written entire articles
inside commands journal feature because
i'll take a highlight from something i'm
reading on the web
get inspired and then i'll just you know
think i'm going to take a little bit of
a note and then it
balloons into a huge article the other
thing that i love about command is it
actually can send the highlights that
you take
to your read wise account and i guess i
should just talk about read wise now
because it is the next app
on our list so read wise is basically a
highlight manager for
the knowledge that you intake from
various sources
books kindle books podcasts using an app
called air which i will talk about a
little bit later
even tweets and content from your web
browser
now there is a way to sync highlights
from mobile safari to read wise but it's
kind of a
friction full process and command makes
it much
much easier so i love doing research and
doing highlighting using the command
browser when i'm reading blog posts and
articles
but coming back to read wise read wise
is essentially a highlight manager that
can resurface and help you recall the
knowledge that you gathered over time
it's got this daily review area which
will actually give you a collection of
different highlights so you can
remember them more usefully i don't use
that too much what i actually do is i
kind of use this as a database
for a lot of the highlights that i take
in books and other pieces of media but
the thing that i really love about raid
wise is that not only does it
store all of my highlights here like
these highlights from the book askiwata
that i've been reading really recently
but there is a native integration with
both notion
and with rome research and also with rem
note i believe
so whenever you take a highlight from
kindle or from the command browser or
from even the safari extension or
tweeting
read wise to roll up a tweet thread
it'll send it to read wise and then read
wise will dutifully kick that highlight
over
to your integration platform in my case
it's notion so i have
a beautiful raidwise database on notion
where i've got all of my highlights from
books and articles and
all kinds of media sources and then when
i'm doing research for an article
i can pull in my highlights into my
research areas and actually now with
notions synced blocks feature i don't
even have to copy and paste i can just
create a synced block
and port content over from my highlights
area into
whatever article that i'm writing which
is pretty sweet next up on our list is
one called tide which is my favorite
pomodoro timer for the iphone now it's
got a ton of different features it can
track your stats it's got all these
nature
sounds so you can create these
soundscapes to help you focus personally
i just like the way that it looks i like
the fact that it's free and i like the
fact that i can open up i can hit the
focus button
i can choose 25 minutes and i can start
a pomodoro session
and like i've said before the pomodoro
technique is one of the most powerful
short-term productivity techniques there
is
because it externalizes the
self-discipline that you need to keep
working
but it also reframes your task from
output based to input based
as in i have to write a paper which is
really daunting and scary too
i just need to work on this paper for 25
minutes and then i'm allowed to take a
break
the next step on my list is actually a
built-in app in the phone so if you have
an iphone you already have this
and it's the fitness app or i don't know
if it's called fitness or activity but
this is absolutely a productivity app
for me
because when i'm active when i'm moving
when i am exercising every day i also
feel more energetic and i get more done
and i work
with more focus exercise is absolutely
associated with cognitive performance
and if you want to learn more about that
there's a great book by dr john ratey
called spark
highly recommend that especially if you
like books full of scientific studies
but having this app and specifically its
integration with the apple watch
and the face here that shows me around
my rings every time i look at the apple
watch
encourages me to get my exercise done
i've actually got
the trends thing activated here so i can
see that pretty much all my trends are
on the
up i've been moving more i've been
exercising more i've been standing more
walking more all kinds of stuff one of
my favorite things about the fitness app
is the sharing aspect of it
so if we go over to the sharing tab
you're going to see that i actually have
shared my fitness data and vice versa
with some of my friends brian from real
engineering who probably forgot to put
on his apple watch today
my friend chris who wrote the
productivity project in hyperfocus
my agent dave and also renee ritchie
from the channel renee ritchie who talks
a lot about apple
so using the sharing feature we all get
notified when we work out we send each
other
fun emojis to encourage each other we'll
sometimes check in and be like hey how
come you haven't gotten your workout
done today
it adds some nice accountability into
your daily exercise routine even if your
friends are far flung across the globe
so
next up on the list is audible which is
an app that i've been using for a very
very long time but i've actually been
using a lot more heavily recently
because
i am now riding an e-bike to my downtown
co-working office on any day where i
don't have to sit
in this chair and film videos in my
studio and i absolutely love
riding my bike getting out of the house
going somewhere else to work
and that whole process of writing
actually about 40 miles on the e-bike
gives me a ton of time to listen to
things that i can use to educate myself
so audible is probably my number one
resource for that since i love listening
to audiobooks and one thing that i did
want to point out on the iphone now that
the
home screen widgets feature is live is
that audible has a widget which allows
you to scroll down and basically resume
the last book that you were listening to
or pick one of the four that you
listened to most recently other than
that one so it's a nice way to just
launch into a book that you were
listening to recently without having to
open up the app and wait for it to load
next up on our list is an app called
adobe scan which is probably the best
free
document scanner app on the iphone this
is going to look really weird because
you're going to see a camera and i'm
moving it around
hi other camera anyway this is a great
app for scanning
paper documents and then exporting them
as pdfs or as
picture files and porting them into your
knowledge management system in my case
it's going to be notion
it might be rom research or evernote for
you but it's really nice to have a
document scanner app on the phone
next up we have spotify for podcasts
yep i have finally switched over to just
using spotify as my default podcast
player i resisted it for a very long
time i was a pocket casts fan but
it's good enough now in spotify they've
got the speed controls they've got the
sleep timer function
and uh it's fast that's really nice
thing now
i really wanted to recommend an app
called
air instead of spotify in this slot in
the video
air is a really cool podcast player that
has a
killer feature my friend ali abdull
actually turned me on to this app so you
may have heard him talking about it if
you watch his videos
but air is not just a podcast player
it's also an app that integrates with
read wise and it has this really cool
feature where if you're listening to
something in a podcast episode
and you want to make a highlight of it
you want to save it you want to add a
note to it
you can do that by hitting this little
quote button here
and it's going to save either last 30
seconds or last minute you can change
the duration if you want and you can add
a little note and it's going to send
that to raidwise which again would send
to notion or roam research or rem note
if you have that integration created
it is super cool but the performance of
this app is just
it's just not great right now it's slow
if i want to like rewind 15 seconds
it takes like five seconds just to do it
and start playing again
so i'm really hoping that they're going
to improve the performance of this app
and once they do that
i'm going to be probably switching over
to using it because i really do want to
use that read wise feature i just need
it to be faster now if you're watching a
video on my channel about iphone apps
then i would say it's probable that you
also watch one of my favorite tech
youtubers
marquez brownlee aka mkbhd and if you do
i want to let you know about a new
course he just launched over on
skillshare all about how to create great
youtube videos
i cannot think of many other people who
i would rather have
teach me how to make a great youtube
video than marquez especially because
his quality is well let's just use the
term that he uses it's absolutely crispy
it's amazing i've taken a lot of
inspiration from his setup his
gear the way he films things to improve
the quality of the footage
on my own channel and if you want to
learn how to upgrade your own youtube
game or even start a channel if you
haven't done it yet
his course over on skillshare is a great
place to start
and the wonderful thing about skillshare
is that when you join you don't just get
access to marquez's class you get access
to thousands of classes that can boost
your skills and your creative abilities
in a ton of different areas
including productivity because i have
three different classes on skillshare of
my own
one on building a productivity system
that combines apps to make sure that
nothing ever falls to the cracks
also on skillshare you're going to find
classes in graphic design in video
animation
in music production in storytelling and
public speaking there is a ton that you
can learn on skillshare and it's also a
very affordable platform
in fact if you are one of the first 1
000 people to sign up for skillshare
today using the link down below
you're going to get a one month free
trial which means that you can go take
my classes you can go take mkbhd's class
for free and test out the platform for a
month before you have to pay
anything it's a great platform i really
think you're going to get a lot of value
out of it and you're going to want to
keep paying for it after that trial
period
is over but you've got that trial to try
it out so once again go to that link
down in the description below
sign up be one of the first thousand
people to get that free one month
trial thank you for watching this video
hopefully you found something helpful
here and i would also like to hear from
you what are your favorite
apps that i did not mention in this
video leave them down in the comment
section below and we can all try new
things out
and uh you know probably end up spending
too much time on our phones and not
actually being productive whoops
anyway i'll see you in the next video
bye