earlier this year I made a video about
whether or not you should change your
answers during exams if you're unsure on
them now the prevailing wisdom has
always been to go with your gut but the
research we looked at presented this as
what they call the first instinct
fallacy and showed that more often than
not changing an answer you're unsure of
is more often the better choice now the
amazing thing about science is that at
any point in time new data can come and
make you wrong and that is exactly what
has happened to me because now my
initial recommendation for you is wrong
and due to that wonderful quality of
science I now have a new and improved
method to suggest to you and since I use
an ambiguous title for this video I'm
just going to lay it straight out for
you so I don't waste your time next time
you're taking an exam whether it's your
final exams if you're watching this
video near its published date or any
exam in the future right after you
answer each question you should rate
your confidence in that answer using a
scale of one to five one being super
unconfident I'm not really sure and five
being I definitely know the answer to
this question now this technique takes
advantage of something called
metacognition which is essentially
thinking about thinking it's our ability
to analyze our own beliefs and decisions
to make an analogy it illustrates how
the brain is a lens that sees its own
flaws one of the core aspects of
metacognition is our ability to judge
our confidence in our knowledge we can
feel uncertain that is we know when we
do not know I first started learning
about metacognition a couple of months
ago when I talked to a guy named Justin
couchman who's a professor of psychology
at Albright College in Pennsylvania and
couchman first phas into the study of
metacognition took the form of research
on reesus monkeys no not not Reese say
monkeys but yeah you know in a study he
helped conduct called and bear with me
because this is a mouthful the highs and
lows of theoretical interpretation in
animal metacognition research he and two
other psychology professors set out to
see if animals have the same
metacognitive capabilities that we have
in their study the monkeys were given
questions of varying levels of
difficulty and they had to either give
an answer or indicate that they didn't
know the answer and couchmen and the
other professors were surprised to find
out that the monkeys were able to
accurately judge their confidence and
indicate when they didn't know they were
able to look inside their brains and
analyze their own thinking much like we
do with the results of this study in
hand couchman started thinking about the
metacognitive abilities of his own
students who are often surprised that
the grades on their exams were often
much higher or lower than they initially
predicted and it turns out that there is
a reason for this the problem with
metacognition is that it isn't perfect I
use the analogy of a lens that sees its
own flaws for a reason our brains are
subject to all sorts of bugs cognitive
biases heris STS flawed modes of
thinking like to quote the AI researcher
elazer owski the brain is a flawed lens
through which to see reality this is
true of both Mouse brains and human
brains but a human brain is a flawed
lens that can understand its own flaws
its systematic errors its biases and
apply second order corrections to them
one of the biggest flaws is that our
memories are notoriously unreliable and
as a result our metacognitive
capabilities Decay as we try to use them
to analyze thoughts that we had further
and further in the past so to learn more
about this couchman decided to conduct
another study this time on humans rather
than monkeys and they set up two
different tests in the first tests they
had students take a real lifee multiple
choice exam but after each question they
asked them to rate their confidence on a
binary scale either writing G or k for
guess or known additionally they asked
the participants to indicate whether or
not they had revised each answer after
giving an initial answer and for this
first test they found that revisions
were more often than not correct
especially for the answers that were
marked guess either than known after
this first test they decided to conduct
a second test and the only difference
here was that instead of using a binary
rating system guess or known they
decided to have the students rate their
confidence on each question using a one
to five scale one being super
unconfident and five being almost
certain and the results here were
interesting because in this case the
initial answers were more often correct
than the revisions now these results
would seem contradictory and that would
be the case if there were only one rule
of thumb either stick with your initial
answer you know go with your gut or as
the previous research showed revisions
are better but using confidence tracking
there's no longer just one rule of thumb
when you assign a confidence score to
each question in the moment that you
answer it you're utilizing your brain's
metacognitive abilities at their most
accurate Point giving your brain a more
sensitive tool with which to make a
decision so to wrap up here there were
two key findings to that study number
one beliefs formed about the exams after
the exams were over were very very poor
predictors of actual performance and
this shouldn't come as a surprise I
remember myself going into many exams as
a student super confident that I was
going to do awesome and then I got a
bunch of questions wrong or on the other
other hand being really worried that I
wasn't ready and then just absolutely
acing it and I'm sure you've had these
experiences as well but more importantly
metacognitive tracking in the moment was
a much more accurate predictor of
success and gave the students a more
accurate tool for judging whether or not
they should make a revision to an answer
so there you have it when you go into
your next final exam or any exam in the
future try assigning a confident score
next to each answer as you answer that
question doing so will help you to more
intelligently make revisions and
hopefully get better grades now if
you're curious and you'd like to know
more about the research that went into
this video I did an hourlong podcast
with Justin couchman where we went more
in depth in his study and you can click
the card right now wherever it is or
down below to listen to it and I've also
linked to all the relevant studies in
the blog post for this video that's all
I've got for you this week so if you're
watching this and you've got a final
coming up pretty soon best of luck on it
and hopefully this technique will help
you out and in next week's video we'll
be talking about an often requested
topic how to make a study schedule for
finals so look forward to that and as
always thanks for watching
hey guys thanks so much for watching
this video If you enjoyed it giving it a
like can definitely help this channel
out and also if you want to get more
study tips every single week you can hit
that big red subscribe button right
there in addition I also wrote a book on
how to get better grades and I made it
free so if you'd like a copy of it put
the picture right there you want to read
the summary and get links to all those
studies click the orange button to go to
the blog post and if you missed last
week's video we talked about 15 writing
apps that can help you become a better
writer lastly if you want to connect I'm
Tom frankley on Instagram and Twitter or
you can leave a comment down below