you've probably heard that multitasking
isn't good for your productivity but do
you know why that is today we're going
to explore the reasons and by the end of
this video you're gonna have a good
understanding of exactly why
multitasking is attempting yet
ultimately ineffective strategy in most
situations
I'll also be recommending some tools and
strategies to reduce the temptation to
multitask which is no small feat given
the sheer amount of tasks we all have to
deal with on a daily basis and the
availability of technology that makes
multitasking so easy what's the price of
go buy it tell my mom that I'm coming
Wednesday sorry nicer thing actually
October ok finally and possibly contrary
to your expectations we'll be talking
about the times at which multitasking
does make sense that's right it turns
out that multitasking doesn't entirely
deserve the bad rap it's gotten from
people like productivity bloggers and
management consultants who often say
that multitasking doesn't exist
multitasking does exist what doesn't
exist is multi focus think of your brain
like a computer or to be more precise a
very specific kind of computer and one
that we haven't seen in probably 10 or
15 years a computer with a single core
processor now most modern computers have
multi-core processors the current lineup
of 15-inch MacBook Pros have quad-core
processors meaning processors with 4
cores and even my aging iPhone 6s has a
processor with 2 cores with multiple
cores comes the ability to truly
multitask each core could run operations
independently however within each core
only one calculation can be executed at
any given time so how are you still able
to run multiple programs at once how was
it that you could be playing runescape
in one window talking to a friend and
MSN Messenger in another and in still
another be writing a video script full
references that show everyone just how
much of an old man you've truly become
how do you do fellow kids well it's
pretty simple the processor switched
back and forth between multiple tasks
but since they could manage millions of
instructions per second they created the
illusion of true multitasking now
unfortunately the human brain was not
designed to switch back and forth
between tasks quickly it takes a little
while for your brain to truly lock on to
any task that requires a high level of
concentration or active attention so
when you switch your attention away to
something else you incur what's called a
cognitive switching penalty
not only do you lose the time that it
takes to switch from one task to the
other and then back again later you also
lose a lot more time while your brain
tries to get itself back into the flow
state and if you're switching tasks
often your brain forever stays in the
shallow end of the focus pool multiple
studies over the past few decades had
demonstrated this inconvenient
biological truth and what's more they've
also demonstrated that multitaskers make
more mistakes which is something that I
was reminded of just last night when I
decided to stream some enter the gungeon
on Twitch I have put over a hundred
hours into that game but because I was
simultaneously trying to answer
questions and be entertaining on the
stream my skill level dropped like a
rock so the science is clear and it's
backed up by experience committing to a
single target of focus will make you far
more effective in the long run once you
enter the flow state on that single task
you'll work more quickly and you're
creative and logical abilities will be
fully unlocked so with all that being
said how can you avoid the temptation to
multitask well one thing that's been
helping me a lot lately is doing all my
writing and my research on this iPad pro
when I first got it a couple of weeks
ago I was initially annoyed that it
wasn't quite as good at doing a lot of
things that I already did my MacBook Pro
copying and pasting was a lot slower a
lot of the keyboard shortcuts I normally
used didn't work I mean I could complain
for hours but then I saw these
inconveniences for what they truly are
useful restrictions yes my iPad sucks
for answering emails and it sucks for
editing video and it sucks for lots of
things but it is very good for writing
which is the most important work that I
do and it's the work that I'm most
resistant to doing because writing is
hard so now every single morning I take
my iPad to the coffee shop and I leave
my MacBook at home and there I do at
least one full Pomodoro of writing and
I'll show you my setup right now on 3/4
of the screen I have Evernote and I
basically write whatever comes to mind
and on the other quarter of the screen I
have an app called tide which functions
as my opponent or timer now you
definitely don't need an expensive iPad
to get the same benefits my friend
Martin back in college actually did the
exact same thing with an old iPod Touch
and a little stand and a Bluetooth
keyboard and of course you can do the
exact same thing with a notebook and a
pen as well as long as your handwriting
muscles have an atrophied if you do have
to use a computer you could use an app
like cold turkey writer which locks down
your computer and lets you do nothing
but write until you've hit a word count
goal or you could use apps like freedom
or
filter to block websites that you find
distracting whatever you use the key is
to lock down your options with all that
being said there are times when
multitasking it can be useful and I want
to give you two examples the first is
any situation where neither the tasks
that you're doing requires intense
concentration and we're one or more of
them is something that you've mastered
to the point where it's essentially
become muscle memory cooking is a great
example your practice I've memorized
several recipes and I've gotten pretty
good at a lot of the basic techniques
like cutting vegetables with proper
guide hand technique of course and
sauteing onions this means that at least
when I'm cooking your recipe I'm
familiar with I can easily handle
multiple things going on at once I can
have the onions on the stove I could be
chopping kale I can keep the timing for
the garlic bread in the back of my head
and I can also easily listen to audio
books while I do it all but if I'm
making a new recipe I can't listen to
audio books and I'm not nearly as good
at managing multiple dishes at once
the moment that an unfamiliar process or
a new technique enters the equation it
is back to single-tasking for me now
aside from that the one other situation
where it can be useful to multitask is
when you want to background process
something in your head as dr. Barbara
Oakley points out in her book a mind for
numbers your brain has two different
modes of processing the focused mode and
the diffused mode when you walk away
from a project after focusing on it for
a while and kind of just let it simmer
in the background you're entering the
diffuse mode and when you do this new
insights can pop up that wouldn't have
otherwise popped up if you remained
focused my friend Martin actually
brought this point up to me while I was
writing this video because right now
he's designing an algorithm that will
suggest articles to people on our
website and he mentioned that after
working on it intensely for a while he
took a break to go fight an easy monster
in Monster Hunter at which point so new
insights popped up into the back of his
head about how to improve it so to recap
all this when you're faced with a task
that requires careful attention focus
only on that task boy the temptation to
multitask and if it's helpful choose
tools that restrict your options and cut
down on that temptation like website
blockers or less capable computers
finally at other times like when you
want to save time on tasks you've
already mastered or when you want to
take advantage of that diffuse mode of
thinking use multitasking as the
context-specific tool that it is
speaking and mastering skills you should
check out skill share if you want to
improve your mastery and web development
graphic design presentations or really
any other skill that you want to learn
skills share is an online learning
platform
with over 17,000 courses in a ton of
different areas including the ones I
just mentioned plus digital animation
marketing photography and audio
production which is actually a skill
that I've been trying to learn a bit
about lately and effort to improve the
background music in my videos if that's
something that interests you as well you
should definitely check out young gurus
class on learning to mix music in
addition to videos going over techniques
like EQ and compression
there's also sample project files that
you can download so you can start
applying what you've learned right away
Skillshare is also more affordable than
most other online learning platforms at
less than ten bucks a month for their
annual subscription and the first 1,000
people that sign up with link in the
description down below are gonna get two
months of premium unlimited access for
just 99 cents I want to give a huge
thanks to Skillshare for sponsoring this
video and once again supporting this
channel and as always guys thank you so
much for watching hopefully you learned
something from this video and if you
found it useful definitely hit that like
button down below you can also click
right there to subscribe to this channel
so you don't miss out on any future
videos and click right there if you want
to get a free copy of my book on how to
earn better grades
lastly you can get one more video on
this channel if you want to keep
watching by clicking right there and I
will see you in the next video thanks
for watching