this video is sponsored by brilliant be
one of the first 200 people to sign up
at the link below to get 20% off your
annual premium brilliant subscription
when I think about being productive I
have to think about a concept that's
usually talked about in the realm of
video games actions per minute or a p.m.
as a lot of people like to say in
real-time strategy games and MOBAs and
in other games like don't starve every
second counts and learning how to move
and act as quickly as possible can mean
the difference between victory and
defeat between well starving and not
starving in other words move fast or get
left behind but the sheer volume of
actions you can perform is only half the
battle if there's no plan behind those
actions no greater vision ensuring that
each movement is the right one then well
you're just wasting energy or possibly
even worse so today we're gonna dig into
how you can effectively plan and
prioritize your work both on the small
scale so you know how to best plan each
workday and on a larger scale turning an
eye towards the weeks and months ahead
now both of these are important to
master in a general sense but even more
so when you're working from home and are
much more responsible for how you manage
your own time and energy when all that
management is on you it's crucial that
you're able to set the right priorities
like for example should I have
prioritized building an entirely new set
for this video well probably not but hey
this is a learning space you see this
tastefully selected amp you see this
vintage camera from the antique store
that doesn't actually work but really
ties the set together yeah this is a
learning space not a judging space Derek
so let's start learning and let's kick
that off with how to properly plan your
day at the most basic level I plan my
day by creating what I call a daily list
now I do this on the whiteboard in my
office but you can do it basically
anywhere you can use a paper daily list
or even rely on the due dates and your
task manager but whatever method you use
there are a few things you should keep
in mind when you're doing your planning
first realize that the due dates in your
task manager may not paint a perfect
picture of what you should actually do
today or indeed what you can do today
now I say this because I know that I am
guilty of continually allowing my
intentions to eclipse my abilities and
if I don't stop myself I will often
write down way more tasks than I can
realistically get done in any one given
day so try your best to keep this list
limited to what you can actually do and
when you fail and you will inevitably
fail sometimes make an observation of it
so you can plan more accurately for the
next day and realize that it might
actually take some time to get better at
this as our brains really aren't built
for making accurate time estimates in
fact researchers have found that people
typically will give nearly the exact
same answer when they're asked to give
estimates for the best case scenario
versus an average case scenario now of
course by definition the average case
will always take more time than the best
case like if we're talking about driving
to work which is probably something that
you don't actually have to do right now
but let's just use it as an example here
the best case would mean hitting every
single green light it would mean never
encountering any traffic at all and an
average case wouldn't look like that at
all but naturally we tend to complete
the two now one thing that can help you
plan more accurately is breaking down
your tasks into small chunks and then
scheduling those chunks this strategy is
called time boxing or time blocking and
to use it you slot your tasks into small
time blocks on your calendar now this
doesn't work well for everyone and some
people feel like it kind of boxes them
in too much makes them feel too much
like cogs and machine but a lot of
people do find that it helps them avoid
procrastinating during the day that's a
big problem especially when you work at
home I'll have to think about it this
way when you're planning your day you
are in planning mode and once you start
working you move over into robot mode at
that point your job is simply to execute
the plans that were made earlier so more
accurate those plans are the more likely
you are to stick to them now if you
don't want to go the uber granular way
of time boxing oh it's just at least
listing your day's tasks out in the
order you're going to do them and for
most people I think it would be best
served by planning to do your most
difficult or dreaded task first
especially when you're working at home
when you're at work you can often to
crass to work a little bit by answering
your emails or doing other little small
tasks first but eventually you're gonna
run out of tiny things to do and you're
gonna have to tackle that really big
dreaded task but
well how do I put this there's always
something to clean there's always
something to organize and honestly I am
not too proud to admit that I have
literally convinced myself that I needed
to hang a picture before starting a
video script and that is because quite
honestly my robot mode is more like
trained monkey mode I am easily
distracted by shiny things so a strong
ordered plan always helps me to stay on
task but that said let's get a
bird's-eye view and take a look at long
term planning so like I mentioned at the
beginning of this video a high number of
actions per minute only matters if those
actions are guided by a strong game plan
and since most of your overall goals are
long term ones you need to know how to
look beyond your daily schedule and
effectively plan for the weeks and
months ahead so you're just a few
techniques for keeping track of things
on a larger scale and even dealing with
things that don't have strict due dates
first I want to show you a great method
for breaking down large projects into
manageable pieces and then tracking
their progress it's called the Kanban
method and it's employed by teams
everywhere around the world to get all
sorts of huge projects done at its core
Kanban uses cards and lists cards keep
details about individual tasks while the
lists indicate the stages of the project
so as you work on tasks and move them to
different stages their respective cards
get moved through the lists as well so
you always have an accurate bird's-eye
view of how things are going here's just
one example of Kanban in action this is
our video project tracker which we of
course keep in notion now normally it's
in ListView but I can also switch it
into a Kanban view and this lets me see
which videos are being researched which
videos are in the writing stage which
videos are being edited and as each
video progresses it moves through each
of these stages so again I can see where
it is and what needs to be done next for
a more complicated example let's take a
look at the Trello board that we used
for the website redesign we did a couple
of years ago now this was a huge project
that had hundreds of tasks and tons of
considerations design typography code
optimizations SEO you name it so there
was a lot more going on in its
respective board but the general idea
was still the same cards
move through their lists as they got
worked on and we can always see the
general state of the project so that's
just one technique that you can use to
plan more effectively for your long-term
projects and of course there are a lot
more that we could talk about but to
keep this video short I want to move on
to the question of prioritization how do
you decide what to work on we're looking
at things on a larger time scale well as
it turns out my friend Martin has a
system for that so let me just bring him
up real quick hey Martin okay so a
couple of months ago I made this video
about something that I dubbed the Martin
system and people liked it and as it
turns out you have yet another Martin
system to share with us I do like making
systems let's see basically my kitchen
system of organizing my todoist and how
is this different than like the normal
kind of category based system that I
have been using forever yeah so I had my
to do a setup like categories before so
you know you know I do a bunch of stuff
it's like podcasts work writing work all
sorts of extra different things server
stuff and programming and what I found
was that every single day I had to look
through like six or seven lists to
figure out what I wanted to do that day
which was cumbersome eventually the list
became full and I stopped wanting to
look through them so I've switched it
now I've got four lists everything goes
in regardless of category and they're
all based off of the kitchen metaphor
putting something on the back burner so
obviously one of the lists is the back
burner
that's where everything goes when I'm
not focusing on it it's not important
right now it might be at some point but
I shouldn't be doing it today and to
complement that I created three lists
one of which is vitamins you know every
day you take your vitamins so this is
stuff like check my email this is stuff
like check the publishing schedule so
make sure we're on track this stuff like
that you do every day it's a small task
you just do it real quick the gummy
vitamins well obviously they're gummy
vitamins I hate I hate just jails and I
hate for chocolate so it's gummies all
the way down anyway the next list is the
front burner you know it's the stuff
that I'm currently looking at the most
important stuff so if I'm prepping a
podcast that we need to record next week
that's on the front burner if I'm fixing
a big bug that's on the front burner
because I want to wake up say
okay what do I got to do those two
projects are important today I should
get to them and the last list is the
oven list so I'm going off the
assumption that I'm running some sort of
oven timer basically these are scheduled
items that happen every once in a while
like backing up image files or running
through a process or checking email
statistics something that might happen
every month or every other month or
every year checking are like Amazon has
three backups to make sure their final
like yeah stuff like that like I don't
need to think about that on a daily
basis but much like an oven timer when
it goes off I should probably see what's
going on I shouldn't forget about yeah
so todoist
obviously has the today list that has
the next seven days and then you could
make filters to have next two weeks so
theoretically you could just use the
classic categorization approach with due
dates what made you feel that that
wasn't good enough that you needed to
build this kind of kitchen system
instead that would be because of my and
I presume many people's complete
inability to understand how long
something might take or how much time
one has in a day so I I'd set all of
these things do optimistically they'd
all have a due date of like I'm gonna do
it all on Tuesday these 10 tasks I'll
get them out of the way and the week's
gonna look great but that's not how it
works what happens is I accomplish maybe
maybe three of them if I'm really lucky
because something else important was
going on and then I now have seven
things that are overdoing todoist
now I can take the time to reschedule
them but what tends to happen with me is
that I just keep rescheduling the same
things over and over because they're
just not important it I've got a huge
list of things that are overdue or do
today and I know now by now that I'm not
I'm not going to do them all yeah that
makes sense all right
so quick recap time on a daily scale
make sure you're creating a daily plan
for yourself each and every day that you
work try to keep this limited to the
tasks that you can actually get done and
be observant about anything you don't
get done so you can become more accurate
over time again aim to bring your
intention and your ability into
alignment
additionally aim to tap your most
difficult tasks first and used
I'm boxing if you need a longer term
scale experimental techniques like the
Kanban method to map out your projects
and make sure you're always maintaining
an accurate view without each piece of
them is going and finally find a way to
prioritize what you're working on and if
the way you've been doing it in the past
isn't working then look for a method
that does work or that one of your own
Martin's kitchen system is a great
example of this and it's also a great
example of how taking a novel creative
approach to solving a problem can yield
great results and if you want to improve
your ability to creatively solve
problems then you might want to take
some of your free time which you should
have more of now if you're not planning
effectively and check out
brilliant brilliant is a learning
resource to can help you to boost your
problem-solving skills and to analytical
abilities their library of more than 60
math science and computer science
courses break down these complex
subjects into bite-sized interactive
chunks that are both logically ordered
and that focus on active learning so
whether you're going through a calculus
and a nut shell course digging into how
neural networks work or learning how
things scientifically you'll be doing so
actively working with interactive
puzzles code writing challenges and more
and their daily challenges feature takes
this even further giving you new
challenges every single day so you make
building your problem-solving skills a
daily habit so to get started for free
heading over to brilliant org slash
Thomas Frank and to sign up with their
free plan you get access to new daily
challenges every single day and if
you're one of the first 200 people to
sign up with that link down below you're
also going to get 20% off their annual
premium subscription which you get to
access to the entire library of in-depth
courses thanks as always for watching
this video hopefully you've found it
useful hopefully you got something
helpful out of it and if you did
definitely hit that like button to feed
the YouTube algorithm with more tasty
tasty data also if you did enjoy this
especially if you enjoy the conversation
I had with Martin in this video then you
might want to check out our podcast as
well I will have that link in the
description down below and you may be
interested to know that our most recent
episode was about working from home so
check that out if you want some
additional tips beyond that you can
subscribe right there if you're not
subscribed already to get new videos
whenever they come out click right there
to get one more video on this channel
and as always you're gonna want to smash
your face into your phone screen because
your fingers aren't as effective for
clicking those boxes to make sure you do
that beyond that go do whatever you want
not
but it will see you in the next video