thanks to hover for sponsoring this
video and supporting my channel
two weeks ago apple released the
long-awaited ios 14.
and while it's got lots of new bells and
whistles we could talk about today we're
going to explore what i think is
hands down the most useful productivity
feature
it has so ios 14 came out of beta just
about a week or two ago
and i think most people would say the
most exciting feature in ios 14 is the
ability to put widgets
on your home screen and to customize
them i know my android user friends have
had this ability for years and i'm sure
there's going to be some in the comments
rubbing my nose in it but personally
as somebody who's been using an iphone
since i think 2011 or 2012
this has been something that i have been
wanting for a really really long time
but as cool as this feature is as a
whole it wasn't really exciting enough
for me to make a full video on it
until i found out about the shortcuts
widget
so shortcuts is an app that apple bought
from a third-party developer a few years
ago and integrated into ios and it
essentially lets you create custom
shortcuts to do
a whole ton of different things and
personally i'd never really played
around with the shortcuts app very much
until i saw
in that list of widget options but after
playing with it over the weekend after
learning what it could do after learning
that i can actually create scripts and
do lots of really cool custom stuff
i started getting that same mental rush
that i get when i pull off a
particularly complex magic the gathering
combo
i live for stuff like that and for stuff
like this so
this is the home screen setup that i'm
rocking right now like i said i've got
my screen time widget and my exercise
widget right here
but the real cool stuff lives here in
the shortcuts widget on the home page
so first i've got a button for notion
and this was actually my
inspiration for making this because
notion doesn't currently have a widget
which i would love
to see them make but for now i can click
this button and i have several different
choices i can go to my inbox which i
talked about in my notion note taking
video
this is my quick capture area where i
can easily create a new note very very
quickly
or i can go to the full notebook area if
i want to get into a specific notebook
like content or music
or i can go to my workspace here
so this is a custom workspace for myself
that i've been developing i can go down
here
and i can see all the different projects
i have in progress across my business
all the videos i'm working on the
newsletters i need to write i can go
down here and see my editorial calendar
and i'm actually working on a course all
about how teams and creators can use
notions so if you are interested in
getting updates about that and maybe
even getting into a beta version
that'll go live before the full price
version i'll have a link in the
description down below where you can
sign up for an email list to get updates
but secondly we have a spotify playlist
thing so often when i go to the gym i
want to easily launch my workout
playlist
i can do that from here and it'll
instantly launch it which is pretty cool
i've got a slack dm button here so i've
got several people across
different slack workspaces who i dm on a
daily basis and it's kind of a pain to
switch workspaces in the slack app
so using deep slack url linking i can
open up say
a dm with tony basically instantly
lastly i've got record now which just
opens up the voice recorder app
and starts recording immediately
so what i want to do for the rest of
this video is show you how to set this
up and hopefully this is going to serve
as both the tutorial for the shortcuts
app and also how to set up widgets in
general
so to start this out let's get a widget
onto the home screen you can hold down
here
until you get this whole edit interface
here and i'm just going to swipe over to
a brand new home screen hit this plus
button and start searching for widgets
you got a ton of different choices here
but the shortcuts one is going to be
near the bottom
so we'll grab that and i'm just going to
go with one of these
four grid boxes here you can do a really
big one if you want you can do a single
one
i like this one so we'll go with that
and right now it's just going to show
the top four shortcuts
in my entire shortcuts app so what we
really want to do is create a custom
folder where we can choose which
shortcuts are shown
in this widget so to do that first we're
gonna go to the shortcuts app itself
and create a folder back here i'll just
create one called
demo for this purpose and as soon as i
add it i can come back to this widget
we've created i can hold it for a second
hit edit widget and then choose this
demo folder
so right now it is going to be empty
which means that we need to start
populating it with
shortcuts so let's go back to that
shortcuts app and
i'm going to create a very very simple
one to start us
out let's do that that voice memos one
since it's kind of a built-in feature
so if you hit plus here we can hit add
an action and you got a whole
bunch of different choices here you can
call people you can text people
you can get into scripting right now
let's just go to apps
and find that voice memos app right here
you got a couple of different choices
listen to my most recent one or record a
new voice memo
this is the one we want to pick for
quick capture i don't want a
show when run confirmation here and then
i want to give it a name so let's just
call it uh record
we can come in here and i'll just choose
a i don't know this
baby wearing a bow because why not
uh oh and one thing i do want to mention
here so i talked about this whole
shortcuts process on my twitter in fact
if you want to follow me over at
tomfrankly you might be able to see
stuff like this before it gets on this
youtube channel which takes a lot more
production time
but if you add this to your home screen
now let's go ahead and do it right now
we'll call it new shortcut i don't
really care what i call it because i
don't really want it
i'm going to add it to my home screen
and then i'll hit done as well
so now it exists in our widget here
and if i tap it it's going to
immediately start recording my voice
which is great that's that's the
behavior we want if we use
the little home screen shortcut here it
works but when i tap it it's going to
pass through the shortcuts app
first which is just kind of annoying i
know it's not really that big of a deal
you get into it and starts recording
immediately but
it's just sort of inelegant so if
anybody at the apple design team is
watching this
i would love for this add to home screen
feature to function just like the widget
just do a no app passthrough just go
right to the app that we want
so this one was easy let's create
something a bit more complicated
how about opening a notion page like my
inbox
right here the cool thing about notion
is you can grab the link to basically
any page that you want so if we go here
to the three dot menu which you can also
do on the desktop and hit copy link
that's going to copy the link to your
clipboard
and if we head back to shortcuts what we
can do is create a shortcut
adding an action in the web category
called
open urls and if we paste that url right
here
it's going to open this page and we're
just going to call that
inbox again i will give it a glyph
this one will be a play button i don't
know why we'll let it be read
and now it's going to be in our demo
widget here so if i click this
and there's our inbox and this process
is not unique to notion if you have an
app that lets you copy a url and that
will launch the app using that url you
can build a shortcut for it so let's go
ahead and do it with a spotify playlist
real quick
i've got my workout playlist here maybe
i want to link to something different
maybe i want to link to
my sunday study playlist so let's find
that
here it is copy the link to it which is
just going to be done through
share and copy link and we can go right
back to shortcuts
go like that go to web go to open urls
paste that url in boom
hit done hit done and
boom now we have a launcher for our
study playlist
but of course what i showed you at the
beginning of this video is a little bit
more complicated than what we've just
built because
on my true widget over here when i tap
these
i get a menu so i can choose several
different places to go
so now i want to show you how to
construct that and to do it
we're going to get a little bit into the
scripting side of
shortcuts now this can get really really
complicated to the point
where people used to share shortcuts
that would be
full of like actual malware and apple
had to clamp down and people sharing
shortcuts and you actually have to go
into your settings and disable that
protection if you want to download
shortcuts from other people
we are not going to get that crazy here
we're just going to use a simple menu
to give you some choices so let's take
this
uh inbox one right here which i realize
i just misspelled
and we'll open the details of it and
instead of just doing this
we'll go ahead and cancel that out and
add an action
from the scripting menu so you've got a
ton of different options here as you can
see you've got if and repeat and all
kinds of weird programming stuff
but the first one is what we're after
choose from menu this is just going to
give you a menu
like you saw in my example and since
we're creating a notion launcher let's
go ahead and make
one for inbox and one for notes
so that's going to give you two
different choices here and now you've
got inbox and notes as little blocks
here
if you hit the plus button you can then
go to our trusty little web category
and hit open urls and then by dragging
it
you can nest it underneath each of these
choices so we're going to get two of
these blocks
nest them like that and then just go and
grab our urls like we did before
first we'll do inbox and we'll copy that
link
and then we'll go over to our general
notes home
and copy that link as well so now just
to review
we've got a scripting tool that opens a
menu giving us the choice of inbox or
notes i can add more items if i wanted
to i can move these around
if i want to and then i've got a block
that will open a url based on the choice
i make
so each one has its own unique url we'll
hit done there and i'll leave it
misspelled because i don't care
now if we go over to our launcher if i
hit this i'm going to have those choices
hitting notes will open up my notebook
and
hitting inbox will open up my trusty
handy dandy
inbox now one final tip i want to share
with you here is that you don't actually
need to have all the shortcuts you want
to use
in a shortcut widget because you can say
the name of the shortcut
to siri like so dm tony
and boom there is my dm with tony so you
can use this trick to easily
launch shortcuts that don't even exist
in this widget just make sure that you
name them something that's easy to
remember and
easy to say and speaking of things that
are easy to say if you want an article
version of this video with some
references for the shortcuts that we
just built you can go over to
thomasjfrank thomasjfrank.com
shortcuts which should hopefully be easy
to remember not least of which because i
have a fairly easy to remember
domain name for my personal website and
not only does that make the reference
easy for you to get to
but ever since i built this website back
in college it's made it easy for
job recruiters and other people to find
my portfolio
and to contact me which is why if you
don't currently have your own domain
name for your portfolio website
you should go over to hover and get it
for yourself however has hundreds of
different extensions to choose from
ranging from your.coms and mes which are
great for portfolio websites but they
also have lots of more fun ones like
lol or even dot blog and once you have
your domain name they also have a couple
of really cool features that can help
make that domain even more useful
number one they've got an email feature
so you can create a very professional
looking email address for yourself like
thomas at collegeinfogeek.com a little
bit more professional than a gmail or a
yahoo or a
hotmail and they also have a connect
feature which lets you easily hook your
domain up to website builders and even
online store builders
so once again if you want to get 10 off
of your domain name purchase and
make sure that you get your domain name
before somebody else takes it
and steals the rug right out from under
your feet go over to hover.com
thomasfrank and grab that domain also if
you enjoyed the video hitting that like
button is a great way to tell the
youtube algorithm that this video isn't
complete and utter garbage and maybe it
should show it to somebody else
once in a while wouldn't that be cool
you can subscribe right there if you
haven't done so already definitely hit
that subscribe button so you don't miss
future videos we have coming out
last but not least i'm gonna have a
playlist of other videos here on tech
videos i've done so if you want to learn
how to set up your home screen
or make your phone a little bit less
distracting check those out
or check out my music channel right here
or don't do any of this
and go buy a cooler llama statue than i
have right here
because as always i can't tell you what
to do i'm not your dad