thanks to trade coffee for sponsoring
this video this month i turned
30 years old yes how do you do fellow
kids
in this video we're gonna go over four
of the biggest regrets that i have
from my 20s from that decade of my life
this is a bit of a
follow-up to a video i did a few years
ago going over some of the biggest
mistakes i made as a student
and like that video the purpose of this
video
is to impart some of the lessons that i
learned through making mistakes and
having regrets
and sharing them with you so you can
hopefully make better decisions that
help you optimize
for the life that you want to live so
with that being said let's get into my
first big regret
which has to do with a bad investment
decision that i made
now i would love to make this a very
juicy story by saying i yellowed all my
life savings on gamestop calls last year
but that's not what happened if you know
me you'll know that for the most part i
have a pretty boring and pretty solid
investing strategy that i've stuck to
for a very long time and actually give
you the context behind that because it
might be useful for you if you're a
beginner investor
i started investing when i was 19 years
old i was sitting in a java programming
class in college
i was bored out of my mind so i went and
figured out how to start investing my
money
i had about a thousand dollars that i
could invest which was fortuitous
because at that time
as far as investments that didn't have
high transaction fees went
a thousand dollars was the minimum
buy-in at least that i could find
so i took my thousand dollars and i put
it into what i thought was the only
investment that i could get into for
that amount of money which was
vanguard's star fund now this isn't a
very aggressive fund as far as the stock
market goes it's pretty balanced
pretty conservative but i just wanted to
get started with investing and after i
had made that thousand dollar deposit
i started putting in money every single
month when i was in college it was
little bits at a time maybe 50 bucks or
100 bucks when i had it and then when i
graduated and started making real money
through my company i set up an automatic
deposit that would deposit money every
single month
so i basically had a robot doing my
investing for me
and that had the dual effect of keeping
my mind off of my investments so i
couldn't make a stupid mistake
and it also utilized what's called
dollar cost averaging
where you're putting money in every
single month or at least on a regular
schedule instead of trying to time the
market
and over the long term this strategy
usually works better for the vast
majority of investors
and because i've been following this
strategy for over 10 years at this point
i've seen some great gains partly due to
the fact that the last 10 years have
been
incredible for the market but also
because i've been consistently investing
and seeing that balance go up over time
but i've always had this philosophy
where if i have you know a pretty decent
nest egg already then i'm gonna take
99 of my investing capital and keep
putting it into the boring stuff
but also on the side maybe take one
percent and put it into some things that
i either believe in or think are fun
so a few years ago i started buying the
one individual stock that i now buy on a
regular basis which is
nintendo i buy it not because i think i
have some you know
super 4d chess strategy for winning the
entire market by buying nintendo
i buy nintendo because i believe in
nintendo i like the company
i love their products so i want to own a
piece of it and it just so happens that
it's been doing pretty well for me over
the past few years
but i started getting re-interested in
investing
earlier this year and as a result i
started following the market again
and this is where the regret comes into
play because since i was following the
market i was seeing some of the
incredible gains that were happening in
companies like
tesla so what did i do well i sold one
thousand dollars
of my nintendo stock which incurred
capital gains tax because i sold it
outside of a retirement account and i
went and i bought tesla
with that thousand dollars so not only
did i take a hit
on the taxes that i had to pay with
selling my nintendo stock
but then i bought tesla at a very high
price and immediately saw that price
crash down and this is a regret not
because i lost money but because i
violated the fundamental principles that
i have been following as an investor for
over 10 years which is don't
try to get smart don't try to be cute
don't try to time the market
and don't be greedy when other people
are being greedy
tesla was a rocket ship at the time so i
should have said to myself hey that's
probably going to come crashing down
instead of
you know falling into this very common
mentality where
people think hey it's going to keep
going up this is called the hot hand
fallacy in sports when a basketball
player has made three or four baskets in
a row
people tend to think hey they're gonna
make the next basket when we see a
trendline we just expect that it's going
to keep going up
it's very easy to fall into this trap so
that's my regret
not necessarily that i lost money but
that i lost money because i violated my
own principles
so going forward into the future i'm
going to be sticking to my investing
principles
which are these number one for companies
that i own
like my own company my youtube channel
my website or companies where i have an
investment and an active hand in what
happens in the business like nebula
swing for the fences bet big but for
passive investing if i'm just putting
money into the market and hoping that
it's going to grow
i need to stick to the tried and true
principles low-cost index funds or
if i'm going to go into you know
possibly riskier territory like
individual stocks
it needs to be for a solid reason
believing in the company looking at the
fundamentals
not getting swept up in mania that
happens in a short period of time and
leaves people
burned regret number two i wish that i
had taken
more breaks and more vacations so the
context here is that i
absolutely had the ability to take more
vacations
over the last 10 years and on many
occasions my fiance anna had asked hey
can we go to europe can we go do
something can we take a break
and the response in my brain almost
every time was you can't do that
you have too much work to do and if you
take this vacation you are not going to
be able to get all your work finished so
you better just
bow out and keep working this despite
the fact that number one even though
this is a productivity channel i know
for a fact that i waste a lot more time
than i need to and number two whenever
business trips came up
opportunities where i saw you know the
ability to grow my business i always
jumped on those
and by jumping on those i knew that i
was putting my current workload on hold
there's no way i'm gonna be able to fly
to vidcon or fly to new york city to
film a collab with
you know another youtuber and also be
able to do all the work that i'm
supposed to be doing
so what i've realized over the last 10
years is
you know it's important to be ambitious
it's important to work hard but it's
also important to be very clear on what
your values are
and there's a common pitfall here
because some values are intangible while
other values are very tangible but in
many cases the
intangible values are actually more
important than the ones that we can see
and track more easily spending time with
my fiance
taking breaks avoiding burnout going on
vacations you know laughing and just
making dumb jokes with anna and my
friends
these are things i value a lot but
they're hard to track
and i have to consciously remind myself
of
how important these things are to me
when i'm constantly bombarded by the
you know more tangible values things
that have metrics attached to them
the money the income and the business
the subscribers and views
and this reminds me of something that my
fiance herself struggled with back when
we were both in college
she was in design school which
admittedly had a much heavier workload
than my business degree had
and she often felt like she could not
take a break from her work to do
something substantial
that she wanted to do like playing a
video game or going out with friends
because she felt guilty
and felt like she had to keep working
yet she will readily admit that she
found herself procrastinating going on
social media
a lot of the time and that
procrastination time ended up
adding up to pretty much equal the time
she would have spent you know
playing a video game taking a real
substantial break these little sources
of procrastination are like a
productivity equivalent of the death by
a thousand paper cuts and that's because
they don't bring in that sense of
guilt that we feel when we consider
something more substantial like a night
out with our friends
we think you know checking twitter or
checking facebook is only going to take
30 seconds so it's harmless
and these social networks are designed
to make you feel that checking them is
harmless but also to keep you coming
back
multiple times a day and to suck you in
and keep you there for longer than you
intended to be there
so the net result is that you end up
wasting just as much time
as you would have if you had truly taken
a break so when i look back
10 years from now on my 30s i would love
to say
hey i took more real breaks and i used
the time pressure created by those
breaks
to work more effectively during my real
work time instead of getting distracted
and looking at twitter regret number
three and i always do this three for
some reason i think i saw it in glorious
bastards and it just kind of got stuck
in my head but anyway
regard number three is buying a house
in the suburbs so last year my fiance
and i
started looking for our first house and
ended up buying it in the late fall
this was caused by me meeting another
youtuber who lives here in denver
charles cornell you might know him i did
a collab video with him he does these
amazing jazz piano videos
but i met him and he's like hey bro uh
my my girlfriend and i are looking for a
house the interest rates are great right
now you should go look for a house
so anna and i started looking for houses
we got a great real estate agent
we toured dozens of houses and i was
determined to make the right decision
on my house purchase the first time so
we didn't go into this all willy-nilly
we went
hardcore like i often do with many
things and we did a ton of research we
toured
around a lot and i learned a ton about
you know mortgages and house financing
and the expenses
to the point where i literally built a
spreadsheet tool where you can put in
multiple properties put in their
purchase price put in your interest rate
your down payment
and see pretty much exactly what you're
going to be paying every single month
which
incidentally helped me avoid the biggest
millennial home buying regret
there is i was actually watching a video
from graham stefan earlier today
and he was reporting on this bank rate
study that found that millennials
biggest home buying regret
is actually underestimating how much
they're going to have to pay per month
because
they see the mortgage amount that they
get and they think hey that's what i
have to pay
and they don't realize there's property
taxes homeowners insurance
maintenance costs you maybe have to fix
the boiler sometimes there's a lot of
hidden costs
so actually if you're looking into
getting your own home keep watching
because i really want to impart this
regret and lesson i learned to you
but also my spreadsheet template is
absolutely free and i'll link that in
the description down below so you can
get a more accurate picture
of what you would pay per month given a
particular house's purchase price
and your down payment amount and all
that cool stuff what i regret
is the area in which i moved it's a nice
neighborhood but it's very suburban
and the reason this is a regret is
because every time
i've made a list of pros and cons or a
list of things that i've wanted in a
house
earlier in my life say five six years
ago i've always put things like
you know ability to easily walk to a
coffee shop ability to easily walk to a
grocery store
in short what i wanted was walkability
and
i think we just got so excited looking
at houses and thinking of what we were
going to be able to do inside a house
that we owned ourselves and i also got
excited at the prospect of being able to
build a big new youtube and music studio
where i could customize
everything i wanted that that priority
the walkability
sort of took a back seat to space
and now we've realized hey we're in a
neighborhood where
pretty much everyone drives everywhere
it's not walkable there's just nothing
within walking distance
so we kind of regret the area in which
we moved and the lesson that i would
impart to you is that if you're looking
at buying a house and you
already have a walkable lifestyle but
maybe you're annoyed by other things
like
dogs barking your neighbors or whatever
and you're thinking hey i could give up
that walkability
really question that choice because i've
come to believe that walkability is
actually one of the fundamentally most
important
things for a lot of people's happiness
and for making a place
truly lovable there's a great book by a
guy named jeff speck called walkable
city
i would highly recommend reading that
book if you're at all interested
in urban design and walkable
neighborhoods regret number four
is failing to stick to a small number of
commitments so i can get very good at
them
so looking back over the past 10 years
of my life
i see a ton of hobbies skills
and different pursuits that i picked up
and then eventually dropped
training for ninja warrior learning to
build iphone apps
learning to sing learning to play piano
i'm the kind of person
who gets easily interested in a lot of
different things and
when i get interested in something i go
hard on it i get obsessed i go learn as
much as i can i have like 50 000 browser
tabs open
and the result of that is i kind of know
a decent amount about a lot of different
things that i tried which is useful for
you know pulling creative insights for
videos
but it also means that i get easily
interested in new things and end up
dropping the old thing that i had just
made a little bit of progress
in and looking back over the past 10
years i look at certain pursuits like
music in particular and i wish i would
have been able to stick with it a bit
more
i'm pretty proud of the music i've put
out over my music channel i've got three
songs that i've released so far
but i've released like one song per year
at this point
and i can't help but wonder if i had
just committed to maybe putting out
one song a month where would i be i've
talked about this my podcast before you
kind of have this dilemma with hobbies
where you either you know allow yourself
to just
pick things up drop them and do things
at your leisure
or you commit to something and you push
through the dip
as seth godin calls it where you get
past that novelty period and you go
through this
log where it's actually hard before you
get to mastery
you have to do that if you want to get
truly good at something so it's kind of
this you know
choice you have do i let myself have fun
and have a casual life
or do i sacrifice and push through the
hard times to get really good and if i
ask myself you know
at 40 years old 50 years old six years
old what would i really regret
i would regret not putting more effort
into music
i would regret not going harder on it
than i currently have
already and i know from my experience as
a youtuber that the only way that i
really stick to something for a long
period of time
even when it gets hard is when i create
external systems that keep me
accountable
with youtube it started out with a tool
called be minder where i would basically
bet money
that i would publish on a weekly
schedule and they would look at the rss
feed which existed back then
and it would charge me money if i didn't
publish a video and uh
at some point that got replaced with
sponsors sponsoring my videos and the
deadlines for those sponsor spots
kept me accountable with real deadlines
instead of fake ones on b minder but
in both ways i've always had deadlines
that have forced me to keep publishing
on a pretty regular schedule
instead of getting marred and
perfectionism on one project or
eventually dropping this pursuit when i
get you know needlessly interested
in something else so when i make this
video again at 40 years old i want to
look back
and say you set up systems of
accountability and you put out more
music
that's something that i care about which
is why this new set exists actually i've
spent the weekend setting up all my
music gear so it's much easier
to turn on and start creating and that's
really all we can do with our mistakes
we can take action
using the lessons they impart to us to
not make those same mistakes in the
future
so whatever your own regrets are own
them own your mistakes
learn from them and use that knowledge
to make better decisions
going forward now one decision that i
definitely don't regret
is making this delicious cup of coffee
that i've been drinking while filming
this video
and this roast in particular it's called
the bowery from a roaster called orens
is my
favorite coffee in the world and i get
it from trade
trade is a great way to try new coffees
from independent roasters and have them
shipped
right to your door and it's a great way
to explore and expand your palette while
also being pretty sure that you're going
to get something that you love
instead of rolling the dice trade has
you take a quiz that ascertains
your coffee preferences do you like it
ground do you like it
whole bean do you like it to be dark or
light and then once your preferences are
saved they're going to match you with
new coffees that you're almost certainly
going to love
all of my favorite coffees have come
from trade they have never steered me
wrong so seriously i think you are going
to love it
if you love coffee like i do once that
quiz is done all you have to do is
select the delivery frequency and you'll
get fresh coffee delivered right to your
doorstep that is roasted and
shipped within 24 hours of each order so
it's super duper mega fresh
and because you are a very discerning
viewer of my channel if you are one of
the first 100 people to sign up at the
link in the description down below
you're going to get
50 off your first bag just use the link
down in the description
take the quiz and use the code thomas50
at
checkout to get 50 off your first bag
get free shipping
and to support my channel if you enjoyed
this video hit that like button for the
youtube algorithm and i will see you
in the next one stay cute